♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Welcome to "Meet WeatherKit"
at WWDC22.
My name is Novall,
and I'm an engineer
on the Weather team.
We rely on weather data
day in and day out,
and where we get
this information is important.
From checking the weather
on your Apple Watch
so you know to bring
an umbrella with you
before you head out the door,
to sustainable agriculture
where predicting rain and frost
can help farmers
plan crop rotation,
to staying safe and prepared
for winter storm travel --
weather impacts everyone.
Accurate weather data
has become even more critical
in today's world affected
by our changing climate.
And having access
to accurate forecasts
is important now more than ever,
which is why
we created WeatherKit.
WeatherKit is powered by the
all-new Apple Weather Service,
a world-class
global weather forecast.
It uses high-resolution
weather models
and machine learning
and prediction algorithms
to give you hyperlocal
weather forecasts
around the globe.
With Apple Weather Service,
we have access to a lot of data,
and all of this is available
to you through WeatherKit.
Accurate weather data
requires location information.
And keeping that data private
is a shared responsibility.
In keeping with
our commitment to privacy,
WeatherKit is designed
to give hyperlocal forecasts
without compromising
user information.
Location is used only
to provide weather forecasts
and is not associated
with any personally
identifying information
and is never shared or sold.
With WeatherKit,
we've made it easy for you
to protect user privacy.
Today I will be diving into
more detail about WeatherKit
so you can get the most
out of our new API.
First, I'll cover
the available data sets
we offer through WeatherKit,
backed by our own
Apple Weather Service.
Next, I'll show you how
to request weather information
using the WeatherKit framework
and a REST API designed
so you can get weather data
on any platform.
And finally,
I'll cover some additional
implementation requirements
and best practices.
Let me start with an overview of
the available weather data sets.
As I mentioned, you have access
to a lot of data in WeatherKit.
So let's talk about
each data set.
The current weather data set
describes the "now" conditions
at the requested location.
It represents
a single point in time
and includes conditions like
UV index, temperature, and wind.
The minute forecast
contains minute-by-minute
precipitation conditions
for the next hour,
where available.
This data set is useful
for deciding whether or not
to bring an umbrella with you
as you walk out the door.
The hourly forecast
is a collection of forecasts
starting on the current hour
and provides data
for up to 240 hours.
Each hour in the hourly forecast
includes conditions
like humidity, visibility,
pressure, and dew point.
The daily forecast contains a
forecast collection of 10 days.
Each day in the daily forecast
provides information
about the entire day,
like the high
and low temperature,
sunrise, and sunset.
Weather alerts contains
severe weather warnings
issued for
the requested location.
This data set contains
important information
to keep your users safe,
informed, and prepared.
And finally, historical weather
provides saved weather forecasts
from the past,
so you can see trends
in weather data.
You can access historical data
by specifying
a start and end date
to the hourly
and daily requests.
This gives you access
to a lot of data.
We think there are a lot
of important and impactful ways
you can use historical weather.
Now that you've seen all of
the rich weather data available,
I'll walk you through
how to request this weather data
with the WeatherKit APIs.
Apple Weather data is available
through both a native framework
and a set of REST APIs.
First, let me show you
how easy it is
to access weather data
with our Swift framework.
All it takes
is a few lines of code.
And with Swift Concurrency,
requesting weather is simple.
First, you'll import WeatherKit
and CoreLocation.
Then you'll create
a weatherService object,
as your entry point
for the Weather Service.
You'll create a CLLocation
with coordinates
for your location of interest.
Here, I'm using my hometown
of Syracuse, New York.
Then you’ll call weather(for:)
on the weatherService instance
and pass in the location
created above.
When the call completes,
you can access the relevant data
you need for your app,
like the current temperature
and UV Index in this example.
Now that I've shown you
how easy it is
to request weather data
with Swift,
let me take you through
another example
I'm using a travel app
that I'm building in SwiftUI.
You can grab the completed
project from the link
associated with this session.
Since I'm really looking forward
to traveling again,
I've decided to create
a flight planner app
to plan my next trip.
I've already created the logic
for my flight itinerary,
but when I tap on each
of the flights in my trip,
I want to show columns
containing the condition,
precipitation, wind, and
temperature at each destination.
First step is to enable
WeatherKit.
Register the App ID
in the Developer Portal,
then select the Capability
and App Services t  abs
to enable WeatherKit.
Then in Xcode,
add the WeatherKit capability
to the project.
With that prep out of the way,
let me walk through how
I'll get the weather data
for each of these locations.
Here I have an Airport struct
already set up
that contains
the latitude and longitude
of my destination airports.
I'll get the hourly forecast
by calling weather(for:)
on our shared weather service
and then pass in
our airport location.
Because I just want
a subset of data,
I've also specified to include
the hourly forecast
in the request.
Now, I'll build and run my app.
Now I can see
my custom view updated
to display the conditions
at each airport.
The next thing I need to do
while building this app
is to display attribution
for the data sources in my app.
First, I'll get
the attribution URL from
the attribution.legalPageURL
property.
This is a link to
the legal attribution page
that contains
copyright information
about the weather data sources.
I'll also need to get the URL
for the combined
Apple Weather mark.
It's available in both light
and dark variants,
so I'll check the
colorScheme environment value
to find out if the SwiftUI view
is currently displaying
in light or dark appearance.
Finally,
I'll build and run again.
Note that the Apple Weather mark
and attribution link
opens in an
SFSafariViewController.
That's all it takes
to get the weather
for our flight planner app,
and there are so many ways
you can use the WeatherKit API
to add weather data
to your apps.
But that was only
the native framework.
The REST API provides
the same rich weather data
as the Swift framework
and can be used on any platform.
In this example, I'm showing how
you can request weather alerts
from the weatherkit.apple.com
endpoint.
First, you request
an auth token.
I'll discuss that more in a bit.
Then, to get the weather object,
you first create a URL
indicating the desired weather
data set for a given location.
Be sure to set
the appropriate language
for a localized response.
Then, provide
the latitude and longitude
of the location of interest.
Indicate the desired data set.
You may notice this parameter
is plural so you can request
several at once by separating
each with a comma.
And finally, the country code
for the requested location.
But note, the country code
is only required
if you're requesting
the weather alerts data set.
Next, you'll fetch
the weather data
using the URL and your auth
token from above,
converting the results to JSON.
With that, you can access
the weather alerts
and their details.
So again, another example
of how easy it is
for you to access weather data,
only this time through REST.
To go into more depth
about the setup you need,
let's revisit auth.
For the WeatherKit REST API,
there are a few additional steps
to handle authentication.
In the Developer Portal,
you'll enable access
for WeatherKit requests by
creating an authentication key
enabled for WeatherKit
and an associated services ID.
The private key can be created
in the Keys section
of the Developer Portal.
WeatherKit requires tokens
to validate authorization
on each request.
So on your server,
you'll deploy a token service
for creating a signed JSON web
token using your private key.
For those familiar with JSON
web token authentication,
this is a fairly standard
authorization flow,
but let me share some details
in case this is your first time
working with it.
To generate a signed token
you'll create the header
containing the fields and values
described in the
developer documentation.
Then create the payload
containing the information
specific to the WeatherKit
REST API and your application,
including items such
as the issuer, subject,
and expiration time.
And finally,
you'll sign the token
for use with a subsequent call
to the WeatherKit REST API.
Going back to
my weather alerts example,
here's where you'll request the
token from your signing service,
and add the token
to the Authorization header
of your HTTP request
for weather data.
So that's
the WeatherKit REST API.
One of two great ways
for you to access weather data
from the Apple Weather Service.
Lastly, I'll cover a few
additional requirements
for publishing on the App Store
or before you go live
on any platform
using the REST API.
Each of these requirements
apply regardless
of whether you're using
the native Swift or REST APIs.
The first requirement
is attribution.
As you saw in my demo,
you'll get a link
from our Attribution API
which you'll need to display
in your native or web app.
The second requirement
is an attribution logo.
The WeatherKit API
makes this easy and convenient
by providing the image assets
you need to display in your app.
And finally, if you'll be
displaying weather alerts,
you'll also need to link
to an event page
provided in the response.
So that's how easy it is
to prepare your app
for publication
on the App Store or the web.
So that's WeatherKit --
hyperlocal forecasts powered
the Apple Weather Service
accessible through our Swift
framework and our REST API.
Both open up a world
of possibilities
for you to use weather data
in your apps,
on any platform or device.
We hope you enjoyed
this session.
Besides checking out the links
associated with this session,
read the docs
and download the project.
And of course,
we'd love your feedback.
We can't wait to see all of
the creative and impactful ways
you use WeatherKit.
Thank you and have a great WWDC!
♪