♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hip music ♪
♪
Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name's Karim,
and I'm a HealthKit engineer.
The HealthKit framework
provides the foundation
for building great
health experiences,
and Apple Watch comes packed
with many health
and safety features,
that keep an eye on things
for you.
One of the most popular
is sleep tracking,
and we are making updates
to capture more detailed
sleep data.
We also have other
great new additions
to HealthKit this year.
We enhanced our APIs
to make it easier
to query for data
with Swift async.
We're improving workouts with
a richer workout representation.
And we're adding support
for saving vision prescriptions,
including a digital copy
of the physical prescription.
I'm excited to tell you more
about all these updates
and how your apps
can leverage them.
Let's get started!
Sleep is such
an essential function
that allows our bodies
and minds to recharge,
and I love using my Apple Watch
to manage my sleep schedule
and get insights
that help me understand
and improve my sleep.
This year we are making
sleep tracking even better
by introducing sleep stages.
Apple Watch
will automatically track
all the different sleep stages
you go through
when you're asleep,
and this data will be accessible
from the Health app
and saved in HealthKit.
Of course,
your app will be able to read
and save sleep stages data.
Sleep data saved
by Apple Watch or your app
is represented in HealthKit
by category samples
with the identifier
sleepAnalysis.
We will support
three sleep stages:
REM, core, and deep.
When saving sleep data
to HealthKit,
you should make sure
to create one sample
for each continuous period
of time in a given sleep stage.
This is what the sleep sample
value enum looks like.
We're adding three cases
to represent sleep stages,
starting with asleepCore,
which corresponds to stages one
and two of the scoring model
from the American Academy
of Sleep Medicine or AASM;
asleepDeep, which corresponds
to stage three
of the AASM scoring model;
and finally, asleepREM,
which corresponds
to the rapid eye movement stage.
Now that we added sleep stages,
we are deprecating
the asleep case
in favor of asleepUnspecified,
which indicates
that the user is asleep
but no sleep stage
was specified.
With the updated sleep
samples enum,
it is now possible to save
and read sleep stages data
from HealthKit.
We added a new predicate to make
it easy to read sleep samples
for a given stage.
Let's say I want to read
sleep samples
in the REM stage.
First, I create a predicate
using the new
predicateForSamples method
with asleepREM as value.
Now, I can start
building my query.
I create a predicate
for my query
with the sleepAnalysis
sample type
and the sleep stage predicate.
And with this query predicate,
I can now create my query.
Running the query
will give me back
an array of sleep samples
in the REM stage.
However, if you're interested
in reading samples
for all sleep stages,
including unspecified,
it's important that
you update your app
to use the new .allAsleepValues
when building your predicate.
If you haven't looked
at HealthKit since last year,
this shorter syntax for querying
may look unfamiliar to you.
Since iOS 15.4,
we have updated our query API
to support Swift async.
Queries are an essential piece
of HealthKit,
and with Swift async support,
they're easier to use
with a more concise syntax.
Queries allow you to read
various data from HealthKit,
using predicates
to filter the results,
and also watch for new data
as it comes in.
All queries are subclasses
of HKQuery.
If I'm interested in knowing
the total calories burned
over a certain period of time,
a great query to get
these computed statistics
is HKStatisticsCollectionQuery.
To get the initial results,
you would set
the initialResultsHandler
closure of the query.
And if you're interested
in watching for any updates,
you would additionally set
the statisticsUpdateHandler
closure.
Once the query is started,
these closures will be called
with the results.
Thanks to Swift async,
we are making this even simpler.
Each query now has
a matching query descriptor,
so HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
becomes
HKStatisticsCollectionQuery
Descriptor.
You get the initial result
by simply calling
the async result(for:) method.
If, on the other hand, you want
to get the initial result
and also watch for updates,
you call results(for:),
which returns an AsyncSequence
that you can loop through
to read the results.
HealthKit is great
for tracking workouts
and relevant metrics
such as burned calories.
To find out how many calories
I burned this week,
I can use the statistics
collection query descriptor.
First, I create
the query descriptor
with a predicate
to match calorie samples.
I use the cumulativeSum option
because I want the total sum.
I'm interested
in this week's data,
so I use thisSunday
as my anchorDate.
And finally,
I want my calorie totals
to be computed for
a time interval of one week.
Once I created
my query descriptor,
all I need to do
is call result(for:)
with a healthStore object.
The returned
statisticsCollection object
gives me a snapshot
of my current data.
But if I want live updates
as my calories change,
it's as simple
as calling results(for:)
and looping through
the returned async sequence
to read the results.
When I'm done
watching for updates,
I just break out of the loop
and that will stop the query.
Now, let's talk about workouts.
HealthKit is a great place
for saving workouts
and all their related metrics
whether you're going
on a casual bike ride
or pushing yourself
to the limit at a race.
And oftentimes,
workouts may contain
more than one distinct activity.
You may be repeating the same
exercise with interval training
or participating
in a triathlon race
which comprises swimming,
cycling, and running.
We are updating our workouts API
in iOS 16 and watchOS 9
to make it possible to capture
these types of workouts
and the relevant statistics
for each activity.
This is the timeline
of a swim-bike-run workout
I did recently.
I started with swimming,
after which
I took a little bit of time
to get ready for the cycling
portion of the workout,
and finally running.
Each activity is represented by
an HKWorkoutActivity object.
Each workout activity
is created with its own
workout configuration,
which includes
the activity type.
A workout activity holds
a list of events
that occurred
during the activity.
And you will be able to read
statistics for each activity,
which is great for when
you're only interested
in analyzing what happened
during a particular activity.
Going back to my timeline,
my three activities
are configured
with their appropriate
activity type.
Activities cannot
overlap in time.
And because there may be
a transition period
between each activity,
they are not required
to be contiguous.
If I'm interested
in analyzing what happened
during transition periods,
I can create an
HKWorkoutActivity
for each transition
with the type transition.
All of these activities will be
saved with the HKWorkout object
under the workoutActivities
property.
If you're using HKWorkoutBuilder
to add workouts to HealthKit,
adding an activity
is as easy as creating
an HKWorkoutActivity object
with a workoutConfiguration,
start and end date,
and an optional metadata.
And then, you simply call
addWorkoutActivity
on the workout builder.
On Apple Watch, you can use
a workout session
to track
a swim-bike-run workout,
and the associated
workout builder
to save the workout
in HealthKit.
Let's go back
to my workout timeline.
To track this workout
on Apple Watch,
I need to set up
a workout session and builder.
I start by creating
a workout configuration
with the type swimBikeRun.
Then I create
an HKWorkoutSession
using my configuration.
At the beginning of the workout
I simply call startActivity
on the session,
and beginCollection on the
associated workout builder.
Now that my session
and builder are ready,
I can add my first activity
using the
beginNewActivity method
with a swimming workout
configuration and a start date.
At the beginning
of each activity,
you should make sure to update
the workout builder data source
to only collect the data types
you're interested in.
Because this is
a swimming activity,
I want swimming distance
to be collected.
At the end of the activity,
I call endCurrentActivity
with the end date.
Because I'm interested in
analyzing the transition period
from swimming to cycling,
I will start
a new transition activity
immediately
after swimming has ended.
Again, because this is
the beginning of an activity,
I update the builder data source
to disable the collection
of swimming distance,
since it's no longer relevant.
I end the transition activity
right before cycling begins.
I can track the remaining
activities of my workout
the same way.
At the end of the workout,
ending the session will
also end any running activity.
Then I can finish
the workout builder,
which will save and return
an HKWorkout object.
I can use the returned workout
to read some
of the associated metrics
such as totalEnergyBurned
and totalDistance,
and display a summary
of the workout in my app.
However,
this small set of properties
is no longer sufficient.
totalSwimmingStrokeCount
is not relevant to all workouts,
and some workouts
may collect more metrics.
In order to make it easier
to read metrics
for all kinds of workouts,
we are deprecating
these properties
in favor of a new method
which returns statistics
for a given quantity type.
As a reminder,
this method is also available
on HKWorkoutActivity,
allowing you to focus
on just what happened
during an activity.
These statistics will be
automatically computed
from any samples collected
with the workout,
only when using HKWorkoutBuilder
or HKLiveWorkoutBuilder.
Along with this richer
workout representation,
we also have a new set
of predicates to help you query
for only the workouts
you're interested in
when driving your analysis
or visualization.
To give you an example,
here's a list
of my recent workouts
with the average heart rate
for each activity.
I would like to find my workouts
with high-intensity activities
where my average heart rate
was above 150.
First, I start by creating
a predicate using the new
predicateForWorkoutActivities
method,
which will act
on workout activities.
I want the average heart rate
to be greater
than 150 beats per minute.
Next, because
I want to query for workouts,
I wrap my heart rate predicate
inside a workout predicate.
Then, I create a query
using that predicate.
And I call the
result(for: healthStore) method
of my query descriptor
to get the list of workouts
that match my predicate.
And that's how I'm able to query
for just the workouts
I'm interested in.
One of my recent workouts
consisted of four
running intervals.
Using HKWorkoutActivity
is a great way
to capture these intervals.
You just need to make sure
that all activities
of an interval workout
have the same activity type
as the workout.
So for a running workout,
all activities are configured
with the .running type.
One benefit of using workout
activities to track intervals
is you can get statistics
for each interval.
With these updates,
workouts now include
a more comprehensive
picture of their activities
and the context
surrounding them.
In order to provide
an even richer picture,
we're introducing
new running metrics
that will be
automatically collected
on Apple Watch Series 6,
SE, and newer --
metrics such as running stride
length, or power in watts.
For swimming workouts,
we're adding the SWOLF score.
It's defined as
the number of strokes
taken in a given length,
and the time it took
to swim that length.
This score will be calculated
for each lap event
and segment event
for swimming workouts
recorded on Apple Watch.
While these metrics enrich
your workouts and allow you
to get a better understanding
of how you performed,
another important metric
that is recorded
after a workout has ended
is heart rate recovery.
It's an estimate of how quickly
your heart rate lowers
after exercise,
and it can be used to understand
how the heart recovers
after stress,
and reveal potential
health problems.
With iOS 16, we are introducing
a new Cardio Recovery data type.
It will be accessible
from the Health app,
and your apps will be able
to read and save this data
in HealthKit.
Heart rate recovery
is a quantity type
with the identifier
.heartRateRecoveryOneMinute.
Additional context information
about each heart rate
recovery sample
can be added as metadata.
In my recent
swim-bike-run workout,
I pushed myself to my limits,
and then observed
my heart rate's recovery rate.
It took me about
three and a half hours
to complete the workout.
I reached a maximum heart rate
of 184 beats per minute
when I was running.
And the minute following
the workout,
my heart rate
dropped by 50 beats.
When using HKLiveWorkoutBuilder
on Apple Watch,
a heart rate recovery sample,
along with
its surrounding context,
is automatically saved
in HealthKit after a workout.
Otherwise, to save
a heart rate recovery sample,
I create a quantity sample
with the
.heartRateRecoveryOneMinute
type.
My heart rate dropped
by 50 beats
the minute
following the workout,
so I set that as the quantity
of my sample.
I also set a start and end date
for the sample.
Then, I put the additional
context information
in the metadata dictionary,
starting with
the recovery test type.
Because my workout
was an all-out effort,
the test type is .maxExercise.
My workout was a swimBikeRun,
so I set that
as the activity type.
I can also add the workout
duration using the
HeartRateRecoveryActivity
Duration key.
Finally, I add the maximum
heart rate observed
during the workout,
which was 184 beats per minute.
With these updates,
it is now easier than ever
to track swim-bike-run,
and interval workouts.
In addition,
the introduction of new metrics
provides a more comprehensive
picture for your workouts
and newer ways
to evaluate progress over time.
While activity and fitness is
something that impacts everyone
there are other aspects
of health
that touch on many of us,
such as vision.
In fact, according to
the Vision Council of America,
approximately 75 percent
of adults in the United States
rely on vision correction
with prescription glasses
or contact lenses.
These prescriptions,
however, are easy to lose,
and it's one more thing
you need to have with you
when ordering prescription
glasses or contact lenses.
So let's put them
in our phones.
Starting with iOS 16,
your apps can now save
glasses and contacts
prescriptions in HealthKit.
A vision prescription
is a sample
with the visionPrescriptionType.
The sample's start date
corresponds
to the prescription's
issue date,
while the end date corresponds
to the expiration date.
Optionally, a digital copy
of the physical prescription
can be attached
to the sample.
A glasses or contacts
prescription sample
is a subclass
of HKVisionPrescription.
For glasses, you use the
HKGlassesPrescription subclass,
and for contacts, the
HKContactsPrescription subclass.
Each glasses prescription
is created
using two glasses lens
specification objects;
one for each eye.
And similarly, contacts
prescriptions are created
with two contacts lens
specification objects.
Now, let's save
my reading glasses prescription
to HealthKit.
The first step is to create
an HKGlassesLensSpecification
for each eye.
Some parameters, such as
vertex distance and prism,
are optional.
I can create the right eye
lens specification the same way.
Next, I create a glasses
prescription sample
with my right eye and left eye
lens specifications.
This prescription
is for my reading glasses,
so I'm adding that
in the description.
Then, I just call save
on the healthStore
with my prescription.
And with that, my prescription
is now saved in HealthKit.
I also took a picture of it,
which I'd like to attach
to the sample I just saved.
A file attachment is represented
by an HKAttachment object.
You use HKAttachmentStore to
save and read file attachments.
Only static images or PDF files
can be attached
to prescriptions.
To attach the picture I took
to my prescription sample,
I start by creating
an HKAttachmentStore object
using a healthStore.
Then I call addAttachment(to:)
with my prescription sample.
I set a name for the attachment.
Here, I'm attaching a PNG file.
And finally,
pass the URL of the file.
The prescription I just attached
contains a lot more information
than just
the lens specification --
sensitive information, like
my full name and date of birth.
One of HealthKit's
core principles
is to protect your privacy
and make sure
that you are always in control
of the data you share.
Because it can be easy to share
more data than intended
with prescriptions
that include an attachment,
we are introducing
a new authorization model
for prescriptions.
Read authorization is granted
for each prescription
object separately.
Users can select exactly
which prescriptions
they grant your app access to,
and update their selection
at any time.
We have a new API
for requesting authorization
for vision prescription objects.
Just like other data types,
you can use queries
to read prescriptions
that your app has access to.
If you're only interested
in certain prescriptions,
you can use a predicate.
To request authorization,
simply call the
requestPerObjectRead
Authorization method
of the healthStore
with the visionType.
Doing so will always display an
authorization prompt in your app
with a list of all
the prescriptions
that match your predicate.
Make sure you're asking
for authorization
in the appropriate context to
ensure the best user experience.
These are just some of the new
things we added to HealthKit
to empower your apps
to provide better health
and fitness experiences.
We can't wait to see
what you will build next.
Have a great WWDC,
and if you have any questions,
we'll be happy to help you
in the Developer Forums.
♪