♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Jon Schoenberg,
and I'm an engineer
on the Location Technologies
team at Apple.
In this session, I'll cover
the new features we've brought
to Nearby Interaction,
that are going to enable you
to build richer
and more diverse experiences
with spatial awareness.
The Nearby Interaction
framework makes it simple
to take advantage
of the capabilities of U1 --
Apple's chip for Ultra Wideband
technology --
and enables creating precise
and spatially aware interactions
between nearby Apple devices
or accessories
compatible with Apple's U1 chip
for Ultra Wideband.
Let's get started
with a quick review
of what's been available to you
over the last two years.
When Nearby Interaction
was introduced at WWDC 2020,
the functionality
focused on creating
and running a session
between two iPhones with U1.
At WWDC 2021,
the functionality was extended
to support running sessions
with Apple Watch and third-party
Ultra Wideband-compatible
accessories.
If you're interested
in a deep dive
into the Nearby Interaction
framework's APIs,
please review the WWDC talk
"Meet Nearby Interaction"
from 2020
and "Explore Nearby Interaction
with third-party accessories"
from 2021.
We've been blown away
by the community's response
to Nearby Interaction,
and in this session,
I'm excited to unveil
the new capabilities
and improvements for you.
I will focus on two main topics:
enhancing Nearby Interaction
with ARKit
and background sessions.
Along the way,
I'll share some improvements
that make it easier to use
the Nearby Interaction framework
and I'll conclude with an update
on third-party hardware support
that was announced
last year.
We're excited about
what you will do
with the new capabilities,
so let's dive right
into the details.
I'll start with an exciting
new capability
that tightly integrates ARKit
with Nearby Interaction.
This new capability
enhances Nearby Interaction
by leveraging the device
trajectory computed from ARKit.
ARKit-enhanced
Nearby Interaction
leverages the same
underlying technology
that powers Precision Finding
with AirTag,
and we're making it available
to you via Nearby Interaction.
The best use cases are
experiences that guide a user
to a specific nearby object
such as a misplaced item,
object of interest,
or object that the user
wants to interact with.
By integrating ARKit
and Nearby Interaction,
the distance and direction
information
is more consistently available
than using
Nearby Interaction alone,
effectively broadening the
Ultra Wideband field of view.
Finally, this new capability
is best used
for interacting with
stationary devices.
Let's jump right
into a demonstration
of the possibilities
this new integration of ARKit
and Nearby Interaction
enable with your application.
I've got an application here
for my Jetpack Museum
that has
Ultra Wideband accessories
to help guide users
to the exhibits.
Let's go find the next jetpack.
As the user selects
to go to the next exhibit,
the application discovers
the Ultra Wideband accessory
and performs
the necessary exchanges
to start using
Nearby Interaction.
The application
then instructs the user
to move the phone side to side
while it begins to determine
the physical location
of the next exhibit,
using the enhanced Nearby
Interaction mode with ARKit.
Now that the application
understands the direction
that corresponds
to the next exhibit,
a simple arrow icon
telling the user
the direction to head
to check it out appears.
This rich, spatially-aware
information
utilizing the combination
of ARKit and Nearby Interaction
can even indicate when
the exhibit is behind the user
and the user is heading in a
direction away from the exhibit.
Finally, the application
can display,
in the AR world, an overlay
of the next exhibit's location,
and the application prompts
the user to move the iPhone
up and down slightly
to resolve where the exhibit is
in the AR world.
Once the AR content
is placed in the scene,
the powerful combination
of Nearby Interaction --
with its Ultra Wideband
measurements --
and ARKit, allows the user
to easily head over
to check out the next jetpack.
I may not have found a jetpack,
but I found a queen.
Let's turn now
to how you can enable
this enhanced
Nearby Interaction mode.
With iOS 15, you probably have
a method in your application
that accepts
the NIDiscoveryToken
from a nearby peer,
creates a session configuration,
and runs the NISession.
Enabling the enhanced mode
with ARKit is easy
on new and existing uses of
Nearby Interaction with a new
isCameraAssistanceEnabled
property on the subclasses
of NIConfiguration.
Setting the
isCameraAssistanceEnabled
property is all that's required
to leverage the enhanced mode
with ARKit.
Camera assistance is available
when interacting
between two Apple devices,
and an Apple device
to third-party
Ultra Wideband accessories.
Let's look at the details
of what happens
when an NISession is run
with camera assistance enabled.
When camera assistance
is enabled,
an ARSession
is automatically created
within the Nearby Interaction
framework.
You are not responsible
for creating this ARSession.
Running an NISession
with camera assistance enabled
will also run the ARSession
that was automatically created
within the Nearby Interaction
framework.
The ARSession is running
within the application process.
As a result,
the application must provide
a camera usage description key
within the application's
Info.plist.
Be sure to make this a useful
string to inform your users
why the camera is necessary
to provide a good experience.
Only a single ARSession can be
running for a given application.
This means that if you already
have an ARKit experience
in your app, it is necessary to
share the ARSession you create
with the NISession.
To share the ARSession
with the NISession,
a new setARSession method
is available
on the NISession class.
When setARSession is called,
prior to run, on the NISession,
an ARSession will not be
automatically created
within the Nearby Interaction
framework
when the session is run.
This ensures the application
ARKit experience
happens concurrently
to the camera assistance
in Nearby Interaction.
In this SwiftUI example, as part
of the makeUIView function,
the underlying ARSession
within the ARView
is shared with the NISession
via the new setARSession method.
If you are using
an ARSession directly,
it is necessary to call run
on the ARSession
with
an ARWorldTrackingConfiguration.
In addition, several properties
must be configured
in a specific manner
within this ARConfiguration
to ensure high-quality
performance
from camera assistance.
The worldAlignment
should be set to gravity,
collaboration and
userFaceTracking disabled,
a nil initialWorldMap,
and a delegate
whose sessionShouldAttempt
Relocalization method
returns false.
Let's turn to some
best practices
when sharing an ARSession
you created.
In your NISessionDelegate
didInvalidateWith error method,
always inspect the error code.
If the ARConfiguration used
to run the shared ARSession
does not conform
to the outlined properties,
the NISession
will be invalidated.
A new NIError code
invalidARConfiguration
will be returned.
To receive nearby object updates
in your app,
continue to use the
didUpdateNearbyObjects method
in your NISessionDelegate.
In your didUpdateNearbyObjects
method,
you probably check the nearby
objects for your desired peer
and update the UI
based on distance
and direction properties of the
NINearbyObject when available,
always being careful
to recall these can be nil.
When camera assistance
is enabled,
two new properties are available
within the NINearbyObject.
The first is horizontalAngle.
This is the 1D angle in radians
indicating the azimuthal
direction to the nearby object.
When unavailable,
this value will be nil.
Second,
verticalDirectionEstimate
is the positional relationship
to the nearby object
in the vertical dimension.
This is a new
VerticalDirectionEstimate type.
Distance and direction represent
the key spatial relationship
between the user's device
and a nearby object.
Distance is measured in meters
and direction is a 3D vector
from your device
to the nearby object.
Horizontal angle is defined
as the angle between the device
running the NISession
and the nearby object
within a local
horizontal plane.
This accounts for any
vertical displacement
offset between the two devices
and any horizontal rotation
of the device itself.
While direction is 3D,
horizontal angle
is a 1D representation of the
heading between the two devices.
This horizontal angle property
is complimentary
to the direction property,
and if the direction
cannot be resolved,
the horizontal angle
can be available
to help you guide your user
to a nearby object.
Vertical direction estimate
is a qualitative assessment
of the vertical position
information.
You should use it to guide
the user between floor levels.
Let's look now at the new
VerticalDirectionEstimate type.
VerticalDirectionEstimate
is a nested enum
within the NINearbyObject
and represents
a qualitative assessment
of the vertical relationship
to the nearby object.
Be sure to check if
the VerticalDirectionEstimate
is unknown
before using the property.
The vertical relationship
can be same, above, below,
or a special
aboveOrBelow value
that represents the nearby
object is not on the same level,
but not clearly above
or below the device.
The Ultra Wideband measurements
are subject to field of view
and obstructions.
The field of view
for direction information
corresponds to a cone projecting
from the rear of the device.
The device trajectory
computed from ARKit
when camera assistance
is enabled allows the distance,
direction, horizontal angle,
and vertical direction estimate
to be available in more
scenarios, effectively expanding
the Ultra Wideband sensor
field of view.
Let's turn now to leveraging
this integration of ARKit
and Nearby Interaction to place
AR objects in your scene.
To make it easier for you
to overlay 3D virtual content
that represents
the nearby object
onto a camera feed
visualization,
we've added a helper method:
worldTransform on NISession.
This method returns
a worldTransform
in ARKit's coordinate space
that represents
the given nearby
object's position
in the physical environment
when it's available.
When not available,
this method returns nil.
We used this method
in the demonstration
to place the floating spheres
above the next exhibit.
We want to make it as easy
as possible for you
to leverage Nearby Interaction
positional output
to manipulate content
in the AR world in your app.
Two powerful systems in iOS,
combined.
Your users must sweep the
device sufficiently in vertical
and horizontal directions
to allow the camera assistance
to adequately compute
the world transform.
This method can return nil
when the user motion
is insufficient to allow
the camera assistance
to fully converge
to an ARKit world transform.
When this transform is important
to your app experience,
it is important to coach
the user to take action
to generate this transform.
Let's look now at some
additions we've made
to the NISessionDelegate
to make it possible
for you to guide the user
similar to what you saw
in the demonstration.
To aid in guiding the user
towards your object,
an NISessionDelegate callback
provides information
about the Nearby Interaction
algorithm convergence
via the new
didUpdateAlgorithmConvergence
delegate method.
Algorithm convergence
can help you understand why
horizontal angle,
vertical direction estimate,
and worldTransform
are unavailable
and what actions
the user can take
to resolve those properties.
The delegate provides
a new NIAlgorithmConvergence
object
and an optional NINearbyObject.
This delegate method is only
called when you have enabled
camera assistance
in your NIConfiguration.
Let's look at the new
NIAlgorithmConvergence type.
NIAlgorithmConvergence
has a single-status property
that is an NIAlgorithm
ConvergenceStatus type.
The NIAlgorithmConvergenceStatus
type is an enum that represents
whether the algorithm
is converged or not.
If the algorithm
is not converged,
an array of associated values
NIAlgorithmConvergenceStatus
.Reasons is provided.
Let's return
to the new delegate method
and say you want to update
the status of the camera
assistance to the user,
you can switch on
the convergence status
and if unknown or converged,
display that information
to the user.
Be sure to inspect
the NINearbyObject.
When the object is nil,
the NIAlgorithmConvergence state
applies to the session itself,
rather than a specific
NINearbyObject.
When the status is
notConverged,
it also includes an associated
value that describes the reasons
the algorithm is not converged.
A localized description
is available for this reason
to help you communicate better
with your users.
Let's look next
at how to use these values.
Inspecting the notConverged
case more closely
and the associated
reasons value,
it is possible to guide
the user to take actions
that helps produce
the desired information
about a nearby object.
The associated value
is an array of
NIAlgorithmConvergence
StatusReasons.
The reason can indicate there's
insufficient total motion,
insufficient motion in the
horizontal or vertical sweep,
and insufficient lighting.
Be mindful that multiple reasons
may exist at the same time
and guide the user sequentially
through each action
based on which is most important
for your application.
Recall how I moved the phone
in the demonstration
and needed to sweep
in both the horizontal
and vertical direction
to resolve the world transform.
That's the most
important bits about
the enhanced Nearby Interaction
mode with camera assistance.
We've made some
additional changes
to help you better
leverage this mode.
Previously, a single isSupported
class variable on the NISession
was all that was necessary
to check if Nearby Interaction
was supported on a given device.
This is now deprecated.
With the addition
of camera assistance,
we've made
the device capabilities
supported by Nearby Interaction
more descriptive
with a new deviceCapabilities
class member on the NISession
that returns a new
NIDeviceCapability object.
At a minimum, checking the
supportsPreciseDistance
Measurement property
is the equivalent
of the now deprecated
isSupported class variable.
Once you've established
that the device supports
the precise distance
measurement,
you should use
NIDeviceCapability
to fully understand
the capabilities available
from Nearby Interaction on the
device running your application.
It is recommended
you tailor your app experience
to the capabilities
of the device
by checking the additional
supportsDirectionMeasurement
and supportsCameraAssistance
properties
of the NIDeviceCapability
object.
Not all devices will support
direction measurements
nor camera assistance,
so be sure to include
experiences that are tailored
to the capabilities
of this device.
In particular,
be mindful to include
distance-only experiences
in order to best support
Apple Watch.
That's all for camera assistance
as a way to enhance
Nearby Interaction with ARKit.
So let's turn our attention now
to accessory background
sessions.
Today, you can use
Nearby Interaction in your app
to allow users to point
to other devices, find friends,
and show controls or other UI
based on distance and direction
to an accessory.
However, when your app
transitions to the background
or when the user locks
the screen on iOS and watchOS,
any running NISessions
are suspended
until the application
returns to the foreground.
This means you needed to focus
on hands-on user experiences
when interacting
with your accessory.
Starting in iOS 16, Nearby
Interaction has gone hands-free.
You're now able to use
Nearby Interaction
to start playing music
when you walk into a room
with a smart speaker, turn on
your eBike when you get on it,
or trigger other hands-free
actions on an accessory.
You can do this
even when the user
isn't actively using your app
via accessory
background sessions.
Let's look at
how you can accomplish
this exciting new capability.
Let's spend just a minute
reviewing the sequence
for how to configure and run
an NISession with an accessory.
You might recognize
this sequence
from last year's
WWDC presentation.
The accessory sends
its Ultra Wideband
accessory configuration data
over to your application
via a data channel,
and you create an
NINearbyAccessoryConfiguration
from this data.
You create an NISession,
set an NISessionDelegate
to get Ultra Wideband
measurements from the accessory.
You run the NISession
with your configuration
and the session will return
sharable configuration data
to setup the accessory
to interoperate
with your application.
After sending this sharable
configuration data
back to the accessory,
you are now able to receive
Ultra Wideband measurements
in your application
and at the accessory.
For all the details
on configuring and running
Nearby Interaction
with third-party accessories,
please review
last year's WWDC session.
Let's look now at how you set up
the new background sessions.
The previous sequence diagram
showed data flowing
between your application
and the accessory.
It is very common to have
the communication channel
between an accessory and your
application use Bluetooth LE.
When paired to the accessory
using Bluetooth LE,
you can enable
Nearby Interaction
to start and continue sessions
in the background.
Let's look closely
at how this is possible.
Today, you can configure
your app to use Core Bluetooth
to discover, connect to,
and exchange data
with Bluetooth LE accessories
while your app
is in the background.
Check out the existing
Core Bluetooth Programming Guide
or the WWDC session from 2017
for more details.
Taking advantage of the powerful
background operations
from Core Bluetooth
to efficiently discover
the accessory and run your
application in the background,
your application can start
an NISession
with a Bluetooth LE accessory
that also supports Ultra
Wideband in the background.
Let's look now at how
the sequence diagram updates
to reflect this new mode.
To interact with this accessory,
first, ensure that it is
Bluetooth LE-paired.
Then, connect to the accessory.
When the accessory generates
its accessory Ultra Wideband
configuration data,
it should both
send it to your application
and populate the Nearby
Interaction GATT service;
more on this next.
Finally, when your
application receives
the accessory's
configuration data, construct an
NINearbyAccessoryConfiguration
object using a new initializer
providing both your accessory's
UWB configuration data
and its Bluetooth
peer identifier.
Run your NISession
with this configuration
and ensure you complete
the setup by receiving
the sharable configuration
in your NISessionDelegate
and send the sharable
configuration to the accessory.
In order for your accessory
to create a relationship
between its Bluetooth identifier
and the Ultra Wideband
configuration,
it must implement the new
Nearby Interaction GATT service.
The Nearby Interaction service
contains a single encrypted
characteristic called
Accessory Configuration Data.
It contains the same
UWB configuration data
used to initialize the
NINearbyAccessoryConfiguration
object.
iOS uses this characteristic
to verify the association
between your Bluetooth peer
identifier and your NISession.
Your app cannot read from
this characteristic directly.
You can find out more
about the details
of this new Nearby Interaction
GATT service
on developer.apple.com/
nearby-interaction.
If your accessory supports
multiple NISessions in parallel,
create multiple instances of
Accessory Configuration Data,
each with a different
NISession's UWB configuration.
That's what's necessary
on the accessory.
Let's turn to what you need
to implement in your application
by diving into some code!
Accessory background sessions
require that the accessory
is LE-paired
to the user's iPhone.
Your app is responsible
for triggering this process.
To do this, implement methods
to scan for your accessory,
connect to it, and discover its
services and characteristics.
Then, implement
a method to read
one of your accessory's
encrypted characteristics.
You only need to do this once.
It will show the user
a prompt to accept pairing.
Accessory background sessions
also require
a Bluetooth connection
to your accessory.
Your app must be able
to form this connection
even when it's backgrounded.
To do this, implement a method
to initiate a connection attempt
to your accessory.
You should do this
even if the accessory
is not within Bluetooth range.
Then, implement
CBManagerDelegate methods
to restore state after your app
is relaunched by Core Bluetooth
and handle when your
connection is established.
Now you're ready to run
an accessory background session.
Create an
NINearbyAccessoryConfiguration
object by providing
both the accessory's
UWB configuration data and its
Bluetooth peer identifier
from the CBPeripheral
identifier.
Run an NISession
with that configuration
and it will run while your app
is backgrounded.
That's it!
Well, there is one more setting
you need to update
for your app in Xcode.
This background mode requires
the Nearby Interaction string
in the UIBackgroundModes array
in your app's Info.plist.
You can also use
Xcode capabilities editor
to add this background mode.
You will also want to ensure
you have
"Uses Bluetooth LE accessories"
enabled to ensure your app
can connect with the accessory
in the background.
One important note
about this new accessory
background session.
When your application
is in the background,
the NISession will continue to
run and will not be suspended,
so Ultra Wideband measurements
are available on the accessory.
You must consume and act on
the Ultra Wideband measurements
on the accessory.
Your application
will not receive runtime,
and you will not receive
didUpdateNearbyObject
delegate callbacks
until your application
returns to the foreground.
When using this new
background mode,
let's review the following
best practices.
Triggering LE pairing
with your accessory
will show the user a prompt
to accept the pairing.
Do this at a time
that is intuitive to the user
why they want to pair
the accessory.
This could be in the setup flow
that it creates the relationship
with the accessory or when
the user clearly indicates
their desire to interact
with the accessory.
While your app is backgrounded,
your NISession
will not be suspended,
but it will not receive
didUpdateNearbyObject
delegate callbacks.
However, your accessory
will receive
Ultra Wideband measurements.
Process these measurements
directly on your accessory
to determine what action
should happen for the user.
Finally, manage battery usage
by only sending data
from your accessory to your app
during a significant
user interaction;
for example, to show
a notification to the user.
That's all you need to know
on background sessions
and leads me to the last topic
on third-party hardware support.
Today, I'm happy to announce
that the previously available
beta U1-compatible
development kits
are now out of beta
and available for wider use.
Please visit developer.apple.com
/nearby-interaction
to find out more about
compatible Ultra Wideband
development kits.
We've also updated
the specification
for accessory manufacturers
to support
the new accessory
background sessions,
including the Nearby Interaction
GATT service,
and it is available
on the same website.
So, let's summarize what we've
discussed in this session.
Nearby Interaction now includes
a new camera-assisted mode
that tightly integrates ARKit
and Nearby Interaction
to provide a seamless experience
for you to create
spatially aware experiences
that guide users
to a nearby object.
The accessory background
sessions enable you to initiate
and extend sessions
into the background
for you to build
a more hands-off experience
for your users.
We've announced
exciting updates
to the third-party compatible
Ultra Wideband hardware support.
That's it for the Nearby
Interaction updates this year.
Download the demos,
reach out with feedback
on the updated capabilities,
review the updated
third-party specification,
and go build amazing apps
with spatial experiences.
Thank you.
♪