♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, everyone!
My name is Ankur Soni.
I'm an engineering manager
on the Maps Services team
here at Apple.
Today, we're going to look at
some exciting new capabilities
coming to the Maps
developer ecosystem.
So let's get started.
Our Maps app offers
various end-user experiences
to Apple customers
around the globe.
We empower developers to create
beautiful geolocation
experiences for their apps
and websites through our MapKit
and MapKit JS offerings.
However, our Apple Maps
developer offering
has always been
very client-centric.
We have listened carefully
to all your great feedback.
You wanted a way to augment
your own data on MapKit
without compromising
on performance or power.
So to round out our ecosystem,
we are excited to introduce
the Apple Maps Server APIs.
We are introducing
four new server APIs:
Geocoding, Reverse Geocoding,
Search,
Estimated Time of Arrival --
or ETA.
These APIs will help you tackle
a variety of use cases
while integrating Maps
into your applications.
With Geocoding APIs,
you can convert an address
to geographic coordinates
latitude and longitude.
Similarly,
with Reverse Geocoding,
you can do the opposite --
go from geographic coordinates
to an address.
With Search API, you can give
your users the capability
to enter a search string
to discover places
like businesses,
points of interest, and more.
Maybe you want to overlay
some of your own data
and present it to the user.
With ETA API,
you can help your customers
get a sense of how far
your business is from them
or do some computations
to find the closest store.
The possibilities are endless!
We think you'll love server APIs
for three important reasons.
You can now deliver a seamless
experience by leveraging
MapKit, MapKit JS, and the new
Apple Maps Server APIs.
This will simplify
your application architecture
giving you a full
Apple Maps stack.
This will make your life
much easier.
For sure, it helped me.
But hey, I'm biased!
The next benefit is
the reduction in network calls.
Many times,
we find ourselves in a situation
where we are making repetitive
and redundant requests
from our users' devices
like an iPhone, iPad,
websites, etcetera.
Maybe you are looking up the
same address over and over again
from your app running
on different user devices.
This causes a lot of network
calls and wasted bandwidth.
Delegating this common operation
to your server
and doing it only once in
the back end using server APIs
will help your application
consume less bandwidth.
A nice side effect of this
is that now your application
is power efficient too, since
some processing is now delegated
to your server using
Apple Maps Server APIs.
Now let's take some of
these APIs for a spin.
Let's say we are building
these contact cards
for your store locator
application.
Here we see three stores
with their addresses
and distance
from the customer location.
In this example,
we'll assume that the customer
has provided their location.
For now, let's focus on building
one of these contact cards.
We'll assume that these
addresses are on a server
which stores and serves the
locations of comic bookstores.
There are many ways
to build this, but for a second,
let's assume we don't have
these new server APIs.
What would a basic architecture
look like?
How would your client
application get this data?
In this diagram, our application
is making a call to the server
to get the list
of store addresses.
The back-end server returns
a list of store addresses
to your client device.
Since we don't have
the server APIs in this example,
now our client application
has to perform various actions
on the address
to build the contact card.
To perform a single task,
a client may have to make
multiple calls
to various back-end services.
Here you can see that
the client app is making a call
directly to
the Apple Maps Server,
either by using MapKit
or MapKit JS.
This chattiness between
a client and a back end
can adversely impact
the performance and scale
of the application.
Over a cellular network
with typically high latency,
using individual requests
in this manner is inefficient
and could result
in broken connectivity
or incomplete requests.
While each request
may be done in parallel,
the application must send,
wait, and process data
for each request
all on separate connections
increasing the chance
of failure.
Finally, you'll have to merge
all the responses on the client.
And while
all these calls happen,
you are showing a spinner
to the user.
Plus, the client device
is using more bandwidth
and power for these extra calls.
That is not
a good user experience.
Now, let's look at
a model architecture
with access
to Apple Maps Server APIs.
You can start using your
back-end server as a gateway
to reduce chattiness between
the client and the services.
Just like before,
here we request a list of stores
to be displayed
from your client.
Next, we make a request
from the server to do geocoding.
We then receive responses
for each API
from the Apple Maps Server.
The comic book server combines
the responses from each service
and sends the response
to the application.
This pattern can reduce
the number of requests
that the application makes
to back-end services,
and improve
application performance
over high-latency networks.
In summary, your client
makes one call to your server
to get the list of stores.
Your server then does
the heavy lifting
to make appropriate API calls
to compose a response
most suited for your user.
So let's go back to our
case study example here.
We'll use Geocoding and ETA API
to get the distance
to the store.
We can use the Geocode API to
find the latitude and longitude
for the store addresses,
which we'll later use
for ETA calculations.
In this example, first,
we are going to take
the address for the comic book
store and URL encode it.
Next, we'll use the Geocode API
and pass this URL-encoded
address as a query parameter.
We'll skip over the
authentication details for now
and come back to it
in a few slides.
In the response, you can see
the latitude and longitude
for the address returned.
We'll repeat
the same process to find
the latitude and longitude
for the customer's address.
This will be later used
for ETA calculations.
As you can see, there are
more fields in the response.
I'll link the detailed
documentation
in the Resources section below.
Now, we can set the origin
and destination on the ETA API
with the data we got
from the Geocode API.
As I mentioned before, we have
the origin latitude, longitude
and the destination
latitude, longitude.
We can specify up to 10
destinations here if needed.
We'll feed that in the ETA API
as origin and as
destination query parameters
which are URL encoded.
The response to the API
is a list of ETAs,
one for each destination
provided.
In this case,
we only have one
since we provided
one destination.
Here for our example, we are
interested in distanceMeters
to calculate the distance
to the store.
With this, we have
all the pieces we need:
the store address
and the distance for the user
to reach your store.
You can also choose
to augment or overlay this data
with your own store information,
like store hours.
In this way, you can leverage
different server APIs
to build your applications.
For other APIs,
please refer to documentation
linked below this talk.
One critical piece we haven't
talked about is authentication.
All the Apple Maps Server APIs
are authenticated.
If you are using MapKit JS,
you are already halfway there.
Apple Maps Server APIs use
the same mechanism as MapKit JS
to authenticate.
First, you'll download
your private key
from your developer account.
You'll then use this private key
to generate a Maps auth token
in JWT format.
There is a detailed doc
about how to generate one
linked below.
You can then exchange
this Maps auth token
using the token API
to get Maps access token.
We'll authenticate the
Maps auth token on the back end
and send back Maps access token.
This is in JWT format
and will be used
for all API interactions.
This access token needs to be
refreshed every 30 minutes
by repeating the highlighted
process here.
Now that we saw how the
authentication flow looks like,
here is a simple example
of how to use the token API
to fetch the access token.
We are using the token API here.
We are passing
the Maps auth token as a header.
You'll get back
a Maps access token
that can be used
to access the API.
This will be in JWT format
and will have standard fields
like expiry, issuedAt, etcetera.
As a convenience,
the expiresInSeconds field
shows for how long
the token is valid for.
In this case, it's 30 minutes.
Keep in mind Maps auth token
is not the same
as Maps access token.
You exchange
the Maps auth token
to get a 30-minute long
Maps access token
to access the server APIs.
Let's take a quick look
at how the API interaction
with Maps access token
looks like.
We'll pass the Maps access token
along with server API call.
It is added as a header
to the API call,
just like we saw
a few slides ago.
The Apple Maps Server will
validate the Maps access token.
Once the validation
is successful,
the Apple Maps Server will
respond with an API response.
Now that I have covered
APIs and authentication,
let me talk about usage limits.
With great power
comes great responsibility,
so use your quota wisely.
There is a daily cap on
how many API calls you can make,
and it's big!
You'll get a quota of 25,000
service calls per day in total.
Keep in mind, calling services
via MapKit JS and server APIs
use the same quota.
If you need more,
please reach out to us.
So, how do you keep track
of all this?
You can view your usage stats
at the Maps developer dashboard.
Anybody using MapKit JS?
This will look
very familiar to you.
The server API usage
is categorized as Services,
which you can see
highlighted here.
When the daily quota
is exceeded,
which means more than
25,000 server API calls,
we'll start rejecting
new service calls
and respond with
HTTP status 429,
which means too many requests.
You should make sure
that the app experience
degrades gracefully
in such scenarios.
In rare scenarios,
when your service
makes an unusual
amount of requests --
maybe it's due to some bug in
your code or infrastructure --
it's possible to get
HTTP status 429 as well.
When you receive HTTP 429,
it is important
not to simply loop repeatedly
in making requests.
A better approach is
to retry with increasing delays
in between attempts.
This approach is known
as exponential backoff.
So, what did we learn today?
We are releasing
four new server APIs.
These APIs are Geocoding,
Reverse Geocoding,
Search, and ETA.
Using these APIs in conjunction
with MapKit and MapKit JS
will help you
better architect your apps
using the Apple Maps stack.
You can optimize redundant
and repetitive calls
by delegating those tasks
to your back-end server
using Apple Maps Server APIs.
Daily quota for these APIs
is 25,000
and is shared with your
MapKit JS service usage.
And that's the new
Apple Maps Server APIs for you.
Be sure to check out the other
sessions mentioned here
and detailed documentation
linked below.
We look forward to seeing
how you take advantage of them.
Thank you!
♪