♪ ♪
Ciao, my name is Geppy Parziale,
and I am a machine learning engineer
here at Apple.
Today, I want to walk you through
the journey of building an app
that uses machine learning
to solve a problem
that would usually require an expert
to perform some very specialized work.
This journey gives me the opportunity
to show you how to add
open source machine learning models
to your apps
and create fantastic new experiences.
During the journey, I will also highlight
a few of the many tools, frameworks,
and APIs available for you
in the Apple development ecosystem
to build apps using machine learning.
When building an app, you, the developer,
go through a series of decisions
that hopefully will bring
the best experience to your users.
And this is also true when adding machine
learning functionality to applications.
During the development, you could ask:
should I use machine learning
to build this feature?
How can I get a machine learning model?
How do I make that model
compatible with Apple platforms?
Will that model work
for my specific use case?
Does it run on the Apple Neural Engine?
So let's take this journey together.
I want to build an app that allows me
to add realistic colors
to my family black and white photos
that I found in an old box in my basement.
Of course, a professional photographer
could do this with some manual work,
spending some time
in a photo editing tool.
Instead, what if I want
to automate this process
and apply the colorization
in just a few seconds?
This seems to be a perfect task
for machine learning.
Apple offers a tremendous amount
of frameworks and tools
that can help you build and integrate
ML functionality in your apps.
They provide everything
from data processing
to model training and inference.
For this journey,
I am going to use a few of them.
But remember, you have many to choose from
depending on the specific machine learning
task that you are developing.
The process I use when developing
a machine learning feature
in my apps goes through a set of stages.
First, I search for the right
machine learning model
in either scientific publication
or specialized website.
I searched for photo colorization,
and I found a model called Colorizer
that may work for what I need.
Here is an example of the colorization
I can get using this model.
Here is another one.
And here is another one. Really great.
Let me show you how it works.
The Colorizer model expects
a black and white image as input.
The Python source code I found converts
any RGB image to a LAB color space image.
This color space has 3 channels:
one represents the image lightness
or L channel,
and the other two represent
the color components.
The color components are discarded
while the lightness becomes
the input of the colorizer model.
The model then estimates
two new color components
that, combined with the input L channel,
provide the resulting image with color.
It's time now to make this model
compatible with my app.
To achieve this, I can convert
the original PyTorch model
to Core ML format using coremltools.
Here is the simple Python script I used
to convert the PyTorch model to Core ML.
First, I import the PyTorch model
architecture and weights.
Then I trace the imported model.
Finally, I convert the PyTorch model
to Core ML and save it.
Once the model is in the Core ML format,
I need to verify
that the conversion worked correctly.
I can do that directly in Python
again using coremltools.
And this is easy.
I import the image in RGB color space
and convert it to Lab color space.
Then I separate the lightness
from the color channels and discard them.
I run the prediction
using the Core ML model.
And finally, compose the input lightness
with the estimated color components
and convert to RGB.
This allows me to verify
that functionality of the converted model
matches the functionality
of the original PyTorch model.
I call this stage Model Verification.
However, there is another
important check to be done.
I need to understand if this model
can run fast enough on my target device.
So I would need to assess
the model on device
and make sure it would provide
the best user experience.
The new Core ML Performance report,
available now in Xcode 14,
performs a time-based analysis
of a Core ML model.
I just need to drag and drop
the model into Xcode
and create a performance report
in a few seconds.
Using this tool,
I can see that estimated prediction time
is almost 90 milliseconds
on an iPad Pro with M1 and iPadOS 16.
And this is perfect
for my photo colorization app.
If you want to know more about
Performance Report in Xcode,
I suggest you to watch this year’s session
"Optimize your Core ML usage".
So Performance Report can help you
make an assessment of the model
and make sure it provides
the best on-device user experience.
Now that I am sure about the functionality
and performance of my model,
let me integrate it into my app.
The integration process is identical
to what I have done until now in Python,
but this time I can do it seamlessly in Swift
using Xcode and all the other tools
you are familiar with.
Remember the model, now in Core ML format,
expects a single channel image
representing its lightness.
So similarly to what I did
previously in Python,
I need to convert any RGB input image
to an image using the Lab color space.
I could write this transformation
in multiple ways:
directly in Swift with vImage,
or using Metal.
Exploring deeper in the documentation,
I found that the Core Image framework
provides something
that can help me with this.
So let me show you how to achieve
the RGB to LAB conversion
and run the prediction
using the Core ML model.
Here is the Swift code
to extract the lightness
from an RGB image
and pass it to the Core ML model.
First, I convert the RGB image
into LAB and extract the lightness.
Then, I convert lightness to a CGImage
and prepare the input
for the Core ML model.
Finally, I run the prediction.
To extract the L channel
from the input RGB image,
I first convert the RGB image
into a LAB image,
using the new CIFilter convertRGBtoLab.
The values of the lightness
are set between 0 and 100.
Then, I multiply the Lab image
with a color matrix
and discard the color channels
and return the lightness to the caller.
Let's now analyze what happens
at the output of the model.
The Core ML model returns
two MLShapedArrays
containing the estimated color components.
So after the prediction, I convert
the two MLShapedArray into two CIImages.
Finally, I combine them
with the model input lightness.
This generates a new LAB image
that I convert to RGB and return it.
To convert the two MLShapedArrays
into two CIImages,
I first extract the values
from each shaped array.
Then, I create two core images
representing the two color channels
and return them.
To combine the lightness
with the estimated color channels,
I use a custom CIKernel that takes
the three channels as input
and returns a CIImage.
Then, I use the new CIFilter
convertLabToRGB
to convert the Lab image to RGB
and return it to the caller.
This is the source code
for the custom CIKernel I use
to combine the lightness
with the two estimated color channels
in a single CIImage.
For more information about
the new CI filters to convert RGB images
to LAB images and vice versa,
please refer to the session
"Display EDR content with Core Image,
Metal, and SwiftUI."
Now that I completed the integration
of this ML feature in my app,
let's see it in action.
But wait.
How will I colorize my old family photos
in real time with my application?
I could spend some time to digitize
each of them and import them in my app.
I think I have a better idea.
What if I use my iPad camera
to scan these photos
and colorize them live?
I think it would be really fun, and I have
everything I need to accomplish this.
But first, I have to solve a problem.
My model needs 90 milliseconds
to process an image.
If I want to process a video,
I would need something faster.
For a smooth user experience,
I'd like to run the device camera
at least 30 fps.
That means the camera will produce
a frame about every 30 milliseconds.
But since the model needs about
90 milliseconds to colorize a video frame,
I am going to lose 2 or 3 frames
during each colorization.
The total prediction time of a model
is a function of both its architecture
as well as the compute units operations
it gets mapped to.
Looking at the performance report again,
I notice that my model has a total
of 61 operations running on a combination
of the neural engine and CPU.
If I want a faster prediction time,
I will have to change the model.
I decided to experiment
with the model's architecture
and explore some alternatives
that may be faster.
However, a change in the architecture
means I need to retrain the network.
Apple offers different solutions
that allow me to train machine learning
models directly on my Mac.
In my case, since the original model
was developed in PyTorch,
I decided to use the new PyTorch on Metal,
so I can take advantage
of the tremendous hardware acceleration
provided by Apple Silicon.
If you are interested in knowing more
about the PyTorch accelerated with Metal,
please check the session,
"Accelerate machine learning with Metal"
Because of this change,
our journey needs to take a step back.
After retraining,
I will have to convert the result
to Core ML format
and run the verification again.
This time, model integration consists
of simply swapping the old model
with the new one.
After retraining a few candidate
alternative models,
I have verified one
that will meet my requirements.
Here it is with
the corresponding performance report.
It runs entirely on the neural engine
and the prediction time is now
around 16 milliseconds,
which works for video.
But Performance Report tells me only one
aspect of the performance of my app.
Indeed, after running my app,
I notice immediately
that colorization is not as smooth
as I expect.
So what happens in my app at runtime?
In order to understand that, I can use
the new Core ML template in Instruments.
Analyzing the initial portion
of the Core ML trace,
after loading the model, I notice
that the app accumulates predictions.
And this is unexpected.
Instead, I'd expect to have
a single prediction per frame.
Zooming in the trace
and checking the very first predictions,
I observe that the app requests
a second Core ML prediction
before the first one is finished.
Here, the Neural Engine is
still working on the first request
when the second is given to Core ML.
Similarly, the third prediction starts
while still processing the second one.
Even after four predictions,
the lag between the request and execution
is already about 20 milliseconds.
Instead, I need to make sure
that a new prediction starts
only if the previous one is finished
to avoid cascading these lags.
While fixing this problem,
I also found out that I accidentally set
the camera frame rate to 60 fps
instead of the desired 30fps.
After making sure that the apps process
a new frame
after the previous prediction completes
and setting the camera frame rate
to 30 fps,
I can see that Core ML dispatches
correctly a single prediction
to the Apple Neural Engine,
and now the app runs smoothly.
So we reached the end of our journey.
Let's test the app
on my old family photos.
Here are my black and white photos
that I found in my basement.
They capture some of the places
in Italy I visited a long time ago.
Here is a great photo
of the Colosseum in Rome.
The color of the walls
and the sky are so realistic.
Let's check this one.
This is Castel del Monte
in the South of Italy.
Really nice.
And this is my hometown, Grottaglie.
Adding colors to these images
triggered so many memories.
Notice that I am applying
the colorization only to the photo
while keeping the rest of the scene
black and white.
Here, I am taking advantage
of the rectangle detection algorithm
available in the Vision framework.
Using VNDetectRectangleRequest,
I can isolate the photo in the scene
and use it as input
to the Colorizer model.
And now let me recap.
During our journey, I explored
the enormous amount of frameworks,
APIs, and tools Apple provides
to prepare, integrate,
and evaluate machine learning
functionality for your apps.
I started this journey
identifying a problem
that required an open source
machine learning model to solve it.
I found an open source model
with desired functionality
and made it compatible
with Apple platforms.
I assessed the model performance
directly on the device
using the new Performance Report.
I integrated the model in my app
using the tools
and the frameworks you are familiar with.
I optimized the model using
the new Core ML Template in Instruments.
With Apple tools and frameworks,
I can take care of each phase
of the development process
directly on Apple devices and platforms
from data preparation, training,
integration, and optimization.
Today, we just scratched the surface
of what you, the developer,
can achieve with the frameworks
and tools Apple provides you.
Please, refer to previous sessions,
linked to this,
for additional inspiring ideas
to bring machine learning to your apps.
Explore and try frameworks and tools.
Take advantage of the great synergy
between software and hardware
to accelerate
your machine learning features
and enrich the user experience
of your apps.
Have a great WWDC, and arrivederci.  ♪ ♪