♪ ♪
Hello and welcome.
I'm Brad Ford from
the Camera Software Engineering team.
In this session, I'll be introducing you
to camera extensions
with CoreMedia IO, which is
a modern camera driver architecture
for macOS
and a replacement for DAL plug-ins.
DAL plug-ins are a technology
that allows you to create camera drivers
for hardware that plugs into a Mac,
or virtual cameras.
They've been around for a very long time–
since macOS 10.7.
DAL plug-ins provide the power
to extend macOS as a rich media platform,
bringing support for great third party
camera products to pros and consumers.
It's part of what makes the Mac, the Mac.
But DAL plug-ins have some problems.
They load untrusted code
directly into an app's process,
making it vulnerable to crashes
if the plug-in has bugs
or to malware attack.
For this reason,
they don't work with Apple apps
such as FaceTime,
QuickTime Player, and PhotoBooth.
They also don't work
with many third party camera apps,
unless those apps intentionally
disable library validation,
or the user turns off
system integrity protection.
Neither of these are practices recommended
as they make the system
less secure and less stable.
They're difficult to develop too.
They carry a C API circa 2011
and a thick SDK of C++ helper classes
for you to learn.
And on top of all that,
they're sparsely documented.
It's time for an upgrade.
macOS 12.3 introduces
a thoroughly modern replacement
for DAL plug-ins called Camera Extensions…
An architecture that places
user security first.
Let's learn how it works.
First, I'll provide a technology overview.
Next, I'll show you how to build
a camera extension from scratch.
Next, I'll introduce the main classes
and functions of the API.
I'll explain how CoreMedia IO Extensions
can be used as output devices.
And finally, I'll cover
our DAL plug-in deprecation plan.
Let's get started.
Camera extensions, otherwise known
as CoreMedia IO extensions,
are a new way to package and deliver
camera drivers to Mac applications.
They're secure.
Your extension code is cordoned off
into its own daemon process
that's sandboxed and run as a role user.
All the buffers your extension provides
are validated
before being delivered to an app.
They're fast.
The framework handles the IPC layers
between your extension process
and the app,
with an emphasis on performance.
The framework can also take care
of delivering buffers
to multiple simultaneous clients.
They're modern.
Your extension can be written
in either Swift or Objective-c.
They're simple.
There are just a few classes to learn,
a few protocols to implement
in order to get up and running.
The framework takes care
of the boilerplate code.
They're easy to deploy.
You can ship them as apps
in the App Store.
And camera extensions are
100% backward compatible
with existing AVFoundation capture APIs.
Camera extensions shows up just like
the built-in camera in all camera apps,
including Apple apps.
Here's how an example
of how a camera extension might appear
in the FaceTime camera picker.
What kind of experiences can you build
with a camera extension?
Let's study three common uses.
The simplest use
is a software-only camera,
such as a camera that displays color bars,
a unique test pattern,
programmatically generated images
at various frame rates or resolutions,
or a camera that streams
pre-rendered content,
such as frames in a movie,
to test A/V synchronization.
The second use case is a driver
for a camera that you intend
to physically plug into a Mac
or discover wirelessly.
Camera extensions fully support
hot plugging and unplugging.
To address your hardware,
you have a few choices.
The preferred method is to use
a DriverKit Extension, or DEXT,
which runs entirely in user space.
If your hardware must be addressed
at the kernel level,
you can use
the legacy IOVideoFamily kext path.
Development of new kext code
is discouraged
as kexts are inherently less secure
and can contribute to system instability.
Apple provides a class compliant extension
for USB video class, or UVC, cameras.
It works great for cameras
that conform to the UVC spec.
If, however, you need to support
a USB camera
that uses nonstandard protocol,
has additional features
outside the UVC spec,
you can create a camera extension
that overrides Apple's UVC extension,
allowing you to claim
a particular product and vendor ID.
If you're interested in learning more
about it, please refer to the article
at developer.apple.com entitled
"Overriding the default
USB video class extension."
It explains how to create
a minimal DEXT bundle
and which IOKitPersonalities keys
you need to override in your Info.plist.
A third common use is a creative camera,
a hybrid between software and hardware.
Your extension accesses a video stream
from another physical camera
attached to the Mac,
applies an effect to those buffers,
and sends them along to clients
as a new camera stream.
Or a creative camera that accesses
video streams from several cameras,
composites them,
and sends them along to the app.
A creative camera like this
might use a configuration app
to control the compositing
or parameterize filters.
The possibilities for creative camera
are really endless.
Now that we've explored
the primary use cases,
let's look at the anatomy
of a CoreMedia IO Extension.
First the "CoreMedia IO" part.
CoreMedia IO is a low level framework
for publishing
or discovering camera drivers.
You already know
that it contains the legacy DAL API
and the new camera extension API
that replaces it.
But it also contains a powerful set
of low level C APIs
for app developers to find
and inspect cameras on the system.
Now, how about that "Extension" part?
CoreMedia IO Extensions are built
on top of the SystemExtensions framework
which first appeared in macOS Catalina.
It obviates the need
for a throw-away installer.
Instead, you ship your extension
inside an app.
The extension executable
lives within the app bundle.
By making calls
into the SystemExtensions framework,
your app can install, upgrade,
or downgrade your extension
for all users on the system.
And uninstalling is a snap.
Delete the app
and the SystemExtensions framework
uninstalls your camera extension
for all users.
This delivery mechanism is
approved for App Store use,
making it easy to deploy
your camera extension to a wide audience.
To learn more about
the system extensions framework,
you can read the documentation
at developer.apple.com/
documentation/systemextensions.
And be sure to check out
the WWDC 2019 video entitled
"System Extensions and DriverKit."
That's it for our technology overview
of camera extensions.
Now, let's actually build one.
Here's a quick demo of how to get
a camera extension up and running
in a matter of minutes.
I've created a single window macOS
application in Xcode, called ExampleCam.
At this point,
I've only added a few lines of code.
The App Delegate is unchanged.
In the main storyboard,
I've added two buttons,
one to install
and one to uninstall the extension,
plus a text field to display status.
In the ViewController class,
I've added IBActions
to hook up the install
and uninstall buttons.
These functions create
OSSystemExtensionRequests
to either activate
or deactivate the extension
found within the app's bundle.
At the bottom,
I've added skeletal implementations
of the OSSystemExtensionRequestDelegate
functions that log status.
The app's entitlements file
has the usual App Sandbox=YES
and it defines an AppGroup.
I've only added one new key here,
the "System Extension" key,
which is required if your app
installs system extensions.
At this point, if I run the app
and click on the Install Extension button,
I'll just get a fatal error,
since the app is looking
for an extension in the bundle
that doesn't exist yet.
To create and embed a system extension,
I go to File,
New, Target,
and under macOS,
I scroll all the way down to the bottom
where the System Extensions are located.
Then I pick "Camera Extension," hit next,
give it a name–I'll choose "Extension"–
I'll make sure that
"Embedded in Application" is set,
and then I click finish.
Inside the new extension folder,
I get four new files.
The Info.plist identifies it
as a CMIOExtension
by defining its MachServiceName.
This is a critical piece of information.
CoreMedia IO's registerassistant will not
launch your extension unless it's present.
While we're here,
let's give it a usage description
for the system extension.
The entitlements file shows
that it's app sandboxed.
And I need to ensure here
that my extension's app group is prefixed
by the MachServiceName
in order for it to pass validation.
So I'll copy and paste that over
from the app extension
to the extensions entitlements file.
And that's it.
The main.swift file serves
as your extension's entry point
and starts the service.
And the ExtensionProvider.swift file
gives us a fully functional camera.
It contains a DeviceSource,
a StreamSource, and a ProviderSource,
all that you need to create
a pure software camera.
Not a bad little template.
In this file, I'll search
for "SampleCapture"
and I'll replace with "ExampleCam,"
so that my camera's name, model,
and manufacturer all have the proper name.
That's it. Let's compile and run it.
When I hit the Install button,
uh-oh, it fails.
That's because system extensions
can only be installed by apps
residing in /Applications.
Let's move it and try again.
This time, it succeeds.
I'm prompted to Allow
the blocked extension to install
by authenticating in System Settings,
where I find Privacy & Security,
and click the Allow button.
I authenticate with my password,
and then I see that my result has changed
to 0 for "no error."
If I use the systemextensionsctl
list tool,
I confirm that I've succeeded,
and now I have one extension active
on my system.
Now I can open any camera app
and find and admire my work.
Let's launch FaceTime.
ExampleCam shows up in the camera picker.
It sort of looks like the old Pong game
from the '70s,
drawing a horizontal white line that moves
up and down the frame
at 60 frames per second.
To get rid of the camera,
all I have to do is delete the app.
The system prompts me to confirm
that I'm also uninstalling the extension
by deleting the app.
The ExampleCam demo shows just how easy
it is make a software camera from scratch.
Now let's take it up a notch
by turning that software camera
into a creative camera.
I call this second example CIFilterCam.
The CI stands for CoreImage,
a framework
with all sorts of effects filters
that you can apply to stills or video.
To create CIFilterCam,
I began with the ExampleCam shell,
but decided to make the app
a configuration app
as well as an installer.
I've added a camera picker button,
a filter picker button,
and an effect bypass button.
I've also added a view
for live video preview.
This is a standard view
backed by an AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
to show you
what the Filter Camera is doing.
By unchecking the bypass button,
I can see various filters
applied to the video,
from color effects
to distortion filters.
I'm kind of partial
to the bump distortion.
I can apply these
to the built-in FaceTime camera
or to any physical camera
attached to my Mac.
I've got my iPhone nearby
set up as a Continuity Camera.
Let's use that.
The CIFilterCam app is nothing special
in and of itself.
Just an effects camera app.
Where it really gets interesting, though,
is when you realize that the app
is a front end to a virtual filter camera
that all apps can use.
I'll launch FaceTime and PhotoBooth
and make sure both of them are
pointed at the CIFilterCam.
Now, as I change filters
in my configuration app,
every app using CIFilterCam
changes in tandem.
If I pick a different source camera,
every camera app picks up the change.
Every button click in the app
translates to a simple property call
to the filter cam extension, telling it,
"Hey, extension, use this camera,"
or, "Hey, extension,
use this other filter."
Or this other filter.
Support for running a hardware camera
inside your extension
requires macOS Ventura.
You also need to add
the com.apple.security.device.camera key
to your extension's entitlements file,
indicating that you will be using
another camera.
And since you'll be using a camera,
the user will be prompted
to grant permission to your extension,
so you must provide
an NSCameraUsageDescription
in your Info.plist.
That wraps up the basics
of building a camera extension.
Now let's move on to the APIs.
At the bottom of the stack
are daemon processes,
one for each first
or third party camera extension.
Within a camera app process,
there are several layers at play,
beginning with the private framework code
that talks to your camera extension
over IPC.
One level up is another private layer
that translates
CoreMedia IO Extension calls
to legacy DAL plug-in calls.
Up again,
we find the public CoreMedia IO APIs
that publish DAL plug-ins.
To the client of this interface,
there's no difference
between CoreMedia IO Extensions
and DAL plug-ins.
Everything looks like a DAL plug-in.
And finally, at the top is AVFoundation,
which is a client of CoreMedia IO.
It re-publishes DAL plug-ins
as AVCaptureDevices.
Contrast this with the legacy
DAL plug-in architecture.
DAL plug-ins may or may not include
a daemon piece,
but all of them run code
loaded by the CoreMedia IO framework
directly in the app process.
This leaves the app vulnerable to malware.
Camera extensions remove
this attack vector completely.
Your extension must be app sandboxed,
or it won't be allowed to run.
Apple's registerassistantservice
identifies it
by its CMIOExtensionMachServiceName
and launches it as a role user account
called _cmiodalassistants.
Sandboxd applies
a custom sandbox profile to your process.
It's tailored for camera use cases.
The custom sandbox profile
allows you to communicate
over the common hardware interfaces
you would expect.
USB, Bluetooth, WiFi–
as a client but not a server
that opens ports–
and even Firewire.
It also allows your extension to read
and write from its own container and tmp.
The camera extension sandbox profile
is more locked down than a regular app.
Some examples of things you can't do are
forking, exec'ing, or posix spawning
a child process,
accessing the window server,
making a connection
to the foreground user account,
or registering your own mach services
in the global namespace.
If, as you develop your extension,
you find the sandbox too restrictive
for a legitimate capture case,
please provide us feedback
through Feedback Assistant
and we'll carefully consider
loosening restrictions.
The earlier architecture diagram
showed your camera extension's
daemon process
passing buffers directly to the app layer.
There's actually one more layer
of security involved.
Between your daemon and the app
is a proxy service
called registerassistantservice.
It enforces transparency,
consent, and control policy.
When an app tries to use a camera
for the first time,
the system asks the user if it's okay.
That consent needs to be granted
for all cameras,
not just the built-in ones.
The proxy service handles
this consent on your behalf.
If the user has denied camera access,
the proxy stops buffers
from going to that app.
It also handles attribution–
it lets the system know
that a particular camera is in use
by a particular app
so that power consumed by your daemon
can be attributed to the app
that's using your camera.
CoreMedia IO Extensions have
four main classes:
Provider, Device, and Stream.
Providers have devices
and devices have streams,
and all three of them can have properties.
You create
each of these three main classes
by providing a source,
respectively, a ProviderSource,
DeviceSource, and StreamSource.
The ExtensionProvider is
your lowest level object.
It lets you add and remove devices
as needed, such as for hot plug events.
It gets informed of the client processes
as they try to connect,
which gives you an opportunity
to limit your device publishing
to certain apps.
It also consults your provider source
object for property implementations.
Here's what your extension's
main entry point might look like.
You create your own
ExtensionProviderSource,
which conforms to
the CMIOExtensionProviderSource protocol
and creates an ExtensionProvider.
To start your service,
you call the provider class method
startService
and pass your provider instance.
ExtensionProvider implements
two read only properties
that do not change
for the life of your extension.
The manufacturer
and the name of your provider.
Both of these are strings.
Next up is the CMIOExtensionDevice.
It manage streams,
adding or removing them as needed.
Your device can present multiple streams,
but be aware that AVFoundation ignores
all but the first input stream.
When you create a device,
you provide a device source,
as well as a localized name,
a deviceID as a UUID,
and, optionally, a legacyID string.
These properties percolate
all the way up to AVFoundation.
Your device's localizedName becomes
the AVCaptureDevice's localizedName.
Your specified deviceID becomes
the AVCaptureDevice's uniqueIdentifier,
unless you also provide a legacyDeviceID.
You only need to provide this
if you're modernizing a DAL plug-in
and need to maintain
backward compatibility
with the uniqueIdentifier
you've previously shipped.
If you provide a legacyDeviceID,
AVCaptureDevice will use it
as the uniqueIdentifier.
You create your CMIOExtensionDevice
with a CMIOExtensionDeviceSource,
which may optionally implement
other properties,
such as deviceModel,
which should be the same
for all cameras of the same model.
isSuspended should be implemented
if your device can enter
a suspended state,
such as if it has a privacy iris.
The built-in cameras on Apple laptops
enter the suspended state
when the clamshell is closed.
Your device's transport type
reveals how it's connected,
such as via USB, Bluetooth, or Firewire.
Lastly, if you have a microphone
physically paired with your camera,
you can expose it as a linked device.
All of these properties are read only.
Next up is the all-important
CMIOExtensionStream,
which does the heavy lifting
in the CMIOExtension.
It publishes video formats
and defines their valid frame rates
and configures the active format.
It uses a standard clock,
such as the host time clock,
or provides its own custom clock
to drive the timing
of each buffer it produces.
And most importantly,
it sends sample buffers to clients.
Your extension stream source publishes
CMIOExtensionStreamFormats.
Those become AVCaptureDeviceFormats.
Clients can read and write
the active format index
to change the active format.
The frame duration, which is equivalent
to max frame rate.
And max frame duration,
which is the same as min frame rate.
The DAL plug-in world exposes
a fourth interface called DAL controls.
Plug-in developers use these to expose
features such as auto exposure,
brightness, sharpness, pan and zoom,
et cetera.
While powerful,
they've been implemented inconsistently,
so it's difficult for app developers
to use them.
In the CMIOExtension architecture,
we don't offer a DAL control replacement.
Instead, everything is a property.
You've already learned about
many standard properties at the provider,
device, and stream level.
You can also make
your own custom properties
and propagate them to the app layer,
just as I did in the CIFilterCam demo.
CoreMedia IO's C property interface
uses a C struct
to identify a property's selector,
scope, and element.
These are considered its address.
The selector is the name of the property
as a four-character code,
such as cust for custom.
The scope can be global, input, or output,
and the element can be
any number you want.
The main element is always zero.
CMIOExtensions let you bridge
your properties to the old world
by coding property address elements
into a custom property name.
First, the characters 4cc_,
then the selector, scope, and element
as four character codes
separated by underscores.
Using this method, you can communicate
any string or data value to the app layer.
AVFoundation doesn't work
with custom properties,
so you must stick
to the CoreMedia IO C API
if your configuration app needs
to work with custom properties.
That's our high-level look at the API.
Now let's talk about output devices.
A lesser known feature of DAL plug-ins
is their ability to present
the opposite of a camera–an output device–
which consumes video from an app
in real time rather than provides it.
This is the "O" part of CoreMedia IO.
Input and Output.
Output devices
are common in the pro video world.
Some common uses are print-to-tape,
where a video signal is sent
to an external recorder,
or real-time preview monitoring,
such as on a pro deck with SDI inputs.
One important thing to note
is that output devices have
no AVFoundation API equivalent.
To send frames to an output device,
you must use the CoreMedia IO C API
directly.
CMIOExtension streams are created
with a direction
of either source or sink.
Sink streams consume data from an app.
Clients feed your sink stream by inserting
sample buffers into a simple queue.
That translates to a consumeSampleBuffer
call in your extension,
and once you've consumed that buffer,
you notify them
with notifyScheduledOutputChanged.
There are a number of stream properties
specific to output devices.
They mainly deal with the queue sizing,
how many frames to buffer before starting,
and signaling
when all data has been consumed.
Now on to our fifth
and final topic of the day.
Earlier in the presentation,
I showed this diagram
of the DAL plug-in architecture
and I highlighted
its many security problems.
We've addressed these shortcomings
with Camera Extensions
and are fully committed
to their continued development.
They are the path forward.
So what does that mean for DAL plug-ins?
It means the end is near.
As of macOS 12.3,
DAL plug-ins are already deprecated,
so you get a compilation warning
when building.
That's a good start, but it's not enough.
As long as legacy DAL plug-ins
are allowed to load,
camera apps will still be at risk.
To fully address security vulnerabilities
and make the system
more robust for all users,
we plan to disable DAL plug-ins entirely
in the next major release
after macOS Ventura.
What does this mean for you?
Well, we hope the message is clear.
If you currently maintain a DAL plug-in,
now is the time to begin
porting your code to a Camera Extension.
And please,
let us know what friction you encounter.
We are eager to address these issues
and provide a rich feature set.
We really look forward
to working with you.
This concludes today's presentation
on camera extensions for macOS.
We can't wait to see what fresh
and creative camera experiences
you'll bring to the Mac.
And hope you have fun doing it.