[upbeat music]
Ron Santos: Hey, hope you're well.
I'm Ron Santos, an input engineer.
Today I’m here to talk to you
about capturing machine-readable codes
and text from a video feed,
or, as we like to call it, data scanning.
What exactly do we mean by data scanning?
It’s simply a way of using a sensor,
like a camera, to read data.
Typically that data comes
in the form of text.
For example,
a receipt with interesting information
like telephone numbers, dates, and prices.
Or maybe data comes
as a machine-readable code,
like the ubiquitous QR code.
You’ve probably
used a data scanner before,
maybe in the Camera app
or by using the Live Text features
introduced in iOS 15.
And I bet you’ve used apps
in your day-to-day life
with their own custom scanning experience.
But what if you had
to build your own data scanner?
How would you do it?
The iOS SDK has more
than one solution for you,
depending on your needs.
One option is that you could
use the AVFoundation framework
to set up the camera graph,
connecting inputs and outputs
to a session and configuring it
to yield AVMetadataObjects
like machine-readable codes.
If you also wanted to capture text,
another option would be
to combine both the AVFoundation
and the Vision frameworks together.
In this diagram,
instead of metadata output,
you create video data output.
The video data output results
in the delivery of sample buffers
that can be fed
to the Vision framework for use with text
and barcode recognition requests,
resulting in Vision observation objects.
For more on using Vision
for data scanning,
check out the “Extract document data
using Vision” from WWDC21.
Okay, so that’s using AVFoundation
and Vision for data scanning.
In iOS 16, we have a new option
that encapsulates all of that for you.
Introducing the DataScannerViewController
in the VisionKit framework.
It combines the features
of AVFoundation and Vision
specifically for the purpose
of data scanning.
The DataScannerViewController users
are treated to features like
a live camera preview,
helpful guidance labels,
item highlighting,
tap-to-focus
which is also used for selection,
and lastly,
pinch-to-zoom to get a closer look.
And let’s talk about features
for developers like you.
The DataScannerViewController
is a UIViewController subclass
that you can present however you choose.
Coordinates for recognized items
are always in view coordinates,
saving you from converting
from image space,
to Vision coordinates,
to view coordinates.
You’ll also be able to limit
the active portion of the view
by specifying a region-of-interest,
which is also in view coordinates.
For text recognition,
you can specify content types
to limit the type of text you find.
And for machine-readable codes,
you can specify exactly
which symbologies to look for.
I get it;
I use your apps, and I understand
that data scanning is only a small portion
of their functionality.
But it could require a lot of code.
With DataScannerViewController,
our goal is
to perform the common tasks for you,
so you can focus your time elsewhere.
Next, I’ll walk you
through adding it to your app.
Let’s start
with the privacy usage description.
When apps try to capture video,
iOS asks the user
to grant their explicit permission
to access the camera.
You’ll want to provide a descriptive
message justifying your need.
To do that,
add a “privacy - camera usage description”
to your app’s Info.plist file.
Remember, be as descriptive as possible,
so users know what they’re agreeing to.
Now onto the code.
Wherever you would like
to present a data scanner,
start by importing VisionKit.
Next, because data scanning
isn’t supported on all devices,
use the isSupported class property
to hide any buttons or menus
exposing the functionality,
so users aren’t presented
with something they can’t use.
If you’re curious,
any 2018 and newer iPhone and iPad devices
with the Apple Neural Engine
support data scanning.
You’ll also want
to check for availability.
Recall the privacy usage description?
Scanning is available if the user
approves the app for camera access
and if the device is free
of any restrictions,
like the Camera access restriction
set here,
in Screen Time’s Content
& Privacy Restrictions.
Now you’re ready
to configure an instance.
That’s done by first specifying the types
of data you’re interested in.
For example,
you can scan for both QR codes and text.
You can optionally pass a list
of languages for the text recognizer
to use as a hint
for various processing aspects,
like language correction.
If you have an idea what languages
to expect, list them out.
It’s especially useful when two languages
have similar looking scripts.
If you do not provide any languages,
the user’s preferred languages
are used by default.
You can also request
a specific text content type.
In this example,
I want my scanner to look for URLs.
Now that you stated the types
of data to recognize,
you can create your DataScanner instance.
In the previous example,
I specified a barcode symbology,
a recognition language,
and a text content type.
Let me take a moment to explain
the other options for each of those.
For barcode symbologies,
we support all the same symbologies
as Vision’s barcode detector.
In terms of languages,
as part of the LiveText feature,
DataScannerViewController
supports the same exact languages.
And in iOS 16, I’m happy to say we’re
adding support for Japanese and Korean.
Of course,
this can change again in future.
So use the
supportedTextRecognitionLanguages
class property to retrieve
the most up to date list.
Finally, when scanning for text
with specific semantic meaning,
the DataScannerViewController
can find these seven types.
We’re now ready to present
the Data Scanner to the user.
Present it like any other view controller,
going fullscreen,
using a sheet, or adding it
to another view hierarchy altogether.
It’s all up to you.
Afterwards,
when presentation completes,
call startScanning()
to begin looking for data.
So now I want to take a step back
and spend some time going
over Data Scanner’s
initialization parameters.
I used one here, recognizedDataTypes.
But there are others that can
help you customize your experience.
Let’s go through each one.
recognizedDataTypes allows you
to specify what kind of data to recognize.
Text, machine-readable codes,
and what types of each.
qualityLevel can be balanced,
fast, or accurate.
Fast will sacrifice resolution
in favor of speed in scenarios
where you expect large
and easily-legible items,
like text on signs.
Accurate will give you the best accuracy,
even with small items like
micro QR codes or tiny serial numbers.
I recommend starting with balanced,
which should work great for most cases.
recognizesMultipleItems
gives you the option to look
for one or more items in the frame,
like if you want
to scan multiple barcodes at a time.
When it’s false,
the center-most item is recognized
by default until the user taps elsewhere.
Enable high frame rate tracking
when you draw highlights.
It allows the highlights
to follow items as closely as possible
when the camera moves
or the scene changes.
Enable pinch-to-zoom or disable it.
We also have methods you can use
to modify the zoom level yourself.
When you enable guidance,
labels show at the top
of the screen to help direct the user.
And, finally, you can enable
system highlighting if you need it,
or you can disable it to draw
your own custom highlighting.
Now that you know how
to present the data scanner,
let’s talk about how you’d
ingest the recognized items,
and also how you’d
draw your own custom highlights.
First, provide a delegate
to the data scanner.
Now that you have a delegate,
you can implement
the dataScanner didTapOn method,
which is called
when the user taps on an item.
With it, you’ll receive an instance
of this new type RecognizeItem.
RecognizedItem is an enum that holds text
or a barcode as an associated value.
For text, the transcription
property holds the recognized string.
For barcodes,
if its payload contains a string,
you can retrieve it
with the payloadStringValue.
Two other things you should know
about RecognizedItem:
First, each recognized item
has a unique identifier you can use
to track an item throughout its lifetime.
That lifetime starts
when the item is first seen
and ends when it’s no longer in view.
And second,
each RecognizedItem has a bounds property.
The bounds isn’t a rect,
but it consists of four points,
one for each corner.
Next, let’s talk
about three related delegate methods
that are called when recognized items
in the scene change.
The first is didAdd,
called when items
in the scene are newly recognized.
If you wanted to create
your own custom highlight,
you’d create one here for each new item.
You can keep track of the highlights
using the ID from its associated item.
And when adding your new view
to the view hierarchy,
add them
to DataScanner’s overlayContainerView,
so they appear above the camera preview,
but below any other supplemental chrome.
The next delegate method is didUpdate,
which is called when the items move
or the camera moves.
It can also be called when transcription
for recognized text change.
They change because
the longer the scanner sees the text,
the more accurate it’ll be
with its transcription.
Use the IDs from the updated items
to retrieve your highlights
from the dictionary you just created,
and then animate the views
to their newly updated bounds.
And finally,
the didRemove delegate method,
which is called when items
are no longer visible in the scene.
In this method,
you can forget about any highlight views
you associated
with the removed items,
and you can remove them
from the view hierarchy.
In summary, if you draw
your own highlights over items,
those three delegate methods
will be crucial
for you to control animating highlights
into the scene,
animating their movement,
and animating them out.
And for each of those three
previous delegate methods,
you’ll also be given an array
of all the items currently recognized.
That may come in handy
for text recognition
because the items are placed
in their natural reading order,
meaning the user would
read the item at index 0
before the item at index 1 and so on.
That’s an overview of how
to use the DataScannerViewController.
Before wrapping up, I wanted
to quickly mention a few other features,
like capturing photos.
You can call the capturePhoto method,
which will asynchronously return
a high quality UIImage.
And if you aren’t
creating custom highlights,
you might not need
these three delegate methods.
Instead, you can
use the recognizedItem property.
It’s an AsyncStream that will be
continuously updated as the scene changes.
Thanks for hanging out.
Remember,
the iOS SDK gives you options
for creating computer vision workflows
with the AVFoundation
and Vision frameworks.
But maybe you’re
creating an app that scans text
or machine-readable codes
with a live video feed,
like a Pick-and-pack app,
a back-of-the-warehouse app,
or a point-of-sale app.
If so, then give
the DataScannerViewController
in VisionKit a look.
As I went over today, it has a number
of initialization parameters
and delegate methods that you can use
to provide a custom experience
that matches your app’s style and needs.
And finally,
I wanted to give a shout out
to the “Add Live Text interaction
to your app” session,
where you can learn about VisionKit’s
Live Text abilities for static images.
Until next time, peace.
[upbeat music]