♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Ben,
and I'm an engineer
on the Core ML team.
Today I'm going to show some
of the exciting new features
being added to Core ML.
The focus of these features
is to help you
optimize your Core ML usage.
In this session,
I'll go over performance tools
that are now available to give
you the information you need
to understand and optimize
your model's performance
when using Core ML.
Then I'll go over
some enhanced APIs
which will enable you
to make those optimizations.
And lastly,
I'll give an overview
of some additional
Core ML capabilities
and integration options.
Let me begin with
the performance tools.
To give some background,
I'll start by summarizing
the standard workflow
when using Core ML
within your app.
The first step
is to choose your model.
This may be done
in a variety of ways,
such as using Core ML tools
to convert a PyTorch
or TensorFlow model
to Core ML format,
using an already-existing
Core ML model,
or using Create ML
to train and export your model.
For more details
on model conversion
or to learn about Create ML,
I recommend checking out
these sessions.
The next step is to integrate
that model into your app.
This involves bundling the model
with your application
and using the Core ML APIs
to load and run inference
on that model
during your app's execution.
The last step is to optimize
the way you use Core ML.
First, I'll go over
choosing a model.
There are many aspects
of a model
that you may want to consider
when deciding if you should use
that model within your app.
You also may have multiple
candidates of models
you'd like to select from,
but how do you decide
which one to use?
You need to have a model
whose functionality
will match the requirements of
the feature you wish to enable.
This includes understanding
the model's accuracy
as well as its performance.
A great way to learn about
a Core ML model
is by opening it in Xcode.
Just double-click on any model,
and it will bring up
the following.
At the top,
you'll find the model type,
its size, and the operating
system requirements.
In the General tab,
it shows additional details
captured in
the model's metadata,
its compute
and storage precision,
and info, such as class labels
that it can predict.
The Preview tab
is for testing out your model
by providing example inputs
and seeing what it predicts.
The Predictions tab displays
the model's inputs and outputs,
as well as the types and sizes
that Core ML
will expect at runtime.
And finally, the Utilities tab
can help with model encryption
and deployment tasks.
Overall, these views give you
a quick overview
of your model's functionality
and preview of its accuracy.
But what about
your model's performance?
The cost of loading a model,
the amount of time
a single prediction takes,
or what hardware it utilizes,
may be critical factors
for your use case.
You may have hard targets
related to real-time
streaming data constraints
or need to make key design
decisions around user interface
depending
on perceived latency.
One way to get insight
into the model's performance
is to do an initial integration
into your app
or by creating a small prototype
which you can instrument
and measure.
And since performance
is hardware dependent,
you would likely want
to do these measurements
on a variety
of supported hardware.
Xcode and Core ML
can now help you with this task
even before writing
a single line of code.
Core ML now allows you
to create performance reports.
Let me show you.
[CLICK]
I now have
the Xcode model viewer open
for the YOLOv3
object detection model.
Between the Predictions
and Utilities tabs,
there is now a Performance tab.
To generate
a performance report,
I'll select the plus icon
at the bottom left,
select the device
I'd like to run on --
which is my iPhone --
click next,
then select which compute units
I'd like Core ML to use.
I'm going to leave it on All,
to allow Core ML
to optimize for latency
with all available
compute units.
Now I'll finish
by pressing Run Test.
To ensure the test can run,
make sure the selected device
is unlocked.
It shows a spinning icon
while the performance report
is being generated.
To create the report,
the model is sent over
to the device,
then there are several
iterations of compile,
load, and predictions
which are run with the model.
Once those are complete,
the metrics in the performance
report are calculated.
Now it's run the model
on my iPhone,
and it displays
the performance report.
At the top,
it shows some details
about the device
where the test was run
as well as which compute units
were selected.
Next it shows statistics
about the run.
The median prediction time
was 22.19 milliseconds
and the median load time
was about 400 ms.
Also, if you plan to compile
your model on-device,
this shows the compilation time
was about 940 ms.
A prediction time of around
22 ms tells me that this model
can support about
45 frames per second
if I want to run it
in real time.
Since this model contains
a neural network,
there's a layer view
displayed towards the bottom
of the performance report.
This shows the name
and type of all of the layers,
as well as which compute unit
each layer ran on.
A filled-in checkmark means
that the layer was executed
on that compute unit.
An unfilled checkmark means
that the layer is supported
on that compute unit,
but Core ML did not choose
to run it there.
And an empty diamond means
that the layer is not supported
on that compute unit.
In this case,
54 layers were run on the GPU,
and 32 layers
were run on the Neural Engine.
You can also filter the layers
by a compute unit
by clicking on it.
That was how
you can use Xcode 14
to generate performance reports
for your Core ML models.
This was shown for running
on an iPhone,
but it will allow you to test
on multiple operating system
and hardware combinations,
without having to write
a single line of code.
Now that you've chosen
your model,
the next step is to integrate
this model into your app.
This involves bundling
the model with your app
and making use of Core ML APIs
to load the model
and make predictions with it.
In this case, I've built an app
that uses Core ML style transfer
models to perform style transfer
on frames from
a live camera session.
It's working properly;
however, the frame rate
is slower than I'd expect,
and I'd like to understand why.
This is where you'd move on
to step three,
which is to optimize
your Core ML usage.
Generating a performance report
can show the performance
a model is capable of achieving
in a stand-alone environment;
however, you also need a way
to profile the performance
of a model that's running
live in your app.
For this, you can now use
the Core ML Instrument
found in the Instruments app
in Xcode 14.
This Instrument allows you
to visualize the performance
of your model when it runs
live in your app,
and helps you identify
potential performance issues.
Let me show
how it can be used.
So I'm in Xcode
with my style transfer app
workspace open,
and I'm ready
to profile the app.
I'll force-click
on the Run button
and select Profile.
This will install
the latest version of the code
on my device
and open Instruments for me
with my targeted device
and app selected.
Since I want to profile
my Core ML usage,
I'm going to select
the Core ML template.
This template includes
the Core ML Instrument,
as well as several
other useful Instruments
which will help you profile
your Core ML usage.
To capture a trace,
I'll simply press Record.
The app is now running
on my iPhone.
I will let it run
for a few seconds
and use a few different styles.
And now I'll end the trace
by pressing the Stop button.
Now I have my Instruments trace.
I'm going to focus on
the Core ML Instrument.
The Core ML Instrument
shows all of the Core ML events
that were captured in the trace.
The initial view groups all
of the events into three lanes:
Activity, Data, and Compute.
The Activity lane shows
top-level Core ML events
which have a one-to-one
relationship
with the actual Core ML APIs
that you would call directly,
such as loads and predictions.
The Data lane shows events
in which Core ML
is performing data checks
or data transformations
to make sure that
it can safely work
with the model's inputs
and outputs.
The Compute lane shows
when Core ML sends
compute requests
to specific compute units,
such as the Neural Engine,
or the GPU.
You can also select
the Ungrouped view
where there is an individual
lane for each event type.
At the bottom, there's the
Model Activity Aggregation view.
This view provides aggregate
statistics for all of the events
displayed in the trace.
For example, in this trace,
the average model load
took 17.17 ms,
and the average prediction
took 7.2 ms.
Another note is that it can sort
the events by duration.
Here, the list is telling me
that more time is being spent
loading the model than actually
making predictions with it,
at a total of 6.41 seconds
of loads,
compared to only 2.69 seconds
of predictions.
Perhaps this has something
to with the low frame rate.
Let me try to find where all
of these loads are coming from.
I am noticing that
I am reloading my Core ML model
prior to calling
each prediction.
This is generally
not good practice
as I can just load the model
once and hold it in memory.
I'm going to jump back into
my code and try to fix this.
I found the area of code
where I load my model.
The issue here is that
this is a computed properly,
which means that each time
I reference the
styleTransferModel variable,
it will recompute the property,
which means reloading the model,
in this case.
I can quickly fix this
by changing this
to be a lazy variable.
Now I'll reprofile the app
to check if this has fixed
the repeated loads issue.
I'll once again select
the Core ML template
and capture a trace.
This is much more in line
with what I'd expect.
The count column tells me
that there are
five load events total,
which matches the number
of styles I used in the app,
and the total duration of loads
is much smaller
than the total duration
of predictions.
Also, as I scroll through...
...it correctly shows repeated
prediction events
without loads
in between each one.
Another note is that so far,
I've only looked at the views
that show all
Core ML model activity.
In this app, there is one
Core ML model per style,
so I may want to breakdown
the Core ML activity by model.
The Instrument
makes this easy to do.
In the main graph, you can click
the arrow at the top left,
and it will make one subtrack
for each model used
in the trace.
Here it displays all of the
different style transfer models
that were used.
The Aggregation view also offers
similar functionality
by allowing you to break down
the statistics by model.
Next I'd like to dive into
a prediction on one of my models
to get a better idea
of how it's being run.
I'll look deeper into
the Watercolor model.
In this prediction,
the Compute lane is telling me
that my model was run
on a combination
of the Neural Engine
and the GPU.
Core ML is sending these compute
requests asynchronously,
so if I'm interested
to see when these compute units
are actively running
the model,
I can combine
the Core ML Instrument
with the GPU Instrument and the
new Neural Engine Instrument.
To do this, I have the three
Instruments pinned here.
The Core ML Instrument shows me
the entire region
where the model ran.
And within this region,
the Neural Engine Instrument
shows the compute first running
on the Neural Engine,
then the GPU Instrument
shows the model
was handed off
from the Neural Engine
to finish running on the GPU.
This gives me a better idea
of how my model
is actually being executed
on the hardware.
To recap, I used the Core ML
Instrument in Xcode 14
to learn about my model's
performance
when running live in my app.
I then identified an issue
in which I was too frequently
reloading my model.
I fixed the issue in my code,
reprofiled the application,
and verified that the issue
had been fixed.
I was also able to combine
the Core ML, GPU,
and new Neural Engine Instrument
to get more details
on how my model was actually
run on different compute units.
That was an overview
of the new tools
to help you understand
performance.
Next, I'll go over
some enhanced APIs
that can help optimize
that performance.
Let me start by going over
how Core ML
handles model inputs
and outputs.
When you create a Core ML model,
that model has a set
of input and output features,
each with a type and size.
At runtime, you use Core ML APIs
to provide inputs
that conform with
the model's interface
and get outputs
after running inference.
Let me focus on images
and MultiArrays
in a bit more detail.
For images, Core ML supports
8-bit grayscale
and 32-bit color images
with 8 bits per component.
And for multidimensional arrays,
Core ML supports Int32,
Double, and Float32
as the scalar types.
If your app is already working
with these types,
it's simply a matter of
connecting them to the model.
However, sometimes
your types may differ.
Let me show an example.
I'd like to add a new filter
to my image processing
and style app.
This filter works
to sharpen images
by operating on
a single-channel image.
My app has some pre-
and post-processing operations
on the GPU and represents
this single channel
in Float16 precision.
To do this,
I used coremltools to convert
an image-sharpening torch model
to Core ML format as shown here.
The model was set up to use
Float16 precision computation.
Also, it takes image inputs
and produces image outputs.
I got a model
that looks like this.
Note that it takes
grayscale images
which are 8-bit for Core ML.
To make this work,
I had to write some code
to downcast my input
from OneComponent16Half
to OneComponent8
and then upcast the output
from OneComponent8
to OneComponent16Half.
However,
this isn't the whole story.
Since the model was set up
to perform computation
in Float16 precision,
at some point,
Core ML needs to convert
these 8-bit inputs to Float16.
It does the conversion
efficiently,
but when looking
at an Instruments trace
with the app running,
it shows this.
Notice the data steps
Core ML is performing
before and after
Neural Engine computation.
When zooming in
on the Data lane,
it shows Core ML is copying data
to prepare it for computation
on the Neural Engine,
which means converting it
to Float16, in this case.
This seems unfortunate
since the original data
was already Float16.
Ideally, these data
transformations can be avoided
both in-app and inside Core ML
by making the model work
directly with Float16
inputs and outputs.
Starting in iOS 16
and macOS Ventura,
Core ML will have native support
for one OneComponent16Half
grayscale images,
and Float16 MultiArrays.
You can create a model
that accepts Float16 inputs
and outputs by specifying
a new color layout for images
or a new data type
for MultiArrays,
while invoking the coremltools
convert method.
In this case, I'm specifying
the input and output
of my model to be grayscale
Float16 images.
Since Float16 support
is available
starting in iOS 16
and macOS Ventura,
these features
are only available
when the minimum deployment
target is specified as iOS 16.
This is how the reconverted
version of the model looks.
Note that the inputs and outputs
are marked as Grayscale16Half.
With this Float16 support,
my app can directly feed
Float16 images to Core ML,
which will avoid the need
for downcasting the inputs
and upcasting the outputs
in the app.
This is how it looks
in the code.
Since I have my input data
in the form
of a OneComponent16Half
CVPixelBuffer,
I can simply send
the pixel buffer
directly to Core ML.
This does not incur any
data copy or transformation.
I then get a OneComponent16Half
CVPixelBuffer as the output.
This results in simpler code,
and no data transformations
required.
There's also another cool thing
you can do,
and that's to ask Core ML to
fill your preallocated buffers
for outputs instead of having
Core ML allocate
a new buffer
for each prediction.
You can do this by allocating
an output backing buffer
and setting it
on the prediction options.
For my app, I wrote a function
called outputBackingBuffer
which returns a OneComponent1
HalfCVPixelBuffer.
I then set this on
the prediction options,
and finally call the prediction
method on my model
with those prediction options.
By specifying output backings,
you can gain better control
over the buffer management
for model outputs.
So with those changes made,
to recap,
here's what was shown
in the Instruments trace
when using the original version
of the model
that had 8-bit inputs
and outputs.
And here's how the
final Instruments trace looks
after modifying the code
to provide IOSurface-backed
Float16 buffers
to the new Float16 version
of the model.
The data transformations
that were previously shown
in the Data lane are now gone,
since Core ML no longer
needs to perform them.
To summarize, Core ML now has
end-to-end native support
for Float16 data.
This means you can provide
Float16 inputs to Core ML
and have Core ML
give you back Float16 outputs.
You can also use the new
output backing API
to have Core ML fill up
your preallocated output buffers
instead of making new ones.
And lastly, we recommend
using IOSurface-backed buffers
whenever possible,
as this allows Core ML
to transfer the data
between different compute units
without data copies
by taking advantage
of the unified memory.
Next, I'll go through
a quick tour
of some of the additional
capabilities
being added to Core ML.
First is weight compression.
Compressing the weights
of your model may allow you
to achieve similar accuracy
while having a smaller model.
In iOS 12, Core ML introduced
post-training weight compression
which allows you
to reduce the size
of Core ML
neural network models.
We are now extending
16- and 8-bit support
to the ML Program model type,
and additionally,
introducing a new option
to store weights
in a sparse representation.
With coremltools utilities,
you will now be able
to quantize, palettize,
and sparsify the weights
for your ML Program models.
Next is a new
compute unit option.
Core ML always aims to minimize
inference latency
for the given
compute unit preference.
Apps can specify
this preference by setting
the MLModelConfiguration
computeUnits property.
In addition to the three
existing compute unit options,
there is now a new one
called cpuAndNeuralEngine.
This tells Core ML to not
dispatch computation on the GPU,
which can be helpful
when the app uses the GPU
for other computation
and, hence, prefers Core ML
to limit its focus to
the CPU and the Neural Engine.
Next, we are adding
a new way to initialize
your Core ML model instance that
provides additional flexibility
in terms of model serialization.
This allows you to encrypt
your model data
with custom encryption schemes
and decrypt it
just before loading.
With these new APIs,
you can compile and load
an in-memory
Core ML model specification
without requiring the compiled
model to be on disk.
The last update
is about Swift packages
and how they work with Core ML.
Packages are a great way
to bundle and distribute
reusable code.
With Xcode 14,
you can include Core ML models
in your Swift packages,
and now when someone
imports your package,
your model will just work.
Xcode will compile and bundle
your Core ML model automatically
and create the same
code-generation interface
you're used to working with.
We're excited about this change,
as it'll make it a lot easier
to distribute your models
in the Swift ecosystem.
That brings us to the end
of this session.
Core ML performance reports
and Instrument in Xcode 14
are here to help you
analyze and optimize
the performance
of the ML-powered features
in your apps.
New Float16 support
and output backing APIs
gives you more control
of how data flows in and out
of Core ML.
Extended support
for weight compression
can help you minimize
the size of your models.
And with in-memory models
and Swift package support,
you have even more options
when it comes
to how you represent, integrate,
and share Core ML models.
This was Ben
from the Core ML team,
and have a great
rest of WWDC.
♪