♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello! I'm Justin,
and I'm an engineer
on the Photos team.
Today, I would like to talk
about some of the improvements
we have made
to the system Photos picker.
The system Photos picker
is the best way for most apps
to access photos
and videos on iOS.
The picker runs out of process,
so your app doesn't need
to request any library access
to use it.
It has an intuitive UI
and an easy-to-use API.
If you aren't familiar
with the PHPicker API,
you can watch our previous
years' WWDC sessions
where we talked
about it in depth.
In today's session,
I'll start with an overview
of the new features
we added to the picker.
Then, I will talk about
additional platforms
and frameworks
the picker now supports.
All right, let's dive in.
The picker supports filtering
between images, videos,
and Live Photos
since its introduction.
However, we understand
that some of your apps
may have some other requirements.
For example,
a screenshot-stitching app
wants to only show
screenshots in the picker.
Now it is possible
with the new screenshots filter
we added this year.
In addition to screenshots,
we added other asset types
like screen recordings
and slo-mo videos.
There is also a way for you
to create a new filter
using PHAsset.PlaybackStyle.
Other than Cinematic videos,
depth effect photos, and bursts,
all of the new filters
are backported.
If your app
is targeting iOS 15,
you can still use them
as long as you are compiling
with the iOS 16 SDK.
For compound filters, in
addition to the existing "any,"
now you also use
"all" and "not."
They are also backported
to iOS 15.
Let's look at some
code examples.
To show videos and Live Photos,
you can combine them with "any."
Or you may only want
to show screenshots.
To show all images
without screenshots,
you can combine images
and screenshots filters
using "all" and "not."
And the last example, you can
use .cinematicVideos filter
if you are targeting iOS 16.
Next, let's talk
about improvements
related to the half-height
picker.
In iOS 15, UIKit has a new
UISheetPresentationController
API which you can use to present
the picker in half-height mode.
It already works great
in many cases.
But some of you may want
to implement a custom UI
to adjust selected assets
and have those changes
be reflected back in picker.
In iOS 16,
you can deselect assets
using their asset identifiers.
As shown here, the second photo
is no longer selected
in the picker after
deselectAssets is called.
You can also call the moveAsset
method to reorder assets.
Now we are familiar with
all of the new picker features,
let's talk about
platform support.
Currently, the system Photos
picker can only be used
by iOS and iPadOS apps.
This year, we are bringing
the Photos picker
to two additional platforms:
macOS and watchOS.
The iPadOS picker is also
updated with a new design
just for the iPad.
Let's take a look
at the new iPad UI first.
The picker now shows a sidebar
to take advantage
of the larger iPad display.
The sidebar allows
faster navigation
between different collections.
But if there is not
enough space,
like in Split Screen mode,
we will fall back to the
existing compact picker UI.
Next, macOS.
The macOS picker also has a
sidebar with Mac-style controls.
And just like the iOS picker,
it supports multiple selection,
fluid zooming in the grid, and
has a powerful search feature
which allows you to search
for things like people, places,
and a lot more.
The new picker UI is also
available in NSOpenPanel.
You can use it to select assets
from the system photo library,
and for the first time,
including those assets
stored in iCloud Photos.
Your app will get
the new UI for free
without needing to do
any adoption work.
Drag and drop is supported
in the NSOpenPanel picker.
It's also supported
in the standard picker on iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS.
If your app only needs to select
a few images or videos,
the NSOpenPanel API
may be all you need.
But keep in mind that selected
files in the photo library
may be deleted by the system
at any time.
You should copy them to
a location managed by your app
if you need to ensure their
availability in the long term.
For media-centric macOS apps,
we encourage you to default
to the new Photos picker
for the best user experience.
However, your app should still
provide an alternative way
to select assets
from the file system
using the NSOpenPanel API.
Sometimes your customers
may still want to select assets
outside their photo libraries.
Last but not least,
let's talk about watchOS.
For the first time,
you can have access to images
stored on the watch
using a new API.
The watchOS picker
also runs out of process,
like the iOS
and the macOS picker,
so you don't need to request
any library access to use it.
It has a UI
similar to the iOS picker
but optimized
for the smaller screen.
You can browse your photos
in the grid or by collections.
You can configure the picker
to show the selection order,
as well as specifying
a selection limit.
However, unlike iOS and macOS,
only images will be displayed
in the watchOS picker.
If the device has more
than 500 images,
only the most recent 500
will be shown.
You may be wondering,
"PHPickerViewController
is UIKit based.
How can I use it for my macOS
or watchOS app?"
As you may have guessed,
new picker APIs are now
available in AppKit and SwiftUI.
Let's take a look
at the AppKit API first.
Actually, it is very similar
to the UIKit API.
You have access to the same
PHPickerConfiguration type
and its properties.
There is only
a small difference:
PHPickerViewController
is a NSViewController subclass
for AppKit apps.
With the introduction
of the AppKit-based PHPicker,
it's time to move away from the
legacy media library browser.
PHPicker is a lot more powerful.
It's also easier to maintain
if you are working on both
UIKit and AppKit apps
at the same time.
Finally, it's time to talk about
the SwiftUI API.
Remember the iOS picker you saw
at the beginning of the session?
It can be presented with only
a few lines of SwiftUI code.
More importantly,
you have access
to the SwiftUI PhotosPicker API
on all picker-supported
platforms:
iOS, iPadOS, macOS, and watchOS.
The picker will automatically
choose the best layout
depending on the platform,
your app's configuration,
and available screen space.
You don't need to worry about
what the picker UI should be,
so you just can focus
on making your app better.
Before we look at the new API
in detail via a demo,
we should talk about how to load
selected photos
and videos first.
The selection you receive
through the SwiftUI binding
only contains
placeholder objects.
You still need to load
actual asset data on demand.
Keep in mind
that some asset data
won't be loaded immediately.
The load operation
could also fail
if an error was encountered,
for example, when the picker
was trying to download data
from iCloud Photos
but the device was not connected
to the internet.
Some large files like videos may
take a long time to download,
so we recommend you to show
a per-item inline loading UI
instead of a blocking
loading indicator.
The PhotosPicker
uses Transferable,
which is a new SwiftUI protocol
for transferring data
between apps and extensions.
You can load SwiftUI Image
via Transferable directly,
but for advanced use cases,
you should define
your own model objects
conforming to
the Transferable protocol
to fully control the type
of data you want to load.
For more information
about Transferable,
you can check out
the "Meet Transferable" session.
If your app needs to deal with
a lot of items at the same time,
or large assets like videos,
it may not be feasible
to load everything in memory
at the same time.
To reduce memory usage, you can
use FileTransferRepresentation
to load selected assets
as files.
When loading assets as files,
keep in mind
that your app is responsible
for managing their lifecycles.
Files should always be copied
to your app directory
when received and deleted
when they are no longer needed.
OK, it's time for the demo!
I have already set up
this demo app
showing an account profile page.
Right now the profile image
is just a placeholder icon.
We want to add an edit button
to change the profile image
using the PhotosPicker API.
The profile image view
can already respond
to the image state
defined in our view model,
so we just need to update
the image state
when a picker selection
is received.
First, let's go
to our view model
and add a new
imageSelection property.
It will be passed
to the PhotosPicker API
as the selection binding.
Now we can go back
to our profile image view,
and add an overlay button
that brings up the picker.
OK, let's pause for a second
and take a look at the code
we just added.
We added a PhotosPicker view,
given it the selection binding
we just defined,
and configured it
to only show images.
The label of the PhotosPicker
is just a pencil glyph
with a circle background.
We can build and run
to see what we have so far.
I can tap the edit button
to bring up the picker.
Tapping an image will
automatically close the picker,
but the profile image
is not updated.
Why?
We still need to connect
the image selection
and the image state.
So, let's do that.
We can go back to the view model
and respond to image
selection did set.
We set the image state to empty
if the image selection is nil.
Otherwise,
we start loading the image.
We are seeing a compiler error
because we haven't implemented
the loadTransferable
method yet.
Let's fix it.
The implementation
is very simple.
We just need to respond
to the completion handler
and update image state
if the request is still
the most recent one.
Let's build and run
to see it in action.
I can tap the edit button
and select an image.
Great!
It works as expected.
Actually, the project is already
set up to run on macOS as well.
Will the code I just added
automatically work on macOS?
Let's build and run to find out.
It compiles!
I can open the picker,
select an image,
and it is reflected in the app.
That's it for the demo.
You just saw the demo
on iOS and macOS,
but the same code will work
on watchOS as well.
However, there are a few things
to keep in mind.
The watchOS picker is designed
for simple flows
and short interactions.
Images are scaled
based on the device size.
Usually, they are synced
from the paired iPhone.
However, Family Setup
lets your family members
who don't have their own iPhone
enjoy the features and benefits
of an Apple Watch.
If a device is in
the Family Setup mode,
the most recent 1000 images in
iCloud Photos can be selected
using the picker.
The picker may need to download
some images from the internet.
And if that's the case,
a loading UI will be shown
in the picker before closing.
Before you go,
I just want to say
that we are committed to making
the system Photos picker
the best way for most apps
to access photos and videos.
We really encourage you
to switch to it
if you are still using
a custom picker.
Thank you,
and have a great WWDC!
♪