♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hello, I'm Neil Foley,
an engineer on the ShazamKit team.
In 2021, we introduced ShazamKit,
allowing you to match audio
against Shazam's
vast catalog of recorded music.
We also introduced custom catalog
matching,
giving developers the ability
to match their own audio
and provide synced experiences.
Now we have some important
updates that streamline
working with custom catalogs at scale.
In this session, I'm going to use
some of the existing ShazamKit concepts
such as signatures,
catalogs, and media items.
If you're not already familiar with those,
check out the "Explore ShazamKit”
and "Create custom audio experiences
with ShazamKit" talks
from WWDC21.
But as quick overview,
ShazamKit lets you convert audio
into a special format that can be matched.
We call these signatures.
Signatures can be combined
with media items containing metadata
to form a reference signature.
And reference signatures can
be stored together in a file
that we call a custom catalog.
Now that we are all caught up,
I'll take you through building
custom catalogs at scale,
and then I'll talk about some tips
and tricks to make great catalogs.
In today's custom catalog workflow,
if you have a small amount
of content you want to be matched,
working with custom catalogs
can be a simple task.
You just need to follow these steps.
Record your audio in a format
that ShazamKit accepts.
Use the signature generator
to transform it into a signature.
Annotate it with your metadata,
and then store it in a custom catalog.
And that's it,
you can provide a Shazam experience.
But some of those steps can be daunting,
especially if you're not familiar
with audio programming.
Dealing with sample rates and buffers
can be tricky
even for the most experienced developer.
And what happens when you have
a vast amount of content
you'd like to make Shazamable,
like 10 seasons of a TV show?
This workflow can become painful.
And if you have large amounts of content,
it can quickly become unmanageable.
If you're thinking of improving
this workflow for yourself,
you'll probably need to write code to
transform audio into signatures,
more code to load
and associate media items,
and each time you change your content,
you'll have to repeat the work.
This is a big investment
when you just want to match some audio.
And then if you want to sync content
with ShazamKit,
you need complicated logic to figure
out what should be shown and when.
I'll introduce some great enhancements to
ShazamKit that streamline this workflow.
But first a quick demo.
Here I have the FoodMath app that
Alex demonstrated in 2021
that syncs a maths quiz
with an on screen lesson.
I've updated it with
the latest ShazamKit features,
and I'm going play back the FoodMath
video to see how it syncs.
Skip to 26 seconds.
2, 3 green apples.
How many apples do I have in total?
Your timer starts…now.
[light music]
Okay, time's up.
Let's see how you did.
Skip to 56 seconds.
Today, to spice it up a bit,
when I went to the shop,
started with 2 red apples...
and I bought 2 green apples.
How many apples did I have
in total this time?
Your timer starts…now.
Okay, time's up.
Seems to be working great.
There's rich content synced with the
video and when I said "now,"
the menu appeared
at exactly the right time.
Also, when content was no longer
relevant, it disappeared right on cue.
But how does it work?
Let's have a look at the code.
There's just a simple loop.
It uses an AsyncSequence on the session
instead of the delegate callbacks
that we used before.
The sequence returns an enum
representing match, no match, or error.
I'm only interested in matches, so I've
restricted the loop to just that case.
And to build the result for display,
I reduce the media items
to the content that I need.
There's actually
not much more to see in the app,
just SwiftUI views that are driven by
the matchResult that we create.
There's no complicated logic or
timing code and it syncs perfectly.
So the question remains,
how does it sync so well?
FoodMaths' secret is the rich
custom catalog that drives the experience.
I created the catalog with a simple tool
that we've built to complement ShazamKit,
and you can use it too to create
rich experiences in your own apps.
The Shazam CLI ships as part of
macOS 13
and provides an easy way to sync content.
It can help to automate
some of the repetitive tasks
associated with creating custom catalogs.
Let's update the custom catalog
that I just showed you.
Time for another demo.
Here's a folder containing
the FoodMath video file,
and here's my terminal in the same folder.
I'll use the CLI to convert
the video into a signature
using the signature command.
I just pass the video file as input
and specify our signature output.
Okay. There's our signature.
Now I want combine this signature
with media items
to make a custom catalog.
The CLI accepts a simple
comma separated file
for describing media items
that I'll copy here.
It describes everything
that I need to sync my content.
Here's where I've specified my titles,
and here's a custom JSON field
I've defined for the equation.
The headers map to media item
properties.
For details on the mapping,
run the custom catalog create command
with the help flag.
It describes the relationship between
the csv headers and media item properties.
Now I want to combine them
together into a custom catalog.
So I'll run the create command.
I pass in the signature file and the csv
file and it outputs a catalog.
Okay, now we have our catalog.
Excitingly, I have early access to
the latest FoodMath episode,
so I want to add that to our catalog file.
Let me copy the files here.
Here's our media items
for our new episode.
I'll run the update command
passing in the video,
the new media, and the catalog to update.
Okay, we've updated our catalog.
That's a quick overview
of how to create catalogs,
but if you're like me,
you'll really you'll want to script this.
The FoodMath app
actually has quite a few new episodes,
and I want to
add them all to this catalog.
I've written a really simple script
that loops through all the episode folders
and combines them into a custom catalog.
I'll run it now.
There we go.
We now have one catalog representing
every FoodMath episode
and the script used the display command
to detail what's inside the catalog.
I think we have everything.
The foodmath project is already
referencing our new catalog.
So let's build and run
so that we can enjoy doing some maths.
Skip to 30 seconds.
How many apples do I have in total?
Your timer starts…now.
[upbeat music]
Okay, time's up.
Let's see how you did.
I like that guy.
That's a great episode.
What about a new episode?
Let's try that.
Skip to 15 seconds.
Over the years, I explored what makes
a guacamole truly delicious,
and I wrote down my favorite
guacamole recipe.
It calls for 4 avocados.
Tomorrow
my friend is visiting.
So for the two of us, I only need
to make half of the portion.
How many avocados do I need?
The timer starts…now.
[rapid beeping]
That's correct.
You need two avocados.
Let's make this guacamole together.
[upbeat music]
Let's give this a try.
Mmm. That turned out to be great.
I hope you had some fun
and see you next time.
Oh!
They have a new host.
Interesting.
Anyway, I've created a rich synced
experience in no time at all.
The Shazam CLI supports
a rich set of commands.
Let's go over them.
You can create a signature
from any media file
that has an audio track.
You can create custom catalogs
by combining signatures and media items.
You can display a catalog's content.
Add, remove, and export both signatures
and media items.
Next, on to how the CLI created
the signatures from the FoodMath videos.
SHSignatureGenerator now has
a method signatureFromAsset
that's available on all platforms.
With this method, there's no more manually
pulling audio buffers from media.
Simply pass an AVAsset with an
audio track to turn it into a signature.
If you have multiple tracks in
your asset, they'll be mixed together
ensuring the signature
captures everything.
Okay, now that I have a signature
that represents the media,
how did I accurately sync content?
I used the Timed MediaItem API.
Attaching a time range to the media
item makes it easy to specify
when it starts and when it ends.
Media items can also have
multiple time ranges
to target more than
one portion of a signature.
Imagine that you have a media item
that targets the chorus of a song.
You can add a time range
for each place it's sung.
Specifying the time ranges is only useful
if you're notified when they start
and when they end.
ShazamKit will deliver a match
callback synced with the time range,
one when it starts and one when it ends.
Signatures can contain many media items,
so this callback will contain only
the media items that are in range
at that specific point in time.
There's a few simple rules for which
media items will be returned
in a callback and their order,
so let's go over them.
Media items outside of their time range
will not be returned.
Media items within their
time range will be returned,
with the most recent events
coming first.
And finally, media items with no time
ranges will always be returned last,
but they will be unordered.
Media items that have no time range
can be a great place
to store global information that applies
to the whole reference signature.
In my FoodMath example, I used it
to store the name of the episode.
It appears when no other
media items are in range.
One final point, if all your media items
have time ranges
and none of them are in scope,
ShazamKit will always return a
media item with basic match information.
This way, you will always
get important properties,
such as the predictedCurrentMatch offset
and the frequencySkew.
And in code, it's easy too.
Timed media items
are created by specifying
the timeRanges media item property.
It's an array of Swift ranges.
It can also be read back
using the timeRanges property.
And for Objective-C programmers,
there's a new SHRange class
as a drop in replacement.
Now that you've
seen how to build them,
let's explore some tips and tricks
to make great custom catalogs.
Avoid creating many small signatures
for one piece of media.
A signature is a one to one
mapping to the media that it represents,
so for each piece of audio you have,
be it from a song or video,
create one signature
for the entire duration.
A longer signature provides more
opportunities for ShazamKit to match
audio peaks, resulting in better
accuracy.
It also avoids issues
with query signatures
overlapping multiple reference signatures.
Using the new Timed MediaItem API,
you can target synced content
to individual areas.
There's no need to divide a piece
of audio into multiple signatures.
I showed an example where we
had one piece of media,
but with multiple media items.
But what should we do if we have
a huge amount of content
that we want to make Shazamable?
How should we split it up?
There's a trade-off you need
to make when splitting your content
across custom catalogs.
If you create individual catalogs
for each media asset,
you'll need to know
which piece of audio is being played
so that you can load the correct catalog.
And if you put them all together
in one catalog,
you'll have a larger download
and use more memory,
but you can match
many more pieces of audio.
Our advice is to keep the catalog
files you create tightly focused.
For example, a catalog per music
track or the whole album,
but not the artist's whole discography.
Keeping things separate means that you
can decide what to load at runtime.
You can do that with the custom
catalog add API.
Try it out
and see if helps with your use case.
If you have multiple audio
assets that sound the same,
maybe a show that always starts with
the same intro music, and you want to
provide a custom experience
for each episode,
or a song that's sampled in another track,
maybe consider using
frequency skew as a differentiator.
Skewing audio is raising or
lowing the frequencies in the recording.
When you do this,
you affect how the audio sounds,
but if you do it by a small enough amount,
it can be noticed by ShazamKit
but not by the average human ear.
So if we take an audio recording,
make a custom catalog from it,
and then play it back
with the frequencies slightly shifted:
ShazamKit will still match the audio,
and it will also report the skew amount
through the frequencySkew property.
Here's how to do that in code.
There are limits to how much
you can skew audio
without the change becoming
either noticeable to the human ear
or unrecognizable to ShazamKit.
Keeping the skew
to less than 5 percent should be safe
and provide enough room to
differentiate multiple skewed recordings.
To really take advantage of this,
use the frequencySkew ranges.
Media items will only be
returned if they fall inside
the specified skew ranges.
The range specifies as a percentage
how much the audio
differs from the original.
A value of 0 indicates the
audio is unskewed and a value of .01
indicates a 1 percent skew.
You can access the property on media items
using the frequencySkewRanges property.
I'll go over the steps to
get this working in your app:
First create a reference signature
of your original audio recording.
Then take a media item and restrict it
by frequency skew to 3 to 4 percent.
Place this inside your custom catalog.
Now play back the audio skewed
by 3 to 4 percent,
and your media item will be returned.
Playing back the audio unskewed
or skewed outside of the range
will not return your media item.
That's frequency skewing.
Now that you've seen the exciting updates
to ShazamKit this year,
you're ready to make
some amazing synced experiences.
So remember these best practices:
First, create one signature
per media asset.
You'll get better accuracy from
ShazamKit and simpler creation pipeline.
Create your signatures
with SHSignatureGenerators
signatureFromAsset.
It accepts a wide variety of media,
meaning you no longer have
to deal with low level audio details.
Target synced content to areas of interest
with the new Timed MediaItem API.
It combines a simple API
with excellent accuracy.
And finally let the Shazam CLI streamline
the way you create custom catalogs.
It's been designed take away the hassle
of dealing with vast amounts of media
and let you focus on the great
experiences you want to make instead.
I hope you enjoyed the latest updates
to ShazamKit,
and I'm excited to see you
make everything Shazamable.
All of the information we discussed
and links to documentation
are attached to this session.
Thanks for joining.
Enjoy the rest of WWDC22.  ♪ ♪