♪ ♪
Greg: Hi, I'm Greg.
Welcome to what's new in StoreKit Testing.
In this session, Peter and I will
highlight some great new features
available for testing
in-app purchases in StoreKit.
We'll begin by taking a look at
some of the ways you can use Xcode 14
to streamline
your in-app purchase testing.
Next, we'll take a look at some brand-new
capabilities you can take advantage of
to cover even more corner cases in
your in-app subscription implementations.
And finally,
Peter will show new enhancements
to the sandbox testing environment.
We'll be working with Food Truck,
an app to provide powerful capabilities
to food truck operators who sell donuts.
I already integrated with StoreKit
to offer the full version
of the Food Truck sales history feature,
and a subscription for an enhanced version
of the Social Feed service.
Throughout the session
we'll use StoreKit Testing in Xcode
to test the in-app purchase
functionality of our app.
Back at WWDC 2020,
we introduced StoreKit Testing in Xcode,
allowing you to start testing
your in-app purchases directly in Xcode.
This year, with Xcode 14,
we're excited to share some updates
to the testing life cycle
of a StoreKit app.
Just like before, you can create
a StoreKit Configuration File in Xcode,
and start testing
your in-app purchase implementation
without setting up an app
in App Store Connect.
When you're ready to configure
your app in App Store Connect,
we're introducing
a brand-new feature in Xcode 14
to allow you to use
the same in-app purchase products
that you've entered in App Store Connect
with StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
If you already have an app on the store,
you can start using StoreKit Testing
in Xcode right now,
without needing to set up a StoreKit
Configuration File from scratch.
This convenient feature enables you
to configure your in-app purchases once,
and use the same configuration
locally in Xcode,
inside your unit tests,
in the Sandbox environment,
and when you're ready for release,
on the App Store.
It's easy to sync your products
in App Store Connect with Xcode.
First, you configure your products
in App Store Connect,
like this Social Feed+ subscription,
for example.
Then, you create a synced
configuration file in Xcode
which will load the product data
into Xcode.
If you want to make a change,
for example updating the US English title,
you can make the change
in App Store Connect
and sync your Configuration
in Xcode again.
You can also convert a configuration
you've synced
into a local, editable file
to make on the fly changes.
Converting a synced configuration
to a local configuration
is a one-way operation,
to sync again you'll need to create
a new configuration file.
I've already gotten started by setting up
a subscription group for Social Feed+,
an enhanced version of the Social Feed
service the Food Truck app offers.
Let's jump into Xcode and take a look
at how to use these products
with StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
I have the Food Truck project
open on my Mac.
To get started we'll create a new
StoreKit Configuration File
by going to the File Menu,
making a new file,
filtering by StoreKit,
and clicking next.
In Xcode 14, when we create
a new configuration file,
we get this checkbox to enable keeping
the file in sync
with an app in App Store Connect.
To create a local file, fill in a name
and leave the box unchecked.
To set up syncing,
we just have to check the box,
and confirm that the correct team
and app are selected.
If desired, we could choose a different
team and app using the picker menus.
We click next,
and choose somewhere to save our file.
As soon as we save the file,
the in-app purchase metadata
begins syncing from App Store Connect.
While the data is downloading,
we can keep working on our app
and keep track of its progress
in the Activity Bar.
When the sync is finished,
you'll notice this file looks different
than a typical
StoreKit Configuration File.
That's because the synced file
is in a read-only state.
We can see all the data
in Xcode at a glance,
but to make changes
we have to open App Store Connect.
I have the Social Feed+ monthly product
up in Safari.
Let's update the English title
for this product by adding a suffix
to help differentiate the product
from the yearly plan.
Now that this is updated,
let's save
and go back to Xcode.
To have this change
reflect in our configuration file,
we just have to press this sync button
in the bottom left corner.
Once the sync is complete,
we can see the change reflected in Xcode.
Even though the synced file is read-only,
we can still copy over data
to a local file
to make quick changes inside of Xcode.
In addition to copying items
from the configuration file,
we can also convert an entire synced file
to a local, editable file.
All we need to do is open our synced file,
go to the editor menu,
and click on
"Convert to Local StoreKit Configuration".
Keep in mind, you can't undo
this operation after converting the file.
To sync with the app again, you'll need to
create a new StoreKit Configuration File.
I want to keep this file in sync
with App Store Connect,
so let's cancel out of this alert.
Now that we have our file synced,
let's configure our testing environment.
To get started,
we'll open the scheme editor.
Select the run action,
and select options.
In the options, we can switch between
different StoreKit environments
from the picker menu.
If we choose "None"
we'll connect to Sandbox,
and if we choose "Food Truck"
we'll connect to the Xcode environment.
It's that easy to switch
between environments
depending on our current testing needs,
and both environments will now be using
the exact same product
and subscription metadata.
Let's pick our synced configuration
file for now.
We've now set up StoreKit in Xcode,
so let's get to testing.
Since we're using a SwiftUI app,
we can preview our subscription store
right in Xcode.
Starting in Xcode 14,
products from StoreKit configuration files
will load right into SwiftUI previews.
This makes it super easy to build and test
great looking store user interfaces,
using real in-app purchase data.
Let's try to add some detail
to the product options
by including a subtitle for our products.
We'll just add a Text view containing
the product's localized description.
And watch the preview update immediately
with the description we set up
in App Store Connect.
I think this is looking a lot better now.
Now that our UI is in good shape,
let's run the app on an iPhone
and start some functional testing.
In Xcode 14,
there are some powerful new tools
in the StoreKit Transaction Manager.
With our app running,
we can open the transaction manager
by pressing the purchases
icon in the debug bar.
On the right
there's a new transaction inspector
that allows us to visualize
all of the under the hood details
about a transaction.
This tool can be useful to understand
the state of an in-app transaction.
For example, we can see the date
this subscription to Social Feed+ expired,
and information
about its upcoming renewals.
We can also jump to the configuration file
for a product,
subscription group, or subscription offer.
We just have to click the jump button
next to this subscription group.
And we're brought straight to Social Feed+
in our configuration file.
This inspector will help us out later
in the session
as we look at more advanced test cases.
We can also filter our transactions now,
which is really useful
for navigating the list of transactions
with all of these Social Feed+ renewals.
In our app you'll notice we have access
to the annual sales history feature.
We have all of
these subscription renewals,
which makes it difficult to tell which
transaction entitled us to the feature.
We can easily find the transaction
for the product
by beginning to type out its ID...
And selecting the product ID filter
from the auto-complete menu.
We can also filter by purchase date,
so we can focus on just the purchases
we're making now.
Since our subscription
to Social Feed+ is expired,
let's go into the app and subscribe again.
Now that we've confirmed the subscription,
we can see
just the new transaction appear.
We just looked at some ways to enhance
your in-app purchase testing in Xcode,
by syncing products and subscriptions
from App Store Connect,
using your StoreKit Configurations
with SwiftUI Previews,
and taking advantage of the new tools
in the Transaction Manager.
Now, we're going to continue testing
Food Truck's in-app purchase functionality
by using some new capabilities in Xcode
to cover advanced subscription cases.
First, we'll look at testing
refund requests,
allowing people to request refunds
for their purchases in Food Truck.
Next, we'll test offer codes,
to offer promotions
to Social Feed+ subscribers,
then we'll look at
handling price increases
in Food Truck's user interface,
and last,
reducing Social Feed+ involuntary churn
by supporting billing retry
and grace period.
To begin testing refund requests,
we'll navigate to this support view
in our app,
which allows us to choose
a recent transaction to refund.
The code for this is simple.
I just added a refundRequestSheet
view modifier to our view,
and when we press the refund button,
we'll flip the isPresented Binding
to true.
Now, let's see this in action.
When the Binding is true, the refund
request sheet appears above our view.
When testing in the Xcode environment,
the issue we select corresponds 1:1
with a RevocationReason
in the StoreKit API.
Let's pick "Developer Issue"
and press "Request Refund".
In the App Store, refund requests
will take some time to process,
but when testing with Xcode or Sandbox,
refund requests
will immediately refund the transaction.
In the transaction manager,
we can look at the inspector
for this updated transaction
to see the revocation reason
we just selected,
and the revocation date.
You can also test refunds
by just clicking the refund button
in the transaction manager.
The refund request API helps us provide
great customer support
for people who use Food Truck.
Now that we looked at how to test
refund requests in Xcode,
let's look at some ways you can use
StoreKit to handle refunded transactions.
After refunding a transaction,
an updated Transaction value will emit
from the Transaction.updates sequence.
We can use the revocationDate
and revocationReason properties
to detect these refunded transactions.
It's easy to test
the two revocation reason cases
by selecting the corresponding option
in the refund request sheet in Xcode.
That's how you test
the refund request sheet in Xcode.
This works on iOS and macOS
when using either the Xcode environment
or Sandbox.
For testing with Xcode,
you'll need your iPhone or iPad
to run iOS or iPadOS 15.2 or later.
To test with Xcode on your Mac,
you'll need macOS 12.1 or later.
Now, let's take a look
at testing subscription offer codes.
For this, we'll be using
our local StoreKit Configuration file.
To make a new offer for codes,
we select a subscription,
and press the "+"
under the offer codes table.
We then can configure our offer.
We'll name this "Free month"
and make it a free offer for one month.
Just like in App Store Connect,
we select which customers are eligible,
and whether the introductory offer
can be redeemed with this offer.
Let's leave the default settings for now.
Now that our code is configured,
we'll press "Done".
Of course, if you're syncing
with App Store Connect
your configured offers will show up
in this table automatically.
Now that our offer is configured,
let's navigate to the store view
in the app.
I've added this button
near the bottom of the view
for redeeming a subscription offer.
If we open the store view's
implementation in Xcode,
implementing offer codes is as effortless
as adding an offerCodeRedemption modifier
to our view,
and flipping the isPresented Binding
to true when someone taps the button.
Let's see how this works.
When we press the button,
the redeem sheet appears above our app.
In the App Store,
people can type in offer codes
that you generate in App Store Connect,
but in Xcode the testing experience
is much more streamlined.
We have a list of all the offers for codes
in our configuration file,
grouped by the subscription they unlock.
To redeem,
let's tap the offer we just created,
and press the redeem button.
The payment sheet appears,
and we can see the offer for codes
will start right after
the pay as you go introductory offer.
After subscribing,
we'll get a confirmation screen,
and we can now close the sheet
and verify our app unlocks access
to Social Feed+.
If we look at the inspector
for this new transaction,
we can see the introductory offer
is currently applied.
Since the offer is pay as you go,
the renewals section shows
we'll get two more renewals
of the introductory offer.
After that,
the free month code we just redeemed.
Then, the standard subscription
will renew indefinitely.
The inspector makes it very clear
what's happening
to the state of our subscription,
even with complicated scenarios
like multiple offers.
We just looked at how to configure offer
codes in our local StoreKit configuration,
and how to test redeeming them on iPhone.
Offer codes are a great way to offer
flexible promotions
to our future and existing subscribers,
and now it's easier than ever
to get started
using offer codes in Food Truck.
Now, let's take a look at how to handle
these offers using StoreKit.
After redeeming the code,
both the Transaction.updates
and Status.updates sequences
will emit new values.
We can check the offerType property
on the transaction value
to see if there is an offer applied
to the current transaction.
In the case we just looked at the value
of offerType will be introductory,
because we allowed the subscriber
to redeem the introductory offer
with the offer for codes.
On the renewalInfo value,
we can check the offerType property
to see what kind of offer
will be present in the next renewal.
In the case we just looked at,
we can expect the initial value
to be introductory
since we used a pay as you go offer.
After two subscription periods
we'll see the value switch to code,
as we have a code offer stacked.
When offerType is code,
we can use the offerID property
to get the reference name
of the applied offer for codes.
That's how you test offers for codes in Xcode.
You can configure offers for codes
starting in Xcode 13.3,
and test them on iPhones and iPads
running iOS 15.4 or later.
Now that we've verified
offers for codes work in Food Truck,
let's test how our app handles
a price increase for Social Feed+.
Testing a price increase
is really simple in Xcode.
To get started, we'll increase the price
for the monthly social feed subscription.
This step is optional.
You can leave the price the same
and still simulate a price increase.
Back to the transaction manager,
all we need to do is select the latest
transaction for a subscription
and press "Request Price Increase Consent"
in the toolbar.
We can see in the transaction manager
our transaction is now in
a "Price Increase Pending" state,
and if we look at the device we'll notice
a sheet appeared above our app,
asking to consent to the price increase.
This sheet will appear on its own
without adding any code,
but we took advantage of the new
Messages API to customize its behavior.
Let's take a look at how we integrated
with the Messages API in the code.
We have a for loop iterating
the messages sequence here,
and if we get a message
like price increase,
make sure we don't have
a sensitive view presented,
like the donut editor.
Otherwise,
we'll use the DisplayMessageAction
to display the message.
If the donut editor is presented,
we'll hold on to the Message value
and display it after
the donut editing is finished.
Let's get back to testing.
In the App Store, existing subscribers
may get multiple price increase messages
at different times
until they make a decision
to cancel or consent
to the price increase.
In Xcode, we have full control
of when these messages come.
Each time we press the button
in the transaction manager,
we'll get a message again,
even if the transaction is already
in a price increase state.
Now we can test
if our deferral logic actually works.
So I'll open the donut editor...
And send a message
to open the sheet again.
The sheet doesn't appear yet,
but if we leave the donut editor,
the sheet appears as expected.
While we could accept the price increase,
or cancel the subscription in the sheet,
in reality, users might respond
to the price increase
via an external source, like an email.
To simulate this, we can use
the approve and decline buttons
in the transaction manager.
Since the donut editing experience
was so great,
I'll consent to the new price by pressing
Approve in the transaction manager.
Using StoreKit in Xcode makes testing
a complicated corner case
like a price increase very smooth.
Now that we looked at how
to simulate a price increase,
let's look at how we can use StoreKit
to handle price increases in our app.
When testing the price increase status,
the status updates sequence will emit
new values with every state change.
We can detect these updates
in our app
by checking the priceIncreaseStatus
property on the RenewalInfo value.
If a customer cancels their subscription
due to a price increase,
we'll be able to detect this
by checking for
didNotConsentToPriceIncrease
in the expirationReason property.
We can also write unit tests
around testing price increase.
To start, disabling dialogs
will allow us to test
without actually showing
the price increase UI above our app.
After purchasing the subscription,
we can use the
requestPriceIncreaseConsentForTransaction
API to start the process,
passing in the ID of the latest
transaction for the subscription.
To verify a test transaction
is pending a price increase,
we'll check the
isPendingPriceIncreaseConsent property.
Finally,
depending on what we're testing,
we can call
consentToPriceIncreaseForTransaction
or declinePriceIncreaseForTransaction
to see how our app responds
to finished price increase cases.
That's all for testing price increase.
Price increase is testable with Xcode 13.3
on all platforms.
Note that the price increase message
is only testable on iOS 15.4 or later.
Finally, let's take a look at subscription
billing retry and grace period.
Billing retry is a state
where an error occurred
when trying to renew a subscription,
like an expired credit card.
In the App Store, during billing retry
the App Store will attempt to fix
the issue and recover the subscription.
You can optionally enable a grace period,
which allows people to keep using
their subscription for a limited time,
at the beginning
of the billing retry state.
Let me demonstrate how to simulate this
when testing in Xcode.
To simulate billing issues
on a subscription renewal,
we open the "Editor" menu on the StoreKit
Configuration we're testing with
and enable "Billing Retry on Renewal".
I want Food Truck to support
a billing grace period,
so let's enable "Billing Grace Period"
in the menu as well.
We'll speed up the subscription rate too,
so we can watch how the state changes.
Let's first subscribe to Social Feed+.
Now, let's wait for it to be time
for a renewal.
When the transaction expires,
notice we first enter
the billing grace period state.
We can look at the transaction inspector
and see the time each state will end.
The billing grace period just expired,
and now we're in
the standard billing retry state.
At any time we can use
the "Resolve Issue For Transaction" button
to simulate fixing the billing error.
Let's test resolving the issue.
Now that the issue is resolved,
we get a new transaction.
So long as we have
"Billing retry on renewal" enabled,
each new transaction
will continue to enter billing retry,
so we can repeat this test
as many times as we'd like.
Handling Billing Retry
and Grace Period properly
is key to retaining subscribers
by reducing involuntary churn.
We just looked at how straightforward
it is to simulate these states with Xcode,
so now let's go over
how to handle them using StoreKit.
As the billing retry
and grace period states change,
the status updates sequence
will emit a new value.
Since we offer
a billing grace period in Food Truck,
we need to make sure
to give subscribers access to Social Feed+
while they're in the grace period.
We can see how long the subscriber's
grace period should be
using the gracePeriodExpirationDate
property on the renewal info.
To check for billing retry,
we just have to check isInBillingRetry.
We can also detect either of these states
easily with the state property of Status.
If we see a customer
is in either of these states,
we can direct them to a deep link
to the App Store to fix the billing issue.
If you're using
any current entitlement API,
you'll receive transactions
for expired subscriptions
while they're in the grace period.
We can also control billing retry
and grace period in our unit tests
by setting
billingGracePeriodIsEnabled
and shouldEnterBillingRetryOnRenewal
on our StoreKit test session.
After our app notices
a subscription enter billing retry,
the test transaction's
hasPurchaseIssue property will be true.
After waiting for various status updates
and asserting our app updates as expected,
we can use the resolve issue
for transaction method
to simulate the App Store
recovering the subscription.
Billing retry and grace period
are testable in Xcode 13.3 or later
on all platforms.
Later in the session,
Peter will go more into detail
on how to test these states in Sandbox
on iOS and iPadOS 16.
We covered advanced test cases
from requesting refunds
to handling billing retry
and grace period.
For more details on how to use
the new StoreKit APIs
to support some of these cases,
check out
"What's new with in-app purchase."
This was just a quick overview
of what's new for StoreKit Testing
in Xcode this year,
but we didn't cover everything.
There are new subscription renewal rates,
you can test the StoreKit 2 in-app manage
subscriptions sheet in Xcode,
and you can write unit tests
for your SKAdNetwork implementations
using StoreKitTest.
Check out "What's new in
SKAdNetwork" to learn more.
Now Peter will walk you through what's new
in the Sandbox testing environment
this year.
Peter: Thanks, Greg.
Hi, I'm Peter,
an App Store server engineer.
We saw how new features
with StoreKit Testing in Xcode
can help you test more complex
in-app purchase implementations.
We're constantly listening
to your feedback,
and we know many of you rely on
the App Store Sandbox environment
to test your in-app purchases
and server implementations.
I'm excited to share some new
enhancements we're making in Sandbox
so you can more easily test your app
and server in an online test environment.
We'll be introducing enhancements
to Sandbox Apple ID creation,
the App Store Connect API,
and billing failure simulation.
To use the sandbox environment,
we first need to set up a Sandbox Apple ID
in App Store Connect.
You'll notice we moved
the Sandbox tester list
to the navigation bar
on the Users and Access page.
Here, we can create a new tester
with the Plus button.
We streamlined the creation process
by removing several fields
from the new tester window.
We're now only asking
for the minimum amount of info,
so you can move forward
with creating your account
without unnecessary information.
You can also use a "plus symbol"
in your email address,
so you don't need to create
a brand-new email address for each tester.
We know creating strong passwords can
be tedious, and we made this easier too.
We've also added in-line suggestions for
helping make your password more secure.
We hope streamlined
Apple ID creation form,
and better password complexity hints,
will help you spend less time
setting up accounts
and more time developing your app.
App Store Connect is the central location
where you create and manage
Sandbox Apple IDs,
as well as manage your app content
and organization.
Over the last few years,
we've been adding features to Sandbox
that you've been asking for,
like changing Sandbox account region
and clearing purchase history.
Many of these features are accessible
in App Store Connect
or on-device in the Sandbox
Manage Subscriptions page.
Later this year, we will be bringing
several of these Sandbox features
to the App Store Connect API,
including querying
for a list of Sandbox Apple IDs,
clearing purchase history,
and setting interrupted purchase state.
This will enable faster testing
with your sandbox accounts
and help you setup automation clients
for commonly-used testing tools.
Finally, I'm happy to announce support
for billing failure simulation in Sandbox.
In 2018, we announced Billing Retry
and Grace Period
for auto-renewing subscriptions,
to help you reduce involuntary churn.
Since launching in 2019,
Billing Grace Period has allowed you
to recover 300 million days
of paid service to your customers.
This results in incremental revenue
for your business
while your customers experience
no interruption in service.
While many of you are already handling
billing failure cases in production,
we want to provide
more testing scenarios in Sandbox,
so you can test and handle billing
failures
before your app is published
on the App Store.
You'll be able to use a new
Sandbox Account Settings page
to enable billing failure simulation
for your account,
test foreground and background
subscription failures
in the context of your app,
and verify subscription status
with verifyReceipt,
App Store Server API,
and App Store Server Notifications V2
in Sandbox.
For more info on Billing Retry
and reducing involuntary churn,
I recommend the 2018 WWDC session,
"Engineering Subscriptions".
This year, we're introducing a switch
in the new Sandbox Account Settings
to simulate
a failed in-app purchase attempt.
This is also the new home for
the Sandbox subscriptions page.
With billing failure simulation enabled,
foreground in-app purchases will fail.
This behavior matches the behavior
when your customer's payment method
is declined.
Billing failure simulation also ensures
that auto-renewing subscription states
match those
for billing failures in production.
This means you can test in-app messaging
for your customers
who are having billing problems.
These subscription states
will be reflected
in your in-app purchase receipts,
verified with V2 Notifications.
Let's review the subscription lifecycle.
When you purchase an auto-renewing
subscription in Sandbox,
you already receive V2 Notifications,
like SUBSCRIBED, and DID_RENEW.
When you test failed in-app purchase
attempts for an account
with an active subscription,
the next renewal
will fall into billing retry state.
You'll now receive billing retry
notifications in Sandbox,
like DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW.
If you disable billing failure simulation
before we stop trying to recover
the renewal of your subscription,
the next renewal attempt
will be successful,
and you will receive
a DID_RENEW notification,
with subtype BILLING_RECOVERY.
If we reach the limit for retry attempts,
and billing failure simulation is enabled,
the subscription will expire
and you will receive EXPIRED,
with subtype BILLING_RETRY.
If you're already using
Grace Period in production,
and V2 Notifications in Sandbox,
you can expect to receive
the DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW notification
with subtype GRACE_PERIOD.
Here's an example subscription
in billing retry state, with Grace Period.
You will receive
DID_FAIL_TO_RENEW notifications
with subtype GRACE_PERIOD,
as well as GRACE_PERIOD_EXPIRED,
if billing failure simulation is still
enabled at the end of the grace period.
When verifying subscription information
with App Store Server API,
you can verify subscription state
by decoding the payload
of signedRenewalInfo.
Here, we see the expirationIntent
and billing retry fields are populated.
When calling /verifyReceipt with a receipt
for subscriptions in billing retry state,
you will see that the
is_in_billing_retry_period flag
is set to 1.
Also, when using grace period,
you can now expect grace period
expiration date fields to be populated.
Once you've completed testing
a billing failure in Sandbox,
you can disable the switch
in Sandbox Account Settings.
We hope this new testability
helps you build
the best possible experience
for your customers.
Today we discussed several
new testing capabilities you can use
to streamline testing
your app's in-app purchase functionality.
By syncing your configuration
in App Store Connect with Xcode,
you can use the same in-app purchase
configuration when testing locally
or with the Sandbox environment.
New capabilities like offer code
and refund testing in Xcode
will help you verify complex
StoreKit implementations.
And, subscription management testability
will enable you to evolve your app
to ensure a great customer experience,
even if their service is interrupted.
For details on how a billing failure
impacts subscription receipts,
plus, App Store Server Notifications V2
in Sandbox,
I recommend the WWDC 21 session,
"Manage in-app purchases on your server."
Also, to hear about what's new
in App Store Server API
and V2 Notifications, check out
"What's new with in-app purchase."
We look forward to hearing your feedback
about these new features.
Thank you for joining.