♪ ♪
Hi, I am Mohamed Samir,
a designer on the Apple Design team.
Today, I'm going to walk you through
some of the best practices
when it comes to designing an Arabic app.
This session is also available in Arabic,
so feel free to check it out.
And before we get started,
I wanted to touch on why it's important
to consider designing
or optimizing your app or game
to be used by Arab audience.
There is around 660 million people
that uses the Arabic script today,
which makes it the third most written
language in the world
after Latin and Chinese.
People from more than 22 countries,
many cities, and regions would potentially
see and use what you've built.
And If you want to reach even a fraction
of that audience,
you would want to consider optimizing
not only for the language,
but also for the directionality of the UI.
And this is because Arabic is a language
that is written from right to left.
To understand this,
let's look at this example,
that says "The Arabian desert" in Arabic,
And as you see, it's written from
the right to the left of the screen.
But this is not only it.
If this phrase exists in a layout,
the entire layout flows
from top to bottom, right to left,
to match the reading behavior
and direction of the language.
This means that things like titles,
paragraphs,
columns, and even imagery
should flow from right to left.
And this directionality behavior
extends beyond the layout to also the UI.
As in this example from the Pages app,
where the Navigation bar order
and direction is from right to left.
And the icons also flow
in the same direction.
And if you start navigating
through the app,
you would find menus, controls,
graphical elements,
and even tables have been designed
to match the natural flow
and behavior of the language.
Now, you might think that this
could be a lot of work to optimize
your app or game to work with Arabic,
but the good news is, a lot of this
has been taken care of by Apple
if you use our native frameworks,
like Swift UI,
so you can focus on the content
and few other UI details
that could be specific
to your app or game.
And in today's session I will share
with you some of these aspects
that you should be looking at
while doing this optimization.
Starting by the UI directionality
and example components
that you would want to consider.
Then we move to the Arabic script
main features
and the typography support
that Apple provides you for Arabic,
and how iconography is a detail
that enhances
the overall Arabic experience.
And at last, the numeral systems
supported by Apple for Arabic usage.
Let's start by the UI directionality.
This is an example from the App Store.
It is a flow that starts
by the story card in the Today tab,
the story page, and it ends
with the product page of an app.
The best way to think about
layout directionality
is to turn it into wireframes.
For Arabic,
you would want to switch the placement
of the UI components of these screens.
Some of the elements would switch
from right to left,
while others from left to right.
Titles, buttons, and the Navigation bar
should change order and position.
Paragraphs should be
always aligned to the right.
Carousals and swipeable elements
should also flow from right to left.
After changing the placement
of the UI components,
localizing the content,
and keeping the images as they are,
now you have a layout
that flows from right to left.
Changing the layout directionality
is only the beginning of your journey
to create an excellent
right-to-left behavior,
You would want to keep in mind
that the entire flow of the app
is now structured differently.
And the user thinks about the navigation
between these pages in a reverse order.
So mentally, they start
by the today tab on the right,
then they navigate through the story card,
and they end with the product page
on the left side–
as if they are navigating
through an Arabic book from right to left.
And as I mentioned earlier,
all of this happens automatically
if you use our native frameworks.
Now I would like to share with you
some other examples
for areas and components
that could be impacted
by changing the directionality of the UI.
Let's look at this example
from the Weather app.
On the left side
you see the English Layout,
while the Arabic layout
in on the right side.
The first thing that you would
notice here is content like images,
videos, and backgrounds remain the same.
In this example,
the sun always rises from the east
regardless the location or the language,
and you would want to avoid
flipping the content
so it doesn't impact
the overall experience.
The second component here is the carousal
of "the weather across the day".
Both, the interaction and the animation
of this component are inverted
to match the UI direction.
The third component that I would like
to share with you in the Weather app
is the temperature scale.
For Arabic, the lowest temperature
is on the right,
while the highest is on the left.
So as the scale gradient and indicator,
which we inverted
to match this behavior.
And as previously said,
the mental model
of switching between pages
is also reversed.
The primary page is on the far right,
and you navigate to secondary pages
on the left.
And therefore the pagination dots
should flow also from right to left.
And our second example here
is from the Calendar app,
in which the progress
and the flow of dates, months, and years
is from right to left
when used in Arabic,
which matches the progress
of physical calendars in the Arab world.
And it is always important to make sure
that your app is culturally relevant.
In this example here
from the Calendar app,
you may have noticed that there are
red lines beneath some dates.
These are actually used to indicate
the beginning of each month
of the Islamic Lunar Calendar,
which we have available for people
in the Arab and Islamic world.
The last example about directionality
is from the battery status in settings
where toggles, segmented controllers,
design, and interaction
are mirrored in the Arabic layout.
And also Charts is another place
where directionality could be impacted
in the UI–
especially charts that include
a time component,
like days, weeks, months, or years.
In the battery usage graph,
days of the week goes from left to right
in the English UI,
while in Arabic it is preferred
to have the days progress
from right to left
to match the calendar behavior that we
referred to in the previous example.
Which means that the early time would be
on the right,
and the late time is on the left.
And other charts and graphs in general
are dependent on the country,
so you would want to double-check
before deciding
on which direction to use for charts.
That was UI directionality.
Now let's talk about typography.
But before we dive into the typefaces
and the typestyle adjustments
that you would want to consider
while designing your app,
let me take you through
a brief introduction
about the Arabic script
and its main features.
These are four letters
that spell the word "Arabic" in Arabic,
but in writing they actually don't
mean anything on their own
until they get connected.
To understand this even more,
let me share with you how I would write
this word in a full Arabic sentence
using the iOS keyboard.
And as you see,
being connected doesn't mean
that all the letters in a given word
would be linked.
So this word is made of two parts.
Each part has two characters.
And this is one of the main features
of the Arabic script–
the connected nature of it.
And this also means
that the possible glyphs for each letter
and each pair can be many.
If we take the first letter here
in this example, the letter "Ain,"
its form changes based on its position
in the word,
whether it's isolated,
at the beginning of the word,
in the middle,
or at the end.
And it's worth noting that this
usually makes Arabic fonts libraries
way bigger than Latin.
Another feature of the Arabic script
that in most cases,
words are more concise than Latin
due to the connected nature
that tends to give
a more condensed feel
to words and phrases.
But it's also slightly taller,
especially with the use of dots,
vocalization, and diacritic marks.
Vocalization marks are used
to emphasize certain letters
or distinguish between words
that sound different
but would otherwise be identical
in writing.
And if your app would include
an intense use of vocalization marks,
make sure to have more vertical spacing
in the UI to avoid clipping.
Now we understand the main differences
between Arabic and Latin.
Let's talk about the typefaces that Apple
provides you if you use our system API.
Apple provides an exclusive
Arabic typeface that is designed carefully
with legibility and functionality in mind.
It is also designed to be consistent
with the Latin SF family style
to make if feel natural
in bilingual contexts.
And similar to Latin,
SF Arabic also provides you
with all possible weights
that you may need in your app.
from Ultralight to Black.
You can see the usage of different weights
in many places in our native apps.
The Clock app is a good example for that;
using Bold in the title,
Regular for the different cities,
and Light for the clock numerals.
You can explore more apps
in our ecosystem
to see how different weights can be used.
Like the Health app where bold,
medium, and regular
are used in titles and body copy.
And the Weather app where multiple weights
are used in numerals and body copy.
SF Arabic also has been made
with scalability in mind.
Which means that its form changes slightly
depending on the point size.
And this is what we call optical size.
You can see
the structural differences here
between the largest
and the smallest point sizes.
Large is usually used
for titles and headings.
And is designed to match the contemporary
grotesque feel of the rest of SF Family.
On the other hand, smaller point sizes,
which are used in paragraphs
and body copy,
are designed to prioritize legibility
and functionality over style.
This happens by adding angularity
to the terminals,
width and contrast
to the overall font structure.
It's worth noting that the system
takes care of this.
It is automatically choosing the
right form depending on the point size.
Here is an example from
the App Store Editorial sheet,
where we use display in the title,
and text is used in paragraphs.
And in both you could see how
Arabic and English typefaces
work seamlessly in this bilingual context.
SF Arabic Scalable typeface
is used across our ecosystem,
but it's also available for you
to use in your app or game.
And this year we're introducing
SF Arabic Rounded to the SF family,
including all its various weights,
from Ultralight to Black.
Here is an example from the Reminders app
where we use SF Arabic Rounded
in the titles and the body text.
And as you see, Rounded could
give your app a more practical,
active, or softer look,
depending on the context.
The usage of the Rounded typeface,
the several weights,
and the scalability of SF Arabic
can all be seen in all of our native apps,
and we can't wait for you to use them
to create the best possible experiences
for the Arab users.
If you would like to learn more
about all the new fonts
that have been announced this year,
including SF Arabic Rounded,
make sure to watch this year's session
"Meet the expanded
San Francisco font family".
Now let's talk about
some typestyle considerations
when using Arabic typefaces.
Arabic is a non-case sensitive script.
Digital Arabic fonts are usually designed
to match the lower case Latin.
But when uppercase is used,
it gives Latin more volume
and it makes Arabic feels smaller
in comparison to Latin.
To compensate for this this
optical size difference in the UI,
you may want to increase
the Arabic font size by 10%.
This subtle difference would also help
with legibility
especially when upper case is used
in smaller point sizes.
The other thing to consider
is letter spacing.
Given the fact that Arabic is connected,
some Arabic typefaces
are not fully optimized
to deal properly with spacing.
This can result
in showing misplaced links,
breaking letters apart,
or showing unnecessary spacing.
If the Arabic typeface you're using
isn't fully optimized for letter spacing,
make sure to use 0 tracking.
or simply, use our system font,
which adds the correct letters linkage.
This linkage in Arabic
is called "Kashida"
and the system adds Kashidas
with different lengths
to have more organic
natural spacing in Arabic.
The last thing to look out for
is transparency.
Sometimes you can see visible joints
between letters.
This often happens
if there is transparency in a font
or a system
that is not fully optimized for Arabic.
Thankfully, if you use our system font,
you don't have to worry about this.
Opacity is applied to the entire word
or phrase
to overcome any potential distortion.
In the typography section,
I talked about the main features
of the Arabic script,
the Arabic typefaces
that we use in our ecosystem,
and some considerations
for certain type treatments in Arabic.
Now let's talk about iconography.
Iconography is one of the UI elements
that could be easily missed,
but they are usually the entry point
to a user flow
or a trigger to a certain action,
which makes having the correct iconography
crucial
to having a seamless experience.
For Arabic,
we are committed to choosing
the most relevant symbols
for our customers.
Let's take the App Store tab bar icons
as an example.
Some symbols have been tweaked, while
others remained the same in the Arabic UI.
And to understand why we made this choice,
let's look at some of them.
The Today tab symbol, for example,
symbolizes text direction,
and it is more relevant for Arabic users
to have the lines aligned to the right
to match the natural reading direction
of the language.
While the magnifying glass's direction
implies the angle of the right hand usage,
which is the behavior of
the majority of users in the world,
regardless their location
so we decided to keep it as it is
in the Arabic UI.
And here some other examples
from other apps
that shows how directionality
can impact the way symbols are treated
in an Arabic UI,
like writing from right to left while
maintaining the angularity of the pen
or changing the speaker's direction
to make it feel natural in the UI
while maintaining the slash direction,
which is consistent
across our Apple ecosystem,
or changing the direction
of the calendar dots
that represent the progress of months
while keeping the clock hands as they are
to match the physical clock representation
in the system.
And on top of directionality,
having more locally relevant symbols
is another layer that we're dedicated
to enhancing over time
to ensure excellence
in our international markets.
And here are few examples
for Arabic specific symbols
from the SF symbols library,
including an exclusively drawn
Arabic signature symbol
and other text formatting ones.
All of this and more than 300 Arabic
and right-to-left symbols can be found
in SF Symbols app.
In the app you can easily choose a symbol
and check the localization section
in the info panel
to see the Arabic local variant
and other non-Latin scripts.
All of the right-to-left and the local
symbols should appear automatically
in your app
if you use our system API.
As we saw, using the right symbols
can transform the entire app experience,
as it becomes more relevant to the users.
And especially for countries
and regions that use a non-Latin script,
we need to pay more attention,
as sometimes we forget about the different
linguistic and cultural nuances.
And I really hope to see your contribution
in creating the most relevant icons
for the Arabic customers.
Now let's talk about Arabic numerals.
The numerals that we're all familiar with
and are used in most countries around
the world are called Arabic numerals.
And this is because they were
invented in the Arab world
and they replaced
the Roman numerals back then.
And you can notice that until today
all mathematical calculations happens
from right to left,
matching the reading behavior
of the Arabic language.
Like this example which starts
the summation process by ones,
then tens, then hundreds.
In today's world this form of numerals
is called Western Arabic numerals,
and that is to contrast it
with the other form of Arabic numerals
which is the Eastern one.
Both forms have been invented
in the Arab world
and are currently used
in different Arab countries.
The Western Arabic numerals is used
in West African Arab countries
like Morocco, Algeria, and Tunisia,
while the Eastern is used in
some Levantine and gulf countries.
Countries like Egypt or Saudi Arabia
uses both versions.
Choosing between both systems
happens automatically
according to the user's country,
and also can be triggered
by the user choice.
And you can see a reflection
of this choice
in the all apps that uses numerals
in our ecosystem.
Including Calculator app,
and the Calendar app,
and the Typograph watch face
that is beautifully designed
in both numeral forms.
And many other watch faces that you can
check in our watch face gallery.
If the app that you're developing
includes numerals,
make sure to count for both forms
or to check which country you're targeting
to validate which form
would be more suitable.
And at last, if you would like to have
more design guidance
for right-to-left languages,
please refer to
our Right to Left guidelines
in the Human Interface Guidelines.
Today I talked about Designing in Arabic,
including the impact that the language
can have on the UI directionality.
And in the typography section,
I gave an introduction
about the Arabic script,
the typefaces,
and some Arabic UI type considerations.
I also talked about iconography
and how it can
transform your app experience,
the Arabic numerals in its both forms,
and the Right to Left Guidelines.
And if you would like to even dive deeper
into how to get all of this right
from a development perspective,
you can also check this year's session
"Get it Right (to Left)".
I hope all of this gave you guidance
and pointed you at the right tools
to start designing or optimizing
your app to be used in the Arab world.
And I can't wait to use all the amazing
Arabic apps that you're going to build.