[spacey music]
Eric: Hello!
Welcome to WWDC!
My name is Eric.
I'm an engineer from the Maps team.
Today, I'm joined by my colleague Yingxiu,
and together,
we're going to explore what's new
in MapKit.
It's been 3 years since Apple
Maps introduced its all-new map
and its immersive Look Around experience.
Originally launched with U.S. support,
the all-new map and Look Around coverage
has been expanding since
and now includes Canada,
many European countries, Japan, and more.
Last year, Apple Maps took things
to the next level
by introducing 3D City Experiences,
featuring turn lanes,
crosswalks, bike lanes,
and beautifully handcrafted 3D landmarks
like the Ferry Building.
The additional detail of the map
allows you
to provide context and precision
that was never before possible,
and the addition of 3D terrain elevation
provides a level of realism
like no other map!
This year, MapKit brings
the latest innovations
from Apple Maps to your apps,
letting your users explore the world
in amazing details.
In this talk, we'll be covering
several new MapKit features.
First, we'll talk about adopting
the all-new map
and fully leveraging it using
the Map Configuration API.
Next, we'll cover various improvements
we made to our overlay APIs
to allow for a seamless integration
of your content with the map.
We'll also discuss
our new blend modes support
and show how you can make use of it
to further enhance the presentation
of your map content.
Then, we'll cover ways of making your maps
more interactive
by adopting our brand-new
Selectable Map Features API.
And finally, we'll cover integrating
the immersive Look Around experience
directly into your applications.
We've got a lot to cover, so buckle up
as we head for our first topic:
adopting the all-new map
and using the Map Configuration API.
Adopting the all-new map in your iOS,
macOS, or tvOS application
couldn't be easier.
Simply recompile your app
with the new SDK,
and it will be automatically opted in
to the all-new Apple map,
including the 3D City Experience,
where available.
For many applications, a simple recompile
is all that's needed.
Of course, there may be situations
where you need more control
over the presentation of the map.
In iOS 15, the way you configure the map
is through various properties
on MKMapView.
In iOS 16, however,
we're soft deprecating those properties,
and we're introducing
our new Map Configuration API
as a replacement.
MKMapConfiguration is the central class
of the new Map Configuration API.
MKMapConfiguration is
an abstract base class
with three concrete subclasses.
The imagery map configuration is used
to present satellite-style imagery.
The hybrid map configuration is used
to present an imagery-based map
with added map features such
as road labels and points of interest.
The standard map configuration is used
to present a fully graphics-based map.
These three map configurations may sound
familiar to you, as they're similar
to our existing map types.
The base map configuration class
supports an elevationStyle property,
which can be either flat or realistic.
A flat elevation style means
that the ground appears flat.
Roads, including
bridges and overpasses, also appear flat.
Flat is the default elevation style.
A realistic elevation style means
that the ground terrain reproduces
the real-world elevation
such as hills and mountains.
Roads are depicted
with realistic elevation details.
Now let's take a closer look
at the map configuration subclasses.
The imagery map configuration
only shows satellite imagery
with no additional map features,
so it doesn't have any other properties.
The hybrid map configuration
has additional properties
to control filtering
of point of interest categories
and whether to show traffic or not.
The standard map configuration supports
an emphasisStyle property
which can be either default or muted.
As the name implies, this is
the default emphasis style
unless otherwise stated.
The muted emphasis style softens
the contrasts of the map details,
allowing you to bring more attention
to additional graphical information
you might want to show on top.
The standard map configuration
also has additional properties
to control filtering
of point of interest categories
and whether to show traffic or not.
And that sums up
the available map configuration classes
and their properties.
This new API ensures
you can only configure
supported combinations of options.
It also allows you to change
the map configuration atomically.
We think this is a great improvement
over our existing APIs.
To recap what we just discussed,
here's a table that shows
the correspondence
between the new map configuration classes
and the MKMapType property.
The all-new map
with the 3D City Experience
requires compatible hardware.
On iOS, the new map support requires
A12-based iPhones and iPads or later.
On macOS, the new map support requires
any M1-based computer or later.
In areas where the 3D City Experience is
not available,
the map will automatically fall back
to present the all-new map
with a flat elevation.
On all other devices, the all-new map
will be presented with a flat elevation.
On M1 Macs, Xcode allows you to simulate
both experiences
simply by changing the OS version.
We encourage you to try out both,
to ensure that your app looks great
on all devices!
The 3D City Experience is available
in many metropolitan areas
around the world.
We're continuously adding new cities
to this list,
so I encourage you to check out
the 3D City Experience section
on the feature availability website linked
in the session notes.
This concludes our section on adopting
the all-new map
and using the Map Configuration API.
Now let's dive into overlays.
MapKit has supported overlays
with several styling options for years.
In iOS 16,
we are improving our existing APIs
to allow your overlays to seamlessly
integrate with the map.
Let's start with a quick recap
of overlay levels.
Overlays can be rendered
at two different levels:
above roads and above labels.
You can specify the rendering level
at insertion time
using one of MapKit's
many overlay insertion functions.
Above labels renders your overlay
above everything, including labels.
Since labels
provide important context information,
we encourage you to only use above labels
in those rare cases
where you don't want your data
to interact with the map at all.
If what you're trying to achieve
is for your content
to stand out against the map,
you might want to consider
using the muted map emphasis
or the blend modes,
which we'll talk about later.
Above roads means the overlay
will be shown on top of the terrain,
including roads, land cover,
or bodies of water.
It will, however, be shown below labels
and, to some degree,
trees and buildings.
More on that in a second.
Above roads will be
the new default mode in iOS 16.
Next, let's talk about a new feature
we're introducing in iOS 16
called transparent buildings.
Regardless of whether your overlay level
is above roads or above labels,
your overlay will always be rendered
on top of buildings
when viewed top-down with no pitch.
However, we've made some improvements
to the experience when using above roads
in combination with a pitched map.
Ground objects such as trees and buildings
are now automatically rendered
with transparency
when appearing above overlays,
so as not to fully obscure them.
The alpha value varies
with the map's pitch angle.
If we revert to showing the map top-down
with a 0º pitch angle,
colliding ground objects effectively
disappear from view,
leaving your overlays fully visible.
Transparent buildings also work
for semi-transparent overlays.
The alpha value of the overlay
will be added to combine
with the alpha value
of the transparent buildings.
There's one more change
we're making to overlays.
When adding an overlay to a map
with realistic terrain,
MapKit will automatically transition
the map to a flat representation.
The map will automatically go back
to realistic when you remove
the last overlay.
One notable exception to this rule
are overlays sourced
through MapKit's directions API.
Those overlays
automatically follow the terrain.
And with that, I'm going
to hand it over to Yingxiu.
Yingxiu: Thank you, Eric.
Hi! I'm Yingxiu.
I'm an engineer on the Maps team.
I'm going to demonstrate
our new MapKit features
and show you how easy it is to build
beautiful map experiences
with our updated APIs.
I will be using our sample app,
which helps users rent scooters
to tour San Francisco.
Our app offers a number of features,
as shown by the rows in this table view.
"Operating Area" allows the user
to see where they can take our scooters.
"Ride" takes the user on a tour
across the Golden Gate Bridge.
"Explore" gives the user
an interactive map
of downtown San Francisco,
which they can use
to explore attractions
near the waterfront.
"Highlights" offers a closer look
at must-see places.
We will implement or upgrade
these features throughout this session.
Let's get started!
First, I'm going to use
the Operating Area feature
to demonstrate how easy it is
to adopt the all-new map,
and then I'll show you
some of the improvements we have made
to overlays.
I already have the project opened
in Xcode.
Let's compile it with iOS 16 SDK
and see how it looks.
Here we are!
We are already opted into the all-new map.
We get a map view with rich details,
including these beautiful lighting
and hill-shading effects on the terrain.
As we zoom in,
you will see buildings, trees...
…and landmarks.
Now let's add a polygon overlay
to visualize our operating area.
Here I already have the polygon data ready
for the operating area.
When the view is loaded, we'll first set
the region and the camera boundary.
Make sure we look at the correct area.
Then, we simply add the overlay.
Let's build it and check it out!
The polygon overlay is opaque
when viewed straight down.
As we zoom in and pitch,
the buildings begin to show,
with the transparency increasing
as we pitch further.
This effect is only available
when using the overlay level AboveRoads.
If you want to leverage
transparent buildings and trees,
make sure you choose
the correct overlay level.
The overlay looks great,
but I'd like the map to show through
even when not pitched.
Let's go back to the code
and make it semi-transparent.
Let's change alpha to 0.8.
Now we have a transparent overlay
and I can see roads and buildings
even when not pitched.
If I zoom in and pitch the map,
I still get an increase in transparency.
This looks great!
That's it for polygon overlays.
Next, I want to show you
how to integrate realistic terrain
and show adding an elevated route line.
This will complete our "Ride" feature,
a tour across the Golden Gate Bridge.
Let's start by configuring the map view.
We can change the elevation style in code,
or we can just open
the Interface Builder inspector
on the right-hand side.
Here are the available map view
configuration settings.
Let's select elevation realistic.
Next, let's work on the route.
For this feature, we want to show a route
when the user toggles
the Show Route switch.
We will also animate the camera
to focus on the route.
Since we want to show a route
across the Golden Gate Bridge,
we'll use the Presidio Park entry
as the start point
and the Battery Spencer as the end point.
When the map view is loaded,
we'll create annotations
to mark the start and destination points.
Set coordinates and title,
append it to the annotation array,
then add them to the map view.
Now, we can focus on the route polyline.
While normal overlays will flatten the
map,
the polyline returned
by MapKit's Directions API
will preserve the realistic terrain.
In this action function, once the switch
is turned on,
we'll create place marks
with the coordinates defined above.
Then we create a direction request,
with source and destination.
Finally, we request the directions.
If the fetch operation succeeds,
simply add the route polyline
as an overlay.
All right.
Let's compile it and see how it looks!
You'll notice the annotations are
automatically upgraded
to the new gradient look.
They are also seamlessly displayed
at the correct elevation.
Once I toggle show route,
the camera will pitch.
Then, you can get a better view of them.
As you can see, the route line follows
the elevated terrain.
This comes in handy
when navigating complex intersections.
It also follows the road
across the bridge.
Also, notice how the route
subtly shows through the bridge pillars.
Finally, when the map is really pitched,
you can see the route show
through the trees
that stand in front of it.
Well, look, the route line color
is washed out here,
where there is no trees.
Let's zoom out and check
what's happening here.
All right, this part of the route goes
through a tunnel,
so we get transparency for it.
ElevationRealisticStyle
and the elevated route line feature
are supported on A12-based iOS devices.
If I run the same app
on an older iOS device,
I will automatically get a 2D route
on a 2D map..
It's that simple to add an
elevated route line
to a 3D city experience map!
With that, I hand it back to Eric.
Eric: Thanks, Yingxiu!
That scooter ride across
the Golden Gate Bridge
looks absolutely stunning!
So that's just some of what's new
with MapKit overlays.
Next up, let's talk about blend modes.
This new API gives you more control
over the look and feel of your overlays
and unlocks a whole range
of new creative possibilities.
I'm sure many of you are already familiar
with blend modes from photo editing apps
or Apple's CoreGraphics API.
During a blend operation,
two graphical layers are combined
following a set of equations
specified by the blend mode.
Now, let's look at an example
of how we might use blend modes
in a MapKit context.
In this scenario, I want to highlight
the area
of the Presidio National Park
in San Francisco
in the center of this map.
First, I'm going to create an overlay
covering my entire map area,
with a cutout in the shape
of the Presidio.
I'm not using any blend modes yet.
This is just a plain overlay,
in the shape of a big square doughnut.
Next, I assign a hue blend mode
to the overlay, with a gray fill.
This desaturates the map
outside of the Presidio.
Next, I'm going to duplicate that overlay
and assign it a hard light blend mode,
with a dark gray fill.
This has the effect of darkening the area
around the Presidio.
This already looks nice,
but lets add another overlay.
This time, we'll add an overlay
in the shape of the Presidio
and assign a saturation blend mode,
with a yellow fill.
Whoa, that's not exactly the effect
I was aiming for here.
The colors are way too bright.
Let's try something else.
We'll apply a color burn blend mode
with a gray fill.
There, that's a little more subtle.
Perfect!
Now, let's look at some code.
To enable the kind of effects we just saw,
we added a property to MKOverlayRenderer,
called blendMode.
All you need to do is set
the desired CoreGraphics blend mode
on the overlay renderer, and you're done!
As previously mentioned, blend modes
are order dependent.
The overlay at the bottom of the stack
is blended with the map,
the second-to-last overlay is then blended
with the result
of the previous blend operation,
and so on.
In MapKit, the order of overlays is
determined at insertion time.
You can use either absolute
or relative positioning
using one of MKMapView's
many overlay insertion functions.
MapKit supports a wide range
of blend modes
and we can't possibly cover
all of them today.
I encourage you try them out.
And that's it for blend modes!
As you've just seen,
blend modes are a powerful tool to control
the styling of your map.
You can use it
to highlight geographical areas,
deemphasize the map to make
your content stand out,
and so much more.
Next up, let's talk
about Selectable Map Features!
This has been a highly requested feature,
and I'm really excited to show it to you!
If you are using MapKit in your app today,
you're likely leveraging annotations
to show the location of cities,
points of interest, or physical objects.
Unless you're using POI filtering,
you are placing those annotations
on a map which already contains
a number of similar annotations
provided by Apple.
Up until now, your users
could only interact
with the annotations you provided.
In iOS 16, we're going to change that.
Using our new Selectable Map Features API,
you'll now have the option to let
your users select features on the map.
Selectable map features include
points of interest,
such as stores, restaurants,
and landmarks;
territories, such as cities and states;
and physical features,
such as mountain ranges and lakes.
To adopt Selectable Map Features
in your app,
all you need to do is go
through a few simple steps.
First, configure which feature types
should be selectable.
As we just saw,
there are three main feature types,
and it might not make sense
for all of them
to be interactive in the context
of your app.
For points-of-interest features,
you can also use our existing filter API
to further restrict which
points-of-interest categories can appear
and therefore be selectable.
Second, implement the MKMapView
delegate callbacks
to handle selection events.
You are free to handle these events
however you choose.
You might want to control how selected
features appear,
or you might want to show
some additional UI
in response to the selection events.
Third, you'll want to request and display
additional place information
in your application's user interface.
The information embedded
in the map feature
is limited to what you see on screen.
To give users more context about the place
they selected,
you'll need to request
additional information.
Let me walk you through the new APIs
for each of these steps.
We'll start with configuring
which map features
should be selectable
using the new selectableMapFeatures
property.
You can choose any combination
of points of interest, territories,
and physical features.
Once you have configured
the selectable map features
and the user taps one of those features,
you'll start receiving
some new delegate callbacks
allowing you to customize
the selection behavior.
The first callback you'll get is
the new didSelect annotation callback.
This callback is a great opportunity
for you to request additional data
about the map item
using the new request API we'll cover
in a moment.
The second callback you'll get is
the existing viewFor annotation callback.
This is where you can customize the view
which will be shown
for the selected state.
While this is existing API,
we've added a new type of annotation class
called MapFeatureAnnotation.
This class will be passed to view
for annotation
when the user selects a map feature.
MapFeatureAnnotation
has a number of properties.
You can inspect the FeatureType property
to determine whether the map feature
is a point of interest,
a territory, or a physical feature.
If the map feature is a point of interest,
the pointOfInterestCategory property
will let you know what its category is,
and the iconStyle property will let you
obtain additional information
about the icon,
such as its background color
and the icon image itself.
Let's look at an example of how
to customize your annotation view
using the viewFor annotation callback.
If you want to achieve
the same selection style
as the Maps app, all you have to do
is return nil.
If you want to customize
the selection style,
you can return an annotationView,
the same way you would
for your own annotations.
The markerAnnotationView
is a great option.
It will give you
the same balloon-style shape
as the Maps app,
a gradient treatment,
and it allows you to choose your own color
or icon.
In my example here, I've chosen to use
the same image obtained
from the feature's icon style
and only change the color
to match the application's tint color.
If you want to go fully custom,
you can provide
any annotation view subclass
that you create.
As you just saw, you can use
the feature annotation
to retrieve visual information
about the selected feature.
By passing the feature annotation on to
our new MKMapItemRequest API,
you can also retrieve a map item
for the selected feature.
This map item contains additional metadata
about the place,
such as an address, a name,
a phone number, and a URL.
The map item also provides a function
to punch out to the Maps app
if your users want to see
additional metadata
which isn't available through MapKit.
And now, I will again hand it over
to Yingxiu.
Yingxiu: Thank you, Eric.
Eric just walked you through
the Selectable Map Features.
I'm going to show you
how easy it is to leverage that API.
For that, we will implement
our Explore feature.
We want our users to be able to explore
some interesting places
near the waterfront.
If they tap on POIs,
annotations should show up.
We will perform a camera animation
to the tapped location,
and show an info card from the bottom.
First, let's filter points of interest
on the map
and remove the categories
which are irrelevant to our tour.
Aside from applying the filter in code,
we can also apply it
in Interface Builder inspector.
Let's select the map view,
and go to inspector
on the right-hand side.
Here, we will do an exclusion filter.
I'll select the categories
that we don't want,
for example: airport,
car rental, hospital, and laundry.
Now we should only have
desired point of interests
on the map view.
It's very simple to enable
Selectable Map Features.
All we need to do is to specify
an option set
of desired selectable features.
In the scope of this sample app,
we'll just use points of interest,
but keep in mind, we also support
selectable physical features
and territories.
We can use the existing delegate method
mapView viewForAnnotation
to create a view
for the feature annotation.
Here, we'll just return nil for now...
To use the default gradient annotation
offered by MapKit.
We'll come back to customize it later.
If an annotation is on Selected state,
we will be informed
through the new delegate method
mapView didSelectAnnotation.
Let's use this function
to perform a camera animation
and zoom in on the selected feature.
First, let's cast the annotation
to featureAnnotation,
then create a map item request with it.
This is a new API to fetch
additional place informations
with feature annotations.
Let's issue the request.
Once the fetch operation succeeds,
we will animate to the map item.
When the camera animation has completed,
we will get details from the feature item
and show them on an info card.
Compile it and see how it looks.
Let's check out some interesting places
at the waterfront.
The gradient annotations show up.
The camera animates to the tab location.
Then the info card shows up.
This is a museum.
Here is the URL.
We can check it out if we're interested.
And we get the full address.
If it's a landmark,
we will get this beautiful iconography.
Now let's go back to the code
and customize our annotation
for the selection state.
Instead of nil, let's create
a MarkerAnnotationView.
We'll cast the annotation
to featureAnnotation first,
so we can use specific data from it
to customize the view.
Let's tint the annotation
with a purple-ish color
so it's in line
with our corporate identity.
We can also customize
the annotation glyph.
SelectedGlyphImage
is for annotations on Selected state.
GlyphImage is smaller.
It is the glyph for annotations
on Unselected state.
We recommend assigning them the same glyph
for a smooth transition
from the Unselected to Selected state.
Let's use the icon style image we got
from the featureAnnotation.
MKIconStyle is a new class in iOS16.
It has the iconography and color info
of the selected POI.
Compile and see how it looks in the app.
Here you go!
Now we have an annotation
that matches our corporate colors,
but still uses Apple iconography.
That's how you can enable
selectable map features
and customize annotations
in your own apps!
With that, I hand it back to Eric.
Eric: Thanks, Yingxiu!
As you just saw,
the Selectable Map Features API
enables your users to interact
with the map
in a whole new way.
The MapFeatureAnnotation class,
in combination
with the MapView delegate callbacks,
allow you to customize
the selection look and feel,
while the MapItemRequest
allows you to resolve a feature
to a map item, giving you access
to additional information
about the selected map feature.
Next, let's talk about around Look Around!
The Maps app introduced Look Around
in iOS 13,
and people absolutely love it.
You can use Look Around
to get a real sense of a place.
Look Around imagery offers
an incredible level of detail,
leveraging 3D models to provide a level
of realism
like no other map.
Look Around is available in many places
around the world, including these cities,
and entire countries!
We're continuously adding support
for new regions,
so I again encourage you to check out
the Look Around section
on the feature availability website
linked in the session notes.
With iOS 16, we're bringing Look Around
to MapKit,
and adopting it only requires
three simple steps.
First, you'll need to check whether data
is available for the desired location.
Even if Look Around is available
in your target region,
not every location can be seen
from a street,
and therefore, Look Around imagery
might not always be available.
Once you've determined
whether Look Around data is available,
you'll need to pass that data on
to either the Look Around View Controller
or the Look Around Snapshotter.
And finally, if Look Around data
is available,
you'll want to update your app UI
to show the Look Around preview.
Let's take a look at the new APIs
you will be using
to accomplish those three simple tasks.
The first step in attempting to show
a Look Around preview
is to check for data availability.
For this, you'll need to create
a LookAroundSceneRequest,
which is a new class we're introducing
in iOS 16.
You can initialize a new instance
with either a coordinate
or a map item.
Next, you'll want to retrieve
its scene property.
This is an optional async property.
If data is available, you will get back
a scene instance.
If data is not available,
you will get back a nil instead.
And if there
was a problem with the request,
an error will be thrown.
The Look Around Scene is an opaque object
with no properties.
It acts as a token
that ensures the availability
of Look Around imagery
for a requested location.
To show an interactive preview
of the Look Around scene,
you simply pass the scene on
to a new
Look Around View Controller instance
as an init parameter
or assign it
to the read write scene property
of an existing instance.
Alternatively, if all you need
is a static image,
you can also pass the scene on
to a new Look Around View
Snapshotter instance
as an init parameter
and subsequently retrieve
its snapshot async property.
The Look Around view controller is
designed to make it as easy as possible
to embed a smaller static preview
of a Look Around image,
which the user can tap on to enter
a full-screen
Look Around interactive session.
And now, we'll hand it over to Yingxiu
once more
so that she can show us how easy
it really is to put it all together.
Yingxiu: Thank you, Eric.
Eric just showed us the immersive
Look Around experience support
coming to MapKit.
I'm going to show you
how straightforward it is
to integrate it in our sample app.
For that, we'll move on
to our last feature, Highlights.
Users can get a realistic view
of must-see places.
We already have a couple
of San Francisco landmark names
in the segment control bar
on top of the screen.
When users tap on one of them,
we want to perform a camera animation
to the tapped location.
We also want to show a Look around preview
at bottom left,
which our users can expand
to full screen.
Let's do it!
First we need to add a container view
for our Look Around preview.
Let's go to the size inspector.
Let's give it a position and size.
We want to hide this preview
at the beginning,
so let's open the attributes inspector
and check Hidden.
Next, we need to create
a Look Around view controller...
And embed it
to the container view.
Same as any other segue,
I need to give it an identifier.
Let's call it
"presentLookAroundEmbedded."
And import it to code so we can update
its visibility later.
Let's name it "preview."
Here, we already have
a LookAroundViewController declared.
We just need to grab
the instance in the prepare function.
Make sure the segue identifier is matched.
Then, in the segment control function,
we'll create a local search
with the landmark name.
If the request succeeds,
we will get a map item
which will be used
in the following camera animation
and Look Around scene retrieval.
For camera animation,
we first need to create a camera
with the new API.
MapCamera looking at map item.
Let's use map view frame size
for the view size,
and set allow pitch to true.
This will give us
a pitch view to landmarks
and a top-down view to other places.
Assign the new camera.
That's it.
Once the camera animation is completed,
we'll show its Look Around preview.
First, we need to determine
if the Look Around data
is available for this map item.
To do that, we need to use
the new LookAroundSceneRequest class.
Let's create our request
and pass in the map item.
Then perform the request.
If get scene request succeeds,
just assign the scene
to our LookAroundViewController.
If there is no error but we get nil
for the scene,
it means Look Around data
is not available at the request location.
Finally, don't forget to show the preview.
Let's see how it looks in the app!
Let's try with the Ferry Building.
There you go.
The Ferry Building is a landmark,
so we see
this fantastic curated camera framing
to a hero angle,
and the Look Around preview shows up.
Let's try with another place, Dragon Gate.
Dragon Gate is not a landmark,
so we get its top-down view.
Let's tap on the preview
to enter full screen.
It's an interactive view,
so I can navigate around.
I also get these beautiful icons
and labels for stores
in the Look Around full-screen view.
It's that easy to add
an immersive Look Around experience
in your own app.
With that, I hand it back to Eric.
Eric: Thank you, Yingxiu!
The Interface Builder support
for Look Around
makes it look so easy!
So we've covered a lot of topics today,
from the automatic adoption
of the all-new map
and the new Map Configuration API,
new behaviors and advances for overlays,
to all-new capabilities
like Selectable Map Features
and Look Around support.
We think you'll agree there's a lot here
you can use to take the map experience
in your app to the next level,
and we can't wait to see
what you'll accomplish with it.
Before I go, there's a few things
I'd like to leave you with.
As always, your feedback is instrumental
in helping us prioritize
what we focus on next,
so please be sure
to use the Feedback Assistant
to send us your bug reports
and the features you'd find
most helpful for your app.
In addition, we've updated
many of our existing samples
to incorporate what we just discussed.
We encourage you to check them out.
And finally, we've announced a new set
of REST APIs
you'll want to take a look at.
We think these APIs will be really useful
for those of you looking to move
common calls
for geocoding, ETA determination,
and more to your server.
For all the details, be sure to check out
the session titled
Meet Apple Maps Server APIs.
On behalf of the Maps team,
thanks for watching...
both: And have a great WWDC!
[spacey music]