[spacey percussive music]
Kaely Coon: Hi, my name is Kaely Coon.
Jennifer Bush:
And I'm Jennifer Bush.
We're writers here at Apple,
working as part
of Human Interface design teams
across Apple products and services.
Today, we're going to share some tips
and best practices we've learned
that we hope will help you,
as developers,
approach writing for your app or game.
Kaely: Sometimes we're called
UX Writers or Content Designers,
and what we write can be
referred to as strings, copy, or text,
but essentially, it's our job
to design through the lens of language.
From the earliest days at Apple,
we wanted to design devices for everyone.
This meant they needed to be able
to communicate with anyone.
The first Macs were built
on the design principle
"what you see is what you get,"
which includes the language.
Mac was built using simple language
that was easy to understand.
It focused on the person using it,
welcoming you in,
and now, across our products,
as soon as you turn them on,
we say "Hello."
Since those early days, we've continued
to be conversational in our interfaces.
When words work seamlessly with design,
you may not even notice them,
but they're pivotal to every part
of a user experience.
The words are there to help people
do what they want to do,
whether it's create a Memoji,
watch a movie, or find focus.
Let's take a look at an app
with the words removed.
Feels a bit empty, doesn't it?
In the Apple Music app, the visuals
give you a hint at what each section is,
but would you know the difference
between an album and a playlist?
How about how
to browse or listen to the radio?
Even if there aren't
a lot of words on a screen,
they help you understand what's expected,
and what to do next.
And if you were to come across an error,
they'd help you find your way.
Writing is about communicating,
which, of course, includes the words,
but it also includes the structure
of those words,
the timing in which they appear,
and the feeling people have reading them.
I mentioned how UX writers
designed through the lens of language.
Now, you may hear that and wonder,
"What does that even mean?"
It means the earlier you make writing
a part of the process
of designing your app,
the better the experience
will be for the people who use it.
In this session,
we'll walk you through the types of things
we consider as we develop
the words in our products.
They're not the only things
we think about when we write,
as there are often many considerations,
but we hope this provides
a useful framework
to keep in mind when writing for your app.
These are: Purpose, Anticipation,
Context, and Empathy.
You'll notice we've given
you an acronym of "PACE,"
which is an important thing
to consider while writing.
Pace is about creating a natural flow
so you keep people engaged
and interested
in what you're telling them.
This means knowing what to say,
how to say it, and when.
Now, I'll hand it to Jen
to talk about Purpose.
Jen: As you develop the screens
in your app,
think about the most important thing
someone needs to know at that moment.
That's the purpose of your screen.
So how do you convey that?
First, consider information hierarchy,
or how you order the elements
on the screen.
Here's an example.
This is an intro screen
for a Messages flow.
You know the purpose because
it's right at the top:
"Share Your Name and Photo with Friends."
You probably noticed that first.
Next, you might have read the button
that says "Choose Name and Photo."
We know people don't always read
the text on screen in order,
so make sure your headers
and buttons are clear.
The rest of the text on the screen
still has an important purpose.
It tells you what you can customize,
and that you can choose
who you want to share this with,
but the text is a little smaller.
The information hierarchy helps
convey this screen's purpose.
Know what to leave out.
When you know the purpose of a screen,
you can make choices about which ideas
you want to keep
in, which you can take out,
or which ones you can move someplace else.
Here's a wireframe of a made-up version
of a temperature warning screen
for iPhone.
The title says "iPhone Needs
to Cool Down." That sounds clear.
But there's a lot more text,
and this screen is trying to do too much.
Think about the purpose of the screen.
Is it to tell you
why iPhone needs to cool down?
If so, it tells you that you might
be in the sun or using too many apps.
Maybe it's to tell you that
you can still make an emergency call.
That button is pretty large.
It almost looks like the screen
is suggesting it's necessary.
Let's look at what we went with.
This screen is much simpler.
The headline is just "Temperature."
Because the thermometer image
conveys that the temperature is high,
we don't need to say that explicitly.
And the single sentence tells you
that iPhone needs to cool down
before you can use it.
The button just says "Emergency,"
so if you needed to make
an emergency call,
it would be clear what to do.
Rather than give too many details,
aim for simplicity.
You can tell people the purpose
of a screen; it's not a secret!
When introducing a new feature to someone,
for example,
tell them why it's there,
and why it's important.
In this intro screen with the header
"Wind Down Shortcuts," it tells you,
"Reducing screen time
is one of the best things you can do
before bed."
That's the purpose of this feature,
and now you know
why you might want to set it up.
Have a purpose for every screen.
When there are multiple steps in a flow,
define the purpose of the entire flow,
as well as each screen within it.
This can help keep screens brief
and reduce unnecessary steps.
At the start,
think about how to welcome people in
and teach them what they need to know.
Here are a few of the screens
in a flow designed to help you set up
Apple Cash for family sharing.
The text tells you who Apple Cash is for,
"family members who are under 18,"
and what they can do with it,
"send and receive money and use
Apple Pay for purchases."
In this next step,
the purpose is to let you know
what you're going to do next,
verify your identity,
and give you some important information
about data and privacy.
This privacy information takes up
quite a bit of space on the screen,
but it's important.
Privacy is one of Apple's core values.
Think about your app's values
and make sure
they're represented throughout.
After you verify your identity,
and you're at the end of this flow,
you're still not quite ready
to start using the feature.
This "Almost Ready" screen tells you
that the "card activation may take a few
minutes," and to expect a notification.
And here it is!
Now you can send money with Apple Cash.
If you're having a hard time
deciding what to write on a screen,
go back to its purpose.
You can convey purpose
by considering information hierarchy,
knowing what to leave out,
and having a purpose for every screen.
Kaely:
Next, let's talk about Anticipation.
It helps to think of the words
in your app as part of a conversation.
A dialogue happens
between your app and whoever's using it.
In any good conversation,
there's a back and forth.
Sometimes you're listening, sometimes
you're talking, or asking questions.
Similarly, in your app,
you're anticipating
how to best communicate for each moment.
Let's say it's a weekend
and you've decided to sleep in,
so you go to the Clock app
to change your alarm.
You want to make sure you're changing
the alarm just for tomorrow,
not your whole schedule.
The action sheet asks,
"Would you like to apply this change
to all weekends in this schedule?"
The first selection is
to "Change Next Alarm Only,"
anticipating that most of the time,
you're likely to just be thinking
about tomorrow's wake-up.
When you head to bed,
the lock screen says "Sleep Well"
and tells you that Sleep Focus is on.
The small button shows you
that your alarm is set for 8:30 AM.
"Sleep Well" has
a friendly and familiar tone,
and acknowledges
that you're going to sleep.
The next morning, if you get up
before the alarm
and start using your iPhone,
it anticipates that you might not want
that alarm to sound.
So it asks, "It looks like you're awake.
Would you like to turn off
your alarm and sleep mode?"
The conversation feels intuitive, like
your device is speaking to your needs.
When it comes to being conversational,
writers talk a lot about voice and tone.
Develop your app's voice first,
and then you can vary its tone.
Start by asking yourself:
what would it say and not say?
Are you developing a game
that's exciting and fun?
Is it a banking app that needs
to be secure and trustworthy?
Is it an app that's kid-friendly?
Think about who you're talking to
to help figure out the type
of vocabulary you'll use.
Make a list of commonly used terms.
This can help shape the voice
that you can also use for your website,
emails, and other communication.
Anticipating what people are going through
helps you consider your tone.
Here, Apple Watch says,
"It looks like you've taken a hard fall"
and if you're okay,
you can answer, "I'm okay."
The tone is calm and clear
in what could be a stressful moment.
Apple has one consistent voice
that you'll recognize
no matter which
of our devices you're using,
but our tone changes
depending on the situation.
Think of how your tone of voice
changes when you pick up the phone
and talk to your friend versus,
say, your bank.
Here, in the Activity app on Watch,
when you've set a Move streak,
it says, "You set a personal record
for your longest daily Move streak:
35 days!"
The tone is quite celebratory,
so it has an exclamation point.
Be careful how often
you use those, though.
They can look silly when they're frequent.
When writing for apps,
you always have to ask, "What comes next?"
Anticipating the next action
or question someone's going to have
will help you know what to say.
In the Breathe app on Apple Watch,
the instructions tell you
to "Be still,
and bring your attention to your breath."
You might not be sure how to start
doing that, so then it says, "Now inhale…"
"And exhale."
It answers your question of how to use it,
as the visuals reinforce the message,
and the watch vibrates
to help with timing.
And in this example from Maps,
when you're likely to be heading home,
you see a notification that tells you
about your commute: "8 minutes to Home"
and to "Take Audubon Ave,
traffic is light."
It helps you make a decision
by anticipating what you'll do next.
When design
and text work closely together,
an app feels seamless as you use it.
Anticipation is about thinking of your app
as being part of a conversation.
Develop your voice and vary your tone
according to the situation.
Then answer
the question of what comes next.
Speaking directly to people
in the right way is one way to take
your app experience from functional
to magical.
Jen: Next, we'll cover context.
Start by thinking outside the app.
When someone uses your app,
are they likely to be at home
in a quiet space,
or traveling at busy airport?
Are they occupied with something else,
like driving or cooking,
or can they give
your app their full attention?
This reminder shows up on your Apple Watch
if it notices that you're exercising,
but haven't started recording the workout.
The context is, you're on an outdoor walk,
so you don't want
to have to stop to read a lot.
There's one large button
clearly labeled "Record Outdoor Walk."
On the other hand, once you stop
exercising, your context has changed.
You can take in
a little bit more information,
like your total distance,
average pace, and active calories.
Here, when taking a panorama photo,
your focus is split
between the camera app and whatever
you're trying to photograph.
An on-screen arrow guides you
with instructions,
to "Move continuously
when taking a Panorama."
The words appear right below the arrow
because that's where you're looking.
Now let's talk
about how to write helpful alerts.
Chances are, your app has some alerts,
which are best used
when you want someone to confirm
an action or make a choice.
They are, by their context, interruptions,
so you want your alerts to be helpful
and clear.
In this alert,
you've opened the Weather app,
and it needs permission
to use your location.
Because it appears at the time
you open the app, it feels contextual.
The alert also gives you the context
in which the permission will be used:
to show local weather
and send relevant notifications.
Some alerts
might have a destructive action,
or something that can't be undone,
like removing a device from your account.
Let's take a closer look.
This alert asks the question
"Remove iPhone?"
And the buttons answer
with Remove or Cancel.
The context here is that someone
needs to make an important choice,
one in which they may lose information.
"Remove" is the destructive action,
so its button is red and on the left.
The "Cancel" button is on the right
and dismisses the alert
without taking any action.
But be careful how you use Cancel.
As you can see in this fake alert
for a made-up subscription,
the title of "Confirm Cancellation"
makes it hard to know which button
to choose,
the one on the left that says "Cancel"
or the one on the right
that says "Confirm."
The rest of the text reads,
"If you confirm and end this plan now,
you'll lose access on June 21, 2022."
This isn't giving much more help.
It's unclear whether you're ending
this plan now
or if you can still access it.
The phrase "this plan" is also vague,
especially if you have
more than one subscription.
With a few small changes, we can fix it.
This new title
of "Cancel Platinum Subscription?"
tells you which subscription
you're canceling and matches well
with the buttons labeled
Cancel Subscription or Keep Subscription.
The message body is brief,
telling you
that "You'll continue
to have access until June 21, 2022."
You'll notice that the buttons
aren't labeled Yes and No.
When writing for alerts,
it's always best to be specific
about the action
the buttons are going to take.
On this alert, if you only read
the button labels,
you would still understand
what you were choosing.
Another context for seeing an alert
is when something goes wrong.
Errors will often show up as alerts,
as shown
in this pretty unhelpful made-up example.
The title of "Oops! you can't do that"
doesn't say what it is you can't do.
You're unlikely to know
what the error code 1234567 means,
and the rest of the message,
"Sorry, bad input.
Please try again,"
doesn't add any information.
And it's unclear why there
are two buttons, Okay and Cancel.
It seems like they'd both do
the same thing.
As for the tone of the message,
interjections like "oops!" or "uh-oh"
can sound patronizing,
and "please" and "sorry"
can sound insincere.
Use them sparingly.
Here's an example of a better message.
The title clearly tells you
there's a billing problem,
and the text explains
exactly what to do about it.
To continue
accessing your subscription,
add a new payment method.
The top button, Add Payment Method,
takes you right to where
you can fix the problem,
and the second button, Not Now,
lets you continue what you were doing
so you can come back later.
Now let's talk
about how to create useful empty states,
or places in your app
where there isn't any content.
Empty states can be times for education
or even celebration,
like when you complete the last item
on your to-do list,
but it depends on context.
Here's another example.
In this made up restaurant app,
you haven't saved anything
to your favorites.
It uses the title
"Nothing strike your fancy?"
which has a whimsical feeling.
That can work
if it matches the voice of your app,
but the idiom might not be
universally understood or translate well,
and the text,
"Please come back if you do find
something you want to eat,"
doesn't give any useful guidance
or indication of how content
might show up here.
On the other hand,
the Apple Podcasts library
clearly tells you that you have
"No Saved Episodes."
It then explains that you can
"Save episodes
you want to listen to later,
and they'll show up here."
Much better.
So to recap, when thinking about context,
think outside of the app,
about what else people
might be doing while using it.
Write helpful alerts that are contextual
and offer clear choices.
And create useful empty states
by using an appropriate tone
and giving helpful guidance.
Kealy: Finally, let's talk about empathy.
In user experience writing, having empathy
means you should aim
to write for everyone.
Your app might have a specific audience,
like musicians,
gamers, or other developers,
and you should speak to them,
but you don't want leave anyone out.
It's best to use simple, plain language,
as idioms and humor can be misunderstood
or not translate, and some phrases
have meanings that exclude people.
A key aspect of empathy is
being responsive to localization needs.
Your app could be used
by people all over the world.
That's an exciting opportunity!
It also means your app needs to adapt
to a lot of languages and cultures.
When you translate
from one language to another,
words can get longer or shorter.
Some languages
require more vertical space.
Someone could be using your app
with a language that reads
from left to right,
or right to left.
Here's an example.
This is the confirmation you see
when changing languages on iPhone,
in this case, from English to Thai.
In English, the notification reads,
"Applying this setting will restart
your iPhone,"
with the buttons
Change to Thai and Cancel.
In Thai, the text
at the top is a little longer,
and the space
accommodates the taller characters,
while in Dutch, the text is much longer.
The space at the top grows
so the text can continue to a second line.
And here's Hebrew,
a language that reads right to left.
There are also considerations
beyond just word length.
In U.S. English,
the calendar abbreviations
for the days of the week
are a single letter, M for Monday,
T for Tuesday, and so on.
But in Catalan,
the days of the week are abbreviated
to two letters--
there isn't a single-letter variation--
while in Arabic, the days of the week
are not abbreviated at all.
Your UI needs to be able to adapt
to those language changes.
Now let's talk about accessibility.
It's important to welcome
everyone into your app.
For your app to be used
by as many people as possible,
it needs to speak
to as many people as possible.
Someone who is blind or has low vision,
for example, may set their device
to display bold or larger text,
or use VoiceOver to navigate.
Pay attention to the language you use
for labeling the elements in your app.
Those words will be some people's
entire experience using it,
and you want
that experience to be well designed.
Every element needs to have thoughtful,
useful, descriptive text.
This includes not just
the Voice Over text for navigation items,
like links and buttons, but any symbols,
graphs, or images as well.
Let's look at how Voice Over
describes a few Memoji Stickers.
This first one is described
as "Person tilting head to the side
with hand beside mouth
as if sharing a secret."
Notice that it isn't just
the physical details that are described,
but the intention,
"as if sharing a secret."
The second is described
as "person meditating
with relaxed arms
and forefingers touching."
Again, both the physical details--
relaxed arms and forefingers touching--
and the context
of meditation are described.
And the third example
again describes both context
and position:
nervous person biting fingernails.
Notice also that each of these examples
is described as a "person,"
not, say, a "man" or a "woman."
You can also help everyone
feel welcome in your app
by avoiding unnecessary references
to specific genders.
Be equally thoughtful
about any descriptive language you use.
It's critical to use empathy
when writing for your app.
Write for everyone, using simple language.
Be responsive to localization needs,
including text size changes.
And design for accessibility,
using thoughtful text
for people who use VoiceOver to navigate.
Don't be afraid to review
your app's language often,
and change things.
Just as language evolves more broadly,
so should the words your app uses.
There is so much more
to know about these topics.
Check out the Human Interface Guidelines
to learn more
about designing inclusive apps.
Today, we talked about Purpose,
Anticipation,
Context, and Empathy,
four concepts you can use to make sure
the text in your app or game
is well designed.
We hope you saw the value
of considering writing early,
as part of your design process,
not as something you fill in later.
Jen: And if you do find yourself
struggling to find the right words,
we have one last tip for you,
and it's the simplest one:
read your writing out loud.
It can really help make sure
your writing sounds conversational,
like how you'd talk to a friend.
Reading out loud can also help you
find unnecessary or repetitive words,
grammatical mistakes, or typos.
Those details matter.
Kaely: Writing for interfaces
begins with curiosity
for who's on the other side of the screen.
Speak to them
with respect and understanding,
and we know you'll find the right words.
[spacey music]