♪ ♪
Gabriel Ting:
Hello, and welcome to our session,
"Explore in-app purchase
integration and migration."
This session is divided into two parts:
one dedicated to migrating
to the App Store Server API,
and one dedicated to migrating
to App Store Server Notifications
Version 2.
My name is Gabriel, and I am discussing
how to migrate
to the App Store Server API.
Alex Baker: My name is Alex,
and I will walk you through
migrating to App Store
Server Notifications Version 2.
Gabriel: Let's first begin with a brief
introduction of the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications.
We introduced the App Store Server API
last year as a powerful, secure,
and efficient way to obtain data
and perform operations from your server.
We aim to give you
just the data that you need,
signed in the JSON Web Signature
or JWS format,
so that you can verify that the data
you receive is untampered with,
intended for you,
and signed by the App Store.
For example,
one of our App Store Server API endpoints,
the Get Transaction History endpoint,
in combination with the new
filter and sort features,
allow you to fetch any set of transactions
that you specify,
with just an originalTransactionId.
On the pane of
App Store Server Notifications Version 2,
with the increased number of states
of a subscription that can be represented,
Notifications Version 2 will update you
of all possible states of a subscription,
in real time.
We aim to proactively provide
all the information that you need
to know about what's going on
with your subscribers,
without having to ask us
for the information.
Alex will walk you through this
more in his portion of this session.
If using these features with ease
and efficacy interests you,
this session is for you.
We will walk you through how to get
started using the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications
Version 2,
as well as some migration tips
and best practices.
For additional information
on each of these,
please refer to these
additional sessions listed below.
So let's get started discussing
migrating to the App Store Server API.
First off, we will be discussing how
to start using the App Store Server API.
Second, we will dive into some
of the details of signing JSON Web Tokens.
Third, we will demonstrate
how to verify signed transactions
you receive from the App Store
are genuine.
Finally, we will discuss how to migrate
from verifyReceipt
to the App Store Server API.
Let's get started.
First, let's get into talking about
how to use the App Store Server API
with different versions of StoreKit,
first with just original StoreKit,
then with just StoreKit 2,
then discussing methods to support both
simultaneously for both clients using
iOS versions that support StoreKit 2,
namely those on iOS 15 or greater,
and those that do not.
First off,
let's take a look at what requests
to the App Store Server API look like.
We see that the five APIs listed here
utilize originalTransactionId
as a path parameter.
This allows you to easily call these APIs
using the originalTransactionIds
that you receive from receipts,
signed transactions,
signed renewals, and notifications.
Next is the Look Up Order ID endpoint.
This endpoint instead uses
the orderId provided by a customer
for support queries.
This is so that you can better assist
with questions directly from the customer,
as the customer is provided an orderId
in customer receipts for each transaction,
but is not provided
an originalTransactionId.
This ensures that you can
directly respond to customer inquiries
with data customers have on hand.
The last endpoints listed here
are notification related,
which Alex will touch on
in his portion of this session.
Next, let's look at where you can get
the originalTransactionIds from
in Original StoreKit.
When you call verifyReceipt
with the unified app receipt,
the originalTransactionId you'll use
when calling the App Store Server API
comes back in the in_app field
in the receipts for each of
the transactions this user purchased,
as well as in the latest_receipt_info
and pending_renewal_info.
Now that we know how to get
the originalTransactionId
from Original StoreKit transactions,
let's look at the whole flow
between a customer,
the App Store Server, and your server.
First, obtain the app receipt
on your server.
Next, take the app receipt and call
verifyReceipt with it from your server.
This will return the decoded receipt.
From the decoded receipt,
gather all of the originalTransactionIds
in precisely the same ways
I previously showed.
Next, you can call
the Get Transaction History endpoint
with any one of the gathered
originalTransactionIds, which will return
the history of transactions
for this user as signed transactions.
These transactions include
non-consumables, refunded consumables,
non-renewing subscriptions,
and auto-renewing subscriptions.
Then, if you want to get the latest signed
transaction and signed renewal information
for a specific subscription, call
the Get All Subscription Statuses endpoint
with the corresponding
originalTransactionId.
This will return all of the signed
transactions and renewals
for the subscription that corresponds
to the given originalTransactionId.
Next, let's look at where
the originalTransactionId is
in the case of StoreKit 2 transactions.
This is the code on the client
to obtain an originalTransactionId
from a transaction.
On devices that support StoreKit 2–
namely devices that are on
iOS 15 or later–
you can get
the originalID property on a verified,
decoded transaction
to get the originalTransactionId.
Now, looking at the server side, here is
an example of a signed JWS transaction,
which is the data type that you receive
in signed transactions and signed renewals
from the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications.
Here, we see that originalTransactionId
is a top level field.
Next, let's look at the whole flow
between a customer,
the App Store Server, and your server
for StoreKit 2 transactions.
First, take the signed transaction
on the device.
With StoreKit 2,
you can verify this transaction on-device.
Using the on-device status listener,
transaction listener,
or last transaction will keep you
updated on latest transactions,
cancellations, and refunds, which can then
be sent to your server for record-keeping.
For example, these are updated
on subscription renewals,
subscription offer redemptions,
expirations, and more.
Send the transaction to your server.
In combination
with App Store Server Notifications,
which Alex will dive more into
in the following section,
you can keep up-to-date
with the latest status and state
of a subscription without having
to call the App Store Server API.
When you do need to perform
an operation on a subscription,
such as extending
the renewal date of a subscription,
you can use the originalTransactionId
from the signed transaction to call
corresponding endpoints
and get back the data that you need.
Now that we've seen how to use
the App Store Server API
with original StoreKit and StoreKit 2,
let's talk about how to support
both StoreKit and StoreKit 2.
You can take advantage
of the App Store Server API
without fully adopting StoreKit 2.
As shown previously,
you can get the originalTransactionId
from a receipt in Original StoreKit.
You can also get the originalTransactionID
in StoreKit 2 from a JWS transaction.
You can also use the App Store Server API
independently of any other APIs.
It is not tied to using a specific version
of other APIs.
In terms of App Store
Server Notifications,
it can be used with either version 1
or version 2 notifications.
We do recommend using version 2
because it notifies you of changes
to subscriptions as they occur,
uses the secure JWS format, and more,
which Alex will dive into more
in his part of this session.
However, you can use
the App Store Server API separately,
with version 1 notifications
or without notifications at all.
Next, let's discuss how you can
process new purchases
after you completed the migration steps
I previously walked through.
To support new purchases
on devices using original StoreKit,
you can take new receipts as they come,
sending them to your server,
and do precisely the same steps
as I previously showed,
while collecting new data along the way–
call verifyReceipt with the new receipts,
and get the decoded receipt with the new
originalTransactionId in latest_receipt,
correlate those originalTransactionIds
with other originalTransactionIds
in the in_app section of the receipt
to group together
your transaction information.
Then, you can take
the new originalTransactionId,
and call the App Store Server API
as needed,
such as if you need to call
the Get All Subscription Statuses endpoint
to get you the latest status
of the corresponding subscription.
Now that we've covered
how to use the App Store Server API
with both Original StoreKit
and StoreKit 2,
let's dive into some of the details
of signing JSON Web Tokens,
a requirement
to call the App Store Server API.
In order to authenticate
that your developer account is the caller
of the App Store Server API,
we use JSON Web Tokens,
also known as JWTs,
to authenticate requests.
This token must be included
in every request
as an authorization header
in calls from your server.
A JWT consists of a header,
a payload, and signature.
Next, we'll go into how to construct
a JWT specific to your application.
Here, we can see
how a JSON Web Token is composed,
as well as the structure
of the header and payload.
The token itself can be broken
into three parts, separated by periods:
the base 64 encoded header,
the base 64 encoded payload,
and then the signature,
which is composed of the base 64
encoded header and payload,
signed using your signing secret.
The header is composed of these fields
that contain metadata
about how to sign your data.
One of the important fields here
is the key ID,
which is your private key ID
in App Store Connect.
This needs to match the key
you use to sign the JWT.
The payload contains
additional information
about your specific application.
Please refer to the article
"Creating API Keys to Use
With the App Store Server API"
for additional information and guidance
on how to obtain your API Key.
For details on each of these fields,
please refer to the article
"Generating Tokens for API Requests."
Once you have the header and payload
with all the appropriate information,
next you will sign the JWT
using the certificate
that corresponds to the keyId.
Here is the core pseudocode
that you can use, regardless of language.
First, make sure that you have
the private key that corresponds
to the key id provided
in the header that we just looked at.
Then, call the signing function
that your JWT library exposes
with your private key, header,
and payload.
Since the header contains
the signing algorithm,
the JWT library signs it
according to the provided algorithm.
Finally, here is an example usage of this
token when authenticating a cURL call
to the Get All Subscription Statuses
endpoint.
Replace $\
and $\
with the values of the token you generated
and your desired originalTransactionId,
respectively.
Next, let's talk about how to verify
that the signed transactions
you receive are for you
and signed by the App Store.
Signed transactions are, in essence,
JavaScript Object Notation,
or JSON objects
that are cryptographically signed
such that if they are tampered with
between the App Store and your server,
you can detect it.
Signed transactions are signed in
the JSON Web Signature, or JWS format.
The signed transactions that the App Store
sends you will arrive in the JWS format.
By verifying the JWSs you receive,
you will verify that the data
came from the App Store,
and the contents are untampered with.
Now, let's look at how to verify
a signed transaction.
First, base 64 decode the header.
Then, one can determine what signing
algorithm to use via the alg claim.
This will be used
as part of verifying the JWS.
The certificate chain in the x5c claim
is issued by Apple,
and validation of the claim
indicates that the data is
properly signed and untampered with.
Please refer to the App Store
developer documentation
for further information
on how to verify JWSs.
In essence,
the x5c chain is a chain of certificates.
Successful verification
of the certificate chain tells you
that the data can be trusted
and that the data is signed by Apple.
Order matters for the certificate chain.
First comes the root certificate.
This root certificate may be followed
by additional certificates,
where each of these certificates
are signed by the previous certificate.
I will refer to the last certificate
in the chain as the leaf certificate.
The first certificate is referred to
as the root certificate
and is self-signed.
This certificate should match
the root certificate you obtain
from Apple's Certificate Authority.
If the certificates do not match,
the chain should not be trusted.
The leaf certificate,
the last certificate in the chain,
is the certificate
that is used to sign the JWS.
Here is an example of what the header
of a JWS the App Store sends
may look like.
First is the algorithm
used to sign the JWS.
Next is the x5c certificate chain,
with the certificates listed in order.
Now, let's look at what generating
an x5c certificate chain looks like
from a high-level overview.
We start off with the root certificate
from Apple's Certificate Authority.
Then, the root certificate is used to sign
the intermediate signing certificate.
The intermediate signing certificate
is then used to sign the leaf certificate.
Now that we've covered what generating
an x5c certificate chain looks like,
let's look at what verifying
a chain looks like.
Starting at the leaf certificate,
we ensure that it was signed
by the intermediate signing certificate.
Then we ensure
that the intermediate signing certificate
was signed by the root certificate.
Additionally,
the root certificate should match
the one from
the Apple Certificate Authority.
If all of these steps are successful,
then the entire chain
is verified as legitimate.
Let's talk about a method
to verify the certificate chain.
Here is a command to verify
the x5c certificate chain using OpenSSL.
Breaking this into pieces,
the command verify, broadly speaking,
allows you to pass in
certificates for verification.
The flag trusted allows you to provide
a certificate to trust–
in other words, a certificate that will be
used to verify the following certificates.
in this case, we are passing in
the root certificate you obtained
from the Apple Certificate Authority,
and thus can be trusted.
We'll use this
to verify the WWDR certificate,
the next certificate in the chain.
The untrusted flag allows you
to provide the certificate or certificates
that you wish to verify
using the certificate that you trust.
Here, we first pass in
the WWDR certificate
from the Apple Certificate Authority,
which is signed by the root certificate.
This should match the second certificate
in the x5c chain.
And finally, the leaf certificate here
is the last certificate,
which is signed
by the previous certificate.
In the case of a successful verification,
a success code is returned.
You may then proceed
to use the decoded information.
In the case
of an unsuccessful verification,
determine the issue
based on the returned error code.
If not possible to verify, this data may
be tampered with and should not be used.
Please refer to the App Store
developer documentation
for complete instructions on verifying
an x5c certificate chain using OpenSSL.
Here is some pseudocode for how one might
go about verifying a signed transaction.
First, obtain the JWS you wish to verify.
Then, take the certificate your JWS
library requires for verification.
Call the verify function
of your JWS library,
using the appropriate certificate.
The certificate that signs
the JWS is the leaf certificate,
though some libraries require
passing in the entire chain.
In the case that the call succeeded,
then you can proceed on with your tasks.
In the case that this was the result
of a call to the App Store Server API,
then you can proceed
to store the validated data.
As for the case of notifications,
Alex will go more into this
in his portion of this session.
In the case that the JWS cannot
be validated, do not use the JWS.
This may mean that it has been tampered
with or was not sent by the App Store.
Alex will dive more into how to better
ensure security when using notifications.
Please refer to the App Store
developer documentation
for complete instructions
on verifying and handling a JWS.
Now, let's review some use cases
for migration from verifyReceipt
to the App Store Server API.
First, let's look at the case
where you want to check
what the latest status is
for any given subscriber.
This keeps you up to date with
any changes to an individual subscription.
Previously,
to obtain the most up-to-date status
of a subscriber,
one had to call verifyReceipt
and determine the status
of the subscription based on fields
such as expiration intent,
grace_period_expires_date, et cetera.
Now, with the App Store Server API,
the Get All Subscription Statuses endpoint
can be called to obtain
the latest status of a subscription,
with a status field containing
the current status,
as well as the latest, most up-to-date
signed transaction
and renewal information.
Let's look at a flow
of how you could execute on this.
First, for any decoded receipt
that you have, you can obtain
the originalTransactionIds from it
just in the way that I showed previously.
Then, you can call
the Get All Subscription Statuses endpoint
for that originalTransactionId,
which will return the latest
signed transactions
and renewals for that transaction.
Next, let's look at the case
of obtaining the latest transactions.
Obtaining the latest transactions
informs you of what a user has purchased,
what has renewed, if there are any changes
to a user's subscription, and more.
Previously, to obtain
the latest transactions for a user,
one had to call verifyReceipt
and use the in_app array
and examine latest_receipt_info,
which contained all of
the transactions for a user.
With the App Store Server API,
to obtain the latest transactions,
the Get Transaction History endpoint
allows you to fetch
the full purchase history for a user.
Furthermore, pagination combined
with the new filter and sort features
that is covered in the WWDC22 talk,
"What's new with in-app purchase,"
ensures that you can efficiently fetch
precisely the data that you need.
Let's look at a flow
of what this may entail.
With any originalTransactionId
belonging to that user,
you can call
the Get Transaction History endpoint,
which will return the history
of transactions for this user
as signed transactions, filtered, sorted,
and paginated to your specifications.
Finally, let’s look at the case
of adopting appAccountToken.
The appAccountToken field
allows you to provide a UUID
that associates a StoreKit 2 transaction
with a user.
Then, on signed transactions,
signed renewals,
and notifications for that transaction,
the appAccountToken will appear.
Previously, there was not support for
appAccountToken with original StoreKit, ,
as it was a feature
that was new to StoreKit2.
Now, we added support for supplying
a UUID in the field applicationUsername
in Original StoreKit
to support compatibility
with Original StoreKit clients.
Under this condition,
that UUID will support
all the functionality
that appAccountToken does.
The appAccountToken then comes back in
verifyReceipt for Original StoreKit users,
and also appears for both
Original StoreKit and StoreKit 2 users
in calls to the App Store Server API
and notifications
from App Store Server Notifications.
That's it for the App Store Server API
portion of this session.
Next, here's Alex to cover migrating to
App Store Server Notifications Version 2.
Alex: Thanks, Gabriel.
My name is Alex,
and I'm excited to be here today
to discuss
App Store Server Notifications Version 2.
First, we'll be covering how to get
started with version 2 notifications.
Next, how version 2 notifications differ
and build upon other models available.
Third, we'll talk about recovering
in the case of missed notifications
and some of the new resources
available to help accomplish this task.
Last, how notifications can provide
insight into customer behavior
and create additional opportunities
for being informed
about the subscription lifecycle.
Let's go over a brief introduction
into what notifications are
and who can use them.
App Store Server Notifications
are messages we send you
whenever certain actions
are taken by users of your app.
These notifications broadly fall
into two categories,
subscription updates and refund updates,
although we're always working
to cover additional scenarios.
We provide these notifications
to help fill in gaps into user actions
that may not be available
to you in the app.
As an example,
one of our most common use cases
is the renewal of a subscription.
A user may not be in the app
when this transaction becomes available.
App Store Server Notifications
help account for this issue
by proactively sending
the latest transaction information
directly to your servers
when the subscription renews.
Version 2 notifications share many
similarities with the StoreKit 2 model
and the App Store Server API
you just heard about from Gabriel.
However, while they work well together,
they are all independent tools
that can be adopted at different times.
Most importantly,
you can continue to support clients
where StoreKit 2 is not available,
pre iOS-15 clients,
while utilizing
Version 2 Server Notifications.
We've worked to make
Version 2 notifications one of our most
in-depth and flexible tools
for providing information
about a user throughout
the entire subscription lifecycle.
We'll go more in-depth in this
later in the presentation,
but notifications provide information
that is almost impossible to capture
for actions taken outside of the app.
I hope I've interested you
in the concept of notifications
and Version 2 notifications in particular.
Before we go further,
while this presentation
walks you through getting started
and best practices
for receiving notifications,
it doesn't tell the whole story.
Please refer to these recent videos
for more information
about notifications and how they can
meet various use cases.
Let's look at getting
Version 2 notifications set up.
We're going to walk through
how to set up your notifications
all the way to receiving your first one.
First, go to your app's page
in App Store Connect.
Scrolling down, you will see a section
for App Store Server Notifications.
Here you'll see options
for both production and sandbox.
Each environment can contain
a separate URL
and a separate notification version.
Here is an example of the options page
for production settings.
Sandbox settings are exactly the same.
We recommend, especially if you are
a Version 1 notification user,
that you first try Version 2 notifications
in the sandbox environment.
This is a great place
to become comfortable with notifications
without impacting your production setup.
Select the Set Up Sandbox button,
provide your server's URL,
and select Version 2 Notifications.
Before triggering notifications,
confirm you have a valid
HTTPS certificate
for your server endpoint.
Also confirm you have allowed
Apple's public IPs access to your server.
Some of the most common failures
when setting up notifications
relate to firewalls and certificates.
These are also great to check if you
suddenly stop receiving notifications
as an initial troubleshooting step.
Now you are ready to receive
your first notification.
In Sandbox, notifications can be triggered
by a variety of actions,
like buying an in-app subscription.
However, for ease of use while testing,
we recommend triggering
a notification using the new
Request a Test Notification endpoint,
part of the App Store Server API.
This endpoint helps to automate
the notification testing process.
After triggering the Request
a Test Notification endpoint,
you should expect to see
a notification arrive soon.
If you are having issues
receiving notifications,
please refer the to new
Get Test Notification Status endpoint,
which can provide a brief status about why
the notification failed to be delivered.
For example,
a status like SSL_ISSUE would be
a clue to double-check
your HTTPS certificates.
We recommend
triggering a test notification
whenever you are performing
a configuration change.
This is a great way to confirm
you can still receive notifications
after the change.
Now, let's move on to understanding
the notification you've just received.
Just like transactions
we saw earlier from Gabriel,
notifications are also in the JWS format.
Let's go over how to decode
and verify a notification payload.
First, when receiving a notification,
you'll want to extract
the signedPayload field of the JSON body.
Next, you'll perform the exact same steps
Gabriel walked you through earlier
for verifying a signed transaction.
You'll follow the same steps
to verify signed data
whether it is a signed notification
payload from a notification
or a signed transaction
from the App Store Server API.
Next, it is important to verify
which app the notification is for.
If you have multiple apps
sharing the same endpoint,
this is a good place
to determine the target app.
It is also important to confirm that
the app the notification is targeted for
is your app, and the notification
was not intended for another developer.
Last, one more useful check is
to make sure that the environment
of the notification matches
your expected environment,
either Production or Sandbox.
Because App Store Connect allows
separate URLs for each environment,
it is possible to enforce
this requirement,
or, if the URLs are shared,
guarantee you are
storing and processing notifications
separately based on the environment.
At this point, the JWS is fully validated
and can be stored for further processing.
We recommend, besides some basic checks,
that your server process
the notification asynchronously.
If processing of the notification takes
too long, our server will record a timeout
and assume the notification
was not delivered successfully.
We will then resend the notification.
Therefore, moving time-intensive
processing outside this function
helps to ensure that the App Store server
records your notifications
as sent successfully
and removes the need for your server
to reprocess the notifications
upon a retry.
Now, let's go over the body
of the notification after verification.
The first fields are notification type
and the optional subtype.
Combined, these tell you the scenario
the notification is for.
These fields also help show what has
changed since the last notification
and provide information about
why these changes occurred.
The notificationUUID is a unique
identifier per notification.
If the server retries a notification,
the retried notification contains
the same notificationUUID.
This helps detect cases where
your server processed the notification,
but did not respond with a successful
HTTP response code in a timely manner.
We recommend adding duplicate
notification detection due to retries,
based on this field.
The signedDate field tells you
when the notification was created.
This is especially useful
for detecting retried notifications.
Next, the appAppleId and bundleId.
These are important
for detecting the target application.
As we discussed earlier, it is important
that you check these fields
and confirm they match expected values
to prevent replay attacks.
Additionally, make sure the environment
of the notification matches
the expected environment,
that sandbox notifications aren't being
recorded as production data,
and vice versa.
Last, the actual signedTransactionInfo
and optional signedRenewalInfo.
These will be the latest status
of the underlying purchase
at the time of signing.
At this point,
having parsed the notification,
you are left with the latest transaction
and renewal information,
and the latest reason
for the change in status.
Now that we've covered setting up
and receiving a specific notification,
let's examine
the Version 2 notification model,
how notifications can fit together
to track the subscription lifecycle,
and the design decisions
behind Version 2 notifications
through a comparison with
Version 1 notifications.
Version 2 adopts a different philosophy
when sending information
about the state of a purchase.
Instead of sending the entire
recent history every notification,
Version 2 notifications focus
only on sending the latest information:
the latest transaction information,
and in the case of subscriptions,
the pending renewal information as well.
With notifications,
we work to provide information
on every step
of the subscription lifecycle.
Therefore, notifications only contain
the latest information
about the purchase or subscription.
Together, these notifications create
a complete timeline
of a subscription's status.
If you need to view the entire
transaction history and don't have access
to the notification history,
this pairs well with
the Get Transaction History endpoint
which lets you query
a user's entire transaction history
in a paginated and filterable context.
Second, version 1 notifications
do not require clients use StoreKit 2.
And that's right, neither does version 2.
In fact, no matter what framework
is used on the client side,
you can start enjoying the benefits
of version 2 notifications today.
Last, version 2 notifications work
to enhance the level of detail provided
and expand cases covered
by adding additional types
and adding the new subtype field.
Through this,
we are able to cover more scenarios
and provide notifications at every step
of the subscription lifecycle.
Some of the notable scenarios
we've added include expiration,
more granular information related
to changes in auto renewal status,
and more scenarios
around the refund process.
Now, to illustrate the complexity
of the scenarios covered
and provide a more concrete example,
let's look at how notifications
can inform you of each step
a subscription takes,
from start to finish.
Let's imagine a user
before a subscription.
Upon subscribing, the user moves
into the renewing subscription state
and a SUBSCRIBED with subtype INITIAL_BUY
notification is sent,
or an OFFER_REDEEMED with subtype
INITIAL_BUY if an offer was used.
Contained in the notification
would be the first signed transaction
and the signed renewal information.
Time passes, and the subscription renews,
staying in the renewing state.
Upon each renewal,
we send a DID_RENEW notification
with the next
signed transaction information.
Whenever the user deactivates
auto renewal,
they move to the expiring
subscription state, and you will receive
a DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS
with subtype AUTO_RENEW_DISABLED
notification.
If they don't reenable auto renewal,
at the end of the period they move
to the expired state,
and you will receive an EXPIRED
with subtype VOLUNTARY notification.
Now, you might be wondering,
where are all the other
notification types?
Here is the subscription lifecycle,
as seen through notifications.
There is a lot going on.
And this diagram doesn't even tell
the whole story.
The refund/revocation lifecycle
isn't included here, for example.
This diagram illustrates
the vast array of scenarios
that version 2 notifications cover
and that they work to inform you
of each step
of the subscription lifecycle.
The other point I would make
is that we work to cover
every possible transition state.
This helps to increase the utility of
notifications by becoming a single source
for tracking subscriptions
and improves confidence
that you are seeing every step
of the subscriber's journey.
However, even though
all of this data is here,
you don't need to work
with every type available.
Even just processing notifications
related to renewal preference changes,
for example, can provide value.
Especially if
you are just getting started,
begin with the notification types
that are most useful for your situation.
Now, let's cover what happens
after you've got your server set up,
everything is running smoothly,
but, alas, your server goes down.
Whether it was for a few days,
a few minutes, or you think you might have
missed just one, let's go over some steps
to help resolve this issue.
Let's image your server.
It is set up successfully
and is receiving notifications.
At some point, your server has an issue
and is unable to receive notifications.
We are still attempting
to send messages to your server,
but now those requests begin to fail.
There are several ways
to deal with this scenario.
The first is just to wait.
If we don't receive
a successful status code from your server
or couldn't connect to it at all,
we will retry notifications
according to our documented retry policy.
For version 2 notifications,
we retry after each attempt,
first after a 1-hour delay,
then a 12-hour delay,
24-, 48-, and finally 72-hour delay.
Waiting works great
for outages less than an hour,
as notifications will be retried
an hour after the first failure.
At some point your server recovers,
and you start receiving
notifications again.
First, you receive a new notification,
unrelated to the missed notifications.
Notifications are retried with a delay,
so as soon as your server comes online,
you will not immediately receive
all missed notifications.
Some time passes and you start to receive
the notifications you missed,
interspersed with new notifications.
This brings up the question,
how can you detect if a notification
is the original or a retried notification?
Let's examine a notification.
In this notification,
we're just showing a few fields.
Notifications contain a signedDate field.
This field can be useful
for detecting retries,
by comparing the signing date with
the time the notification was received.
If you see notifications with
a signing date significantly earlier
than the date
you received the notification,
this indicates you may have
experienced an outage.
Imagine in this scenario
the notifications labeled 6 and 3
were for the same subscription.
This could be determined by comparing
the originalTransactionIds.
In this case, just because notification 3
was received after notification 6
does not mean it contains
newer information than notification 6.
Other times, a notification
may have been received by your server,
but it failed to respond
with a successful HTTP 200 status code.
This can cause a notification
to be redelivered to your server.
As discussed earlier, make sure to check
the notificationUUID field
to deduplicate these requests.
You may see significant numbers
of retried notifications
even though you successfully
recorded the notifications.
In this case, make sure you are responding
with an HTTP 200 response
every time you receive a notification.
Additionally, make sure that you are
doing so in a timely manner,
and are not doing extensive processing
before responding successfully,
to prevent us from recording a timeout
and resending the notification.
Sometimes, especially with longer outages,
the next retry may be hours or days away,
or for an extended outage,
retries may have been exhausted.
The next option for recovering
from missed notifications
is the Get Notification History endpoint.
We've just announced the new
Get Notification History endpoint,
which provides a six-month history
of notifications we have sent your server.
Refer to "What's new
with in-app purchases" video
for an overview of this endpoint
along with other great features
we are announcing.
Here we will be focusing on
best practices when using this endpoint
and scenarios where it can assist.
After an outage is resolved,
note the start and end timestamps
of the outage.
The Get Notification History endpoint
allows queries to be made
over a specific timespan.
By specifying the start
and end times of the outage,
you can only process notifications
that you likely missed,
instead of requiring paging
through the entire history.
This will help improve
the speed of recovery
and reduce work reprocessing
already-recorded notifications.
Next, the Get Notification
History endpoint
allows you to filter
by type of notification.
If you have experience an extended
outage and expect a significant
number of notifications,
consider filtering by type, and starting
with types that may have immediate impact,
like DID_RENEW and EXPIRED.
These will help you take action
on the most relevant cases first.
One tip when passing notification types,
if the notificationSubtype
field is omitted,
this will only return notifications
that also do not have a subtype.
Therefore, for the example shown
for the DID_RENEW notificationType,
this would not return
DID_RENEW notifications
with subtype BILLING_RECOVERY.
Last, the Get Notification
History endpoint allows filtering
to a specific user by using
an originalTransactionId.
Thinking back
to the subscription lifecycle,
we've worked to make sure
every step of a user's journey
is covered by notifications.
Therefore, if you find yourself
jumping around in unexpected ways,
for example from a renewing subscription
straight to expiration,
this may indicate that you missed
a notification for that user.
This can also be useful
in a customer-support context
if a user's account is in a different
state than you would expect.
In these cases, you can send a query
for that user's notification history.
Let's go over the response from
the Get Notification History endpoint.
Only certain values are shown
in the response for simplicity.
The values returned in the response
are in the notificationHistory array.
Each entry in the array
represents a single notification.
The signed payload field contains
the exact notification
that was sent to you.
Second, we have
the firstSendAttemptResult field.
This field contains one of several values
based on the result
of the initial notification attempt
as recorded by our servers.
In the successful case,
this will be the value SUCCESS.
However, as we've just been discussing,
sometimes notifications fail
to reach your server.
These messages are meant to be
a general guide to help point you
in the direction of the issue,
to simplify the resolution process.
For example, we see SSL_ISSUE here.
This indicates there is a problem
with the SSL certificate
or process on the server.
This field provides improved visibility
into diagnosing servers issues
beyond seeing
the notification did not arrive.
We also provide this same field in
the Get Test Notification Status endpoint,
to provide this functionality
when using test notifications.
These can be used to help while
onboarding or during troubleshooting,
or retrospectively during determining
the root cause of an outage.
Notifications may not cover
all cases of a user's history.
You may have just adopted notifications
and have existing users
with histories not covered.
You also may wish to examine a history
longer than the retention period
of notifications in the Get
Notification History endpoint.
That's where the Get Transaction
History endpoint enters the picture.
This endpoint,
as we saw earlier in the presentation
from Gabriel,
solves these issues by providing histories
for your customers that cover cases
before you started using notifications.
Now, let's go over how notifications
can provide insight
and opportunities above and beyond
the purchase history.
One of the new additions in Version 2
notifications is the subtype field,
adding additional context
to the notificationType field.
This field is meant to provide
more detail in certain scenarios,
like EXPIRED
or DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS.
For example, with EXPIRED,
the action you take is usually the same,
mark the subscription as inactive
and revoke access to the product.
However, it can often be useful
to understand why the user expired.
Was it due to a billing issue,
voluntary choice,
or a price increase
that was never accepted?
Another notification,
DID_CHANGE_RENEWAL_STATUS,
is a great example of gaining
additional information
and opportunities
when using notifications.
On the surface,
it looks to be of low priority.
No action needs to be immediately taken.
The important notification
for revoking access to the product
is the EXPIRED notification.
Don't be fooled.
There is a lot of opportunity here.
One, this notification is
a great opportunity
to attempt to win back the customer
before their subscription expires.
Especially since deactivating
auto renewal may occur
outside the application,
this can be the only trigger
to be informed in this change in
renewal status before the expiration date.
This notification also provides insight
into customer behavior.
This notification can be used to determine
when in the renewal period
subscribers are cancelling.
Is it the day before renewal?
Are new subscribers
deactivating auto-renewal
soon after signing up for your service?
This type of information can be
important for understanding
the causes of cancellation
and improving your product.
Last, certain scenarios
may never be reflected
in a user's history without notifications.
For example, a user may deactivate
but then reactivate auto-renewal,
before their subscription period
has expired.
Because this all occurs
within a subscription period,
there is no effect
on the subscription's long-term status.
These decisions can be important
for understanding your customers,
and notifications provide information
to detect and record
these types of scenarios.
Overall, notifications work
to enhance and create opportunities
for understanding customer behavior
by providing information
at every step of the customer journey,
covering more scenarios than ever before.
In conclusion, today we've covered
both the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications.
These are available
to improve the capabilities
surrounding managing
and tracking purchases.
They use updated message types
and cover more cases than ever before.
These systems are available
for all clients
and cross-compatible with both
Original StoreKit and StoreKit 2
and can improve your ability
to monitor the subscription lifecycle.
Last, these tools are already available
in both Sandbox and Production
and are a great addition to any system.
Thank you for joining us,
and have a great WWDC.