♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi there! I'm Kendall Bagley,
a software engineer
on the Safari team.
It's been a full year since
we last got together at WWDC,
and today, we're going
to be talking about
all the amazing features
and enhancements
to Safari and WebKit
from both what's new here
at this year's WWDC
and from what we've seen
throughout this whole past year.
In fact, it's been
quite a busy year!
Since last fall, each release
of Safari has delivered
new and exciting features that
we know y'all as web developers
have been asking for.
Each of the new enhancements
delivered this year
aimed to address some of
the biggest points of feedback
you've been sharing with us.
Like adding a parent selector
with the :has() pseudo class,
the new flexbox inspector,
and even container queries.
We want to make your daily work
that much better and easier
while building the best
and most powerful software
for the web.
In fact, what's here
is just some of the new content
that we'll be going over today.
But there's so much more that
we wouldn't possibly be able
to cover it all
in this one session.
There's been a total
of 162 new web platform features
and improvements across
the seven Safari releases
this past year.
We've been proud to provide
so many new tools for you to use
to make your websites
and web apps.
And for macOS, the best way
to see what's new and exciting
as soon as possible is through
Safari Technology Preview,
where you can try out
the latest and greatest
for Safari and WebKit
and also help us know
what we should have come next.
But like you saw, there's
a whole bunch of new features,
so let's take a look
at everything that
we're going to cover.
Today we'll be looking
at new HTML features,
CSS enhancements --
including a bunch to help
your code architecture --
new Web Inspector tools,
a wide selection of new web API,
great JavaScript
and WebAssembly features,
and improvements
to security and privacy.
So, let's get started
with what's new with HTML
by taking a look
at a web page I'm creating
for my coworkers and I to use.
I personally really like to
thrift and repurpose my clothes
as a way to make my wardrobe
more sustainable,
and I thought
a clothing swap website
would be a great way
to have my team try it out too.
My design for the site includes
a Request Item button
that should show you
a form to fill out
when you spot a piece
of clothing that you like.
And I want that form
to show up in an overlay
over top of the whole page.
The new dialog element
provides a really easy way
to create overlays in a robust
and accessible manner
that we can use
for our request form.
And the new backdrop
pseudo-element in CSS
makes it possible
to style the background
behind the modal.
Let's bring up the dialog
by requesting an item.
See that shadow and animation?
It's really looking great!
Then, once an item
is requested on our site,
the person who posted it
needs to be able
to accept the request.
At the bottom of the page,
there's a carousel
to flip through
all your received requests.
But I don't want someone
to accidentally interact
with a button or a text field
for one of the items
that's not the frontmost,
with either clicks
or keyboard navigation.
I can use the inert attribute
to fix this.
By dynamically applying
the inert attribute
with the JavaScript here,
I'm disabling any interactions
for elements on slides
that aren't the currently
selected slide
as we switch between them.
And, using inert
includes disabling interactions
for assistive technologies
and prevents screen readers
from reading those
disabled items aloud,
giving much clearer guidance
on which elements
are intended for interaction.
And lastly for HTML, there's
the new lazy loading for images.
On my site,
there's some icons in the header
that I need to load right away,
but for the clothing item images
that are offscreen
on that first load,
we can utilize
lazy loading for them,
so the images only load
when the user scrolls to them,
making the page feel faster
and more responsive.
I'm really loving
how the site's looking so far,
and it's going to work great
for those using
assistive technologies as well.
And those HTML features
are just getting us started,
because there's so much
to check out
with CSS this year too.
A huge part of our CSS focus
has been around
making your CSS easier to reuse
through more
powerful architecture.
With that, we know
the number one request
for new web technology
has been container queries.
And we're thrilled to announce
container queries
will ship in Safari 16!
You'll be able to use
both size queries
and container query units.
Here, I'm experimenting
with an alternative layout
for the clothing swap website.
I'm making the card that
presents a piece of clothing
into a reusable component
and dropping that component
into several different
places in the page layout.
Here in the sidebar,
the available space
is a bit narrow,
so I want all the content
inside my component
to stack vertically.
In the main grid of items,
I want to feature the first one
as a hero graphic
that should take up all
the available space horizontally
and arrange the content in a
fashion that makes more sense
for a wide layout.
The rest of the items
in the main content area
should be divided
into smaller columns.
So I've created another layout
that works when there's a medium
amount of horizontal space.
Using container queries to
handle the change in the layout,
rather than media queries,
I can write the layout code
for this component just once
and use that component
any place on my site
in a container of any size,
and the correct layout
will always get applied.
I specified which element
to use for the container
and whether I want to measure
against just the inline size
or both inline and block size
at the same time,
by using
the container-type property.
I can optionally
name my container
using
the container-name property,
which gives me more flexibility
in how I structure the HTML.
Then I use the @container rule
to apply styles conditionally,
based on the size
of the container.
Here, if the clothing card
component is in a container
that's wider than 250 pixels,
the grid will change to have
two columns instead of one.
Next up with CSS architecture:
cascade layers.
This is a powerful change
to the CSS cascade.
Since the beginning of CSS,
the cascade has been made up
of these different layers.
But no matter what specificity
of any given selector
inside each layer,
author styles --
the styles you write
as web developers --
always beats UA styles.
Inline styles are always more
powerful than author styles,
and so on
with the rest of the hierarchy.
Cascade layers takes
this same concept
and allows you to create
your own custom layers
where specificity is calculated
independently inside each layer.
One entire layer
beats another entire layer,
no matter what the specificity
is of the selectors being used.
And you determine which layer
has power over the others
through the order of how you
define the layers in your CSS.
Cascade layers
will be a useful tool
for architecting CSS
on large projects
and maintaining
that code over time.
Perhaps your team will use them
to separate a design system
from overrides
or a framework you're using for
custom styles for your project.
It's totally up to you!
And, to round out all
the amazing new enhancements
for your CSS architecture
is :has(),
a pseudo-class that can act as
the long-wanted parent selector
and much more.
Combined with
any other selector in CSS,
:has() can look for siblings,
attributes,
states of form fields,
and much more.
It's really powerful.
Here, I want to highlight
the entire message box
whenever someone has checked
the "Urgent?" checkbox
for one of their messages.
I can use the :has pseudo-class
here to say that anytime
the form element has an input
of type checkbox
with that checkbox checked,
apply this CSS.
And I don't even need
to use any JavaScript.
We hope all these
great improvements
to handling
your CSS architecture,
with :has(), cascade layers,
and container queries,
make your work
as a web developer
that much better.
But these aren't
the only CSS additions
that we're excited about.
You've wanted a tool similar
to existing viewport units
but would be more useful
on devices where scrolling
causes the size of the viewport
to change.
And for that, there's new
viewport units for y'all.
When you want to know
the height of the viewport
when it's at its smallest,
use svh.
For the height of the viewport
when it's at its largest,
use lvh.
Just remember: s for small,
l for large.
For a dynamic number
that changes to always match
the current actual height
of the viewport, use dvh.
And it's not just for height.
We've got you covered
with even more viewport units.
There's width units,
which are good for completeness
to match up with
the highly used height units.
We've got block and inline --
both being useful
when writing
for multiple languages
with differing ways
in which text can flow.
And we didn't forget,
min and max, too.
But what about when you want
to create some movement
on your page,
not just react to it?
Animation has previously
been very declarative
where you can specify a start,
an end, and a duration
to get objects moving.
But it's been a challenge
to animate elements on a page
either when trying to get it
to follow a curved path
or even just being able
to move it around by an offset.
And I'd like to add
a secret animation
for the header
when you click on it,
Really just thought it'd be fun.
With the new offset-path,
you can define a path
that you want your object
to animate along.
Set the path with offset-path
and use offset-distance
for the keyframe effect.
Then use the animation property
to apply the keyframe effect,
giving you all the control
you'd want with your animations,
all in CSS.
We also want to give you
more control over your page
even with the parts of the web
that have typically been
defined by
the browser engine itself,
and over scroll-behavior is just
our first example of this.
Since the beginning of the web,
if you click on a link
that moves you to another part
of a web page,
it visually appears as a jump.
Sometimes this is disorienting
to your users.
The scroll-behavior property
in CSS provides a way
to specify if you want
this behavior or not.
By default, it's set to auto,
and it'll appear as that jump.
By specifying scroll-behavior
as smooth,
you can ask the browser
to instead scroll smoothly
to the next place on the page.
You can also do this
with the JavaScript methods
window.scroll(), scrollTo(),
or scrollBy().
You know your customers best
and should be able to define
your own web page experience
outside of the browser
engine defaults,
which is also where
the use of :focus-visible
as well as accent-color
can come into play.
You're probably familiar
with the focus selector
if you've ever wanted
to apply a specific style
to the focus indicator,
likely to have it more in line
with your overall design.
But there are some
accessibility pitfalls
of losing the browser-based
heuristic when you do that.
And on my site, instead
of the built-in form colors,
I'd love to use a custom color.
Let's use the teal color
that's already in my header
for both the focus highlight
and the checkbox.
With the :focus-visible
pseudo-class,
you can style the focus
indicator how you choose
while also having that
stylized indicator only show
if it would be shown natively
by the browser.
And to add another layer of
customization to your forms,
you can use accent-color
to change the color
of different parts
of the form control UI.
It'll take affect
on that checkbox
as well as radio buttons,
and so much more.
Also with CSS,
we've been replacing more
and more of the WebKit prefixes.
These used to be the perfect way
to try out experimental
features, but now,
we're able to move towards their
standards-defined properties
to make your CSS easier to write
and more interoperable.
But don't worry, your existing
CSS with WebKit prefixes
will keep working
as you transition
to their web standards
counterparts.
Backface-visibility,
print-color-adjust,
and text-align: match-parent
are all exactly the same
as their prefixed counterpart.
Both mask
and text-combine-upright
have had their syntax updated
from the prefixed version
to match the standard.
And the nonprefixed appearance
property also adds support
for the new auto value
but has removed
the WebKit-specific values
in Safari 16,
like caret or listitem,
as it got brought up
to standards specifications.
There's been a lot to note
about our typography additions
as well.
In particular, we've added
the font-palette property
that allows for easy selection
of a color palette
within a color font.
It's something that I think
would be really cool
to try out with some
potential logos for my site.
We can test out how it looks
with the built-in
dark or light palettes
or even what it'd be like
to customize it
to exactly what I want
with color overrides
and get some yellow in there
to brighten it up.
And with typography,
there's been the addition of
text-decoration-skip-ink,
which allows you to control
what happens when
an underline or overline
intersects
with a letter or character.
Plus the ic unit, which makes it
possible to precisely line up
CJK characters
in the block direction.
It's useful for creating
a clean typography grid
in languages like Chinese,
Japanese, and Korean.
To wrap up our discussion
of all these great CSS features,
we've definitely
got to talk about subgrid.
For years, layout on the web
was pretty hard.
CSS Grid has been revolutionary,
but it only affects the direct
children of a grid container.
Here, I'm using CSS Grid
to layout these cards,
and to automatically
adjust the layout
to fit the viewport width
by adding and removing columns
without any media queries.
But the size of the content
on each card isn't the same;
some headlines are longer,
the photos have
different aspect ratios,
and that's causing the visuals
to look really messy.
I'd like for all
the Request Item buttons
and the message boxes
to line up across the page,
and I'd like a longer title
on one card to affect the layout
on the other cards, so they all
get the same spacing.
Now, we can accomplish
this using subgrid.
I've put a grid
on each article,
and I've tied all of those grids
to the grid of their parent
simply by writing
"grid-template-rows: subgrid."
You can see how all the content
on each clothing card now
perfectly lines up by using the
Grid Inspector in Web Inspector
where I can turn on all the
grids I could possibly need too.
A lot of CSS work becomes easier
when we use the Web Inspector.
In fact, there's been some
amazing additions
to the Web Inspector
that I think you'll be
really excited to try out.
First off,
layout is easier to write
when you can see
what's going on,
which is exactly what makes
the Web Inspector so important.
And with the new
Flexbox Inspector,
you can actually visualize
the spacing between elements.
Here on my website,
I was having some trouble
adding these icons to my header.
All I need to do
is inspect the element,
and go to the Layout tab,
and since I'm not concerned
with my grids right now,
I can go ahead
and collapse that section
to get right to the new
Flexbox Inspector.
I can even turn on
all the views
with just a single click and
still have smooth performance.
And with all the views
turned on,
I can clearly see
with the hash marks
and container boxes how
my elements are being arranged
and how the empty space
is taking up the view.
So now I want to make sure
I'm getting my alignment right,
which I can use
the new alignment editor for.
I can go to the Styles tab
to find a new button
next to align-items.
Here, I'm able to toggle
through the different options
to find what works best
for my header,
and I can do the same
with justify-content as well.
Again, just toggling through
each of the options
and then landing on the one
that I think looks just right.
I also think the yellow icons
are a bit too small,
and I want to try making them
the same size as the red icons,
which I believe
are using a variable
with "medium" in the name,
but I really can't remember
the full name.
I can try out
changing the size
by inspecting
one of the yellow icons
and editing its height
in the inspector.
And, thanks to our new
CSS fuzzy autocompletion,
I can go ahead and type "medium"
and the variable I want pops up
even though "medium"
is at the end of the name.
And those yellow icons
definitely aren't too small
anymore.
And when those other variables
for the different icons
aren't being used
for the element I'm inspecting,
they get hidden away
with our new CSS tooling.
But don't worry,
there's a button to reveal them
when you need them.
And probably most excitingly
for Web Inspector this year,
we are happy
to announce support
for developer tool extensions
for the Safari Web Inspector.
The creators of your favorite
developer tools extensions
will now be able
to port them to Safari,
using the same underlying APIs
that they use in other browsers.
If you're interested in learning
how to make an extension
for the Web Inspector,
exploring the new APIs,
and getting set up
to start using them yourself,
make sure to watch
"Create Safari Web Inspector
Extensions" at this year's WWDC.
Now we've covered
a lot of what's new
with our front-end technologies,
so let's switch gears
and get into
what's new with our web APIs.
Which we are so excited to
announce support for web push.
It'll be available in Safari 16
on macOS Ventura.
It's coming to iOS
and iPadOS next year.
Web push lets you remotely
send notifications to your users
from your website or web app.
This is a fully interoperable,
standards-based implementation.
If you've implemented
web push already
and it works in other browsers,
it should just work in Safari
without any modifications.
And you don't need an
Apple Developer account either.
To learn all about the details,
watch "Meet Web Push for Safari"
here at WWDC22.
If you're excited
about web push,
then you'll probably
be excited about
new web app manifest
improvements too.
Now, you can define the icon
that's used when people save
your web app to the Home Screen
in your manifest file.
To have the icons
in the manifest take precedence,
you'll need to ensure
that there is no
apple-touch-icon
defined in the HTML head.
If you want to deliver
one icon to iOS and iPadOS,
while delivering a different
icon to other mobile platforms,
you can still do so by defining
the icon for Apple devices
in that HTML head
using the apple-touch-icon.
And if you don't declare
an icon in either place,
then when a user saves
your site to the Home Screen,
they'll simply get
a screenshot of your site.
Excitingly, we also no longer
wait for the user to choose
"Add to Home Screen"
from the Share menu
to load the manifest file,
which means you can use
that manifest file to define
characteristics of your web page
on all your sites
and even further reduce
the need to use meta tags.
Continuing with our APIs,
we've done a lot to improve
the use of web pages
in multiple browsing contexts
with the same origins.
Broadcast channels allow you
to send notifications
between those different
browsing contexts.
Let's imagine someone is using
the clothing swap website
and they have it open in
two windows at the same time.
Then they claim a piece
of clothing in one window.
We'll be able to post a message
and sync that unavailable state
to any other
open tabs or windows.
But maybe it's not updating
a tab in the background,
but updating a file
saved for your site.
For that,
there's been the addition
of the File System Access API.
We've had incremental updates
to this API
across multiple
releases this year,
starting with origin
private file system,
which is private storage
based on origin.
So for instance,
my clothing swap site
wouldn't have other sites,
like apple.com,
reading its files.
We then added to the API
with the getFile() method
of FileSystemFileHandle,
which reads an existing file
retrieved from your site's
root directory,
like we're doing
with a draft file here
that we also happened
to have just created.
Now let's take a look
at our most vibrant
API addition this year
with some new color richness.
The Display P3 color space
makes it possible
to represent colors
that just don't exist in RGB.
Here, we've got some examples
of the color picker.
On the left
of the squiggly white line
is color that exists in RGB.
And on the right of the line
are colors only available in P3.
In 2016, we added P3 support
for videos and photos.
Last year, we were thrilled to
be the first browser engine to
implement the new color syntax
defined in CSS Color Level 4.
This year,
we've added support for P3 color
for content inside
the canvas element.
So, no need to use
the colors based on devices
all the way from the 90s,
when you can now start utilizing
the full color capabilities
of all the amazing devices
of today.
But there's even more to
check out with our new Web APIs
from this past year, including
shadow realms, web locks,
and updated support
to the ResizeObserver API
for the ResizeObserverSize
interface,
which will help you observe
changes to an element's
box-sizing properties.
There's so much to try out
across all of our
new API additions,
and of course, with all of our
new features too.
In fact, we've still
got more to cover.
So let's next get into
all that's new
in JavaScript & WebAssembly.
If your website uses workers,
and you want instances
of these workers to be shared
across tabs and windows,
then the new shared workers
interface will definitely help
and potentially
reduce memory usage.
Instead of spawning new workers
for every task that you want
to happen in the background,
you can have just one worker
in use for each browsing context
with the same origin.
Each script would create
a shared worker in the same way,
and then they can receive
and post messages
using the same port.
The shared worker
would be able to receive
and respond to messages
sent from all
of the different scripts.
This will result in less
demand on your servers,
while also making your webpage
fast and responsive
for your customers.
We've also got a whole array
of array features to show you.
Instead of having to mutate
an array using reverse()
when you want to search
from the end,
you now can use the findLast()
and findLastIndex() methods,
like I've done here to find
the item and index
for the last item
containing a "shoestring."
The new at() method
also makes searching
from the end
of an array even easier.
Using braces works great
when the index is positive,
but with at(),
we get the additional feature
of indexing with negative values
making your code
more concise and readable.
But even with that good number
of new array features,
nothing much can beat
the sheer number
of new internationalization
features we got for you.
WebKit has continued
to add regular updates
to our Intl implementation
throughout this past year.
There's been added support
for different numbering systems
with new methods
in NumberFormat,
calendars, thanks to updates
with Locale as well as
DisplayNames, and currency
with the Intl Enumeration API.
And like I said,
there's a lot that's been added
to our Intl implementation
this year
that you'll have no shortage
of things to try out and explore
to cater to your users
across the world.
And for all those that have
existing code in all sorts
of different coding languages,
like C, Objective C, or Swift,
that they'd like
to bring to the web,
WebAssembly gets them running
without any need to rewrite.
And with this year's
improvements,
your web apps using WebAssembly
are only getting more powerful
with the addressable memory
being expanded to 4GB,
and the performance
gains that come
with the new zero-cost
exception handling.
Overall, there's definitely
some exciting stuff
for JavaScript and WebAssembly
to try out here.
And speaking of WebAssembly,
we also have some security
and privacy enhancements
that not only
will protect the users
of the web who we develop for,
but will also bring new
potential for you as developers.
With both of the new
Cross Origin Opener Policy
and Cross Origin Embedder Policy
HTTP response headers,
your site can opt in
to process isolation,
which means your site will run
in its own dedicated
webContent process.
We know that a lot of apps
can benefit from running
on multiple threads in parallel
using WebAssembly threading,
and with these new headers,
you're able to do so securely.
Our second security enhancement
also involves HTTP headers
with our improved support for
content security policy level 3.
CSP provides enhanced
security control
over your loading content
and mitigates risk
of cross-site scripting
and other vulnerabilities.
With the level 3 updates,
the most exciting addition
has been the new strict-dynamic
source expression.
The designers of strict-dynamic
realized you can use nonces
to allow certain scripts,
then extend that trust
to scripts loaded
by the already trusted ones.
No explicit allow list needed.
Look how much simpler
the header becomes.
Going from that original
long list of domains
that could potentially end up
allowing too much.
And with that, we wrap up our
security and privacy features,
which also brings us to the end
of all that we'll get
to cover today,
but there's even more
to explore on your own.
For instance,
we've had media updates
including support for capturing
a specific Safari window
with the getUserDisplay() API,
WebRTC Perfect Negotiation,
In-band chapter tracks,
and requestVideoFrameCallback().
As well as a lot of cool
additions for web extensions
with manifest version 3 support,
and a bunch of new
web extensions APIs.
To dive deeper into all these
features covered here today,
and to explore all the 162
features and improvements
developed in Safari
and WebKit in the past year,
make sure to download
Safari Technology Preview
to keep up with what's
coming in the future,
explore web technology by
checking out our release notes,
blog posts, and all the great
content on webkit.org,
including extensive
documentation for Web Inspector.
And as always,
let us know what you think
and what you'd like to see next
by filing your bug reports.
If you come across
a bug in WebKit --
something about HTML, CSS,
JavaScript, DOM APIs,
or the Web Inspector --
make sure to send your feedback
through WebKit's bug tracking
system at bugs.webkit.org.
And for suggestions or bugs
with the Safari interface,
file issues in Apple's
Feedback Assistant.
We look forward to delivering
more of the amazing features
that make the work
of web developers like you
that much better
with all the Safari
and Safari Technology Preview
releases
to come in this next year.
Thank you for joining me today,
and I hope you have
the best time here at WWDC.
Bye now!
♪