♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Welcome to the "Adopt
declarative device management"
session.
My name is Cyrus Daboo,
and I am an engineer
on the Device Management team.
I am here to tell you about
the exciting new features
in declarative
device management.
At WWDC21,
my colleague Melissa introduced
declarative device management,
a new paradigm
for managing Apple devices,
reenvisioning
the MDM protocol itself.
As we learned in that session,
declarative device management
is powerful
because it enables devices
to be autonomous and proactive.
The device is autonomous,
as it reacts to its own
state changes
and then applies
management logic to itself,
without prompting
from the server.
The device is proactive,
with the status channel
asynchronously reporting
to the server when important
state changes occur,
avoiding the need for servers
to poll devices.
There are two key elements
to the declarative device
management data model:
declarations and status.
Declarations encompass
activations and predicates,
configurations, assets,
and management types.
And status covers status items
and status reporting.
Let's take a moment
to talk about why this matters,
what it means for you,
and the organizations
that use your products.
We have created this technology
to support new complex
management strategies,
enhance the overall user
experience of managed devices,
alleviate the repetitive and
tedious tasks of an IT admin,
and empower devices
to be the driver
in their own
management state.
For you, as a developer
of a device management solution,
the declarative approach
allows your servers
to be lightweight and reactive.
And with
the declarative data model
more closely mapping to how
organizations are structured,
that means changes to devices
becomes more intuitive.
Status reports provide
a rich feedback channel,
which enable your servers
to monitor devices more closely,
and present
pertinent information
in a more timely
and reliable fashion,
without the need
for complex strategies
used to implement polling.
All of this means a simpler
development effort,
enabling you to focus on
the device management features
that add value
where it matters most,
and create a solution
your customers will love.
For IT admins,
the declarative approach
inspires more confidence
that the device
is in the expected state.
And in the situations
where it is not,
that it is in a safe state
that protects
any sensitive organization data,
even when connectivity
to the server is lost.
It provides critical feedback
from devices via status reports,
that also improves
efficiency for admins
through less utilization
of resources
such as network bandwidth.
For the organization's users,
device management
becomes a more responsive
and reliable experience
with faster onboarding,
quicker recovery times
and better support
from their organization.
With all these benefits in mind,
know that the focus
of future protocol features
will be declarative
device management,
making it even more important
for you to adopt
declarative device management
in your products today.
For an in-depth introduction
to declarative device management
and the steps needed
to adopt it,
make sure you watch
the WWDC21 session video.
In this release,
we have three focus areas:
expanding the scope of
declarative device management,
enhancing status reports,
and enhancing predicates.
Let's start
with expanding the scope
of declarative device
management.
When declarative device
management was introduced,
it was supported on only
iOS with user enrollments.
Now, declarative device
management is available
for every enrollment type
MDM supports:
automatic device enrollment,
which includes
supervised devices;
profile-based enrollment;
and profile and account-based
user enrollments.
Declarative device management
is now also available
on Shared iPad.
In iOS 16, users can now
find configurations
in the MDM profile details view
in the Settings app.
Tapping the Configurations row
reveals details
about the active configurations.
And I am also pleased
to announce
that declarative device
management is available
on every platform MDM supports.
macOS Ventura now supports
declarative device management,
for all MDM enrollment types
supported on macOS.
tvOS 16 now supports declarative
device management
for MDM device enrollment types.
Where supported by the OS,
the same set of declarations
and status
that are available on iOS
are also available
on macOS and tvOS.
On macOS, a Configurations
section is present
in the MDM profile details view,
revealing the active
configurations.
The same goes for tvOS,
where a Configurations section
is present in the
MDM profile details view.
One last thing to note here:
both macOS
and Shared iPad devices
each have two MDM channels.
These are the device
and user channel.
The device channel
allows management
of device level state,
whereas the user channel
targets management state
for specific users.
To use declarative device
management on any channel,
it must be enabled separately
for that channel.
That means sending the
DeclarativeManagement command
on the corresponding channel.
Also, declarative device
management status reports
are separately generated
for each channel,
so they need to be
separately monitored as well.
Now on to our second focus area:
status reports.
Let's do a quick review
of status reports.
Devices can incrementally report
status to the server,
for subscribed status items.
The device tracks successful
responses from the server
to ensure status updates
are reliable
and not missed in the case
of networking
or other types of problem.
Status reporting
makes the device proactive.
There is no need for servers
to continuously poll the device
to watch for state changes.
In iOS 15, we introduced
a set of status items
for device properties,
such as model type
and operating system version.
For this release we are
expanding status in three areas:
passcode state,
accounts installed
by configurations,
and MDM installed apps.
Let's start
with passcode status.
In iOS 15, we introduced
a passcode policy configuration.
There can be some lag between
the policy being applied,
and the passcode
becoming compliant
when changed by the user,
just as there is with
MDM passcode policy profiles.
So, MDM servers have to poll
the device to determine
when the passcode
becomes compliant.
But with the new declarative
device management
passcode status items,
there is no need to do that.
We have added two status items:
Passcode.is-compliant
and passcode.is-present.
Compliance indicates
if the passcode is compliant
with all passcode policies
applied via MDM profiles
or configurations.
These status items
have Boolean values
that mirror
the equivalent properties
that can be retrieved
via MDM queries.
Let's explore
a typical server behavior.
Often, an organization
has security sensitive state
to apply to a device.
For example,
VPN or Wi-Fi profiles
to allow access
to protected networks.
That state should only
be active on a device,
when a strong passcode
policy is present,
and the passcode is compliant
with that policy.
With traditional MDM,
a server has to send
a passcode policy profile
then poll the device,
to wait for the passcode
to become compliant
when the user changes it.
Initially the passcode
is likely not compliant,
so the Wi-Fi profile
cannot be sent.
Eventually, the user
changes the passcode
to bring it into compliance.
On the server's next poll,
it detects the changed
compliant state
and determines it is OK
to send the Wi-Fi profile,
which then gets installed
on the device.
Declarative device management
removes the need
for the server to poll by using
an activation predicate
that is triggered by
the passcode compliance state.
The server sends both
the passcode policy
and the Wi-Fi profile
as configurations,
with the Wi-Fi configuration
tied to an activation
predicated on
the passcode compliance.
The passcode configuration
is immediately activated
and applies a strong
passcode policy.
Initially, the passcode
is likely not compliant,
so the activation predicate
evaluates to false,
and the Wi-Fi configuration
is not activated.
At some point, the user updates
the passcode to be compliant.
This triggers reevaluation
of the activations
and the predicate
now evaluates to true,
resulting in the Wi-Fi
configuration being activated.
All this happens without any
intervention from the server,
and in fact can happen
without any connection
to the server being present.
The server does automatically
get a status report
from the device when
the configuration activates,
so it knows when
the change takes place.
This illustrates how
we have successfully moved
business logic from
the server to the device,
to avoid the need to poll
and get a more responsive
and reliable device behavior.
Now, let's turn
to account status.
In iOS 15, we introduced
account configurations
to install accounts
of various types on a device.
These are typically
organization accounts,
giving the user access
to organization data.
It is useful for the admin
to know when accounts
have been
successfully installed,
and what state they are in,
to help support users
who might be having problems.
This release adds eight
account status items for mail,
calendar,
and other account types.
Note, that status
is only reported for accounts
installed by configurations
and won't include
accounts created manually
or installed via MDM profiles.
Each new status item corresponds
to an account
configuration type,
with status for incoming
and outgoing mail accounts
reported separately.
The new status items each use
a different type of JSON object,
to represent the status of
the corresponding account type.
Here are examples
of an incoming mail status item,
and a subscribed
calendar status item.
The value of the identifier key
is a unique identifier
for an object within the array
of status item objects --
more on this in a minute.
The value of the
declaration identifier key,
matches the identifier
property value
of the configuration
that installed the account,
making it easy
to cross-reference
the status item object and
its associated configuration.
These two keys
are always present
in all types of account
status item object.
The other keys are specific
to the type of account.
For example, hostname and port
for the mail server,
or calendar-URL
for the subscribed calendar.
This release introduces status
items whose value is an array,
to support reporting
on one or more accounts
of the same type.
Such array values
have special behavior.
Each item in the array
is a JSON object
with the same schema used for
all objects in a single array.
Each object type always
has an identifier key,
acting as the primary key
for locating objects
within the array.
Other keys are present
and tied to the underlying type
of status being reported.
To ensure forwards compatibility
with any keys added
in future OS releases,
your server must accept
unknown keys in array objects.
Changes to an array value
are always reported
incrementally to the server
on a per-object basis,
for performance reasons.
Let's run through an example
that shows how
this new feature works.
In this example,
the server sends
two mail account configurations
to the device.
These are both active
resulting in two mail accounts
present on the device.
The server now sends
a status subscription
for the mail account
status item.
When the subscription
is activated,
status for the accounts
is collected,
and the device sends
a status report to the server.
The status report will include
the two account status objects
in the status array,
giving the server
a complete picture
of what is currently
present on the device.
Each array object
has a different identifier.
After processing this report,
the server has status
for two mail accounts,
matching what is on the device.
When the server adds
a mail account on the device
by sending a new configuration,
the status item on the device
has a new object added
to its array value,
and another status report
is sent to the server.
Only the new item is reported.
The value of the identifier
key does not match
any the server already has,
so the server can infer this
corresponds to a new account.
After processing this report,
the server has status
for three mail accounts,
the two initial ones
and the new one,
again matching exactly
what is on the device.
When account status changes,
such as when a user toggles
the mail or notes enabled state,
the status item on the device
will have an updated object
in its array value,
and again, a status report
is sent to the server.
Only the changed item
is reported.
In this case, the user
turned off the notes feature
for the account.
The value of the identifier key
matches one
the server already has,
so the server can infer
that this is an update
to an existing account.
Consequently,
it replaces the existing
status item array object
with the new one.
After processing this report,
the server has status
for three mail accounts,
but one has changed.
When an account configuration
is removed from the device,
the status item on the device
has the corresponding object
marked for removal,
and another status report
is sent to the server.
Only the removed item
is reported.
To indicate removal,
the array item object
contains only two keys:
the identifier key --
whose value matches
one the server already has --
and the removed key,
set to the value true.
This allows the server
to update its representation
of the device state
by removing the existing item.
After processing this report,
the server has status
for only two mail accounts,
correctly matching
the state of the device.
One last point about
status reports.
The device will limit the rate
at which status reports are sent
to avoid performance issues.
The device aggregates
changes to status items
over a variable interval
of up to one minute
before sending a status report
to the server.
This means status
is reported quickly,
but it is not immediate.
Next, let's turn our attention
to solving a perennial
MDM-bottleneck problem:
monitoring
application install status.
MDM servers often install apps
on devices to give users access
to the tools needed
for their work or education.
Server-side logic
is often dictated
by whether an app is installed
successfully or not.
So MDM servers need to monitor
app installation progress
and watch for the possibility
of users removing managed apps
on their device.
Currently, MDM servers can use
the InstalledApplicationList
or ManagedApplicationList
commands to poll the device
to observe
app installation progress.
We can avoid polling
by having the device
proactively send app install
progress to the server.
And the tool to do that
is declarative device management
status reports.
This release adds
an mdm.app status item.
Its value is an array of objects
that each represent an app
that has been installed
by the MDM server.
Since this value is an array,
it is reported incrementally,
using the procedure
described earlier.
Note that only apps installed
by MDM are reported here,
even on supervised devices.
This status report includes
a status item for an app
that has finished installing.
The identifier key
is the unique identifier
for the array item object,
and in this case,
is the app's bundle identifier.
The name key indicates
the name of the app.
The three version keys
provide normal, short,
and external
version identifiers.
And the state key
is an enumeration
that indicates the current
install phase for the app.
The values of these keys
correspond
to the equivalent items
in the MDM
ManagedApplicationList
command response.
With all this information, the
server can immediately identify
which app is being reported
and what its state is.
Let's examine an example of the
flow of data as an app installs.
On the right side,
we have an iOS 16 device
that is being managed
by an MDM server.
The server has already enabled
declarative device management
and sent a status subscription
for the MDM-installed
app status item.
The next step for the server
is to install an app
using the MDM
InstallApplication command.
Since this is a user enrollment,
user approval is needed
to install the app,
so a prompt appears
when the device processes
the app install command.
At this point, the installation
progress is paused,
waiting for user input.
The device will send
a status report to the server,
and that will contain a single
MDM-installed app status object,
with the bundle ID of the app
and the state set to prompting.
At some point, the user taps
the Install button,
and the app install
starts on the device.
As the install proceeds, another
status report will be sent,
this time with the app state
set to installing;
indicating the app is being
downloaded and installed.
Eventually, the app
completes installation
and is ready for use.
At that point, another
status report will be sent
with the app state
set to managed,
indicating the app is properly
installed and managed.
Now, let's say the user manually
deletes the app on the device.
Again, a status report
will be sent,
this time with the app state set
to managed-but-uninstalled.
This indicates the app
is no longer installed,
but its management state
is still being tracked
on the device.
Let's assume the server
wants to remove
the app-management state.
It does that by sending
a RemoveApplication command
to the device.
That removes the internally
maintained management state,
and if the app were
still present,
it would be removed too.
Another status report will be
sent with the app object
marked as removed
from the app status array.
This illustrates the power of
the new MDM status item
to help improve
the responsiveness
and reliability of app installs,
and it only takes a few steps
to implement.
Now, let's examine our third
focus area: predicates.
Let's quickly review
activation predicates.
Activations can include
an optional predicate
that determines
whether the configurations
referenced in the activation
will be applied to the device.
Predicates can reference
status items
to allow the values of those
status items to be tested.
When a status item referenced
in a predicate changes,
the device will reprocess
all of the activations,
reevaluating any predicates.
Predicates are specified
as a string
using the NSPredicate syntax
documented on
the Apple Developer site.
To support more complex
predicate expressions,
we have extended the predicate
syntax to make it easier
to detect status items
in the expression.
The new syntax places
the status item name
inside an @status term
in the predicate string.
In the example,
the serial number status item
appears in
the predicate expression,
using the new syntax.
The previous syntax
will continue to work
for backwards compatibility,
however, it is now deprecated,
so please switch
to the new one.
Let's examine how
predicates can be used
with status item array values.
As we just described,
we now have status item values
that are arrays
for the accounts
and MDM-installed
app status items.
It is useful to be able
to predicate an activation
on an item in the array.
For example, we might want
an activation to be triggered
when an app with a particular
bundle identifier
is installed and managed
on the device.
NSPredicate has
a SUBQUERY term
that can be used
to operate on arrays.
This NSPredicate expression
uses a SUBQUERY
targeting the MDM-installed
app status item.
The status item is used as the
first argument to the SUBQUERY.
The second argument
defines a variable
that will refer to each
element of the array.
The third argument is
a predicate expression
that tests each element
identified by that variable.
The SUBQUERY expression
returns an array of elements
that match the predicate
in the third argument.
The @count operator
then returns the length
of that array,
and the length is checked
to determine if there is
one resulting match.
When the specified app
is installed and managed,
this SUBQUERY expression
will return an array
with a single element,
and the predicate
will evaluate to true.
When the app is not installed,
the SUBQUERY expression
will return an empty array,
and the predicate
will evaluate to false.
Note that in order
to reference the keys
in the status item array object,
the @key extension term
must be used to ensure the key
paths are properly processed.
The new predicate syntax
is extensible,
and we will now discuss
how it can be used
to add predicate terms
for a new type of data.
Servers need to be able
to more directly control
the evaluation of predicates, so
that complex server-side logic
can translate into simple
state changes on the device,
without the need to synchronize
large sets of configurations
to trigger those changes.
An example of this might be
an organization that has users
with multiple roles
and wants efficient,
just-in-time assignment
of devices
as they are handed out to users,
or organizations that need
to quickly distribute
replacement devices,
or quickly put devices
into a safe mode
to protect organization data.
To support this,
I am pleased to say
we are adding a new declaration
to allow servers
to set arbitrary properties
on the device,
that can be directly used
in activation predicates.
This is the new management
properties declaration.
The declaration consists
of a JSON object
whose key names
are defined by the server.
The JSON object values
can be any JSON value type,
including arrays or objects.
The management properties
declaration here,
includes three properties:
the name and age properties
that have a string
and integer value,
and the roles property
that is an array of strings.
This is an activation
with a predicate
that references some
management properties.
First, it tests the age property
to determine
if its integer value is
greater than or equal to 18,
then it tests the roles property
to determine
if the string Grade12 is
in the property array value.
Each property is referenced
using the @property
extension term,
with the property key name
inside the term.
Multiple management
properties declarations
can be sent to the device,
but the keys should be unique
across all of them.
If there are duplicate keys,
one of the values
will be arbitrarily chosen
when the property is referenced
in a predicate, leading
to unpredictable results.
So please avoid using
duplicate key names.
Let's explore
an example use case.
This example involves a school.
And of course, the school
has a set of teachers.
The school has two divisions:
Upper and Lower.
Each division has its own campus
with its own Wi-Fi network.
Some teachers function
as an IT Admin
and require access
to a shared mail account.
Some teachers also function
as a sports coach
and should have
a subscribed calendar
for all the team
game schedules.
There are thus four different
roles that a teacher may have,
and sometimes
they have multiple roles.
Each role has a set
of configurations
that must be applied to devices
based on the roles
of the teacher
assigned to the device.
Let's consider two teachers
in our example.
Teacher one teaches
in Lower school
and is also a sports coach.
Teacher two teaches in Upper
school and is also an IT admin.
How might such a use case
be handled
by a traditional MDM server?
Typically, the server has
to wait for a device
to be assigned to a teacher
before it can fully
configure that device.
The server has to determine
what roles the teacher has.
It then determines what profiles
are linked to each role.
It then has to install
each profile on the device
one at a time.
If a teacher changes roles,
the server has to add
or remove profiles
to match the new roles.
This is time-consuming
and can introduce
significant bottlenecks
to a device-management system
particularly at peak times,
which in our case would be
the first day of school
when assignments are done.
With the new management
properties declaration,
we have a more efficient
alternative to this.
This involves preloading
a full set of declarations
on the device ahead of time.
Configurations
are assigned to activations,
with predicates that are
triggered for different roles
via management properties.
When a device is assigned to
a teacher, the server sends only
a management properties
declaration
with the teacher's roles,
which triggers activation
of the configurations
for those roles.
This method minimizes
the overall server
and network traffic
and reduces the complexity
of making rapid changes
to device state.
Let's go back
to our school example.
The server will preload the
following sets of declarations:
two activation/configuration
pairs
that set up the Wi-Fi network
for each division.
Then, we have an
activation/configuration pair
for the IT admin role,
that installs a mail account.
Finally, we have an activation
and configuration
that installs
a subscribed calendar.
Each activation has a predicate
that tests the division
or function's name using
the roles management property.
When initially loaded
on an unassigned device,
all the predicates evaluate
to false, so nothing is applied.
Now, let's examine what happens
on the day of assignment.
All the server needs to do
is create
management properties
declarations
customized to each teacher.
Teacher one has a roles property
that lists Lower and Sports.
Teacher two has a roles property
that lists Upper and IT Admin.
When these declarations
are separately sent
to each assigned device,
the preloaded activations
will all be reevaluated.
So teacher one's device
has the configurations
for Lower and Sports
roles activated.
And teacher two's device
has the configurations
for the Upper and IT Admin
roles activated.
Only a single declaration
is needed to trigger
the application
of many configurations.
Finally, let's examine
what happens when
a teacher changes roles.
In this case, teacher two
has become a sports coach
in addition
to their existing roles.
The management
properties declaration
for the teacher's assigned
device is now updated
to include
the additional role name.
When that declaration
is updated on the device,
all the activations
are reevaluated.
In this case, the subscribed
calendar configuration
for the new Sports role
will be applied.
Again, only a single declaration
change is needed as a trigger.
This illustrates
how the management
properties declaration
provides a powerful way
to quickly and easily switch
between sets of configurations
on a device,
so that complex
server-side logic
can translate into simple
state changes on the device.
Now, let's wrap up.
We have extended the scope of
declarative device management
on iOS 16, tvOS 16,
and macOS Ventura,
as well as making it available
for all applicable types
of MDM enrollment,
including Shared iPad.
This provides full support for
declarative device management
across all Apple devices
that support MDM.
We have added new status items
for passcode, accounts,
and MDM-installed apps.
The MDM-installed app status
provides a great solution
for one of MDM's
key bottlenecks.
Finally, we have enhanced
the predicate syntax
to make it more extensible
and easy to use
and added the new management
properties declaration
that gives servers
even more opportunity
to move complex business logic
to the device.
Now is the time to add
declarative device management
to your products.
And we're excited to learn
what you'll do
to reimagine device
management solutions
using declarative
device management!
As always, your feedback
is greatly appreciated.
Thank you and enjoy
the rest of WWDC.
♪ ♪