♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi. I'm Curt, an engineer
on the SwiftUI team.
There are some exciting new APIs
for navigation in SwiftUI.
I've been enjoying building apps
with these new APIs
and I'm thrilled to be able
to share them with you.
These APIs scale
from basic stacks --
like on Apple TV,
iPhone, and Apple Watch --
to powerful multicolumn
presentations.
The new APIs
bring robust support
for programmatic navigation
and deep linking,
letting you compose pieces
to build the perfect structure
for your app.
In this talk, I'll give you
some straightforward recipes
for cooking up an app
with navigation in SwiftUI.
And if you're already
using SwiftUI,
we hope these new APIs will
help you kick it up a notch.
I'll start with the ingredients
that go into the new
data-driven navigation APIs.
Then, we'll move
to our tasting menu:
several quick and easy recipes
for full programmatic
control of navigation.
For the dessert course,
I'll share some tips
on using the new APIs to persist
navigation state in your apps.
If you've used navigation
in SwiftUI before,
you might be wondering
how the new APIs are different.
So before digging in, let's
review some of the existing API.
The existing APIs are based
on links that send views
that are shown in other columns
or on a stack.
For example, I might have a list
of navigation links
in a root view.
When I tap one of these links,
the link pushes
its view on the stack.
This works great
for basic navigation,
and you can continue
using this pattern.
But let's pop back
to the root view.
With the existing
navigation API,
to present a link
programmatically,
I add a binding to the link.
For example,
I can present this link's view
by setting item.showDetail
to true.
But this means I need a separate
binding for each link.
With the new API,
we lift the binding up
to the entire container,
called a NavigationStack.
The path here
is a collection
that represents all the values
pushed on the stack.
NavigationLinks
append values to the path.
You can deep link
by mutating the path;
or pop to the root view
by removing all the items
from the path.
In this talk, I'll show you
how the new navigation API
enables data-driven
programmatic navigation.
I hope you find it
powerful and easy to use.
Before jumping into recipes for
using the new navigation APIs,
I thought it would be helpful
to share what's on the menu.
I've really gotten
into cooking lately
and I've been working on an app
to keep track of my recipes.
I have a lot of ideas
about different ways
to present this info.
For example,
here's a three-column approach.
The first column lets me
select a recipe category.
When I select a category,
the second column lists
the recipes I've collected.
And when I select a recipe,
the detail area shows
the ingredients for that recipe.
The detail area also has links
to a selection
of related recipes.
My grandma always said,
"The crust makes the pie."
So that's what
we're cooking up today.
Our ingredients are
the new navigation APIs.
Let's dig into those,
then we'll look at some
specific navigation recipes
that mix them together.
The new navigation APIs
introduce a couple
of new container types
that you can use
to describe
the structure of your app,
along with a fresh new varietal
of NavigationLink
for helping your guests
move around that structure.
The first new container
is NavigationStack.
NavigationStack represents
a push-pop interface
like you see
in Find My on Apple Watch,
Settings on iPhone,
and the new System Settings app
on macOS Ventura.
The second new container type
is NavigationSplitView.
NavigationSplitView
is perfect for multicolumn apps
like Mail or Notes
on Mac and iPad.
And NavigationSplitView
automatically adapts
to a single-column stack
on iPhone,
in Slide Over on iPad,
and even on Apple Watch
and Apple TV.
NavigationSplitView
has two sets of initializers.
One set, like shown here,
creates a two-column experience.
The other set of initializers
creates a three-column
experience.
NavigationSplitView
comes with a cartload
of configuration options that
let you customize column widths,
sidebar presentation,
and even programmatically
show and hide columns.
I won't dive into
the configuration options
in this talk, but please check
out my colleague Raj's talk,
"SwiftUI on iPad:
Organize your interface"
and the great documentation
on how to tune
NavigationSplitView
to be just right for your app.
Previously, NavigationLinks
always included
a title and view to present.
The new varieties
still include a title,
but instead
of a view to present,
they present a value.
For example,
this link is presenting
the recipe for apple pie.
As we'll see,
NavigationLink is smart.
A link's behavior depends on
the NavigationStack or list
that it appears in.
To see how these
tasty new APIs work together,
let's look at some specific
recipes for using them
in my cookbook app,
and in your apps.
Our first recipe
is a basic stack of views,
like you'd find in
Find My on Apple Watch
or Settings on iPhone.
I have a section
for each category.
Within a section, I can tap
on a recipe to see the details.
Within any recipe, I can tap
one of the related recipes
to push it onto the stack.
I can use the back button
to return to the original recipe
and then to the categories list.
This recipe combines
a NavigationStack
with the new variety
of NavigationLink,
and a navigation
destination modifier.
Let's see how.
I'll start with a basic
NavigationStack.
Inside, I have a List that
iterates over all my categories
and a navigationTitle.
Inside the List, I have
a section for each category.
Next, inside each section,
I'll add a NavigationLink
for each recipe in the category.
For now, I'll make the link
present my RecipeDetail view.
This is using the existing
view destination
NavigationLink.
And that's enough to get
this navigation experience
cooking along.
But what about
programmatic navigation?
To add programmatic navigation,
I need to tease apart two pieces
of this navigation link:
the value it presents
and the view
that goes with that value.
Let's see how.
First, I'll pull the destination
view out of the link
and into the new
navigationDestination modifier.
This modifier declares
the type of the presented data
that it's responsible for;
here, that's a Recipe.
The modifier takes
a view builder
that describes what view
to push onto the stack
when a recipe value
is presented.
Then, I'll switch to one
of the new NavigationLinks
and just present
the recipe value.
Let's peek under the hood
and see how NavigationStack
makes this work.
Every navigation stack
keeps track of a path
that represents all the data
that the stack is showing.
When the stack is
just showing its root view,
like shown here,
the path is empty.
Next, the stack also keeps track
of all the navigation
destinations declared inside it,
or inside any view
pushed onto the stack.
In general, this is a set,
though for this example,
we only have one destination.
Let's add the pushed views
to the diagram, too.
Now, because the path is empty,
so is the list of pushed views.
Now, like milk and cookies,
the magic happens
when we put these together.
When I tap
a value-presenting link,
it appends that value
to the path.
Then, the navigation stack
maps its destinations over
the path values to decide which
views to push on the stack.
Now, from my apple pie recipe,
if I tap Pie Crust,
the link appends
that to the path, too.
NavigationStack does its magic
and pushes another RecipeDetail
view onto the stack.
For every value
I add to the path,
NavigationStack
pushes another view.
When I tap the back button,
NavigationStack removes
the last item from the path
and from the pushed views.
And NavigationStack
has one more trick to offer.
It lets us connect to this path
using a binding.
Let's go back to our code.
Here's where we were.
To bind the path,
first I'll add some State.
Because every value pushed
on this stack is a recipe,
I can use an array
of recipes as my path.
If you need to present
a variety of data on a stack,
be sure to check out
the new type-erasing
NavigationPath collection.
Once I have my path state,
I add an argument
to my NavigationStack
and pass a binding to the path.
With that in place,
I can make my stack sizzle.
For example,
I could add a method
to jump to a particular recipe.
Or from anywhere on my stack,
I can pop back to the root
just by resetting the path.
That's how to prepare
a pushable stack using
the new NavigationStack,
value-presenting
NavigationLinks,
and navigationDestinations
in SwiftUI.
This recipe works on all
platforms, including the Mac,
but really shines on iPhone,
Apple TV, and Apple Watch.
To see NavigationStack in
action, be sure to check out
"Build a productivity app
for Apple Watch."
Our next recipe is for
multicolumn presentation
without any stacks, like you'd
find in Mail on Mac and iPad.
On iPad,
the sidebar is initially hidden.
I can reveal it
and choose a category.
Then, in the second column,
I can choose a recipe.
The third column
shows the recipe details.
This recipe combines
a NavigationSplitView
with the new variety
of NavigationLink,
and a List selection.
This recipe is great
on larger devices
because it helps avoid modality.
I can see all my information
without having to drill in.
Let's see how.
I'll start with a three-column
NavigationSplitView
with placeholder views
for the content and detail.
Then, I'll add a List
in the sidebar
that iterates over
all my categories,
and a navigationTitle.
Inside the List,
I have a NavigationLink
for each category.
Next, I'll introduce some State
to keep track of which category
is selected.
I'll tweak our list
in the sidebar
to use the selectedCategory.
Note that we're passing
a binding to the selection.
This lets the list
and its contents
manipulate the selection.
When you put a value-presenting
link inside a list
with a matching
selection type --
category here --
the link will automatically
update the selection
when tapped or clicked.
So now when I select
a category in the sidebar,
SwiftUI updates
the selectedCategory.
Check out Raj's
"Organize your interface" talk
that I mentioned earlier
for some great information
on selection and lists.
Next,
I'll replace my placeholder
in the content column
with a list of the recipes
for the selected category,
and add a navigationTitle
for this column too.
Just like
for the selected category,
I can use the same technique
to keep track of the selected
recipe in the content list.
I'll use State
for the selectedRecipe,
have my content list
use that state,
and use a value-presenting link
for each recipe.
Finally,
I'll update the detail column
to show, well, the details
for the selectedRecipe.
With this in place,
I again have full programmatic
control over navigation.
For example, to navigate
to my recipe of the day,
I just need to update
my selection state.
That's how to prepare
a multi-column
navigation experience using
the new NavigationSplitView,
value-presenting
NavigationLinks,
and Lists with selection
in SwiftUI.
One super cool thing
about combining List selection
and NavigationSplitView
like this,
is that SwiftUI
can automatically adapt
the split view
to a single stack on iPhone
or in Slide Over on iPad.
Changes to selection
automatically translate
into the appropriate
pushes and pops on iPhone.
Of course,
this multicolumn presentation
also works great on the Mac.
And although Apple TV
and Apple Watch
don't show multiple columns,
those platforms also get
the automatic translation
to a single stack.
NavigationSplitView in SwiftUI
works on all platforms.
Next, let's look at how we can
put all these ingredients
together by building a
two-column navigation experience
like that in Photos
on iPad and Mac.
When I select a category,
the detail area shows a grid of
all my recipes in that category.
When I tap a recipe,
it's pushed onto a stack
in the detail area.
When I tap a related recipe,
it's also pushed onto the stack.
And I can navigate back
to the grid of recipes.
This recipe is our
pièce de résistance,
combining navigation split view,
stack, link, destination,
and list.
Let's see how all these
ingredients go together.
I'll start with a two-column
NavigationSplitView.
The first column is exactly
like the previous recipe.
I have some State to track
the selectedCategory
and a List that uses
a binding to that state
and a value-presenting
NavigationLink,
and the requisite
navigationTitle.
The differences in this recipe
are in the detail area.
The new navigation APIs really
take advantage of composition.
Just like I can put a list
inside a column
of a NavigationSplitView,
I can also put a NavigationStack
inside a column.
The root view
of this Navigation Stack
is my RecipeGrid.
Notice that the RecipeGrid
is inside the NavigationStack.
That means I can put
stack-related modifiers
inside RecipeGrid.
Let's zoom in to
the body of RecipeGrid
to see what that means.
RecipeGrid is a view and takes
a category as a parameter.
Because category is optional
here, I'll start with an if-let.
The else case handles
an empty selection.
Inside my if, I'll add
a scroll view and a lazy grid.
Lazy grid layout
takes a sequence of views.
Here, I'm using ForEach
to iterate over my recipes.
For each recipe,
I have a value-presenting
NavigationLink.
The link presents
a recipe value.
The link's label,
in this trailing closure,
is my RecipeTile
with the thumbnail and title.
So what's left
to finish this grid?
Well, I haven't told
the NavigationStack
how to map
from recipes to detail views.
Like I mentioned
with the first recipe,
the new NavigationStack
uses the navigationDestination
modifier
to map from values on its path
to views shown on the stack.
So let's add a
navigationDestination modifier.
But where should I attach it?
I'm tempted to attach it
directly to the link,
but this is wrong
for two reasons.
Lazy containers, like List,
Table, or, here, LazyVGrid,
don't load all of their views
immediately.
If I put the modifier here,
the destination
might not be loaded,
so the surrounding
NavigationStack
might not see it.
Second, if I put
the modifier here,
it will be repeated
for every item in my grid.
Instead, I'll attach
the modifier to my ScrollView.
By attaching the modifier
outside the ScrollView,
I ensure that
the NavigationStack
can see
this navigationDestination
regardless
of the scroll position.
Another thing I like about
putting the modifier here
is that it's still close
to the links that target it.
Navigation destination gives me
flexibility to organize my code
the way that makes sense
to me or my team.
Popping back
to my NavigationSplitView,
there's just one more thing
to enable full programmatic
navigation here.
I need to add a navigation path.
I'll add State to hold the path
and bind the state
to my NavigationStack.
With full programmatic
navigation in place,
I can write a method
to show my recipe of the day
in this navigation experience.
That's how to prepare
a multicolumn navigation
experience with stacks
using the new
NavigationSplitView,
NavigationStack,
value-presenting
NavigationLinks,
and Lists with selection
in SwiftUI.
As with the previous recipe,
this one also automatically
adapts to narrow presentations
and works on all platforms.
It was fun exploring
these recipes for structuring
the navigation in my app,
but our navigation feast
wouldn't be complete
without dessert.
For that, let's look at how
to persist the navigation state.
To persist navigation state
in my app,
I just need
two more ingredients:
Codable and SceneStorage.
This recipe
has three basic steps.
First, I'll encapsulate
my navigation state
in a NavigationModel type.
That lets me save
and restore it as a unit
so it's always consistent.
Then, I'll make my
navigation model Codable.
Finally, I'll use SceneStorage
to save and restore my model.
I'll have to take care
along the way --
I don't want my app to crash
like a fallen soufflé --
but the steps
are straightforward.
Let's look at step one.
Here's the code
from the end of our last recipe.
My navigation state is stored
in the selectedCategory
and path properties.
The selectedCategory tracks
the selection in the sidebar.
The path tracks the views
pushed onto the stack
in the detail area.
I'll introduce
a new NavigationModel class
and make it conform
to ObservableObject.
Next, I'll move my navigation
state into my model object,
changing the property wrappers
from State to Published.
Then,
I'll introduce a StateObject
to hold an instance
of my NavigationModel
and change the parameters
to use the new model object.
Next, I'll make my
navigation model Codable.
I'll start by adding
the Codable conformance
to the class.
In many cases,
Swift can automatically generate
Codable conformance,
but I want to implement
my own conformance here.
The main reason is that
Recipe is a model value.
I don't want to store
the entire model value
for state restoration.
There are two reasons for this.
First, my recipe database
already contains all the details
for the recipe.
It's not a good use of storage
to repeat that information
in my saved navigation state.
Second, if my recipe database
can change independently
of my local navigation state --
say, because I finally get
around to adding syncing --
I don't want my local navigation
state to contain stale data.
For custom codability,
next I'll add CodingKeys.
One of the keys
is just selectedCategory.
But notice that I named
the other "recipePathIds”
I'm planning to just store
the identifiers of the recipes
on the path.
In my encode method,
I'll create a keyed container
using my coding keys
and add the selected category
to the container.
I'm using encodeIfPresent,
so I only write the value
if it's non-nil.
Then, I'll add
the recipe path identifiers.
Note that I'm
mapping over the path
to get the identifiers
to encode.
For example,
suppose my navigation state
included Dessert
as a selected category,
with Apple Pie
and Pie Crust on the path,
like shown
in the green box on top.
This might be encoded to JSON,
like shown in this other box.
To finish up Codability,
I'll add the required
initializer.
The interesting bit is here
where I decode the recipe IDs,
then use my shared data model
to convert the IDs
back into recipes.
I'm using compactMap
to discard any recipes
that couldn't be found.
For example, this might happen
if I delete a recipe
on another device
after I have sync working --
something I'm definitely
going to do someday.
This is a place you'll need
to use discretion
in your own apps to make sure
any restored navigation state
still makes sense.
Finally,
I'll add a computed property
for reading and writing
my model as JSON data.
Now that I have
a navigation model
and it knows how to encode
and decode itself,
all that's left is to actually
save and restore it.
For that I'll use SceneStorage.
Here's where we left
our main view.
I was using a StateObject
to hold my NavigationModel.
Now, I'll introduce
some SceneStorage
to persist my NavigationModel.
SceneStorage properties
automatically save and restore
their associated values.
When the type of the storage
is optional, like my data here,
the value is nil when
a new scene is created.
When the system
restores a scene,
SwiftUI ensures that the value
of the SceneStorage property
is also restored.
I'll take advantage of this
to persist my NavigationModel.
To do that, I'll add
a task modifier to my view.
The task modifier
runs its closure asynchronously.
It starts when the view appears
and is cancelled
when the view goes away.
Whenever my view appears,
I'll first check whether I have
any existing data
from a previous run of the app.
If so, I'll update my
navigation model with that data.
Then, I'll start an asynchronous
for loop that will iterate
whenever my
navigation model changes.
The body of this loop
will run on each change,
so I can use that
to save my navigation state
back to my scene storage data.
And that's it!
When I leave my app
to go check out
some vintage Julia Child
cooking shows on the web,
it remembers where I was.
When I return to the app,
it takes me back
to where I left off.
Now, no cookbook
would be complete
without a weird section at
the end with handy kitchen tips.
I don't have three great
substitutes for cilantro,
but I do have some
navigation tips to share.
Switch to the new
NavigationStack
and NavigationSplitView
as soon as you can.
If you're using NavigationView
with the stack style,
switch to NavigationStack.
NavigationStack is also
a good first choice on Apple TV,
Apple Watch,
or in sheets on iPad and iPhone,
where the stack style
has always been the default.
If you're using
a multicolumn NavigationView,
switch to NavigationSplitView.
And if you've already adopted
programmatic navigation
using the links
that take bindings,
I strongly encourage you to move
to the new value-presenting
NavigationLink
along with navigation paths
and list selection.
The old-style programmatic links
are deprecated
beginning in iOS 16
and aligned releases.
For details and examples
on migrating to the new APIs,
check out the article,
"Migrating to new
navigation types"
in the developer documentation.
Next, keep in mind that List
and the new NavigationSplitView
and NavigationStack
were made to mix together.
Compose them to create
navigation experiences
your guests will love.
When using navigation stacks,
navigation destinations
can be anywhere inside
the stack or its subviews.
Consider putting destinations
near the corresponding links
to make maintenance easier,
but remember not to put them
inside of lazy containers.
Finally, I'd encourage you
to start building
your navigation experiences
with NavigationSplitView
when it makes sense.
Even if you're initially
developing for iPhone,
NavigationSplitView
will automatically adapt
to the narrower device.
And when you're ready to support
iPhone Pro Max in landscape,
or to bring your app
to iPad or Mac,
NavigationSplitView
will take advantage
of all that additional space.
Thanks for the chance
to share the new SwiftUI
Navigation APIs with you!
Besides the talks
I mentioned earlier,
I invite you to check out
"Bring multiple windows
to your SwiftUI app"
for some great info on opening
new windows and scenes
in your apps.
I hope that these recipes for
navigation in our cookbook app
were palate-pleasing.
I'm looking forward to seeing
the great experiences
you cook up in your own apps.
Bon appétit!
[LIPS SMACK]
♪