♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi!
My name is Devon.
I'm an engineer
on the watchOS team,
and today,
I'll be talking about iOS.
And I'm Graham,
an engineer from iOS,
and today,
I'll be talking about watchOS.
We'll be talking about
API additions to WidgetKit
that enable you to write
accessory widgets
for the Lock Screen
and complications for watchOS.
We'll show how you can
develop both together,
along with additions to SwiftUI
to help you along the way.
If you're unfamiliar
with widgets,
timelines, and reloading,
I encourage you to seek out
prior WidgetKit sessions.
First, we'll talk about
the history of complications
and how they've evolved.
Then, we'll talk about new API
to color your widgets
and complications
in their new environments.
After that, Graham will demo
how to get started
making your own widgets
and moving your existing
widget extension to watchOS.
Next, Graham will
walk you through
how to make the most
of these smaller views.
And lastly, we'll talk about the
different privacy environments
your widgets may appear in.
Complications are a key piece
of the watchOS platform,
presenting quick, glanceable
information on the watch face.
They convey
immediately accessible,
high-value information
and a tap takes you
to the relevant location
in the app.
In watchOS 2,
ClockKit enabled you
to create your own
complications.
Complications have come
a long way since then.
Rich complications were
introduced in watchOS 5,
with graphic content
and a suite of new families.
SwiftUI complications
and multiple complications
were introduced in watchOS 7,
which enabled you
to take your complications
to the next level
and provide more options
than ever.
Today, complications
have been reimagined
and remade with WidgetKit,
embracing SwiftUI
and bringing the glanceable
complication experience
to iOS in the form of widgets.
With WidgetKit in iOS 16
and watchOS 9,
you can build great glanceable
widgets and complications
across both platforms,
enabling you to write your code
once and share infrastructure
with your existing
Home Screen widgets.
To do this, we've added
new widget families
to the existing
WidgetFamily type,
prefixed with the word
"accessory."
The new accessoryRectangular
family can be used
to show multiple lines of text
or small graphs and charts,
similar to the existing ClockKit
graphicRectangular family.
The accessoryCircular family
is great for brief information,
gauges, and progress views.
This family also replaces the
graphicCircular ClockKit family.
The all-new accessoryInline
is a text-only slot
present on many faces on watchOS
and above the time on iOS.
The inline slot
comes in many sizes,
and we'll talk about how
to make the best use
of them all later on.
Specific to watchOS is the new
accessoryCorner family,
mixing a small circle of widget
content with gauges and text.
This talk focuses on families
common between iOS and watchOS.
For more details
on this new watchOS family
and complication-specific
features, check out
the "Go further with WidgetKit
complications" session.
Let's talk about colors
and rendering modes.
You may have noticed
that accessory widgets
take on a few
different appearances.
The system controls the look
of accessory family widgets,
and we've given you some tools
to help adapt them
to the rendering style.
There are three different
rendering modes
your widget
may be shown in.
Your widget can be full color,
accented, or vibrant.
We've introduced the
WidgetRenderingMode type
to represent these three
different presentations.
You can access this value
from the Environment,
using the widgetRenderingMode
keypath.
After that, you can change
your content conditionally
to make sure it looks just right
everywhere that it'll show up.
In watchOS's full-color mode,
your content is displayed
exactly as you specify.
Many existing complications
take on a colorful appearance
in full color, like the gradient
in Weather's gauges,
or the Activity rings' colors.
In the accented rendering mode,
your views are split
into two groups
and colored independently.
The two coloring groups
are flatly colored,
preserving only
their original opacities.
You can tell the system
how to group your views
with the .widgetAccentable()
view modifier,
or switch out your content
based on
the Widget Rendering Mode
environment value
to look perfect when flattened.
Note that the system
can tint your content
in a number of ways,
some of which are inverted.
Some are on a black background,
while others are
on the new full-color
backgrounds in watchOS 9.
In the iOS vibrant
rendering mode,
your content is desaturated
then colored appropriately
for the Lock Screen background.
The system maps
your greyscale content
in to a material appearance.
This material is adaptive
to the content behind it,
appearing just right
in its environment.
Additionally, the Lock Screen
can be configured
to give the vibrant
rendering mode a colored tint.
A light source color ends up
mostly opaque and brighter.
On the other end,
a dark source color
appears as a less prominent blur
of the background behind it,
with only a slight amount
of brightening.
To ensure legibility,
avoid using transparent colors
in this mode.
Instead, use darker colors
or black
to represent less
prominent content
while maintaining legibility.
To help you with
some of this nuance,
we've also introduced the
AccessoryWidgetBackground view
to give a consistent backdrop
to widgets that need them,
like this circular calendar.
While most accessory widgets
have no background,
some styles can be
enhanced with one.
The background view takes on
different appearances
in the various
widget rendering modes
and is tuned by the system
to look right
for the style of the face
or Lock Screen.
This is a soft transparent view
in full color and accented,
and black in
the vibrant environment,
which results in
a low brightness and full blur.
Graham is super excited to get
started making some new widgets
for the Lock Screen
and complications on watchOS --
I'll hand it off to him.
Hi again!
I'll be adding support
for our new widget families
to an existing app --
Emoji Rangers --
which some of you might be
familiar with from WWDC2020's
"Widgets Code-along."
Before I begin, a note for those
with existing
widget-free projects.
You can get started by adding
the Widget Extension target
to your project,
which already exists on iOS
and has been brought
to watchOS.
But I know that many of you
have apps with widgets already,
so today let's start there
and talk about
adding new widgets
and complications.
We'll continue
the Emoji Rangers project.
This app keeps track
of our favorite Emoji Rangers
and keeps you up to date with
their health and recharge time
with the use
of Home Screen widgets.
We've already brought Emoji
Rangers over to watchOS,
bringing our favorite app
to our wrists.
Today we'll be extending
Emoji Rangers with support
for our new widget families
and bringing its widget
extension to the watch.
Let's get started with getting
the widget extension
onto the watch.
We'll add a new watchOS target
that shares code
with the existing iOS target.
We'll duplicate the iOS
widget extension target,
give it a better name,
change the bundle identifier
to be prefixed
with the watch app's,
target watchOS,
and embed our new extension
in our watch app.
Now we need to get our code
building on watchOS --
let's get on with that.
Glancing through the
EmojiRangerWidget code,
we can see
the timeline provider,
which is used when the
system reloads content,
the view which uses SwiftUI
to generate content
for our different families,
the widget configuration,
and the Xcode preview provider.
The Emoji Rangers app
already supports
iOS Home Screen widgets.
It offers the system small
and medium families,
and here in the
widget configuration,
I'm going to add
the new families.
Because system families are
unavailable on the watch,
we'll need to use
a platform macro
to specify our
supportedFamilies.
In the preview provider,
I'm going to add previews
for the new families.
Next, we need to implement the
new IntentRecommendation API
before we can successfully
build for watchOS.
While Intents are
fully configurable
in the widgets editing UI
on iOS,
on watchOS, we need to provide
a preconfigured list.
We can do that by overriding
the new recommendations method
on our IntentTimelineProvider.
Now we're building successfully.
Let's resume the previews
and see what
our circular widget looks like.
The content intended
for even a small widget
doesn't fit well inside
our new form factor.
The new widget families
are smaller than iOS widgets
found on the Home Screen,
and you'll need to consider
the content of
your complications.
Now let's talk about
some new views we can use
to make our complications
stand out.
Let's go to the view.
We can see code for the
systemSmall and other widgets;
let's add code for
the accessoryCircular case.
I think it would look good
just with the avatar.
This provides a quick shortcut
in to our app
but doesn't offer users
any information.
Let's add a progress view
around the edge,
which will give the users
an idea of when the Ranger
will be ready for combat again.
Trouble is animating
this progress view to be current
will require a lot of timeline
entries in short succession.
Instead, we can use SwiftUI's
new auto-updating ProgressView.
That takes a date interval
over which our Ranger
will be fully healed.
The system will keep
our progress view updated,
meaning we only need
one timeline entry here.
Much better.
Now let's add
the rectangular family.
We'll select
the rectangular preview.
This gives us more space,
so we'll make a three-line view
in the style of a complication.
First the character's name,
then their level,
and then the time
until fully healed,
for which we'll use
an auto-updating date field.
I'd like the character's name
to stand out,
so I'll size the text,
using a font style of headline,
and add the
widgetAccentable modifier
which will adjust its color.
Our view looks great here
in vibrant,
now let's see how it looks
in our other rendering modes
on the watch.
You can see how the character's
name takes on the accent color.
To make your widgets
and complications feel at home
in their environment,
it's important
that you use
the default font parameters
and make use of font styles.
The font styles and sizes
are different
between iOS and watchOS.
iOS uses the regular
text design,
while watchOS uses
a rounded design
with a heavier weight.
Your widgets and complications
will sit onscreen
adjacent to others.
And so they look consistent,
we recommend using
the font styles Title, Headline,
Body, and Caption.
Xcode's preview shows
we still have room leftover
to add the avatar too.
Let's see how this looks
on the iPhone.
That looks great!
Finally, let's add the third
style, accessoryInline,
which displays a line of text
and optionally an image.
Note that inline accessories
are drawn
according to system-defined
coloring and font.
Let's select the preview.
Let's show our hero's name
and recharge countdown.
This text is too long
for our watch slot.
So now's a good time
to show you ViewThatFits.
I can supply multiple views,
from lengthy to concise,
and ViewThatFits will choose
the first content view
that fits the available space
without truncation or clipping.
Let's shorten the text.
Even that might be too long
for the shortest watch slot,
so let's offer
a third alternative
by switching out the avatar
for the name.
Let's see what that looks like.
Refer to the "Compose Custom
layouts with SwiftUI" session
for more about this.
Awesome!
Even Emoji Rangers like
to enjoy some privacy,
so I'll hand it back
to Devon to talk about that.
Hello again!
Let's talk about privacy.
So far in this talk,
we've discussed the active state
of your widgets
and complications.
However, across our platforms,
you'll need to consider
whether the device
is redacting content
or in a low-luminance state.
On the iOS Lock Screen,
the default behavior
is to show your content even
while the device is locked,
which is the top-left cell
in our grid here.
However, this is configurable
in Settings,
and users can choose to redact
their widget when locked,
much like Notifications.
On watchOS,
the device stays unlocked
as long as the watch
is being worn.
When inactive, the watch
transitions into always-on,
with content in
a low-luminance presentation
and a lower update cadence.
By default, your content is not
redacted in low luminance,
which is the state
on the bottom left.
Like the Lock Screen,
your users can configure
their complication content
to be redacted
in this always-on state.
In this state, you'll need
to make sure your content
is prepared for both redaction
and low luminance.
Together, the platforms cover
each of the four states
shown here.
Consider all these possible
states and ensure
your complications and widgets
work well in all cases.
Let's talk about
how you can do that.
On the watch, your widget
needs to support
the always-on
display experience.
You can adapt your content
for always-on
with the \.isLuminanceReduced
environment value.
If you're coming from ClockKit,
note that you now can prepare
always-on content for every
timeline entry, not just one.
When in always-on,
your time-relative text
and progress views will change
to a reduced fidelity mode
to support the low update
cadence of always-on.
To support this mode, use the
environment value to remove
any time-sensitive content
and optimize your content
for the lower update frequency.
Now let's talk about redaction.
By default, the privacy mode
will show a redacted version
of the placeholder view
your TimelineProvider creates.
If you have some elements
that are sensitive
and others that don't need
to be redacted,
you can use the
.privacySensitive modifier
to mark only some of
the views to be redacted.
In this example, we've redacted
the heart rate in our widget
but left the image unredacted.
Now you're ready to make awesome
widgets for the Lock Screen
and WidgetKit complications.
For more on what's new
in SwiftUI,
check out the "Compose Custom
Layouts with SwiftUI" talk.
Thanks for watching.
♪