♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Nick.
And I'm Franck,
and we are SwiftUI engineers.
Today, we're going to
cover "What's new in SwiftUI."
SwiftUI is growing alongside
our operating systems,
each pushing the bounds
of the other.
We continue to be amazed
and delighted
by what you are making
with SwiftUI.
We take to heart all flavors of
feedback from the community.
That's why we're especially
excited to share
what we've focused
on this year.
With this year's APIs,
we've gone deeper.
We've made more custom
experiences possible.
We've introduced some amazing
new graphical techniques.
We've architected a new SwiftUI
app structure, and much more.
SwiftUI enabled us to build
designs and features
that reflect the future
of our platforms.
From redesigns of classic apps
to completely new features
to deep system integrations.
This comprehensive adoption
within Apple
further pushes evolution
of SwiftUI.
Many of these new designs
and features
are only possible because
of how SwiftUI has evolved
how we write apps at Apple.
Today we're celebrating
these APIs,
[NOISE MAKER BLOWS]
And we're also celebrating
SwiftUI's birthday,
[NOISE MAKER BLOWS]
Franck and I are
the lucky cochairs
of the party-planning committee.
Let me tell you
about the activities
we've got planned
for the party.
I'll introduce you
to a brand-new framework
called Swift Charts
that allows you to create
delightful data visualizations
across all of our platforms.
I'll show off SwiftUI's
data-driven,
strongly-typed model
for navigation
and new window techniques.
Franck will take you
through a suite of new controls
and deeper customizations
of existing controls.
Then he'll show you how
we've brought sharing elegantly
into the universe of SwiftUI
with the Transferable protocol.
Finally, I'll close with
whimsical new graphics APIs
and advanced
new layout APIs.
Let's get going
with Swift Charts.
Swift Charts
is a declarative framework
for building beautiful
state-driven charts.
The fundamental
design principles
that make SwiftUI great
and the process of plotting data
have been composed harmoniously
to create Swift Charts --
a world-class data-visualization
framework.
This is a bar chart plotting
the number of party tasks
Franck and I need to complete
before the party can start.
Swift Charts has built
a magnificent,
customizable chart from
only a few lines of code.
Like SwiftUI, Swift Charts
picks intelligent defaults.
Here, the framework chose
satisfyingly round numbers
for the y-axis values,
and provided a default color
for the bar marks.
If you know SwiftUI, you can
already read the declarative,
state-driven syntax
of Swift Charts.
Chart is just some View,
and you declare it just like
you do lists and tables --
by providing data and then
building the chart content
with that data.
For this chart,
I've chosen a BarMark,
but if I switch to a LineMark
and add a foreground style
to group by category,
I can see more to the story
as Swift Charts draws individual
lines for each category
and adds a legend
to the chart automatically.
It's fun to give these
charts a little personality.
I can add points to the line
with the symbol modifier
on the LineMark.
These modifiers are no different
from SwiftUI modifiers.
You can even use
SwiftUI views within a chart.
Like List,
the data argument to Chart
can instead be passed
to a ForEach.
This allows adding
more marks to the Chart builder,
like a RuleMark
to show our daily goal.
The spirit of SwiftUI
shines through again,
as Swift Charts handles
localization, Dark Mode,
and Dynamic Type automatically,
and of course, works across
all of our platforms.
If you want to see how
to make your own charts,
check out "Hello
Swift Charts."
If you're interested in advanced
plotting techniques,
follow it up with
the "Raise the bar" session.
Next up, let's talk about
navigation and windows.
SwiftUI already supports
the most common app
navigation patterns,
such as immersive
push-and-pop navigation stacks;
expansive,
detail-rich split views;
and powerful,
multi-window experiences.
This year,
SwiftUI has big updates
for all three of these patterns.
Let's start with stacks.
SwiftUI is introducing
a new container view,
simply called
NavigationStack,
for supporting
push-and-pop-style navigation.
A NavigationStack wraps
a root content view,
like this food inventory list
for our party-planning app.
As you'd expect, it works great
with existing APIs
like NavigationLink
and navigationTitle().
When we select a link,
SwiftUI pushes its detail view
on top of the stack.
In our app, each detail view
contains more links
for related food items
for quick browsing.
This approach might be
all you need.
But there is a new way
to present views
and have programmatic control
over that presented state.
If you need control
of a navigation stack's state,
adopt the new data-driven APIs.
The new navigationDestination()
modifier
lets us associate
navigation destinations
with specific data types.
And this year,
we taught NavigationLink
a new party trick:
instead of a destination view,
it can take a value
that represents a destination.
When tapping on a link, SwiftUI
will use its value's type
to find the right destination
and push it on the stack,
just like before.
Because we now use data
to drive our stack,
it's possible to represent
the current navigation path
as explicit state.
In this case, the navigation
path is simply an array
of all the food items
that we've visited.
With direct access
to this state,
it couldn't be easier
to add a button
for quickly jumping back
to the first selected item.
As views are pushed
onto the stack,
items are appended to
the selectedFoodItems array.
In the button's action,
we can just remove all the items
from the path
except for the first one.
And with a tap, we're right back
where we started.
Now let's talk about split views
for multicolumn navigation.
We're introducing
another new container
called NavigationSplitView
for multicolumn navigation.
NavigationSplitView can declare
two- and three-column layouts.
Party Planner uses
a simple two-column layout,
wrapping a sidebar list
of our party-planning tasks
and a detail view
that changes its content
with the selected task.
Split views work great with the
new value-based NavigationLinks
we saw earlier,
using the link's value
to drive
the list's selection.
NavigationSplitView will
automatically collapse
into a stack on smaller-size
classes or devices,
making it a great tool
for building adaptive,
multiplatform apps.
NavigationSplitView
and NavigationStack
are designed to work together
and can be directly composed
to build more complex
navigation structures.
We use this in the Party Planner
app to turn the detail column
into its own, self-contained
navigation stack,
which also shows off
the new support
for navigation stacks
on macOS.
Well, we've talked a lot
about food,
but I hear that my colleague
Curt is cooking up a storm
over in his talk, "The SwiftUI
cookbook for navigation."
Check it out to learn even
more about navigation stacks
and navigation split views.
But for now,
let's step outside the box
and talk about new scene APIs.
You're likely already familiar
with WindowGroup,
which is a great way to build
the main interface of your app,
and can generate
multiple windows
to allow different perspectives
into your app's data.
New this year,
we're adding window,
which -- you guessed it --
declares a single,
unique window for your app.
Here, I've added
a Party Budget window
that shows the total cost
of the party.
By default the window
is available and can be shown
by selecting its name
in the app's Window menu.
But we can make
that even easier by assigning
a Command-0 keyboard
shortcut to open the window.
To make sure I stay a
budget-conscious party planner,
I'll add a toolbar button
with an action
that also shows this window.
Using the environment action
openWindow,
I can now programmatically open
new SwiftUI-managed windows.
In fact, we've added
a whole suite
of new window customizations
this year,
including modifiers
for default size,
position, resizability,
and more.
I don't want the party budget
getting in the way,
so by default it appears
as a small corner window.
But if I adjust
its position or size,
SwiftUI will automatically
remember that
across app launches.
The new standalone
window scene is great
for little auxiliary windows
like this one on the Mac,
but Party Planner
is a multiplatform app,
and we need a better design
for smaller screens.
For example, on iOS we've chosen
to display our budget
within a resizable sheet
instead.
This is possible with the new
presentationDetents() modifier.
In this case, I configured
a resizable sheet
that sticks to two different
sizes: one at 250 points,
and another at a system-defined
medium height.
It is simple to iterate
between platforms this year
with multiplatform targets
in Xcode
powering up
your SwiftUI-based apps.
One target can be deployed
to multiple platforms.
Just pick your platform
from the usual pull-down menu
in Xcode's toolbar.
Watch "What's new in Xcode"
and follow it up
with "Use Xcode to develop
a multiplatform app"
to learn more.
For the final new scene type,
we can turn our attention
to the menu bar.
With macOS Ventura, you can
now build MenuBarExtras
entirely in SwiftUI!
These can be defined
alongside other scene types
in your application and will
always be shown in the menu bar
while your app is running.
Or, you can build an entire app
using just a MenuBarExtra!
These are such a fun way to
bring even the simplest of ideas
to life on macOS.
"Bring Multiple Windows
to your SwiftUI App"
has more detail
on how to take advantage
of all the new scene types
and features.
Now that we've got control
of windows,
I'll pass it over to Franck,
to put controls in windows.
Franck: Thanks, Nick!
This year, we have
a variety of enhancements
across all our APIs for building
interactive content.
We have a lot to cover,
so let's get this party started
with some fun enhancements
to forms.
macOS Ventura comes with a
brand-new System Settings app,
that features a streamlined
navigation structure,
built using the navigation
split view and stacks
that Nick just
walked us through.
It also sports a fresh
and modern interface style.
Settings interfaces
are control-heavy,
so this style was
specifically designed
to present forms
containing many controls
in a consistent and
well-organized fashion.
We've also adopted
this new design
within our Party Planner app.
Let's take a look.
Our Event Details view
also features
many different types of controls
grouped into sections,
serving a similar purpose
as a settings interface.
This makes it a great candidate
to adopt the new visual style
from System Settings.
You can enable this design
using the new grouped
formStyle on macOS.
And thanks to the flexibility
of SwiftUI's declarative APIs,
content and controls
within the form
will automatically adapt
to the new style.
For example, sections will
visually group their content
below their headers;
and controls will consistently
align their labels and values
to the leading
and trailing edges.
Some controls may adapt
their visual appearance as well,
such as how toggles display
as trailing mini switches
for consistent layout
and alignment.
And since the form
itself provides
a lot of visual structure,
other controls adapt
to this context
with a lighter-weight
visual appearance,
and reveal more prominent
control backings on rollover.
SwiftUI makes it easy to align
other types of content
to this new style, using the new
LabeledContent view,
which can be used
to build new controls
or even just display
some read-only information.
In this case,
we're displaying some text
for the location of the event,
and SwiftUI automatically
adjusts the styling
and allows selection
of that text.
But LabeledContent can
also wrap any kind of view,
like if we wanted
to use a custom view
for displaying
more entire addresses.
SwiftUI is now smarter about
applying default styling to text
in other cases too.
It will hierarchically format
multiple pieces of text
within a control's label
to form titles and subtitles.
This new form design
looks great on macOS,
but we can also share
a lot of this same code
with the iOS version of our app.
You'll notice some improved
designs on iOS as well,
like these pop-up menu
pickers with a visual style
inspired by macOS,
but with their interactions
and appearance optimized
to fit beautifully
within a touch-based interface.
Of course, the same code works
great on iPad's larger screen,
and together with the Mac,
you can see how SwiftUI's
declarative model helps you
share code when building
shared interfaces,
helping you bring the party
to every platform.
Of course, we're also
improving controls
beyond just form styles.
So let's take
a lightning-round tour
of some other new control
features we're using
in the Party Planner app.
Let's start with the New
Activity page in our iOS app.
Text fields can be configured
to expand vertically
using the new axis parameter,
growing their height
to fit the text
and, if specified, capping
their height to the line limit.
But the lineLimit modifier
now also supports
more advanced behaviors,
like reserving a minimum amount
of space and expanding
as more content is added,
and then scrolling once the
content exceeds the upper limit.
Below our text fields,
we also see an example
of the new
MultiDatePicker control,
supporting noncontiguous
date selection
to help us spread our party
activities throughout the week.
Now at this point, maybe you're
having some mixed feelings
about the party theme
for this talk.
The great news is you can
now express those feelings
in SwiftUI,
using mixed-state controls!
Here we have a group of toggles
that can be collapsed
into a single aggregate toggle.
The inner toggles
each take a single binding
whereas the aggregate Toggle
takes a collection
of all the bindings
displaying a mixed state
if their values don't all match.
Pickers work the same way.
This decoration theme picker
changes its value
to reflect the currently
selected decoration.
But if we select
multiple decorations,
it will show the themes
for all them
using a mixed-state indicator.
Now, let's switch back
to our iOS app.
We have a few
button-style toggles
for choosing the event hashtags.
We can help
differentiate each toggle
by simply adding
a bordered button style.
Button styles like this will
now apply to any control
that supports
a button-like appearance,
including toggles,
menus, and pickers.
Moving on to steppers,
you can now provide
a format for its value.
On macOS, a formatted stepper
will display its value
in an editable field.
And steppers are also now
available on watchOS.
Apple Watch sports
one of my favorite new features:
Accessibility Quick Actions,
an alternative way
to perform actions
by clenching your hand.
A Quick Action can be defined
just like any other UI action,
using a button, allowing us
to share the same code
for both visible buttons and
their equivalent Quick Actions.
All right, we just covered
a lot of different controls,
but of course, controls
are not the only sources
of interactivity.
So let's take a look
at what's new
with larger interactive
containers,
like tables and lists.
I am excited to share
that tables are now
supported on iPadOS.
As you would expect,
tables on iPadOS are defined
using the same Table API we
introduced last year for macOS,
making it easy to share code
between platforms.
Our Invitations table shows
three columns for the name,
city, and invitation status
of each person,
taking advantage
of the iPad's large display.
But this table will also render
appropriately
in compact size classes,
including on iPhone,
showing just the primary column
within the smaller screen space.
Let's switch contexts and
check out this table on macOS.
It's looking great!
But speaking on contexts, I'd
love to add some context menus
for performing common actions
within the table.
This is a job
for the new selection-based
contentMenu modifier.
The modifier takes
a selection type,
and will be enabled
within any compatible table
or list that supports selection.
Within the menu builder,
you are given a collection
of the current selection,
allowing you to build
advanced context menus
that can operate
on a single selected row,
multiple selected rows,
or even no row selected,
such as when clicking
on the empty area of the table.
Context menus reveal actions
directly within the table,
which is great for speed
and efficiency.
But I would also like to make
these actions more discoverable.
A great way to improve
discoverability
is by displaying common actions
as buttons in the toolbar,
and iPadOS has a new
and improved toolbar design
to help achieve
that extra level of polish.
iPad toolbars can now support
user customization
and reordering,
which your app can implement by
providing explicit identifiers
for each toolbar item,
the same API available on macOS.
These identifiers allow SwiftUI
to automatically save
and restore custom
toolbar configurations
across app launches.
Note that on iPadOS,
not all toolbar items
allow customization.
Customizable actions
are configured
using the new secondaryAction
toolbar item placement,
which shows up in the center
of the toolbar by default,
or in an overflow menu
in compact-size classes.
All right!
The word is spreading around
and it looks like
the number of attendees
is growing exponentially.
Let's help our table
manage the scale
by adding support for search.
SwiftUI already
supports basic search
with a searchable modifier.
And new this year, search fields
can support tokenized inputs
and suggestions to help build
more structured search queries.
To help with filtering results,
SwiftUI now supports
search scopes,
which appear in a scope bar
beneath the toolbar on macOS
and as a segmented control
within the navigation bar
on iOS.
We have only scratched
the surface
of what is possible with SwiftUI
on iPad this year.
Check out the "SwiftUI on iPad"
series and learn more.
Now that we have a bit more
control over the event details
and logistics,
let's share the news
and get people
even more excited.
Sharing content
with other people,
as well as sharing data
across applications
are essential parts
of many apps.
Taking advantage
of these features
makes your app even more
integrated into the workflows
of the people who use them.
This year we have
a few exciting areas
to make that even easier.
Let's start with PhotosPicker,
a new multiplatform
and privacy-preserving API
for picking photos and videos.
Since photos are an essential
part of any party,
I've added a feature
to the Party Planner app
that adds fun birthday effects
to photos that were taken.
The new PhotosPicker view can
be placed anywhere in your app,
and on activation, presents
the standard photos-picking UI
to select photos or videos
from the user's library.
PhotosPicker take a binding
to a selected item,
which provides access to
the actual photo and video data.
It also has additional
rich configuration options,
such as filtering
the type of content,
preferred photo encoding,
and more.
This is the most photogenic
cupcake I have ever seen.
But one cupcake
isn't enough.
Let's apply the special effect
as we move on.
Now that we have
our customized photo,
we're ready to share it
with the new ShareLink API.
Each platform has a standard
interface for allowing people
to share content from your apps.
With watchOS 9, you can now
also present the share sheet
from within your watch apps.
The new ShareLink view
enables presenting
that system share sheet
from within your app.
You can simply provide it
with the content to be shared
and a preview to use
in the share sheet,
and it automatically creates
a standard share icon button.
On tap, it presents
the standard share sheet
to send off the content.
Share links adapt to the
context they're applied to,
such as in context menus
and across platforms.
PhotosPicker, ShareLink,
and more all take advantage
of the new
Transferable protocol,
a Swift-first declarative way
to describe how types
are transferred
across applications.
Transferable types are used
to power SwiftUI features
like drag-and-drop, which
makes it easy to drop images
from other apps into
the Party Planner gallery.
This makes use of the new
dropDestination API,
which accepts a payload type,
in this case, just an image.
The completion block
provides a collection
of the received images together
with the drop location.
Many standard types,
such as string and image,
already conform to Transferable.
So it wasn't much work to get
the ball rolling in our app,
but you can easily
take things further
and implement Transferable
in your own custom types.
When it's time to do that,
your conformance declares
the representations
appropriate for your type,
such as using Codable support
and a custom content type.
To learn more
about Transferable,
other representations,
and advanced tips and tricks,
check out the
"Meet Transferable" talk.
While we were preparing
the cupcakes,
Nick was laying out
all the supplies.
Nick, how's it
going over there?
Nick: Almost done!
I'm arranging these party horns
in a completely custom layout,
but I'll need
a little more time.
Let's talk graphics first.
ShapeStyle has new APIs
to achieve rich
graphical effects this year.
We'll use these APIs to give
this guest card some party pop!
Color has a new
gradient property
that adds a subtle gradient
derived from the color.
These look great
with the system colors.
ShapeStyle also got
a new shadow modifier.
Adding it to the white
foreground style
adds a shadow to the text
and to the symbol.
And the detail of this shadow
is remarkable.
The drop shadow has applied
to every element
of the Calendar symbol.
With the whole world
of SF Symbols
and the new SwiftUI
ShapeStyle extensions,
you can make some
absolutely gorgeous icons.
Now, it's time to bring that
grid of SF Symbols to the party.
We'll iterate quickly on it
using SwiftUI Previews,
which has some fantastic
improvements this year.
Previews have always been
a convenient way
to see a view in multiple
configurations at the same time.
With Xcode 14, we're making
this easier than ever
with preview variants.
These let you develop your view
in multiple appearances,
type sizes, or orientations
at the same time
without writing
any configuration code.
We can use that
same gradient again,
or we can style it
as an elliptical gradient
to give these images
a soft glow.
and preview it in dark
and light appearances.
Previews now runs
in live mode by default.
It can't be a great
birthday party
without a little dancing,
so let's get these
SF Symbols dancing.
♪ Electronic dance music ♪
♪
Those jovial icons
demonstrate something profound.
SwiftUI has taken text and image
animations to the next level.
Let's watch that text animate
again in slow motion.
Text can now be beautifully
animated between weights,
styles, and even layouts.
And the best part:
this takes advantage
of the same animation APIs used
throughout the rest of SwiftUI.
Let's close by talking about
my absolute favorite part
of UI programming,
applied geometry --
or as we call it, Layout.
SwiftUI has added new ways
to lay out views.
Grid is a new container view
that arranges views
in a two-dimensional grid.
Grid will measure its subviews
up front to enable cells
that span multiple columns
and enable automatic alignments
across rows and columns.
In fact, you already
got a look at grid earlier.
Using Grid, GridRow, and
the gridCellColumns modifier,
you can build up
a grid piecemeal.
Of course, just like all
layouts in SwiftUI,
they're built for composition.
We introduced SwiftUI's layout
model with the first release,
providing a toolbox
of primitive layout types
to achieve some
of the most common layouts.
Most of the time,
you can get the job done
with these primitive layout
types, but sometimes,
sometimes, you want
that imperative layout code:
the size, the minX,
the frame.origin.x minus
frame.midX divided by 2 plus 3.
It's times like these
when you should reach
for the new Layout protocol.
With it, you have the full power
and flexibility we used
to implement SwiftUI's
stacks and grids
to build your own first-class
layout abstractions.
Using Layout, I built this
bespoke seating chart layout
for the guests
at our birthday party.
Should our party guests
sit in rows or pods?
With the power of Layout,
we don't have to choose.
Using the Layout protocol,
you can build
all kinds of efficient layouts,
tailored to the specific needs
of your view hierarchies.
To learn how to adopt Layout
and about other new,
great layout techniques,
check out the "Compose custom
layouts with SwiftUI" session.
I've prepared a taste of Layout
especially for you.
Using the new AnyLayout type,
I can switch
between the Grid layout
and a custom scattered
layout I've written.
As this session
draws to a close,
there's one surprise left:
You're invited!
♪
You are invited to celebrate
SwiftUI's birthday
and all of the new APIs
with us this week.
There is a lot of detail left to
explore in the APIs we covered,
and even more APIs that
we didn't have time to include.
Enjoy the party,
and enjoy WWDC 2022.
And we are going
to enjoy some cake.
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪