♪ ♪
Paul: Hello, and welcome to
Compose Custom Layouts with SwiftUI.
I'm Paul, and I work
on developer documentation.
SwiftUI provides
a rich set of building blocks
that you use to compose
your app's interface.
You can combine built-in views
that display elements like text, images,
and graphics to create
custom, composite views.
To arrange all these elements
in ever more sophisticated groupings
SwiftUI provides layout tools.
Containers like horizontal and
vertical stacks let you tell SwiftUI
where to put views
relative to one another,
while view modifiers give you
additional control
over things like spacing and alignment.
In this talk,
I'm going to introduce some new tools
that will make some common layouts
even easier to build,
and will make
more complicated layouts possible.
Along the way, I'll give you some tips
for working with layout in SwiftUI.
I'll start by showing you a new member
of the grid family
that's perfect for two-dimensional layouts
when you have a static set of views
to display.
Next I'll talk about how you can create
a custom view container type
that lets you interact directly
with the layout engine,
using the new layout protocol.
Then I'll talk about ViewThatFits,
a container type that automatically
selects from a collection of views
for the one that,
well, fits in the available space.
And finally, I'll show you how to add
seamless transitions
between layout types using AnyLayout.
To see all these new features in action,
let's take a look at an app
I've been working on.
In recent years,
there's been some debate
among some of my colleagues about
who makes the best furry companion.
I have my own opinion, but I was curious
to see if we could come to some consensus,
so I decided
to make an app to take a poll.
And I want to include folks
with fur allergies, too,
so I'm throwing in one extra option.
Now, I like to do most of
my interface design in SwiftUI,
because it's so easy to prototype
using previews,
but as a starting point, I drew
a quick sketch of what I'm aiming for.
I expect the voting to go on
over a period of time,
so I want a leaderboard in
the middle showing the current standings.
I'll put buttons for voting at the bottom.
And at the top, I'll display some images
of what folks are voting for.
Okay, the first thing I want to do
is to build the leaderboard.
So let's take a closer look at that.
The leaderboard is a two-dimensional grid
of elements with rows for each contender,
and columns that show names,
percentages, and a vote count.
I have a couple of specific things
I want to achieve here.
First, I want the two text columns
to be only as wide as they need to be
to accommodate the widest cell
in each case
because I want the progress views
that represent percentages
to get as much space as they can.
And this needs to be true
no matter how big the counts get
for my friends that speak other languages
or for anyone who uses
different text sizes on their devices.
Second, I want the names
to be leading edge aligned,
but the amounts to be
trailing edge aligned.
Now, SwiftUI already has lazy grids,
which are great for scrollable content.
These containers are very efficient
when you have a lot of views,
because they only load views
that are visible, or about to be visible.
On the other hand,
that means the container
can't automatically size
its cells in both dimensions.
For example, the LazyHGrid can figure out
how wide to make each column,
because it can measure all the views
in a column before drawing them.
But it can't measure every view in a row
to figure out the row's height.
To make this work,
the lazy grids need you
to provide information about one
of their dimensions at initialization time.
For a closer look at lazy grids and other
existing SwiftUI layout container types,
see the Stacks, grids,
and outlines talk from 2020.
But in my case, I don't need scrolling,
and I'd like to let SwiftUI
figure out both the height
and the width for each cell.
For this kind of layout,
SwiftUI now offers a Grid view.
Unlike the lazy grid,
the grid loads all of its views at once,
so it can automatically size
and align its cells
across both its columns and rows.
Let's take a look at the code for this.
Here's a basic version
of my leaderboard written as a Grid.
This particular grid view
contains three GridRow instances.
Within a row,
each view corresponds to a column.
So in this example,
the first text view in each row
corresponds to the first column,
the progress view is in the second column,
and the last text view
is the third column.
Notice that the grid allocates
as much space to each row and column
as it needs to hold its largest view.
So the first text column is wide enough
for the longest name, but no wider.
Flexible views like the progress indicator
take as much space as the grid offers,
which in this case
is whatever is left over
after allocating space
for the text columns.
I want to adjust this a bit, but first,
let me create a basic data model
to give me somewhere
to store vote counts.
I'll need more logic to manage
and share the data across the network,
but while I'm prototyping the interface,
I just need a simple structure like this.
I'll include Identifiable conformance,
because that'll make it easier
to use this type in a ForEach,
and Equatable conformance
to make it possible to animate changes.
And I'll create a set of example data
to use in my previews while I prototype.
Going back to my grid,
I can create a state variable
and initialize it with my example data.
And using that data,
I can now create rows with a ForEach.
Notice that the rendered output
hasn't changed
because it's still displaying
the same data.
That's already pretty close,
but I need to fix the cell alignment.
Right now,
all the cells are center aligned,
which is the default for a grid,
but if you remember,
I want the names
to be leading edge aligned,
and the values
to be trailing edge aligned.
To do that, I'll initialize the grid
with leading edge alignment.
The value I use here
applies to all the cells in the grid.
That works fine for my first two columns,
but what about the last?
To affect the alignment
of a single column,
I can apply the gridColumnAlignment view
modifier to any one cell in that column.
So I'll do that with the text view
in the last column.
Okay, it's getting there,
but now that I'm looking at it,
I feel like it would be better
with a divider between each row.
If I just add a new row
to the ForEach with a divider,
this isn't exactly what I want,
but notice that this shows
a couple of interesting things.
First, because
the divider is a flexible view,
it's causing the first column
to take more space.
Basically, the grid is now giving
the last column what it needs,
and dividing the remaining space
between the first two columns.
Second, for a grid row that doesn't
have as many views as other grid rows,
the missing views just create empty cells
in the later columns.
But what I really want is to have the
divider span all the columns of the grid,
and SwiftUI has a new view modifier
that lets me do that.
By adding the gridCellColumns
modifier to a view,
I can tell a single view to span
some number of columns;
in this case, all three.
And actually, for the case where
the view should span the entire grid,
I can simplify this by just writing
the view by itself, outside of a grid row.
Okay, my leaderboard is in
pretty good shape
so let me take a look at the buttons
used for voting next.
At first glance,
there's nothing too fancy here.
However,
I do have one special requirement.
On the one hand,
I don't want to bias my participants
with smaller buttons for certain choices.
But I also don't want the buttons
to grow as large as their container,
which could be very large on iPad or Mac.
Instead, the buttons should all have
widths equal to the widest button text.
So what happens
if I try to build this with an Hstack?
What I find is that each button
sizes itself to fit its text label,
and the HStack
packs these together horizontally.
This default stack behavior is exactly
what you want in a lot of cases,
but it doesn't quite meet
my spec for this project.
For a refresher
on layout fundamentals in SwiftUI,
see the Building custom views
with SwiftUI talk from 2019.
Using concepts from that talk,
let's take a look at this view hierarchy
to see what I can change
to get the behavior I want.
First, the stack's container
proposes a size to the stack.
Based on this, the stack proposes a size
to its three buttons,
and then each button passes that size
through to its text label.
The text views calculate the size
they actually want,
which depends on the string they contain
and report this to the button.
The button passes the information
back through.
The stack sizes itself
with this information,
places the buttons in its space, and then
reports its own size to its container.
Okay, so if the buttons
take the size of their text,
what if I wrap each text view in
a flexible frame and allow it to grow?
The text hasn't changed,
but the button sees a flexible subview,
which takes as much space
as the HStack offers.
The stack then distributes its space
equally among the views that it contains.
So the buttons are all the same size now,
which is great,
but their actual size depends
on the stack's container.
The stack will expand to fill
whatever space the container offers,
and that's not what I want.
What I really want is a custom stack type
that asks for the ideal size
of each button,
finds the widest, and then offers
that amount of space to each one.
Fortunately, SwiftUI has a new tool
that lets me do just that.
Using the Layout protocol,
I can define a custom layout container
that participates directly
in the layout process
with behavior
that's tailored to my use case.
Let's see how this works.
Looking at the HStack again,
let me change it to an EqualWidthHStack
a type that I'm going to define
to solve my specific problem.
This type is going to allocate width
to the buttons equally,
in an amount that's as wide
as the widest button's ideal width.
I'll keep the flexible frames
so that buttons with narrower text
can expand to fill the space
that the stack offers.
But the buttons will still have
an ideal size that I can measure,
which is the width of their text.
So let's see how I can implement
MyEqualWidthHStack.
I start by creating a type
that conforms to the Layout protocol.
For a basic layout,
all I need are the two required methods.
Let's add stubs for those.
The first method is sizeThatFits,
where I'll calculate and report
how large my layout container is.
I get a proposed view size input,
which is a size proposal from
my layout's own container view.
And I can propose sizes to my layout's
subviews using the Subviews parameter.
Notice that I can't access
the subviews directly.
Instead, the subviews input
is a collection of proxies
that let me interact in specific ways
with the subviews,
like proposing a size.
Each proxy returns a concrete size
based on the proposal that I’ve made.
I'll collect all those responses
and use them to do some calculations
and then return a concrete size for
the EqualWidthHStack to its container.
The second method that I have to
implement is placeSubviews.
I'll use this to tell my layout's subviews
where to appear.
This method takes the same size proposal
and subviews inputs,
and it also takes a bounds input
that represents the region
that I need to place my subviews into.
Bounds is a rectangle
that has the size that I asked for
in my sizeThatFits implementation.
Remember,
views pick their own size in SwiftUI,
so my layout container
will get the size that it asks for.
The origin of the region
is at the top left,
with positive X to the right,
and positive Y down.
You can assume this for all
your placement calculations,
even in right to left
language environments,
because the framework automatically flips
the x position of each view
when laying out views in that direction.
However, don't assume that the rectangle's
origin has the value (0,0).
Among other things,
allowing for a non-zero origin
enables layout composition,
where the placeSubviews method
of one layout
calls into the same method of another.
To make it a little easier to work with,
the rectangle provides properties
for accessing important parts
of the region,
like the minimum,
center,
and maximum points in each dimension.
Now, before I move on,
notice one other parameter
that these methods both have:
a bidirectional cache that I could use
to share the results of intermediate
calculations across method calls.
For many simple layouts,
you won't need this,
and I'm just going to
ignore the cache for now.
However, if profiling your app with
Instruments shows that you need to improve
the efficiency of your layout code,
you can look into adding one.
Check out the documentation
for more information about that.
Okay, let's implement sizeThatFits.
Remember, I want to return
a size for my container
that fits all of the buttons arranged
horizontally, all at the same width.
So first,
I'll ask each button for its size,
which I do by proposing a size
and seeing what comes back.
To measure the flexibility of a subview,
I can make multiple measurements
using special proposals for minimum,
maximum, and ideal sizes,
or I can propose a specific size.
In this case, I use the unspecified
size proposal to ask for the ideal size.
Then I'll find the largest value
in each dimension
for all the sizes that I get back.
In this case,
the goldfish button sets the width,
and the heights are all the same.
Now let me refactor that into a method,
because I'll need it again
when I place my subviews.
Next, I need to account
for the spacing between views.
I could just use a constant spacing,
like 10 points,
but the layout protocol lets me do better.
In SwiftUI, all views have spacing
preferences that indicate
the amount of space the view prefers
to have between itself and the next view.
These preferences are stored
in a ViewSpacing instance
that's available to layout containers.
The view might prefer different values
on different edges,
and even different values for
different kinds of adjacent views.
For example,
a view might want more or less space
between itself and a text view
than it wants between itself and an image.
And the values can vary
by platform as well.
You can ignore these preferences
if it makes sense for your layout,
which is essentially what's happening
when you initialize a built-in stack
with a custom spacing,
but respecting these preferences
in your own layouts
is a good way to get results
that automatically follow
Apple's interface guidelines,
and as a result,
match the look of the rest of the system.
Now, every view
has preferences on all edges,
and when I bring two views together,
the preferences on a common edge
might not match.
To resolve this,
a built-in layout container
uses the larger of the two preferences.
And I can do the same thing
in my own layout.
The subview proxies give me a way
to ask for each button's preferred spacing
to some other button along a given axis.
So let me create an array of values by
scanning through the subviews
and calling the distance method
on each proxy's spacing instance
to get the spacing
to the next view's spacing instance
along the horizontal axis.
This call takes into account
the preferences
of both views on their common edge.
The first element in this array
tells me how much space
the cat button wants horizontally
to the goldfish button,
and the next tells me how much the
goldfish button wants to the dog button.
I'll force the last element in the array
to be zero
because there aren't any more buttons
to compare against.
Okay, let me refactor that
into a method for later too.
Now I can combine the spacing values
to find the total spacing
and use that that with the width
and height measurements
to return a size value.
This is the size that my layout needs,
given the ideal sizes of its subviews
and each subview's preferred spacing.
The other method that I need
to implement is placeSubviews.
As I mentioned before,
I get both the bounds of the container,
and the collection of subview proxies
that I can use to direct the buttons.
First, I calculate maxSize
and the spacing array
just like I did in sizeThatFits method,
because I'll need those values here too.
Then I'll create a size proposal
that I can use for each of my subviews,
this time based on the size
that I want them to have,
rather than their ideal size.
I only need one proposal, because I want
all the buttons to the be the same size.
And I'll find a starting position
in the horizontal dimension
for my first subview, calculated as
the leading edge of my bounds,
plus half the width of a button.
Notice I'm not relying
on the origin to be zero,
but instead starting
with the minX value instead.
Finally, I can go through
each of the subview proxies
and call its place method with a point,
a statement of what that point represents
in terms of the button,
and the size proposal.
Each time through the loop,
I update the horizontal position
by the width of a view,
plus the spacing for the next view pair,
to get ready for the next iteration.
And that's it.
Now let's see what happens
when I use this new view layout type.
And there it is.
I instantiate my own
custom layout container
just like I would a built-in HStack,
and the buttons are arranged horizontally,
all at the same width.
Now, I want to pause here for a moment
and talk about how the Layout protocol
solves a problem
that you might have tried to use
geometry reader for in the past.
Geometry reader is, after all,
a tool for measuring view sizes.
However,
it's not the best choice in this case.
And that's because a geometry reader
is designed to measure its container view,
and report the that size to its subview.
The subview then uses the information
to draw its own content.
Notice that for the intended use
of a geometry reader,
the information flows downward.
The measurement that the reader makes
has no effect
on the layout of its own container.
This is great for things like drawing
a path that scales with its container.
The geometry reader tells the path logic
how much space it has to work with,
and the path logic inside the subview
adjusts accordingly.
If the container changes size,
so does the path,
because the geometry reader
passes along the new size.
However, for my buttons,
and I'll just focus on one here
to make it easier to see,
I need to measure the text view,
and then use that to decide how to set
a frame that's the text view's container.
So I could add a geometry reader
in an overlay to the text view–
remember, it measures its container–
and then somehow send the measurement data
back up to the frame,
outside of the normal flow.
But notice that if I do this,
I'm bypassing the layout engine,
which might result in a loop.
The reader measures the layout
and changes the frame,
which might change the layout, which could
require another measurement, and so on.
Now it is possible to make this work,
but if I'm not careful,
I could end up crashing my app.
As a result,
this strategy isn't recommended.
Fortunately, the layout protocol gives you
a better way to solve this problem,
by letting you work
within the layout engine.
Okay, let's look at the buttons again.
There's something else I want to do here.
First, to make this
a little easier to read,
I'll refactor the buttons
into their own subview.
Now, I happen to know that one
of my colleagues uses larger type
on their device.
My app automatically supports Dynamic Type
because I've used default fonts,
so I should mostly get
the right behavior for free.
Let's see what happens
if I increase the type size.
Uh-oh, the buttons don't fit anymore.
Remember that my custom stack
doesn't constrain the button widths,
but just lets them have their ideal size,
which in this case
exceeds the width of the display.
So what can I do?
Well, I could modify the layout
to do something more complicated
when the views don't fit,
taking into account the size proposal
from the layout's container.
But for this case,
I can use the new ViewThatFits container
to do most of the work for me.
This new type picks the first view
that fits in the available space
from a list of views that I give it.
By wrapping my custom stack
in a ViewThatFits structure,
and then adding a vertical stack version
of the same content,
I can let SwiftUI figure out when the
buttons need to be arranged differently.
Of course, the built-in VStack
doesn't have the equal width property
that my custom horizontal stack does,
so I've gone ahead and implemented a
vertical version of the custom stack too.
It's very similar to the one
I already described,
except that it places equal width items
along the vertical axis
instead of the horizontal axis.
And of course, when I remove
the dynamic type size override,
it goes back to the horizontal layout.
Now, there's one last piece of the app
I need to build,
and that's the images at the top.
I could do something simple, like
just show a group of profile pictures,
but I thought I'd have a little fun
with it.
So I made another custom layout type
that draws views in a circular arrangement
and then rotates the arrangement
according to rankings.
So this configuration shows
goldfish in first place,
and the other two tied for second.
And then if dog pulls ahead of cat,
I can rotate a bit to show that.
Or I can show
a slightly more realistic result,
all by rotating a radial layout.
Creating this layout is actually quite
straightforward with the layout protocol.
Like before, I just need two methods.
For size that fits, I want my view
to fill the available space,
so I'll return whatever size
the container view proposes.
I'll convert the proposal
into a concrete size
using the replacing-unspecified-dimensions
method.
That method automatically handles
nil values that could be present
if the container asks for an ideal size.
Then inside place subviews method,
I'll offset each subview from the middle
by some radius that's based
on the size of the layout region,
and apply a rotation that depends
on the index of the view.
As a baseline,
this places the views at 0, 1,
and two-thirds of the way around a circle.
To reflect the current rankings,
I'll also apply an offset
that affects all the views equally.
But where do I get the rankings?
Remember, my layout can only access
the subview proxies,
and not the views,
let alone my data model.
Well, it turns out that the layout
protocol has another trick up its sleeve.
It lets you store values on each subview,
and read the values from inside
the layout protocol methods.
Let's see how I can use that
to communicate the rank information.
First, I declare a new type that conforms
to the LayoutValueKey protocol,
and give it a default value.
In addition to providing a value for
a view when you don't explicitly set one,
the default value establishes
the associated value's type,
which is an integer in this case.
Then, I create a convenience method
on View to set the value
using the layoutValue view modifier.
Now in my view hierarchy,
I can apply my convenience rank modifier
to the views in my layout.
Here, I calculate the rank of each pet
and add it to the pet's corresponding
avatar view inside my radial layout.
Finally, back in my place subviews method,
I can add some code to read the values
from each subview
by using the layout value key as an index.
And I can use the ranks
to calculate an offset.
I won't go through that logic here,
but it basically produces
an appropriate angle
for any possible set of rankings.
Well, all except one.
What happens if there's a three-way tie?
There's no way to rotate
the layout to get all the views in a line,
so I'd have to substitute completely
different layout logic for that case.
However, there is already
a layout type that does this,
and that's the built-in HStack.
So what I'd really like
is to transition to an HStack
when I detect a three-way tie.
And it turns out that
there's a new tool for that, too.
The AnyLayout type lets you
apply different layouts
to a single view hierarchy,
so that you maintain the identity
of the views as you transition
from one layout type to another.
So here I have the radial layout
that we saw before,
and all I have to do is replace that
with a new layout type
that depends on whether
there's a three-way tie.
Because the isThreeWayTie property
is derived from state,
SwiftUI notices when it changes
and recognizes
that it needs to redraw this view.
But because the structural identity
of the view hierarchy
always remains the same,
SwiftUI sees this as a view that changes,
rather than as a new view.
As a result,
with only one more line,
I can create smooth transitions
between layout types.
And in fact,
by adding the animation view modifier,
I also get animations between all
the different states of the radial layout,
because the configuration of the radial
layout depends on the same data.
And here's what
all that looks like in action.
As I tap on different buttons
to change the vote counts,
you can see how the avatars move around
smoothly to reflect the current standings.
So those are some of the new tools
that SwiftUI has
for composing your app's view layouts.
You can use the Grid type
to build highly customizable,
two-dimensional layouts
of static information.
You can use the Layout protocol
to define your own general purpose,
reusable layouts, or layouts that are
highly targeted to a particular use case.
You can use ViewThatFits when you want
to let SwiftUI pick from a group of views
to best fit in the available space.
And you can seamlessly transition
between layout types using AnyLayout.
Thanks for joining me today,
and I hope you have as much fun
playing with these new layout tools
as I have.