♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello.
My name is Ashwath
and I am an engineer
with the Education team.
Today I am excited
to talk to you
about Sign in with Apple
at Work & School.
In this presentation,
I will be covering
the key features that we are
introducing this fall.
I will first walk you through
what Sign in with Apple at Work
& School is and how it works.
Then I will talk
about the Roster API
and specifics about
how you can make use of it.
And finally, I will be talking
about access management,
where I discuss how IT admins
can manage access
to Sign in with Apple
at Work & School
and the Roster API
on behalf of their organization.
Let me begin
by covering two concepts
you may be familiar with
but are important to review
for this session.
The first is Sign in with Apple.
Sign in with Apple
is a fast and easy way
for users to sign in to apps
with their Apple ID.
Users are able to create
an account within your app
with a simple tap.
The second concept
is Managed Apple IDs.
Like Apple IDs,
Managed Apple IDs
are used to personalize
a device.
They're also used to access
Apple apps and services.
Unlike Apple IDs,
Managed Apple IDs
are owned by an organization
and managed through
Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager.
With those definitions in mind,
I am excited to share
that Sign in with Apple
has now been extended
to support Managed Apple IDs.
Now you can get the benefits
of a fast and easy
sign-in experience
of Sign in with Apple,
but with the management
capabilities
of Managed Apple IDs.
To showcase the user experience
of Sign in with Apple
at Work & School,
let us take a look
at an example.
Here is the login screen
for Slack.
To use Sign in with Apple,
a user can just tap
Continue with Apple.
When using an Apple ID,
they will then see
this welcome screen
for Sign in with Apple.
On the other hand, if they are
using a Managed Apple ID,
they will see
the welcome screen
for Sign in with Apple
at Work & School.
You will notice a difference
in the welcome screen.
What do we mean when we say
we make it easy for apps
to provide access control?
Let's take a look at an example.
When using their personal
Apple ID
with Sign in with Apple,
the user sees
the account creation screen
where they may
edit their name
and choose whether to share
or hide their email.
But in an organizational
context,
it is important for the app
to understand who is logging in
and what level of access
to provide them.
In the example
shown on this screen,
the user is signing in
to Slack at work.
In order to know
which Slack channels
this employee should be
allowed to join,
Slack needs to know
which user is signing in.
So this is an example of Slack
providing access control
using the name and email
shared with their app
when using Sign in with Apple
at Work & School.
So this is what the user sees,
but what does this mean for you?
It means when a user
uses Sign in with Apple
at Work & School,
the name and email fields
will always be accessible.
If you are a developer
working on a client-side app,
here's a look
at some example code
showing the authorization
controller.
On a successful authorization,
the highlighted statements
indicate the full name and email
received by your app.
This assumes that
the request for authorization
included the scopes
for the full name and email.
If you are a developer
supporting Sign in with Apple
on the web,
here's a look
at some example code
that uses the signIn method to
start the authorization process.
Upon successful authorization,
the server returns the response
to the data object.
That data object
looks like this.
The highlighted fields
contain the email
and full name
of the user signing in.
It is important to note
a few points here.
In this release, Sign in
with Apple at Work & School
uses the primary
Managed Apple ID
that is signed in on the device.
Even though the example screens
that we showed you
were for the login flow
on the device,
the web flow is supported
as well.
Some accounts may not have
email addresses provided.
For example, schools may not
assign email addresses
to younger students.
Let's see what the account
creation screen looks like
in this scenario where
an email address is not present.
This user, Fatima Silva,
does not have an email address,
so only their full name
is present
on the account creation screen.
If you have already implemented
Sign in with Apple,
there is no work
needed from your end
to add support
for Managed Apple IDs.
If you haven't implemented
support yet,
I would highly suggest
taking a look
at the "Get the most out
of Sign in with Apple" session
from WWDC2020
and the "Enhance your Sign in
with Apple experience" session
from this year.
That was Sign in with Apple
at Work & School,
which brings the fast and easy
sign-in experience
of Sign in with Apple
to Managed Apple IDs.
Now let's dive into
the Roster API.
But before jumping into
any specifics,
let's consider
the following scenario.
You're a developer
in the education space.
Your app is being used
by school districts.
You have implemented support for
Sign in with Apple in your app.
That's great!
Students, teachers, and staff
can use their Managed Apple IDs
to log in to your app.
In this scenario,
your app allows teachers
to share assignments
and announcements
with their students.
To support this,
IT administrators
need to enter students,
teachers, and classes
into your app prior to the start
of the school year.
For a school with hundreds
or thousands of students,
creating these records by hand
would quickly become
a time-consuming
and tedious process.
We've created the Roster API
to address this problem.
The Roster API provides
programmatic access
to resources
like users and classes
in Apple School Manager.
This allows an IT admin
to automate the process
of importing this information
to your app.
These resources are defined
in the form of REST endpoints.
This data can be
accessed by your app
after the IT admin
has granted permission
through a successful OAuth 2.0
authorization.
The Administrator
and Site Manager accounts
in Apple School Manager
can manage which apps
are able to access the data.
As part of this release,
we have created
a standardized way
for apps to request access
to organizational data.
We call this
Organizational Data Sharing.
We wanted to follow
industry standards
when it comes
to UI design patterns
and choice of technology
so developer adoption is easy.
So we created an authorization
flow using OAuth 2.0,
which includes using scopes
and asking the IT admin
to consent to sharing
their organizational data.
Here is what it looks like.
The consent screen provides
information on which app
is requesting access
to the organization's data
and what data the app
is requesting access to.
Looking more closely,
the consent screen
contains information
on the requestor --
which represents the app
requesting access to the data
made available by
Apple School Manager;
in this case, the requesting app
is Quizzler --
and the scopes,
which represent the data
that the app
will have access to.
In this case,
once the IT admin consents,
Quizzler will be able to access
all user and class information
for this organization.
What does your implementation
journey look like?
The first step is to register
in the developer portal,
which involves
requesting scopes.
The next step is to request
consent from the IT admin
to share the data with your app
through the OAuth 2.0
authorization flow.
Finally, your app queries
the Roster API endpoints
to fetch the data.
Let us take a look
at each of these steps.
To request scopes,
visit the Developer portal.
Under the Certificates,
Identifiers & Profiles page,
click on Configure
under Account & Organizational
Data Sharing.
In the next step, click on
"Set up a configuration."
Choose the primary app ID
from the drop-down
and hit Continue.
In the additional configuration
details page,
under Organizational Data
Sharing Scopes,
choose the scopes desired.
Right now, we offer two:
user access and class access.
Ensure return URLs
are configured for your app.
This step is important
as the return URLs will be used
in the OAuth 2.0
authorization flow.
Hit Continue.
Finally, confirm
your configuration.
Now we're ready
for the next step.
The second step
in the implementation journey
is getting the access token
through the OAuth 2.0
authorization flow.
Let us look at this in detail.
The IT admin
first logs in to your app.
The IT admin then
interacts with your app
to initiate
the authorization flow --
for example,
by clicking a button
named "Connect to Apple
School Manager."
This starts a sequence of events
following the OAuth 2.0
standard.
The first step is
to execute a GET API call
to the authorize endpoint.
Let us take a look
at the details of this request.
The request takes in
a few query parameters:
the client_id,
the redirect_uri,
the state, response_type,
and scopes.
The response will be a redirect
to the Apple OAuth
consent screen
to request access
from the IT admin.
In this diagram,
we assume that the IT admin
has authenticated
with their Managed Apple ID.
If they have not,
they would be prompted
to authenticate first.
The IT admin is presented
with the consent screen
to confirm that they
would like to share
their organizational data
with your app.
This is the same consent screen
that we saw earlier.
As a reminder,
it looks like this.
Once they click Allow,
your app is provided
with an authorization code
at your return URL
that you registered
in the developer portal.
The final step involves a POST
request to the token endpoint
to retrieve your app's
access token.
Let us see what this request
looks like.
The request body is composed
of standard OAuth parameters
including the authorization code
received on your return URL.
The response would have
the access token,
its expiration,
and the refresh token
that is used to create a new
access token when it expires.
Let us take a look
at the request details
to generate a new access token
using a refresh token.
The request body is composed of
the standard OAuth parameters,
including the refresh token,
and the response would have
the access token
and its expiration.
After successfully completing
the OAuth 2.0
authorization flow,
your app now has
the access token,
which can be used to fetch
user and class information
from the Roster API.
As part of our current release,
we are introducing
five endpoints
that the apps can query.
These include
fetching a list of classes,
a list of users,
a specific class,
a specific user,
users in a class.
Let's walk through
a simple example flow
to demonstrate how you can
fetch users and classes.
Your app server
can first retrieve
the list of students,
teachers, and staff
by querying the users endpoint.
Let us take a look at the
request and response in detail.
The users endpoint takes in
three query parameters.
The pageToken and limit
are pagination parameters,
and an optional role parameter
lets you query for students,
instructors, or staff.
The request requires
the authorization header
with the access token
generated from
the authorization flow.
The response is a JSON payload
that includes a "users" key,
which has the list of users;
the "nextPageToken" key
that is used to fetch
the next set of records,
and a "moreToFollow"
Boolean key that indicates
if there are any more records
to query.
Let's take a look
at an example request.
The API call here is retrieving
a list of students
with a maximum of 10 students
in the response.
This is the first API request,
so the pageToken query
parameter is not specified.
The response has
standard user information
such as givenName,
familyName, etcetera,
but I would like
to draw your attention
to the stable unique identifier
for the user.
This is the same identifier
your app receives
when the user authenticates
with Sign in with Apple.
The email address of the user
and their roles in the
organization are also included.
The nextPageToken
needs to be used
in the subsequent API request
as a query parameter
to fetch the next
set of students,
since the moreToFollow key
is set to true.
After querying
the users endpoint,
your app server can now query
the classes endpoint,
which gives you
the list of classes
for that particular
school district
and the relationship between
the class and the students
and teachers associated
with that class.
Let us take a look at the
request and response in detail.
As part of
the get classes request,
the request takes in
two query parameters:
the pageToken
and the limit parameter,
both of which we saw before.
The headers are the same
as when querying users.
The response is a JSON payload
in which the "classes" key
holds the list of classes.
Let us take a look
at an example request.
This request retrieves
a list of classes
with a maximum of 200
to be included in the response.
The API request also has
the pageToken parameter,
which means it is in the middle
of fetching all classes.
The response has
standard class information
such as the name,
the class identifier, etcetera,
but I would like
to draw your attention
to the list of instructor IDs
and student IDs
that belong to the class.
That was the Roster API.
With these endpoints,
your app can now
programmatically query
users and classes
from Apple School Manager.
Finally, I would like to talk
to you about access management.
It is vital to provide
management capabilities
to organizations using
Organizational Data Sharing
and Sign in with Apple
at Work & School.
Let me explain what this means
in more detail.
When using Sign in with Apple,
users manage their own account
and it's solely up to them
to decide which apps
they choose to sign in to.
But when using Sign in
with Apple at Work & School,
the IT admin at the organization
centrally manages access
on behalf of all the users
at that organization.
This is because the IT admin
is responsible for ensuring
the safety and security
of the organization's data.
So, they must be empowered
to manage which apps
users are allowed to use Sign in
with Apple at Work & School,
and which apps are allowed to
use Organizational Data Sharing.
These access management
capabilities can be configured
in Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager.
For Sign in with Apple
at Work & School,
we offer two modes.
The first mode
is "Allow all apps."
Let us see what this mode
looks like.
Here, the IT admin is logged in
to Apple Business Manager.
On selecting Access Management
from the sidebar
and choosing Sign in with Apple,
they are presented
with the two modes.
The "Allow all apps" mode lets
all users of the organization
log in to all apps that support
Sign in with Apple.
The second mode
is "Allow only certain apps."
Let us see what this mode
looks like.
The "Allow only certain apps"
mode lets the IT admin
search for apps that support
Sign in with Apple
to add to the list.
Users will only be able
to use Sign in with Apple
with the apps that have been
added to the list.
If a user tries to log in to
an app that is not on the list,
they will see
an error message.
It is important to note
that this functionality
is the same
for Apple School Manager,
Apple Business Manager,
and Business Essentials
customers.
Similar to Sign in with Apple
at Work & School,
Organizational Data Sharing
also has the same two modes.
Let's take a look.
The "Allow only certain apps"
mode lets the IT admin
search for supported apps
to add to the list.
It is these apps that can access
user and class information
using the Roster API.
In addition
to the consent screen,
this is a second layer
of control for the IT admin
to manage which apps
can access organizational data.
With the release of Sign in
with Apple at Work & School,
now users in any environment
can use an Apple ID
or a Managed Apple ID
to log in to your app.
If you haven't already
implemented Sign in with Apple,
I encourage you to do so.
I would also highly encourage
you to adopt the Roster API
if you are
in the education space.
Implementing support
for Roster API
will provide a seamless
onboarding experience
for IT administrators, staff,
teachers, and students.
As always,
we love hearing from you.
So please submit
any feedback you may have.
If you'd like to learn more,
I would highly suggest
the "Get the most out of Sign in
with Apple" session from 2020
and the "Enhance your Sign in
with Apple experience" session
this year.
Thank you so much for watching
and we hope you enjoy
this year's WWDC.
♪