♪ ♪
Dhruva: Welcome to WWDC 2022.
My name is Dhruva,
and I am a GPUSW Engineer.
Today, Matteo and I will explore
all the new features and enhancements
introduced for machine learning
this year in Metal.
Machine learning training is the most
computationally intensive process
of the ML pipeline.
Due to their parallel nature,
GPUs excel at ML workloads.
The Metal machine learning APIs
are exposed through a framework
called Metal Performance Shaders,
or MPS.
MPS is a collection
of high performance GPU primitives
for various fields like Image Processing,
Linear Algebra,
Ray Tracing, and machine learning.
These Metal kernels are optimized
to provide the best performance
on all of our platforms.
For example the MPSImageCanny filter
returns an edge-map for an input-image.
This is a common operation
in image segmentation applications.
This year,
the Canny filter is able to process
4K, high-resolution images
up to eight times faster.
MPS Graph,
is a general purpose compute graph
for the GPU which sits on top
of the MPS framework
and extends support
to multidimensional tensors.
I recommend watching the previous session
to get more details
on how to use MPS Graph.
High level ML frameworks
like CoreML and Tensorflow
sit on top of MPS Graph.
You can accelerate your TensorFlow
networks on the GPU
with the TensorFlow Metal plug-in.
For more on how to make the most
of TensorFlow,
check out last year's session.
Matteo and I have three topics to cover
in this session.
First, I'll introduce the newest ML
framework coming to Apple GPUs,
PyTorch.
Next, I'll dive into the enhancements
made to TensorFlow over this year.
Finally, Matteo will talk about what's new
in the MPS Graph framework.
We are really excited that you will now be
able to accelerate your PyTorch networks
on your Mac GPUs.
PyTorch, is a popular open source
machine learning framework.
The number one most requested feature,
in the PyTorch community
was support for GPU acceleration
on Apple silicon.
We are bringing the power of Metal
to PyTorch
by introducing a new MPS backend
to the PyTorch ecosystem.
This backend will be part
of the official PyTorch 1.12 release.
The MPS backend implements
the PyTorch operation kernels,
as well as a Runtime framework.
The operations call into MPS Graph and MPS
and the Runtime component uses Metal.
This enables PyTorch to use
the highly efficient kernels from MPS
along with Metal's Command queues,
Command buffers,
and synchronization primitives.
The operation kernels
and PyTorch MPS Runtime components
are part of the open source code
and merged into the official
PyTorch GitHub repo.
Using the MPS PyTorch backend
is a simple three-step process.
First, starting with PyTorch 1.12,
you can install the base package
using ‘pip install torch'.
This package is available in
the official python package repository.
For more details
on environment setup and installation,
please refer to
the Metal Developer Resources web page.
Second, import PyTorch
and create the MPS device.
This code snippet
uses the MPS device backend
if it is available,
otherwise it'll fall back to the CPU.
The last step is to convert your models
and inputs to use the MPS device.
To demonstrate how to do this,
I will use an example which runs inference
on a pre-trained ResNet50 model
from torchvision.
By default, the model will run on the CPU.
You can use the "to" method to convert
the model to use the MPS device.
This ensures that intermediate tensors
inside the model
will also use the accelerated MPS backend.
Finally, you can run the model.
This example passes a random
input tensor to the MPS model.
By default,
all tensors are allocated on the CPU.
In order to use the MPS backend,
you will also need to provide
the mpsDevice here as well.
All subsequent operations on this tensor
will be accelerated on the GPU.
Finally, pass the sample input
to the MPS model to get a prediction.
Now that you know
how to use the MPS device,
I'll show you an example
of PyTorch in action.
I've always wanted to be a famous artist.
So I decided to use machine learning
and my GPU
to help create my artwork
using the StyleTransfer network.
This network allows you to apply
a different artistic style to an image.
In this case, the goal is to learn
how to apply Van Gogh's style
in Starry Night to this picture of a cat.
With the new MPS device,
you will be able to use the GPU
to train your PyTorch networks
significantly faster.
To demonstrate this,
I'll start training this network
on both the CPU and GPU simultaneously
on an M1 Max.
It takes thousands of iterations
to learn this style,
but the GPU is able to converge
to a reasonable model in much less time.
In addition to StyleTransfer,
we have seen amazing speedups
on all these PyTorch benchmarks.
On the M1 Ultra,
we saw speedups of up to 20 times faster
with an average of 8.3 times faster.
PyTorch makes it easy
to develop machine learning models,
and you'll be able to save a lot of time
by using Apple GPUs to train them.
Next, I'll dive into all the enhancements
we've made this year to TensorFlow.
TensorFlow Metal acceleration
has been available
since TensorFlow version 2.5
through the TensorFlow Metal plug-in.
Since then, several additional features
and improvements have been added.
These include improved training
with bigger batches,
new operations and custom op support,
RNN improvements,
and distributed training.
The TensorFlow Metal plug-in releases
are aligned with major TensorFlow
releases,
so make sure you update
your TensorFlow packages
to get the latest features
and improvements.
Let's start with bigger batch sizes.
This year software improvements
in TensorFlow Metal allow you
to leverage the unique benefits
of the Apple silicon architecture.
This graph shows speedups
training a ResNet50 model
with various batch sizes.
The data shows that performance improves
with bigger batch sizes
because each gradient update corresponds
more closely to the true gradient.
Apple silicon's
unified memory architecture
allows you to run larger networks
or larger batch sizes.
Now you can run your workload
on a single Mac Studio
instead of splitting it
across a cloud cluster, which is awesome!
The Apple Silicon architecture
also has high performance per watt,
meaning your networks run
more efficiently than ever.
Next l'll talk about the new operations
and custom operations.
The Tensorflow Metal plug-in now has
GPU acceleration
for a variety of new operations,
including argMin, all, pack,
adaDelta, and many more.
But what if you want GPU acceleration
for an operation
that's currently not supported
in the TensorFlow API?
To do this, you will need to create
a custom operation.
Here's an example
of a simple convolutional network
running for two iterations.
The timeline represents the work done
on the GPU and CPU,
above and below respectively.
The network does a convolution
followed by maxpool-ing
and then a softmax cross entropy loss.
All of these operations
are GPU accelerated
in the TensorFlow Metal plug-in
through MPS Graph
But you might want to use
a custom loss function.
Without MPS GPU acceleration
for this custom loss,
that work will need to be performed
on the CPU timeline
which introduces synchronization overhead
and starves the GPU.
You can achieve far better performance
by doing this custom loss on the GPU.
In order to implement a custom operation,
you will need to understand
the TensorFlow Metal Stream protocol.
This is a protocol which you use
to encode GPU operations.
The Metal stream holds a reference
to the MTLCommandBuffer you use
to encode your GPU kernel.
It also exposes the dispatch_queue
to use for CPU side synchronization
while encoding as there may be
multiple threads submitting work.
Use the commit or commitAndWait methods
to submit the work to the GPU.
CommitAndWait is a debugging tool that
will wait until the current command buffer
is done so you can observe
serialized submissions.
Now let's see how these concepts
can be used to implement a custom op.
There are three steps
to write a custom operation.
First, register the operation.
Next, implement the operation
using a MetalStream.
And finally, import the operation into
your training scripts and begin using it.
I'll start with registering the operation.
Use the REGISTER_OP macro
exposed by TensorFlow core
to specify the semantics of the op
and how it should be defined
in the TensorFlow Metal plug-in.
Next, implement the op using
the TensorFlow_MetalStream.
Start by defining the "compute" function.
Now, inside this function,
get the TensorFlow_Tensor objects
for the input and define the output,
which might require an allocation.
Then create an encoder
using the Metal stream's command buffer.
Next, define the custom GPU kernel.
Your op should be encoded inside
the dispatch_queue
provided by the Metal stream.
This ensures submissions
from multiple threads are serialized.
Then commit the kernel
by using the method provided
in the TensorFlow_MetalStream protocol.
Finally, delete the references
to the allocated tensors.
Last, import the operation into
your training script to begin using it.
In this step, build the custom op's shared
dynamic library file called zero_out.so.
Refer to Metal Developer Resources
for info on how to build and import
.so files.
This example imports the operation
into the training script
by using the TensorFlow load_op_library,
which is an optional step.
Now, this works like a python wrapper
and our custom op can be invoked
in the training script.
Next, I'd like to show you an example
of an interesting application
called Neural Radiance Fields, or NeRF.
We wrote a custom operation
that elevated the network's performance
by enabling GPU acceleration
for a better algorithm.
NeRF is a network used
to synthesize 3D views of a model.
For training, NeRF takes as input,
images of an object from different angles.
The NeRF network consists of
two stacked Multi-layer perceptrons,
and the output is a volumetric
representation of the model.
A key performance optimization
for real time training
uses a hash table implementation.
This updated network allows
a much smaller multi-layer perceptron.
TensorFlow does not support
hash tables natively
so we use the custom op feature
to implement them in the Metal plug-in.
The GPU acceleration for hash tables makes
it possible to train NeRF much faster.
I'll start on this MacBook
and run original multi-layer perceptron
implementation.
In order to render anything reasonable,
we need at least 20 epochs
but each epoch takes about 100 seconds.
That means it will take about 30 minutes
before anything is seen.
So now I will restart training
from a pre-trained checkpoint file,
which was left to train
for 30 minutes beforehand.
This starts at epoch 20.
The 3D model is blurred and unclear
even after 30 minutes of training.
It would require a much longer
training time for the network
to learn a clearer model.
The original two stacked multi-layer
perceptron approach
without custom hash tables is too slow.
Now on this MacBook
I'll kick off the optimized version
that uses custom hash tables.
This implementation is already able
to render a much clearer model
and each epoch takes only 10 seconds
to learn.
For more information on this project,
check out the sample code which we have
uploaded to Metal Developer Resources.
NeRF is just one of the many networks
which demonstrates
how you can implement GPU acceleration
for your own custom operations
to make your networks run blazing fast.
I look forward to learning
about all the creative customizations
you make, going forward.
Now I want to show you how to use
Apple GPUs
to distribute training of ML workloads.
In order to distribute
training of workloads,
you can run multiple instances of the
training script in separate processes
where each process evaluates
a single iteration of the model.
Each process will read data
from a central data store.
After which, it will run through the model
and calculate the model gradients.
Next, the processes will average
the gradients and communicate this
to each other so each process has the same
gradients before the next iteration.
Finally, the model is updated
and you can repeat this process
until all the iterations are exhausted.
To demonstrate this on TensorFlow,
I will use an example
of distributed training
using a popular open source
framework called Horovod.
Horovod uses a ring all-reduce approach.
In this algorithm,
each of N nodes communicates
with two of its peers multiple times.
Using this communication,
the worker processes synchronize
gradients before each iteration.
I'll show this in action
using four Mac Studios
connected to each other
with Thunderbolt cables.
For this example, I will train ResNet,
a classifier for images.
The bar to the side of each Mac Studio
shows the GPU utilization
while training this network.
For a single Mac Studio, the performance
is about 200 images per second.
When I add another Mac Studio
connected via Thunderbolt,
the performance almost doubles
to 400 images per second
since both GPUs are utilized
to the fullest.
Finally,
when I connect two more Mac Studios,
the performance is elevated
to 800 images per second.
This is almost linear scaling on
your compute bound training workloads.
Now here's a look at the Distributed
training performance of TensorFlow.
This chart shows the relative speedup
for one, two, and four Mac Studios.
They are connected in a ring topology and
run compute bound TensorFlow networks
such as resNet and DistilBERT
with the latest TensorFlow Metal plug-in
and Horovod.
The base is the performance
on a single Mac Studio.
The graph show that network performance
scales with the addition of each GPU
so you can now leverage GPUs
on multiple devices,
to speed up your training time
and make the most
out of all your Apple devices.
All the improvements and features
unlocked for TensorFlow this year
culminate into this chart
showing the relative performance
against the CPU implementation
with more improvements to come
in the future.
Now Matteo will share what's new
in the MPSGraph framework.
Matteo: Thanks, Dhruva.
Hi, my name is Matteo,
and I'm a GPU software engineer.
PyTorch and TensorFlow sit on top
of the MPSGraph framework.
In turn, MPSGraph uses
the parallel primitives
exposed by the MPS framework
to accelerate work on the GPU.
Today I am going to talk about
two features that you can use
to accelerate your compute workloads
even further with MPSGraph.
First, I will show
the new shared events API
which allows you to synchronize work
between two graphs.
Second, I will go over new operations,
which you can use to do even more
with MPSGraph.
I'll begin with the Shared Events API.
Running applications on
the same command queue
ensures synchronization between workloads.
In this example,
the compute workload is guaranteed
to always terminate
before other workloads,
such as post processing and display,
are dispatched.
In cases like this,
you will leverage the GPU parallelism
within each single dispatch.
However, some applications could benefit
from more parallelism,
where a first portion of the GPU
is used for the compute,
and a second portion is used
for the post processing and display.
This could be achieved by submitting work
to the GPU on multiple command queues.
Unfortunately, in this case,
the post processing pipeline
may be dispatched before
the compute has produced the results,
introducing a data race.
The Shared Events API can be used
to solve this problem
and introduce synchronization
across command queues
to make sure that workflow dependencies
can be satisfied.
Using shared events within
your code is very simple.
Let's assume
you are working with two graphs.
The first is responsible
for the compute workload.
The second, is responsible
for the post processing workload.
Let's also assume that the result
of the compute graph is used as input
for the post processing graph,
and that they run
on different command queues.
The new MPSGraph track
in the Metal System Trace
indicates that the command queues
are overlapping with each other.
This produces a data race.
You can solve this problem
using a shared event.
First, create the event
using the Metal device.
Next, invoke the signal method
in the execution descriptor,
providing the event, the action,
and the value.
Then all you have to do is to call
the wait method
on the second descriptor,
providing event variable and the value.
Now, the Metal system trace
indicates that the two command queues
are run sequentially,
and the dependency between
compute and post processing graph
has been resolved.
That's how you can use shared events
to solve synchronization problems
in your applications.
Second, I'll talk about the new operations
supported by MPSGraph.
These operations allow you
to do even more with the framework.
I'll go through some of the details of
each of these new ops, starting with RNNs.
MPSGraph now exposes three operations
commonly used
within Recurrent Neural Network
applications.
These are the RNN, LSTM,
and GRU layers.
These operations all work similarly,
so I'll just focus on LSTMs today.
The LSTM operation is commonly used
for natural language processing
and other applications.
This diagram shows
how the LSTM operation works.
To learn more about it,
check out our previous WWDC session.
You could implement the LSTM unit
yourself, but to do so,
you would have to build this
rather complicated custom subgraph.
Instead, you can use
the new LSTM operation,
which efficiently encodes all the GPU work
required by the recurrent unit.
This new operation makes LSTM-based CoreML
inference models significantly faster.
To use the new LSTM operation,
first create an MPSGraphLSTMDescriptor.
You can modify the descriptor properties
as needed,
for example
selecting the activation functions.
Next, add the LSTM unit to the graph,
providing the input tensors.
You can also provide a bias vector,
as well as the initial state and cell
for the operation.
Finally, provide the descriptor.
That's all you need to do
to set up an LSTM.
The other RNN operations work similarly.
I encourage you
to try these operations out
and see what kind of speedups
you can get in your application.
Next, I'll show you
the improved support for Max Pooling.
The Max Pooling operation takes
an input tensor and a window size
and computes,
for each application of the window,
the maximum value of the input
within the window.
It is commonly used in computer vision
to reduce the dimensionality of an image.
The API has been extended to return
the indices of the maximum value location
extracted by the pooling operator.
You can use indices in the gradient pass,
where the gradients must be propagated
through the locations
where the maximum values were extracted.
The new API works for training too.
Reusing the indices during training
can be up to six times faster
for PyTorch and TensorFlow.
To set this up in code, first,
create the GraphPooling descriptor.
You can specify the returnIndicesMode,
for example, globalFlatten4D.
Then you can call the pooling operation
on the graph with the Return Indices API.
The result of the operation is twofold.
First, the poolingTensor,
and second, the indicesTensor.
You can cache the indicesTensor
for later use,
for example, on a training pipeline.
MPS Graph now exposes
a new parallel random number generator,
which can be used, for example,
to initialize the weights
of a training graph.
The new random operation
uses the Philox algorithm
and returns the same results
as TensorFlow for a given seed.
The new operation takes,
as input, a state tensor;
it returns as output a random tensor
and a new state tensor that can be used,
for example,
as input for a second random operation.
To use the new random operation,
call the randomPhiloxStateTensor method.
This method initializes
an input stateTensor with the given seed.
Then declare the RandomOp descriptor,
which takes as input
the distribution and the data type.
In the example,
the descriptor specifies
a truncatedNormal distribution
of 32bit floating point values.
You can also use
Normal and Uniform distributions.
You can further define
the distribution characteristics
by specifying the mean,
standard deviation,
minimum, and maximum values.
Finally, you can create the random
operation, providing a shapeTensor,
the descriptor,
and the stateTensor just created.
In addition to Random,
MPSGraph now supports
a new GPU accelerated operation
to compute the Hamming distance
between two bit vectors.
The hamming distance,
defined as the number of bits
that differ between two inputs
with same length,
is a measure of the edit distance
between two sequences,
and it is used on several applications,
from bioinformatics to cryptography.
To use HammingDistance,
call the API on the graph,
providing primaryTensor,
secondaryTensor, and the resultDataType.
Note that the new kernel supports
broadcasting over batch dimensions
on the GPU.
Now, I'll show you all about
the new tensor manipulation operations,
which are very easy to use.
You can now expand the dimensionality
of the tensor, for example,
from two to three dimensions.
And you can squeeze the dimensions back.
You can also split a tensor evenly
providing a number of slices and an axis.
or stack tensors along a given axis.
You can also generate coordinate values
along tensor dimensions
for a given input shape.
For example, you can populate
a tensor of shape two by four
with coordinates along the 0 axis.
This can be also used
to implement a range1D operation.
For example, assume you want to generate
the range of numbers
between 3 and 27 with increments of 4.
You can do so
by first creating the coordinates
along the dimension 0
of a tensor of shape 6.
Then, all you have to do is to multiply
by the increment, and add the offset.
Those are all of the new operations
added this year.
With all these new operations,
you will be able to do even more
and get higher performance across
the Apple ecosystem using MPSGraph.
Now, I am going to show you
the performance improvements you can get
on Apple silicon out of MPSGraph.
Blackmagic has just released
DaVinci Resolve version 18,
which uses MPS Graph to accelerate
machine learning workloads.
Magic Mask is a feature of Resolve
that uses machine learning
to identify a moving object on screen and
selectively apply filters on top of it.
First I'll demonstrate how this works
in the previous version of Resolve,
and then I'll compare it
to the current version.
To create the mask,
you just need to select the target object.
You can view the mask
by toggling the overlay.
The mask is identified by the red area,
which correctly marks
the shape of the subject.
Now, if I play the video, the mask will
track the object as it moves on screen.
This looks great, but it's running
at a pretty low frame rate,
as the machine learning pipeline
runs under the hood.
Now I'll switch to the newest version
of Resolve,
which uses MPSGraph to accelerate
the Magic Mask network.
Running the same timeline again,
the frame rate is way faster than before.
This results in a much better
editing experience on Apple silicon.
These are the kind of speedups you can get
just by adopting MPS Graph.
I encourage you to explore what kind
of performance it can bring to your app.
To wrap up,
you will now be able to leverage
GPU acceleration for PyTorch,
and the project is now open source.
You will find new ways to accelerate
training workloads
using the TensorFlow Metal plug-in,
for example, using custom operations
and distributed training.
Finally, you will be able to optimize the
most demanding machine learning tasks
with the MPSGraph framework
to make the best out of Apple silicon,
using shared events and new operations.
Dhruva and I can't wait to see
how you will use these new features
in your applications.
Thank you for watching the session,
and have a great WWDC.