[spacey music]
David Duncan: Hi, I’m David Duncan,
and in this video,
I’ll be introducing you
to desktop class iPad.
iOS 16 brings advances to the tools
used to design and build great apps,
apps that bring more and better tools
to the forefront
and take advantage of all the hardware,
both built in and attached.
UIKit adds many tools to help you
meet these goals for your apps.
Updates to UINavigationBar allow you
to take better advantage
of screen real estate and build
a great experience on all Apple platforms.
The new Find and Replace UI
is a snap to enable on built-in views
and easy to add to custom ones.
The Edit menu has been overhauled,
with a new interaction-based API
that integrates with the menu system.
And collection view improvements
make it easier than ever
to build interfaces that let your users
select and act on their content.
For more information
on Find and Replace and Edit Menu,
watch "Adopt desktop
class editing interactions."
And to see how all these features
work together,
watch "Build a desktop class iPad app."
In this video, I'll discuss changes
to navigation
that impact how you design
your app for iOS 16.
First are new features that make it easy
to build more discoverable interfaces.
Then features that are especially powerful
for document based apps.
And, finally, updates to Search to help
accelerate and polish the experience.
UINavigationBar is used
for many different purposes on iOS,
and iOS 16 acknowledges that
by providing
new optimized UI for many of these cases.
UINavigationItem adds a style property,
used to select from these styles:
navigator, browser, and editor.
I'll dive into each of these styles now.
The default style, navigator,
behaves exactly
as a traditional UINavigationBar.
The title is centered, there are
leading and trailing bar button items,
and a back button appears when
there is more than 1 item on the stack.
The browser style rearranges contents
to be better optimized for interfaces
where history matters as much as location,
like in Files or Safari.
The title is moved to the leading position
in this styling.
The editor style is optimized for
when the primary function
is document editing.
Just like the browser style,
the title is leading aligned.
Editor UIs are often a destination,
such as after selecting a document
with a document picker,
and so present
a back button for easy access to that UI.
The browser and editor styles both free up
a lot of space in the center of the bar.
iOS 16 takes advantage
of this liberated space
by allowing you to place
additional controls in this region.
Center items are part
of a suite of changes
to take better advantage
of screen real estate,
and include support for
UIBarButtonItemGroup,
customization support, and overflow.
Overflow support is available
in all modes,
and allows the navigator style
to indirectly support
center items as well.
Individual controls continue
to be specified as UIBarButtonItems,
but now are organized
as UIBarButtonItemGroups.
This allows for denser presentation
when space is at a premium.
In this example, there are 5 items
in the bar, consisting of 4 groups.
The first group contains
a single bar button item,
so this example uses a convenience method
of UIBarButtonItem,
creatingFixedGroup(), to create it.
If you need
a fixed group with more than 1 item,
you can use
the UIBarButtonItemGroup method instead.
Fixed groups
always appear first in the bar,
and cannot be removed
or moved by customization.
The draw group contains a single item,
so it also uses a convenience API,
creatingMovableGroup
(customizationIdentifier).
Like fixed groups, movable groups
cannot be removed, but can be moved.
Because of this,
they require a customizationIdentifier
so their position
can be tracked and saved.
If you need a group
with more than one item,
you can use the UIBarButtonItemGroup
method instead.
The shapes group contains multiple items,
and so uses
the UIBarButtonItemGroup API
to create the group.
This group
should be movable within the bar,
as well as removable,
and so is created as an optional group.
This group also specifies
a representativeItem,
allowing UIKit to collapse the group
to save space when necessary.
The representativeItem does not specify
an action, further allowing UIKit
to synthesize a menu allowing selection
of the items in the group.
When the customization UI is invoked,
UIKit automatically applies
the rules you've specified based
on how you've created your groups.
While fixed and movable groups
must stay in the bar,
optional groups can be added
or removed in any number.
UIKit will try collapsing groups
to keep as much functionality as possible
in the bar,
but if space isn't available,
extra items will be moved to overflow.
The overflow menu contains any items
that are part of the customization
but could not be fit into the bar,
as well as the option
to customize the bar.
While UIKit will synthesize default
menu elements for each bar button item,
you have the option to customize
the menuRepresentation if you wish.
Finally, this example
enables customization
and adds the centerItemGroups.
You enable customization by setting
UINavigationItem.customizationIdentifier.
The customizationIdentifier
defines a unique customization of the bar,
so pick a string that won't conflict
with other customizations within your app.
UIKit automatically saves and restores
customizations based on this identifier.
Next, provide
the centerItemGroups themselves.
The first four groups
I've already covered.
The format group is an optional group
that isn't in the default customization,
and so this code
overrides the default value
of the isInDefaultCustomization
parameter to exclude it.
You can still use centerItemGroups
without setting
UINavigationItem.customizationIdentifier,
but customization will not be available.
In Mac Catalyst, the UINavigationBar
automatically translates its content
to NSToolbar.
The leading, center,
and trailing item groups
are added in order,
and the customization properties
of the center item groups are respected
when using NSToolbar customization.
All of the expected NSToolbar behaviors
are available,
as well as other properties
such as the title & window proxy.
All of this occurs by default
when you optimize for the Mac.
Next, let’s focus in
on interactions that are powerful,
specifically when dealing with documents.
UINavigationBar now supports
adding a menu to the title view,
giving a central location to add actions
that operate on the content as a whole.
Additionally, you can add support
for the share sheet
and drag & drop from this menu.
First, I’ll focus
on the menu items themselves.
Once enabled,
the default title menu offers 5 commands:
duplicate, move, rename, export,
and print.
These items are filtered
based on specific methods
in your responder chain.
UINavigationBar
has specific support for renaming,
and so it will also be included
if you’ve implemented a renameDelegate.
To enable the title menu,
set the titleMenuProvider,
a closure that returns
the final menu to be displayed.
The closure is passed
an array of suggested elements.
You can use these as is,
filter them, or add your own.
In our example, we're adding
a single additional action to the menu.
Finally, you return the composed UIMenu.
The title menu also allows
sharing via the activity view controller
and support for drag & drop.
To enable these features, you provide
a UIDocumentProperties instance
that describes your document.
UIDocumentProperties represents
metadata about your document,
including a preview.
This example creates one with a URL,
allowing UIKit to fetch
the necessary metadata automatically.
To enable additional features,
this example creates
an NSItemProvider
to represent the document.
Set a dragItemsProvider
to enable drag & drop.
This closure is past a UIDragSession,
and returns an array of UIDragItems.
This example returns a single item
representing the document.
Setting a activityViewControllerProvider
enables sharing.
This closure configures and returns
a UIActivityViewController.
Finally, assign the filled-out object
to UINavigationItem.documentProperties,
and when the title is tapped,
UIKit presents the header
alongside other titleMenu items.
On Mac Catalyst, the suggested items
that would be passed
to the titleMenuProvider
already exist in the File menu.
Any items that you would have added
to the title menu
will need to be made available
by other means.
You can use
the UIMenuBuilder API to add these items,
or filter existing items as necessary.
If you specify document properties,
UIKit will automatically use
the URL provided
to manage the macOS proxy icon.
If you set the representedURL
for your windowScene manually,
that will supersede UIKit's management.
UIKit provides
two mechanisms to enable Rename.
Inline Rename is provided by setting
UINavigationItem.renameDelegate,
and provides a dedicated UI
for editing the title on all platforms.
When completed, the resulting name
is passed to the delegate.
Alternatively you can take full control
over the rename experience
by implementing UIResponder.rename(_:)
and providing whatever UI you prefer.
On iOS, the UINavigationBar
provides the rename UI
directly within the title view.
On macOS, the rename UI is provided
by the window's title
when the navigation bar is hosted
in an NSToolbar.
To implement inline rename, conform
to the UINavigationItemRenameDelegate
protocol and set
the navigation item's renameDelegate.
There is only one required method,
navigationItem(_:didEndRenamingWith:),
that is used to receive
the title accepted by the user.
For file based apps,
UIDocumentBrowserViewController
now offers a renamed API.
Search is how many users
find their most important data,
and advances in iOS 16 make it easier
to provide an excellent search experience.
The first thing to note is that search
now takes up less space
by being in line in the navigation bar
on iPadOS
and the toolbar on macOS.
On iPadOS,
you can restore the old behavior
with UINavigationItem
.preferredSearchBarPlacement.
Additionally,
the search bar can collapse to a button
to grant more space for other controls.
When search is activated,
search suggestions appear,
and they can be updated
alongside the updating search query,
allowing you the opportunity
to assist your users in their search.
Next, I'll describe the code
needed to setup search suggestions.
To manage search suggestions,
conform to UISearchResultsUpdating
and set your searchController's
searchResultsUpdater.
This allows you to update
suggestions as the query changes
and to act
on a selected search suggestion.
When the query changes,
updateSearchResults(for:) is called,
allowing you to update search suggestions.
What suggestions to provide is up to you.
Setting an empty array
will clear the suggestions UI.
UIKit provides UISearchSuggestionItem
to specify suggestion content.
To respond
to the selection of a suggestion,
implement
updateSearchResults(for:selecting:).
This method passes
the selected search suggestion,
so you may react to it appropriately.
In this example I update the search
by replacing the current query
with the one specified
by the search suggestion.
UISearchTextField also has
searchSuggestions,
so if you prefer to use that class
on its own,
you can still implement
search suggestions.
But if you are using UISearchController,
you should use its property instead.
In iOS 16, UIKit provides new API
to help you
bring more productivity to your users.
Bring more discoverability
to your advanced features
with center items and the title menu.
Improve your document support
by providing drag & drop
and sharing directly
from the navigation bar.
Make it easier and faster to search
by providing search suggestions
and get a great Mac experience
right out of the box,
with nearly zero effort.
Thanks for watching this video.
I can't wait to see how you
enhance your apps to be desktop class!
[spacey music]