♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hip music ♪
♪
Hi, everyone.
I'm Jeff, an engineer
on the SwiftUI team.
Today, I'm excited
to talk to you
about bringing multiple windows
to your SwiftUI app
on iPadOS and macOS.
In this session,
we'll open with an overview
of the various scene types
in the SwiftUI lifecycle,
including a few new types
we're introducing.
Followed by showing
how these scene types
can be composed together,
by adding auxiliary scenes.
Then we'll cover some
new APIs for opening windows
for a particular scene
in your app.
And we'll wrap things up
with a few ways
for customizing an app's scenes.
Let's start with an overview
of the existing scene types
before digging in
to some new ones.
You'll recall from previous
sessions that apps in SwiftUI
are composed of scenes
and views.
Scenes commonly represent their
contents with a window onscreen.
For example,
here is an app I've built
to keep track of the books
I'm reading.
It's defined as
a single window group
which shows my reading list
in a platform-appropriate way.
On platforms which support
multiple windows,
such as iPadOS and macOS,
a scene can represent itself
with several such windows.
The behaviors and
representation of a scene vary
based on the type used.
For example, a scene
may only represent itself
with a single instance,
regardless of platform
capabilities.
Let's take a look at
the current list of scene types
in SwiftUI.
WindowGroup provides a way to
build data-driven applications
across all of Apple's platforms.
DocumentGroup lets you build
document-based apps
on iOS and macOS.
And Settings
defines an interface
for representing in-app settings
values on macOS.
These scene types
can be composed together
to extend your app's
functionality.
We're extending the list of
scenes with two new additions.
The first of which is Window,
a scene which represents
a single, unique window
on all platforms;
as well as a new scene type
for macOS: MenuBarExtra,
which renders as a persistent
control in the system menu bar.
As with the other
scene types,
you can use
Window and MenuBarExtra
both as a standalone scene,
or composed with other scenes
in your app.
Unlike WindowGroup, the Window
scene will only ever represent
its contents in a single,
unique window instance.
This characteristic
can be useful
when the contents of your scene
represents some global app state
that would not
necessarily fit well
with WindowGroups' multi-window
presentation style
on macOS and iPadOS.
For example,
a game may wish to only allow
for a single main window
to render its contents.
MenuBarExtra is a new
macOS-only scene type
which behaves
a little differently
from our other scenes.
Rather than rendering
its contents in a window,
it will place its label
in the menu bar
and show its contents
in either a menu or window
which is anchored to the label.
Additionally,
it will be useable
as long as its associated app
is running,
regardless of whether
that app is frontmost.
MenuBarExtra is great for
creating standalone utility apps
that provide easy access
to their functionality.
Or it can be composed
with other scenes
to provide an alternate way to
access your app's functionality.
It also supports two rendering
styles: the default style,
which shows the contents
in a menu
which pulls down
from the menu bar,
as well as a style
that presents its contents
in a chromeless window
anchored to the menu bar.
With the addition of
these two new scene types,
SwiftUI apps can represent an
even richer set of functionality
across all of our platforms.
Let's see how these new APIs
can be used
in conjunction with our
existing scene types.
Here's the definition
of my BookClub app
that I showed earlier.
It currently consists
of a single window group.
On macOS, my BookClub app
could benefit
from an additional window
to display our reading activity
over time.
This is a great example
of how macOS apps can make use
of the additional
screen real estate
and flexible windowing
arrangements
present on that platform.
We'll add an auxiliary scene
to our app
for representing this interface.
Our Activity window's data
is derived
from our overall app state,
so a window scene
is the ideal choice for it.
Opening multiple windows
with the same state
would not fit well
with our design.
The title provided to our scene
will be used as the label
for a menu item which is added
to a section of the Window menu.
When selecting this item, the
scene's window will be opened
if not already so.
Otherwise, it will be
brought to the front.
Now that we've covered
adding an auxiliary scene
to our BookClub app,
I'd like to discuss some of
the new scene presentation APIs
we're adding and how you can
integrate them into your app
to provide richer experiences.
Our BookClub app has a context
menu that can be invoked
for any book
in our Content List pane.
This context menu
will include a button
for triggering
our window presentation.
We'll fill in the details
shortly.
SwiftUI provides several
new callable types
via the environment
for presenting windows
tied to the scenes
your app defines.
The first of these
is openWindow action,
which can present windows
for either a WindowGroup
or window scene.
The identifier passed
to the action must match
an identifier for a scene
defined in your app.
openWindow action can also take
a presentation value,
which the presented scene will
use to display its contents.
This form of the action is only
supported by WindowGroup,
using a new initializer that
we'll take a look at shortly.
The type of the value
must match
against the type provided
to the scene's initializer.
There are also two callable
types in the environment
for presenting document windows:
newDocument action,
which supports opening
new document windows
for both FileDocuments
and ReferenceFileDocuments.
This action requires that the
corresponding DocumentGroup
in your app is defined
with an editor role.
The document provided
to this action will be created
each time the window
is presented.
For presenting document windows
where the contents are provided
by an existing file on disk,
there is the openDocument
action.
This action takes a URL
to the file you wish to open.
Your app must define
a DocumentGroup
for presenting the window,
and the document type
for that group must allow
for reading the type of the file
at the provided URL.
Revisiting our button, we'll add
the openWindow environment
property to our view.
Since this type is a callable,
we can just call it directly
from our button's action.
Our Book type conforms
to identifiable,
so we'll pass its identifier
as the value to present.
Now, before we move on, I'd like
to discuss the values passed
to the openWindow action.
I noted that I'm passing
the book's identifier,
which is a value
of the UUID type.
In general,
you'll want to prefer to use
your model's identifier
like this,
rather than the value itself.
Note that our Book type
is a value type.
As such, if we were to use it
as the presented value,
our new window would get
a copy of the one
which originated
the presentation.
Any edits to either one
will not affect the other.
Using the book's identifier
lets our model store
be the source of truth
for these values instead
by providing multiple
bindings to a single value.
For more info
on value type semantics,
please see
the developer documentation.
The type being presented
must also conform
to both the Hashable
and Codable protocols.
Hashable conformance is needed
to associate the presented value
with an open window;
while Codable
conformance is required
in order to persist
the presented value
for state restoration.
I'll discuss both
of these behaviors
in more detail shortly.
Lastly, when possible, prefer
passing lightweight values.
Our book's identifier is
another great example of this.
Since the value will be
persisted by SwiftUI
for state restoration,
using smaller values
will result in greater
responsiveness of your app.
Now, our button now has
the necessary pieces
to present our detail windows,
but nothing will show
when it is selected.
This is because we've told
SwiftUI to present a window
for a certain data type,
but haven't defined a scene
in our app that reflects that.
Let's head back to our app
and make that change now.
Alongside our primary
WindowGroup
and auxiliary window,
we'll add
an additional WindowGroup
for handling our book details.
Our book details WindowGroup
uses a new initializer.
In addition to the title,
we're noting that this group
presents data
for the Book.ID type --
in our case, UUIDs.
This type should match
the value that we are passing
to the openWindow action
we added earlier.
When a given value is provided
to the WindowGroup
for presentation,
SwiftUI will create a new
child scene for that value,
and the root content
of that scene's window
will be defined by that value,
using the group's view builder.
Each unique presented value
will create a new scene.
The value's equality
will be used to determine
if a new window
should be created
or if an existing window
can be reused.
When openWindow
presents a value
for which a window
already exists,
the group will use that window
rather than creating a new one.
Using our BookClub app
as an example,
selecting the context menu
action for a book
which has already
been presented in a window
will result in that window
being ordered front,
rather than a second window
showing the same book.
The presented value will also
be automatically persisted
by SwiftUI for the purposes
of state restoration.
Your view will be
given a binding
to the initial presented value.
This binding can be modified
at any time
while the window is open.
When the scene is recreated
for state restoration,
SwiftUI will pass
the most recent value
to the window's Content view.
Here, we're giving the Book.ID
binding to our detail view,
which can look up
the specified item
in our model store
for display.
With all our pieces in place,
we can now select
our context menu item
and view our book details
in its own window.
Lastly, I'd like to go over
some of the ways
in which you can customize
the scenes in your app.
Because we've defined our app
with two WindowGroup scenes --
one for the main viewer window
and one for our
detail windows --
SwiftUI by default
will add a menu item
for each group in the File menu.
The menu item
for our detail window
doesn't quite fit
our use case, however.
I'd prefer that the windows
can only be opened
via the context menu
that was added earlier.
A new scene modifier,
commandsRemoved,
allows you to modify a scene
such that it will no longer
provide its default commands,
like the one in the File menu.
After applying this modifier,
our File menu now only contains
an item for opening windows
for the primary WindowGroup.
I'm not quite happy
with the current presentation
of the auxiliary window scene
for showing my reading activity,
so let's focus on that next.
Since I'm going to apply
a few modifiers to it,
I'll extract it out
into a custom scene,
which will keep
my app definition cleaner.
Absent any previous state
for a window,
SwiftUI will by default place it
in the center of the screen.
I'd prefer it
if the Reading Activity
was placed in a different
location by default, however.
By adding the new
defaultPosition modifier,
I can specify
a position to be used
when no previous state
is available.
This position is relative
to the screen size
and will place the window
in the appropriate location
taking into account
the current locale.
This new position helps
differentiate my Activity window
from the other viewing windows
on the screen.
I'd also like my Activity window
to show at a certain size by
default, but still be resizable.
Alongside the defaultPosition,
I'll add the defaultSize
modifier.
The value provided to it will
be given to the layout system
to derive an initial size
for the window.
Now that I've customized
the presentation of my window,
let's add one more modifier
to customize its behavior.
The keyboardShortcut modifier
has been expanded
to work on scene types as well.
When used at the scene level,
this modifier affects
the command
which creates a new window.
Here, I've modified my Activity
window so that it can be opened
with the shortcut
Option-Command-0.
This can be a great way
to customize your app
by providing shortcuts
to commonly used scenes
and can also be used to
customize the default shortcut
of Command-N,
which is added to the primary
WindowGroup in your app.
This closes our tour
of the new scene
and windowing functionality
in SwiftUI.
We're really excited about
the potential of these new APIs
and hope you are too!
For more great info on
how to add functionality
to your iPadOS and macOS apps,
please check out
these other sessions:
"SwiftUI on iPad:
Organize your interface"
and "SwiftUI on iPad:
Add toolbars, titles, and more."
Thanks for watching.
♪