♪ ♪
Tarun Belagodu:
Hello and welcome to Metal 3.
My name is Tarun Belagodu
and I'll be sharing the latest
in Metal's evolution.
First, let's start with the basics.
Metal is Apple's low-overhead
graphics and compute API.
It's designed to be the fastest
and most efficient way
to drive the incredibly powerful GPUs
behind Apple products.
It offers multi-threaded
and direct control
over the commands sent to the GPU,
a rich shading language that supports
explicit shader compilation,
and deeply integrated tools
to help debug and profile
complex applications and games.
Since its introduction,
Metal has added
many advanced graphics
and compute features,
with a focus on GPU-driven rendering,
machine learning, and ray tracing.
Apple silicon paves the way
for incredible graphics performance
and efficiency on every new Mac.
And Metal unlocks these capabilities.
This year, Metal is making a leap
to the next level with Metal 3.
Metal 3 is a powerful set of new features
that enable even higher performance
and rendering quality to help your apps
and games run faster
and look amazing.
Let's start with fast resource loading.
Modern games and apps have demanding
asset loading requirements,
and streaming many small asset requests
quickly from files to your Metal resources
is often the key to high quality visuals.
But existing storage APIs
are designed for large, bulk requests.
Metal 3's fast resource loading
lets you request many small loads
using the same explicit, multi-threaded
command model as graphics and compute.
Each request is a command,
and many commands can be queued
for asynchronous submission.
It loads directly into your Metal buffers
and textures without additional steps,
saving you both development effort
and transfer time.
Fast resource loading also makes it easy
to coordinate
between GPU operations
and loading operations,
using the Metal synchronization primitives
that you already know.
Texture streaming systems
really benefit from fast resource loading.
Let's look at an example.
Metal Sparse Textures allow applications
to stream textures at a tile granularity.
The texture streaming system
built on Metal sparse textures
consists of four steps:
First, decide what to load
based on feedback from the previous frame.
Second, load tiles from file storage.
Third, copy from your staging area
to your sparse textures.
And finally, draw your frame.
The longer it takes to load and copy
means the more time
your app draws with lower quality.
Fast resource loading
minimizes loading overhead
and ensures the storage hardware has
enough requests in its queues
to maximize throughput.
This provides faster
and more consistent performance
so that more time is spent
drawing at high quality.
Fast resource loading will greatly
simplify the code you need to write
to achieve high quality asset streaming.
To learn more about fast resource loading,
check out the "Load resources faster
with Metal 3" session.
Next, let me tell you how
the new offline compilation workflow
will help you reduce load times
and stutters in your apps.
Shader binaries
are GPU-specific machine code
that are traditionally generated
while the app is running
as part of the Metal pipeline
creation process.
Generating these binaries
is an expensive operation
that is usually hidden behind
a loading screen during app launch.
However, sometimes
they need to happen in-frame,
which in turn causes frame rate stutters.
These binaries are cached by Metal
so that you don't pay the cost often,
but their cost is still observed
on the app's first launch
or whenever the binary is first needed.
With offline compilation, you can
eliminate shader binary generation
at run time.
By moving binary generation
to project build time,
you can dramatically reduce the time spent
creating Metal pipelines at load time,
and reduce stutters in your app when
those pipelines are created just-in-time.
Let's take a closer look at
what it means to reduce stutters.
Here's an example of a game
that needs to create
a Metal pipeline state object
during encoding.
Since this is a pipeline
that Metal hasn't seen before,
it generates the needed shader binary.
This is a long operation that interrupts
encoding the rest of the frame,
and causes the app
to miss its frame rate target.
This only happens once,
but it's enough for your users
to notice a frame stutter.
In contrast, offline compilation
means the shader binary can be generated
at build-time so that every pipeline state
creation is fast, and execution is smooth.
Offline compilation can have a dramatic
effect on your app loading times too.
Let's look at an example.
Most apps create the majority
of Metal pipeline state objects
in a dedicated loading phase.
And shader binaries
are generated on first load.
This can be a long wait for your users
if your app creates many such pipelines.
With offline compilation,
shader binary generation can again
be moved to project build time,
resulting in smaller load times
and getting users
into your app more quickly.
Offline compilation is a game changer
for apps with many complex pipelines.
To learn more about offline compilation
and other improvements,
check out the "Target and optimize
GPU binaries with Metal 3" session.
Now, let's move on to MetalFX,
which provides platform-optimized
graphics effects
for Metal applications.
MetalFX Upscaling helps render
high-quality graphics in less time
through high-performance upscaling
and anti-aliasing.
You can choose a combination
of temporal or spatial algorithms
to help boost performance.
Here's why it matters.
While Retina resolution
provides crisp detail
that you want your apps
and games to take advantage of,
generating all those pixels
can also affect performance.
With MetalFX Upscaling,
you can generate pixels
at a lower resolution
and then let the framework
generate a high-quality,
high-resolution image at a lower cost
for a much higher frame rate.
MetalFX is a powerful framework
that makes high-performance,
high-quality upscaling a reality.
To learn more
about MetalFX Upscaling,
check out the "Boost performance
with MetalFX Upscaling" session.
Next up is Metal's new flexible
geometry pipeline:
Mesh Shaders.
The traditional programmable graphics
pipeline lets you transform vertices
in a shader,
that are then assembled into primitives
for rasterization
by fixed-function hardware.
That's enough for most applications,
but some use cases like culling
require access to the entire primitive.
Each vertex is also read,
transformed, and output independently.
So you can't add vertices or primitives
in the middle of your draw.
Advanced geometry processing
requires more flexibility.
And traditionally
that meant pre-processing your geometry
in a compute pass.
But that requires storing a variable
amount of intermediate geometry
to device memory,
which might be hard for you to budget for.
Metal mesh shaders introduce an
alternative geometry processing pipeline,
It replaces the traditional vertex stage
with a flexible 2-stage model
and enables hierarchical processing
of your geometry.
The first stage analyzes whole objects
to decide whether to expand,
contract, or refine geometry
in the second stage.
It achieves this by providing
compute capabilities in the render pass,
without the need
for intermediate device memory storage.
Mesh shaders are a great fit for apps
that perform GPU-driven culling,
LOD selection,
and procedural geometry generation.
Let's take a closer look.
In this example,
a compute pass evaluates the surface
and then generates its geometry.
That geometry and its draw commands
are then written to device memory
for consumption by a later render pass.
With high expansion factors
and indirect draw calls,
it can be hard to predict
the amount of memory needed.
Mesh shaders improve efficiency
by running two compute-like stages
inline in the render pipeline.
The Object stage evaluates the input
to decide how many meshes
need to be generated.
And the Mesh stage then
generates the actual geometry.
These meshes are sent directly
to the rasterizer,
bypassing the roundtrip to device memory,
and the need for vertex processing.
Mesh shaders will let you build
efficient procedural geometry,
culling, and LODing systems for your apps.
To learn more about mesh shaders,
check out the "Transform your geometry
with Metal mesh shaders" session.
Metal 3 also brings significant speedup
to the ray tracing pipeline.
Everything from
acceleration structure builds,
intersection
and shading have been optimized.
Metal also adds support for
GPU-driven ray tracing pipelines
to further optimize your app.
Let's compare Metal 3's ray tracing
to what was previously available.
Metal 3 ray tracing saves
a significant amount of CPU and GPU time.
First, acceleration structures
build in less time,
giving you more GPU time
to draw and trace rays.
Second, CPU operations such as culling
can move to the GPU
thanks to the new Indirect Command Buffer
support for Ray Tracing.
Finally, Metal 3 ray tracing
supports direct access to primitive data
to streamline and optimize
intersection and shading.
Metal 3 ray tracing continues to become
better and more powerful than before.
To learn more about ray tracing,
head over to the "Maximize your Metal
ray tracing performance" session.
Now, I'll show you how Metal 3 accelerates
machine learning inference and training.
Metal 3 has major improvements
to accelerate machine learning,
with additional support for
accelerating network training on the Mac,
and significant optimizations
for ML inference optimizations
in graphics
and media processing applications.
TensorFlow is a popular framework
for machine learning
that is GPU-accelerated on the Mac.
The recently released Mac Studio
provides up to a 16 times speedup
on M1 Ultra versus training on the CPU,
across a variety of networks.
And Metal 3 also accelerates
many new TensorFlow operations.
That means less synchronization
with the CPU
for even more scalable performance.
PyTorch is another very popular
ML framework for network training
that recently gained GPU acceleration
using Metal.
And on Mac Studio with an M1 Ultra
you can achieve significant training
speedups compared to the CPU.
For example, you can train the BERT model
up to 6.5 times faster
and train ResNet50 up to 8.5 times faster.
Metal optimizes ML inference across
Apple silicon
to maximize performance.
This is especially useful for
Metal-based high performance video
and image processing applications,
like BlackMagic Design's DaVinci Resolve.
DaVinci Resolve is a color-grading-focussed
video production platform
that uses Metal and machine learning
extensively in their workflows.
And the results are incredible.
With Metal's support
for accelerated machine learning,
BlackMagic Design achieved dramatic
performance improvements
to their editing and color grading
workflows
and their ML-based tools.
To learn more about updates
to machine learning,
head over to the "Accelerate
machine learning with Metal" session.
Now let me tell you what hardware
supports the Metal 3 features
that I just described.
Metal 3 is supported on all modern iOS,
iPadOS, and macOS devices,
including iPhone and iPad with A13 Bionic
or M1 chips or newer,
and all Apple silicon Mac systems
and Mac systems with recent AMD
and Intel GPUs.
And to find out whether
a given device supports Metal 3,
use the supportsFamily query
on the Metal device.
Metal 3 is much more than features;
it also includes a comprehensive set
of advanced developer tools.
Let me show you a few now.
The Metal Dependency Viewer
in Xcode 14 makes it even easier
to visualize your entire renderer
or zoom into a single pass.
And to make it easier to adopt
GPU-driven pipelines
or synchronize with fast resource loading
for example,
the Dependency Viewer now includes
synchronization edges
to help you analyze
and validate your dependencies.
The improved Acceleration
Structure Viewer in Xcode 14
helps you get the most out
of Metal 3's optimized ray tracing.
First, you can now highlight
individual primitives in the scene.
And selecting a primitive
shows its associated primitive data
in the outline on the left.
Last, if your scene has
motion information,
the Acceleration Structure Viewer can
now visualize different points in time.
And that's just a quick look at a few of
the Developer Tools updates in Xcode 14.
There are a host of other new features
such as Dylib support,
a new resource list,
file navigation in the Shader editor,
custom Buffer Viewer layouts
and many more.
To learn more about tools and
how to get the most out of advancements
in Metal 3,
be sure to check out these other sessions,
which will help you build
advanced graphics, games and pro apps.
Today, I introduced you
to Metal 3's advanced features
for improving performance and quality:
fast resource loading
for higher-quality texture streaming;
Offline compilation for shorter load times
and less stuttering;
MetalFX Upscaling to render
at high resolution in less time;
Mesh shaders
for advanced geometry processing;
faster acceleration structure builds,
intersections,
and shading for ray tracing;
and more accelerated machine learning.
Finally, I showed you some of
advanced tools that help you
use advanced features such as
GPU-driven pipelines and ray tracing.
To learn more with new code samples
and documentation,
head over to developer.apple.com/Metal.
Thank you for joining.