♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hello. My name is Knott.
I'm from Game Center Engineering.
Today, I'm going to walk you
through improvements we're making
in Game Center this year.
Game Center is
Apple's social gaming platform.
With Game Center, players set up
a profile and connect with friends.
Using GameKit,
you can easily integrate with Game Center.
Players will be automatically signed in,
can compare scores with their friends
and other players on leaderboards, and
can track progress through achievements.
You can also integrate support for
multiplayer matchmaking and realtime play.
Over the past couple of years,
we've introduced the Access Point,
redesigned the achievements
and leaderboards experiences —
introduced the friends API,
and improved the multiplayer experience.
Additionally, we've been bringing
Game Center activity to more places
across the device including surfacing
what you and friends are playing
in the App Store,
and creating new widgets like
Continue Playing and Friends are Playing.
This year,
we're going even further to make
the experience better for all players,
provide more exposure
for all of the great things
happening in your games,
and give you some new tools
to integrate more easily with Game Center.
I'll walk you through Activity
which brings together
all of the Game Center events
from your games into one place.
But before we get to that,
I have an announcement to make.
We know a lot of game developers
are leveraging Unity
to help build gaming experiences
on Apple platforms.
This year,
we are releasing a Unity plug-in
we've developed specifically for GameKit!
The plug-in provides
an entire GameKit API in C#.
So, you don't have to choose
between building your game with Unity,
and taking full advantage of the first
class gaming features in Game Center.
Throughout this session,
you'll see code examples
provided not only in Swift,
but also in C#.
Now, let's dive right into one
of the biggest changes to Game Center
this year: Activity.
There are so many exciting
things happening in your games
that friends might want to
tell each other about.
For example, when they get a
new achievement, or jump up a leaderboard.
We've redesigned the Game Center dashboard
this year so that it will now include
activity from a player's friends in your
game and across games, all in one place.
When a player opens the dashboard,
they will see recent activity in your game
like achievements earned, when friends
have made huge jumps on the leaderboard,
or when one friend has beaten
another player's high score.
And, of course we are designing this
to work on iPad, Mac and Apple TV as well.
I am really excited about what this means
for players to see
and engage more
with what their friends are doing,
and to have your game and all of
the great activity from your game
discovered in more places.
If you are already using Game Center for
your games, you don't have to do anything!
Your games
will already appear in Activity.
But if not,
it's really easy to get started.
All you need to do is enable
the Game Center capability
and write just a few lines of code
to make sure authentication goes smoothly.
First, go to your game's Xcode project,
then head over
to the Signing and Capabilities tab.
Click on the add capability button,
then select Game Center.
Then, go to your app record
in App Store Connect
in order to enable Game Center
for your game.
This is also the place where you
can configure Game Center features,
such as leaderboards and achievements.
And finally, import GameKit,
then authenticate the local player
by setting the authenticateHandler.
You'll want to place this code
as early as possible in your game,
even on the title screen.
Then, if there is a view controller
available from the callback,
present it here.
For Unity developers,
just call "authenticate" on GKLocalPlayer.
This static method returns the
local player object once authenticated.
Congratulations! Your game
is now Game Center enabled.
Players will see this welcome banner
when they launch your game,
and gameplay activity for your game will
start appearing in the players' feeds.
Now, all that's left is for you to provide
players easy access to the Dashboard.
The best way to do so is through
the Game Center Access Point.
Access Point provides your players
a convenient way to launch
the Game Center dashboard.
Let's jump back to some code.
Showing the access point is easy.
First, you'll want to decide on
the most appropriate time to display it.
You should consider what makes
the most sense for your game,
but for many games, the ideal presentation
occurs on the game menu page.
Once you've determined that,
all you need to do
is set a location for its appearance,
and then set the GKAccessPoint's
'isActive' property to 'true.'
As a result, the Access Point
will show up in your game.
And here is how Unity developers
can use GKAccessPoint in C#.
Set the Access Point's location
and set IsActive to true.
When players interact
with the Access Point,
the system brings up the Dashboard.
This provides a familiar place for
players to learn more about your game
as well as check in on recent activity.
Players can explore your game's
own achievements and leaderboards.
Next, players will see gameplay events
for your game, featured first in the feed.
Here, Cloeax,
Jeezzzy and I are playing The Coast.
With just those few lines of code,
your game will get increased reach
and distribution
while tying in to the broader gaming
experience on Apple platforms.
There are a lot of things you can add
in your game that will generate Activity.
Let's start with Leaderboards.
Leaderboards are a powerful way to
increase your game's exposure in Activity.
They encourage friendly competition,
giving players more reasons
to jump back into your game.
After you have set up
a leaderboard in your game,
players will see new activity when their
friends are doing well on a leaderboard.
Here, my friend placed
in the top 25% of a leaderboard.
Activity also highlights when a player's
friend beats their leaderboard score.
Here, Simundane just beat my score
in a game we've been competing on
back and forth.
For this activity,
players will also get a notification.
This notification is sent from
Game Center,
and you don't need to worry about
asking the user to opt in
to notifications for your game.
If your game
already provides leaderboards,
these activities
will appear automatically.
Even if you're already taking
advantage of leaderboards,
consider expanding your leaderboard sets
to provide more moments of competition
for players and their friends.
Recurring leaderboards in particular
provide a sense of timeliness
and a reason to re-engage
with your game on an ongoing basis.
Next, I'd like to talk about
how Game Center Achievements
are featured in Activity.
Achievements provide players an
additional way of engaging with your game,
tracking gameplay progress,
and sharing that progress with friends.
When a player completes
an achievement in your game,
this will be reflected in their activity
and their friends' activity as well.
When a player completes
every achievement in your game,
we take a moment to recognize that
with a special celebratory activity.
Achievements provide players with
a sense of progress and accomplishment,
and can help tell a story of how far
a player has made it through your game.
With prominent placement in Activity,
achievements instantly receive
wider visibility throughout
the Game Center social network.
Players can see
how their friends are doing,
and they'll have more reasons to
jump into your game and play together.
You just saw what players will see
when they land on your game's Dashboard.
Players can also visit a friend's profile
to see all of their
recent activity in one place.
And of course, what you see or don't see
on someone's profile
is still based on
the profile privacy option
they choose in Game Center settings.
And that is Activity: a place
where players can discover
their friends' activity in your game,
as well as check in
on their friends' activity across games.
In summary, Game Center
is helping you help your players
have more fun playing with
and competing against their friends.
Activity is a great destination for
players to check in on their progress
as well as their friends' progress
and provide you more distribution.
And for Unity developers,
it is now possible to take advantage
of the full extent of GameKit
with our brand new Unity plug-in.
You can learn more about how to bring
the best out of Game Center features
from your game,
how to use recurring leaderboards,
and how to use GameKit
in your Unity games
in the sessions linked to this video.
I have covered a lot today.
And we trust that this year's updates will
bring more joy to players of your games.
Thank you for watching.
[speaking language]