[upbeat music]
Andy: Hi there.
Welcome to "Adopt desktop class
editing interactions."
I'm Andy, a UIKit frameworks engineer,
and I will be joined later
by my colleague, James.
The iPad is continuously evolving,
without compromising the interactions
that make it simple and easy to use.
In this video, you'll learn about the
exciting new editing interactions
that will transform your app
to become more desktop class.
First, I'll go over the new edit menus,
which received a major facelift in iOS 16.
Later, James will dive into the new system
find and replace experience.
In iOS 16, the edit menu
features an all-new design
that remains familiar
but is more interactive
and is easier to discover actions.
The edit menu now
has alternate presentations
based on the input method used.
For touch interactions,
the edit menu still has
the familiar compact appearance,
but with an improved paging behavior,
allowing actions to be more
discoverable than before.
With the Magic Keyboard or a trackpad,
a context menu is presented
on secondary or right click
for a more desktop class experience.
Similarly, touch interaction on the iPhone
will display the new edit menu.
And for Mac Catalyst apps,
context menus that Mac users
are familiar with is presented.
In iOS 16, the text edit menu
gets a major power-up
with new data detectors integration.
This includes inline unit
and currency conversions,
as well as smart lookup
which displays contextual actions
depending on the selected text.
For example,
if you select an address in Safari,
you will get Maps-based actions,
like "Get Directions" or "Open in Maps,"
on top of the existing edit menu actions.
The best part is,
there is no adoption required!
These features are available
in every text edit menu,
including text interaction views,
WebKit and Safari, as well as PDFKit.
To insert actions into a text view's menu,
implement the new TextViewDelegate method
to customize the displayed menu
for text in the given range
with system provided actions.
If you don't need to customize anything,
return nil
to get the standard system menu.
There are also similar methods
on UITextFieldDelegate and UITextInput
to customize the menu there too.
Please note that inserting menu items
using UIMenuController
is now deprecated in iOS 16,
and you should instead
move to use the new methods
to add menu elements
into your text edit menus,
because where we're going,
we don't need menu controllers!
Here is an example of a text view
with some custom actions.
When a menu is presented
on some text selection,
a custom "Highlight" and
"Insert Photo" action is shown
after the system suggested actions.
Selecting the highlight action performs
a highlight on the text as expected.
Next, when the menu is presented
without any text selection
where there is nothing to highlight,
the menu only displays
the "Insert Photo" action
after the system suggested actions.
I'll show you how to add these actions
using the new API.
To insert actions into the menu
dynamically on presentation,
implement the UITextViewDelegate method
textView editMenuForTextIn range
suggestedActions
In this example,
I only want to add the "Highlight" action
when there is selected text,
so I can add the action dynamically
through this method.
The "Insert Photo" action is always valid,
so I can add it into the array
to always display the action in the menu.
Finally, I'll append my actions
to the system suggested actions,
which includes items like Cut, Copy,
and Paste, and return the menu.
And that's it!
UIEditMenuInteraction is the UIInteraction
API that powers the new edit menu.
The interaction allows you
to programmatically present
the lightweight edit menu
outside of text views
based on your own gesture,
and has native support to present
a context menu on secondary click.
In iOS 16, UIMenuController
and all of its related APIs
are replaced by the new edit menu
interaction.
To present an edit menu from scratch,
first, create the interaction
and add it to the view.
Next, configure a gesture recognizer
to present the menu from.
To ensure that the menu
only appears on direct touch
and not from indirect pointer clicks,
be sure to set
the allowedTouchTypes property
of the gesture recognizer
to be direct touch only.
Then, add the gesture recognizer
to the view.
Finally,
when the gesture recognizer fires,
determine if there is content
at the location of the gesture
that could display the menu.
Then, create an edit menu configuration
with a source point
at the gesture's location.
The source point is used to
determine performable actions
in the interaction's view
to display in the menu.
Once configured,
call presentEditMenu(with: configuration)
to show the menu.
When I right-click anywhere within
the selected "Jello there!" view,
a context menu is presented
with performable system actions
for the app's content.
Even more,
when I tap on the selected view,
the edit menu is presented
where my touch occurred,
showing the same actions
as the context menu.
This is good, but it can be better.
While it is nice that the menu appears
where the touch occurred,
it's actually blocking
the selected view's content.
Moreover, I want to insert
a new "Duplicate" action into the menu,
which is not a system default action.
Let's go back and change this.
To show the menu around the selected view,
implement the delegate method
editMenuInteraction
targetRectFor configuration
This method returns a CGRect used to
determine where to present the menu from
and is in the coordinate space
of the interaction's view.
If the method is not implemented
or a null CGRect is provided,
the menu will be presented from
the source point of the configuration.
In this case, to prevent the menu
from occluding the selected view,
return its frame.
Next, to add the "Duplicate" action,
implement editMenuInteraction
menuFor configuration suggestedActions
and append the custom action
after the system suggested actions,
similar to how you would insert actions
into a text view's menu before.
Now, when I tap again
on the selected view,
the menu no longer occludes "Jello there!"
and instead presents around it.
The new "Duplicate" action is also
included when the menu is presented,
all with just a few lines of code.
Brilliant!
For Mac Catalyst apps,
the edit menu bridges
to the familiar context menus
that users expect on the Mac
when they right click
on the interaction's view.
For iPad idiom Mac Catalyst apps,
programmatically presented edit menus
also bridge into context menus.
Please note that programmatic presentation
of the edit menu is not supported
for Mac idiom apps.
To offer seamless bridging
between different presentation styles,
UIEditMenuInteraction is built on top
of the UIMenuElement family of APIs.
These offer more flexibility
and customizability than before,
including support for submenus and images.
If this is your first time using UIMenus,
watch "Modernizing Your UI for iOS 13"
to learn more about menus and actions.
Building on top of UIMenuElement
also means that
the edit menu has access
to a wide variety of APIs,
like UIMenuSystem,
that support menus already.
The edit menu uses the existing
UIMenuSystem.context system
to build its menus.
To find out more about the menu builder,
as well as a deeper dive on responder
chain traversal and command validation,
watch "Taking your iPad apps
to the next level."
Speaking of menus, there are several
new enhancements to UIMenu in iOS 16.
UIMenu now has a preferred
element size property that allows
you to choose between different layouts
in the context menu.
The small size gives the menu
a more compact side-by-side appearance,
fitting more actions in a single row.
The medium size also displays actions
in a side-by-side appearance
but with a little more detail.
This is used by the text edit menu
to display the standard edit menu.
And finally, the large element size
gives the menu its default,
full-width appearance.
Additionally, there is a new
.keepsMenuPresented attribute
on UIMenuElement to keep menus presented
after an action is performed.
Use this attribute to allow actions
to be performed multiple times
without re-presenting the menu.
That's just the tip of the iceberg
for the new edit menu.
Extend text editing functionality
by customizing the text edit menu.
Make sure that your actions
have titles and images
so that the menus look complete
in different presentation styles.
Most importantly,
adopt the new UIEditMenuInteraction
for better customizability
and improved consistency across platforms
and different input methods.
Adding support for the new edit menu
is a great first step.
To complete the desktop class
editing experience,
I'll hand it over to James to talk about
the new system
find and replace experience.
James Magahern: Ah, there it is!
Hi, I'm James Magahern, a UIKit engineer,
and I'm here to talk about
find and replace.
New in iOS 16,
we introduced a new UI component
for finding and replacing text in apps.
It's standard across the system
and included with
many of the built-in apps,
and allows your users to flex their
muscle memory
with even more commonly used
editing shortcuts.
This is the new
find panel running on iPad.
We will automatically transition from
floating inline with the shortcut bar
when a hardware keyboard is attached,
to resting on top of the software keyboard
when used without a hardware keyboard.
On iPhone, we'll adapt
to the smaller screen size
by using a more compact layout.
Automatic dismissal, minimization,
and keyboard avoidance
are all taken care of by the system.
When running your app on a Mac,
we'll present the find panel inline
with your content,
behaving just like the AppKit find bar,
and using a familiar layout
that users expect on the Mac.
If you're using UITextView,
WKWebView, or PDFViews
to display text content in your apps,
all you need to do to get started is set
isFindInteractionEnabled to true
on the built-in find interaction.
It's that simple!
In addition, if you're using
QuickLook to display text content,
this will already be available
without any work from you.
With a hardware keyboard,
all of the standard system shortcuts
like command+F for find,
command+G for find next,
command+shift+G for find previous,
et cetera, will work just as expected.
Access to these commands are available
via the menu bar when running on a Mac.
All you need to do is make sure
the view displaying the content
can and does become first responder.
For users who are not using
a hardware keyboard,
you can invoke the find interaction
programmatically
via presentFindNavigator,
on the included find interaction property.
It might be a good idea
to make this available
via a navigation bar item, for example.
When running on a Mac, there's a couple
other things to keep in mind.
For instance, on iOS,
the find panel is presented
as part of the software keyboard
or shortcut bar.
On the Mac, we'll display it
inline with your content.
If you're installing the find interaction
on a scroll view,
we’ll automatically adjust the content
insets to accommodate the find panel,
and adapt to trait collection
changes automatically.
You should otherwise make sure
that there's enough room
to host the find panel
in your UI on macOS.
Additionally, we'll show a menu containing
a standard set of find options available
when tapping on the magnifying glass icon.
You can customize the contents
of this menu
by using the optionsMenuProvider
property on UIFindInteraction.
This will be more important
with custom implementations.
And that's all it takes if you're using
one of the built-in views
that I mentioned before.
If your app is displaying textual content
by other means,
like a completely custom view
or something like a list view, shown here,
you can still add the find interaction
to your app.
Let me show you how.
The good news about find interaction
is that you can install it
on any arbitrary view.
If you have an existing find and replace
implementation in your app,
it's a snap to bridge over
to UIFindInteraction
and take advantage of the system's UI.
If you don't already have an existing find
implementation for your custom view,
it's still super easy to get started,
especially if you've already implemented
the UITextInput protocol
in order to work with the system keyboard.
Here's how UIFindInteraction works
with custom views.
After installing UIFindInteraction
on your custom view,
set up a find interaction delegate.
The find interaction delegate,
besides being notified
about when a find session begins or ends,
is responsible for dealing out
UIFindSessions.
UIFindSession is an abstract base class
that encapsulates all of the state
for a given session,
such as the currently highlighted result.
It also services all actions
requested from the UI,
such as "go to the next result,"
or "search for this string."
If you want to manage
all of this state yourself,
you can choose to vend
a subclass of UIFindSession
from your find interaction delegate.
This is a good option
if you already have an existing
find and replace implementation
in your app,
and want to bridge it over
to the system UI.
Otherwise, it would be a much better idea
to let the system take care
of the state for you,
and instead adopt
the UITextSearching protocol
on whatever class encapsulates the content
of the document being displayed.
To do this, you would return
a UITextSearchingFindSession,
and connect it with your document class.
This is the best option
if you don't yet have
a find implementation
for your custom view.
Here's how to do this in code.
This example has a custom document class
and a custom view
which displays this document.
The UIFindInteraction
will be installed on this view,
and a UITextSearchingFindSession
will be provided with this document
as the "searchable object."
Make sure either your view controller
or your custom view
can become first responder
so keyboard shortcuts work as expected.
Create the find interaction,
and provide a session delegate
to deal out find sessions.
Here, the view controller
is the session delegate.
Then, when asked for a find session
by the interaction,
just return a new
UITextSearchingFindSession
providing your document
as the searchable object.
You will of course need to make sure
that your document class
conforms to the UITextSearching protocol.
The class which implements
the UITextSearching protocol
is responsible for actually finding
text in your document.
The system will call performTextSearch,
and hand you an aggregator object
to which you can provide results.
The aggregator works with UITextRange
to represent results in your document.
This is another abstract class
that you can use
to encapsulate whatever data
makes sense for how you store text.
For example,
this could represent a DOM range
for clients who use WebKit to render text.
The aggregator is also thread-safe,
so you can provide it results
on a background thread.
Finally, since the find interaction
doesn't know how to display results
using your custom view,
you'll also need to decorate results for
a given style when decorate() is called.
The UITextSearching find session
and protocol
also support multiplexing
across multiple visible documents
using the same interaction.
In other words,
if your app displays content
in a manner similar
to Mail's conversation view,
where each "document" in that case
is a mail message,
you can install a single find interaction
on the root level collection view
and perform a find across all documents
at the same time,
allowing your users to jump between
results in different documents with ease.
So that's all it takes to get started
with the new find interaction in iOS 16.
For system views
that display a lot of text content,
make sure to enable
isFindInteractionEnabled.
Move your existing find implementation
to UIFindInteraction.
Implement UITextSearching
and use UITextSearchingFindSession
if you don't yet have
text searching in your app.
And lastly, check and make sure
you don't have any conflicting
keyboard shortcuts in your app.
And that is what it takes to refresh your
app's editing interactions for iOS 16
and make them truly desktop class.
Try the new text edit menu in your app,
and adopt the edit menu interaction
for custom UI.
And boost productivity by making
your app's text content searchable.
I'm looking forward to finding
these great new features in your app.
Thanks for watching!
Make sure to like, comment, and subscribe.
[upbeat music]