♪ ♪
Mohammed:
Hi, I'm Mohammed from UIKit.
Thank you for joining me
for this deep dive
into building a Desktop Class iPad app.
In this video,
we'll use iPadOS 16 APIs
to update an existing iPad app
to a desktop class experience.
We'll start by using
new navigation bar API
to surface powerful functionality,
increase UI density,
and provide customizability.
Then, we'll adopt new UICollectionView
and menu API
to enable complex workflows
and quick actions on multiple selections.
And we'll round things out by enabling
the new Find and Replace experience
and enhancing text editing
with the new Edit Menu.
The app we'll be updating is
a Markdown editor built for iPadOS 15.
As we walk through each step
of the modernization process,
I'll discuss best practices
and motivations behind our choices,
giving you an idea of the factors
you should consider
while taking your own app
through a similar process.
If you'd like a bit of a primer
before getting started,
check out “Meet Desktop Class iPad”
for a breakdown of
all of UIKit's new iPadOS APIs,
and check out
“What's new in iPad app design”
for tips on how to design
the best Desktop Class iPad app possible.
All right, let's dive right in!
To start things off, let's consider
the organization of our app's controls.
Since the app is designed for iPadOS 15,
it already exposes
its most important controls
in the navigation bar
and places secondary controls
in various menus and popovers.
In iPadOS 16, UIKit formalizes
the existing navigation style
and introduces two new ones with
a denser and more customizable layout.
This allows apps to express the layout
that's most appropriate to their content
while bringing more functionality
to the forefront of the UI.
Navigator apps have a familiar
push / pop navigation model.
This is generally appropriate
for apps that display hierarchical data,
like Settings.
Browsers, like Safari or Files
are ideal for looking through
and navigating back and forth between
multiple documents or folder structures.
And Editors are great for focused viewing
or editing of individual documents.
Being a Markdown editor, this style
is the perfect choice for our app.
The editor style aligns the title
towards the leading edge of the bar,
opening up its center
for a new set of items.
This'll allow us to expose
additional functionality
that might've been hidden away
in other views or menus.
We're going to do a few things to make
as much use of this design as possible.
We'll start by customizing
the built-in back action to fit our needs.
Then we'll add a title menu
with some document info
and common document actions.
We'll also add support for renaming
via the new built-in rename UI.
And finally, we'll make previously buried
functionality more easily accessible
by bringing it to the center of the bar.
Let's start by opting into
the editor style by setting
our view controller's navigationItem's
style property to .editor.
This immediately gives us
the leading aligned title
and opens up the center area.
After that,
let's remove our trailing done button
and replace it
using the new backAction API.
This way we get a more standard look
for the action
that dismisses this view
and returns to the document picker.
Next let's figure out whether our app
would benefit from a title menu.
As the name implies,
the title menu is presented
from the navigation bar's title view.
It's a great place to show
document metadata
and surface actions
that apply to the whole document.
If your app isn't document based,
it may be a good place to surface actions
that apply to the entire view.
For our app, it makes sense
to use the document menu's header
to surface some useful information
about the document.
We'll also be able to provide
a draggable representation of the document
and easy access to sharing functionality.
And now it's time to write some code!
Our app is UIDocument backed,
so we can use the UIDocument's fileURL
to instantiate
a UIDocumentProperties object.
Next, we'll use that same URL
to create an NSItemProvider.
Then we'll use the item provider
to create a UIDragItem
which we'll return from the properties
object's dragItemsProvider.
We'll also use it to construct
a UIActivityViewController
which we'll return from the properties
object's activityViewControllerProvider.
And finally, we'll set the properties
object as the editor view controller's
navigationItem's documentProperties.
The code we just wrote results in
this document header,
which provides a quick overview
of the document
including its name, size,
and an icon representation.
Since we specified drag item
and activity view controller providers,
I can drag the icon to copy
the document outside the app
or tap the share button to bring up
an activity view controller.
In addition to displaying
the document header,
the title menu is a good place
to provide functionality
that applies to the entire document.
There are two kinds of actions
that can be displayed in this menu:
system-provided ones with pre-defined
localized titles and symbol images,
and entirely custom ones
that the app provides.
Since it comes with
some additional behavior,
let's start with the rename action.
We can add this action to our menu
by conforming
to the rename delegate protocol.
When triggered, the action presents
the bar's built-in rename UI.
First we'll assign our view controller
as its navigation item's renameDelegate.
Then, we'll implement
navigationItemDidEndRenamingWithTitle
to handle the actual renaming
of the displayed document.
This function is called
when the rename action is committed.
It's the app's responsibility to handle
this by actually renaming the document.
The API is intentionally open ended
to support any kind of data model
your app may have.
Moving on to other
system provided actions,
we'll first need to override their
functions on our editor view controller.
Here we've implemented
the duplicate and move functions.
UIKit automatically surfaces
system-provided actions,
including the rename action,
in the navigationItem's titleMenuProvider
as an array
of suggested UIMenuElements.
To include them in our title menu,
we'll just add them
to the returned menu's children.
In addition to the system-vended actions,
we can add entirely custom actions
or even whole menu hierarchies.
Here I've added an Export submenu
with export as HTML and PDF sub-actions.
And with that, tapping the title view
now brings up a menu
with the document header
and all the actions we just added.
And when I select rename,
the built-in rename UI is activated
and I'm able to rename the document.
Now that we've started establishing
the base structure of our app,
it's a good time to check in
on how things look
when we build our app with Mac catalyst.
When we run the app on a Mac,
we'll find that the editor style
with its leading aligned title
has been translated nicely.
Our back action
has also been carried over,
and when clicked,
brings up a file browser.
The system provided actions
and rename functionality
are automatically surfaced
in the app's File menu.
Note that the titleMenuProvider
is not called on Mac Catalyst,
so our custom actions are not included
in the File menu.
To expose these actions,
we would need to manually add them
to the app's main menu
using the main UIMenuSystem.
All right, let's continue
our modernization process.
We'll keep checking in on the Mac
as we make progress towards our goal.
Let's consider the opportunities
made available by the bar's center area.
The iOS 15 version of the app
has a menu that holds
a number of secondary controls and tools.
With center items, we're able to make
these tools more discoverable.
Since the center area is customizable,
we can include a large set of controls
without worrying about filling the UI
with less commonly used ones.
Each person can tailor the bar's contents
to fit their workflow.
The first step in enabling customization
is specifying a customizationIdentifier
on the navigation item.
Next, we'll define the center items
as UIBarButtonItemGroups.
Groups are an existing concept
that's been extended to UINavigationBar
and enhanced to support
customization in iOS 16.
This screenshot shows the set of
center items we'd like to show by default.
The synchronize scrolling button
all the way on the left
provides an important function
that can't be reached
by any other means,
so it makes sense to place it
in a fixed group
using UIBarButtonItem's
new creatingFixedGroup() function.
Fixed groups are not customizable
and cannot be moved by the user.
The add link button, on the other hand,
doesn't provide critical functionality,
and the same task can be achieved
by typing link tags in the editor,
so we'll use creatingOptionalGroup
to create a completely customizable item.
And we'll give it a unique
customizationIdentifier
so the customization is persisted
across app launches.
We'll follow a similar process
to define the remaining items
in the default set,
then move on to lower priority items
that don't need to be available
by default.
One such item is the text format group,
which includes the bold,
italics, and underline items.
It's not important enough
to show by default,
but we want it in the customization
popover so it can be dragged into the bar.
To achieve this,
we'll use UIBarButtonItemGroup's
optionalGroup initializer with
isInDefaultCustomization set to false.
We'll also be sure to give the group
a representative item
so it has a title in the popover,
and has a compact representation
that it can be collapsed to
when the bar runs out of space.
Back on the iPad,
the center items we defined
show up in the center of the bar.
If I click the newly added More button,
a menu shows up
with a Customize Toolbar action.
And if I click that,
the customization mode is activated.
The sync scrolling button that we marked
as fixed is de-emphasized and static,
while all the other items lift and shake
to show that they're customizable.
Optional items like the Format group
show up in the popover
and can be dragged into the bar.
When we run the app on a Mac,
we find that the center items
have been converted to fully customizable
macOS toolbar buttons.
Before we move on, let's go back to
the iPad for a minute and resize the app.
Now that we have less space available
in the toolbar,
the center items are no longer visible.
UIKit automatically handles
showing and hiding center items
in response to the available space.
Any items that don't fit
are displayed in the overflow menu.
Standard bar button items
are automatically converted
to their menu representation,
but we're also able to provide
a custom menu representation if we like.
Since UIKit has no insight
into the purpose of a custom view item,
our slider item
isn't automatically translated.
We'll need to manually
specify a menu representation.
Here's our slider item.
It's a single bar button item
with a custom view,
wrapped in an optional bar button group.
To provide the core functionality
of the slider,
we'll define the menu representation
as a UIMenu with Decrease,
Reset, and Increase actions.
Using UIMenu's
new preferredElementSize property,
we can give the menu a more
compact side by side appearance.
And using the
new keepsMenuPresented attribute,
we can keep the menu presented
after each action is performed,
allowing the font size to be changed
multiple times
without dismissing
and re-presenting the menu.
Let's run this on the iPad again.
Now when we bring up the overflow menu,
the slider appears as an inline menu
with three side-by-side actions,
covering the full functionality
of the slider.
Since the small element size
doesn't exist on the Mac,
the actions will appear
as standard macOS menu items.
And that's it for UI organization
and customization.
Next, let's look into speeding up
some workflows in the app
using new collection view and menu API.
Our app has a table of contents sidebar
that can be used
to quickly navigate the document
or take action on top level tags.
Prior to iOS 16,
adding the ability to edit multiple items
would've likely meant implementing
a distinct edit mode,
with bulk actions relegated
to buttons in a toolbar.
iOS 16 introduces a new design
for multi-item menus
with a flock of items that clearly
communicates which items the menu affects
and provides a direct transition
to a multi-item drag.
In a desktop class iPad app,
this new menu design is best paired
with a lighter weight selection style.
"Lightweight" here
means selecting multiple items
without kicking the collection view
into an edit mode
or making significant changes
to the app's UI.
We can achieve this and enable
keyboard focus using existing API.
First, we'll set
allowsMultipleSelection to true.
Then we'll enable keyboard focus
by setting allowsFocus to true.
And we'll allow focus to drive selection
by setting selectionFollowsFocus to true.
If we run this on our iPad,
we immediately notice
that as each item is added
to the selection,
it still fires its selection action,
causing the editor view to scroll.
Let's head back to our code and
figure out what's going on.
There it is!
The code in didSelectItemAtIndexPath
tries to disallow scrolling
while in edit mode
by checking
the collectionView's isEditing property.
Now that we allow multiple
selection outside of edit mode,
this code runs for every selection.
We can fix this using a new
UICollectionViewDelegate method.
We'll implement
performPrimaryActionForItemAtIndexPath
and just move our scrolling code
to this new function.
Since this function is only called
when a single item is tapped
and the collection view is not editing,
we no longer need the check for edit mode.
And since we don't have
any selection related behavior,
we can remove our implementation
of did select item at indexPath.
Back on the iPad,
selecting multiple items no longer scrolls
to the corresponding text
in the editor view.
With that done,
let's actually add support for the menu.
In iPadOS 16, UICollectionViewDelegate's
existing single item menu method
is deprecated.
Its replacement supports displaying menus
for anywhere from zero to many items.
The number of items in the given
indexPaths array
depends on how many items are selected,
and where the menu is invoked.
If the array is empty, then the menu was
invoked in the blank space between cells.
If it has a single indexPath,
then it was invoked on an item
that is either deselected
or is the sole selected one.
If it has more than one item,
then the menu was invoked
on an item that is part
of a multiple selection.
If I head back to the iPad,
select the top four items again,
and two-finger click
one of the selected items,
a new multi-item menu comes up.
When I do the same thing on a Mac,
a ring is drawn around the selected cells
to highlight them.
With multi-item menus done,
let's look into enhancing
the text editing experience
using the new Find and Replace
and edit menu features.
Our app uses a UITextView for its editor
and doesn't require
any custom Find and Replace behavior,
so all we need to do
to enable the default system functionality
is set the text view's
isFindInteractionEnabled property to true.
With that set,
hitting Command+F while editing text
brings up the Find and Replace UI.
Adding custom actions to the text view's
edit menu doesn't take much,
and can enable
some great quick editing features.
We'll just implement
the new UITextViewDelegate method
edit menu for text in range
suggested actions.
In the implementation,
we can construct and return a UIMenu
that combines custom actions,
like this Hide action,
with the system menu.
And this is the result. W
hen I select some text
and bring up the edit menu,
both our custom actions and
the system-provided ones are displayed.
For more information about
Find and Replace and the edit menu,
check out “Adopt desktop class
editing interactions.”
And that's it!
With these few changes,
we've taken some great basic steps
towards making our app desktop class
and translating it seamlessly to the Mac.
Use the APIs offered in iPadOS 16
to take your own app
through a similar process.
Start by choosing a navigation style
that fits your app.
Enhance document workflows with
document properties and the title menu.
And surface important functionality and
provide customizability with center items.
Enable quickly acting on multiple
items with multi-item menus.
And enhance your app's text editing
experience using Find and Replace
and the new edit menu.
Whether you're building a new app
or updating an existing one,
I can't wait to use the apps you build
with these new tools.
Thanks for watching.