♪ ♪
Tommy Pauly: Hi, I'm Tommy Pauly,
and I'm excited to share how your apps
and websites can work together
with Apple and fraud prevention providers
across the industry
to reduce the need for CAPTCHAs.
Today, I'll talk about:
Private Access Tokens,
and how they can be powerful tools
for fraud prevention;
how to enable support
for Private Access Tokens
on the servers you operate;
and, how you can use these tokens
in your apps.
To introduce Private Access Tokens,
I'll start by explaining why
CAPTCHAs are used in the first place.
Chances are, if you've signed up
for a new account on a website,
or tried to sign in
with an existing account,
you've encountered CAPTCHAs like these
at some point.
Sometimes,
a CAPTCHA is just a button to press,
but others can be a challenge to fill out.
You likely don't enjoy being
interrupted by these.
I certainly don't.
The reason these experiences exist
is to prevent fraudulent activity.
If you run a server, you don't want it
to be overwhelmed by fraud.
Some attempts to create accounts
or buy products
come from legitimate users.
But other attempts
may be from attackers or bots.
Unfortunately,
the common tools to prevent fraud,
like CAPTCHAs,
often make it harder
for people to use your app or website.
Finding the right balance
between a good experience
and preventing fraud is a challenge.
CAPTCHAs often lead to a slower
and more complex user experience.
By trying to prevent attacks,
you may also lose valuable customers.
CAPTCHAs can also pose a privacy risk.
In order to determine
if a client is trusted
and can get an easier CAPTCHA,
servers often rely on tracking
or fingerprinting clients
by using their IP address.
This kind of tracking is at odds
with the direction of internet privacy
being taken by Safari,
Mail Privacy Protection,
and iCloud Private Relay.
And CAPTCHAs can pose a serious problem
for accessibility.
By trying to prevent access from bots,
they also block out real humans
who have disabilities
or language barriers.
There is a better way.
Even if someone is interacting
with your website for the first time,
if they are loading it through an app
or browser like Safari,
they've already performed many actions
that are hard for a bot to imitate.
First, they have an iPhone, iPad, or Mac,
and they've unlocked the device
with their password,
Touch ID, or Face ID.
They're almost always signed in
to the device with their Apple ID.
And they've launched a code-signed app.
This information can help your servers
trust legitimate clients
and prevent fraud,
without relying on CAPTCHAs,
and without compromising privacy
by tracking clients.
Private Access Tokens
are what allow your servers
to automatically trust clients,
new in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura.
Before explaining how these tokens work,
I'm going to show them in action.
You're going to love this.
I want to read an article
on the Financial Times website.
I'm very excited
about these cinnamon buns.
And I've loaded the site
on two different phones:
one running iOS 15
and one running iOS 16,
which supports Private Access Tokens.
Starting with the iOS 15 phone,
I click Sign In,
and fill out my account and password.
But then, I get hit with a CAPTCHA.
I need to type in the letters
before being able to read that article.
When I do the exact same thing
on the iOS 16 phone
that supports Private Access Tokens,
I get right through.
This is going to save a lot of people,
a lot of time,
and your customers
will appreciate being trusted.
Private Access Tokens let servers
avoid CAPTCHAs, like you just saw,
by using technology being standardized
in the IETF Privacy Pass working group.
Apple is working with companies
across the industry to make this possible.
Using this protocol,
servers can request tokens
using a new HTTP authentication method,
PrivateToken.
These tokens use RSA Blind Signatures
to cryptographically sign the fact
that a client was able to pass
an attestation check.
These signatures are "unlinkable",
which means that servers
that receive tokens
can only check that they are valid,
but they cannot discover client identities
or recognize clients over time.
Here's how the protocol works.
First, when the iOS or macOS client
accesses a server over HTTP,
the server sends back a challenge using
the PrivateToken authentication scheme.
This specifies a token issuer
that is trusted by the server.
When the client needs to fetch a token,
it contacts an iCloud attester
and sends a token request.
This token request is "blinded"
so it can't be linked
to the server challenge.
The attester performs device attestation,
using certificates stored
in the device's Secure Enclave,
and verifies
that the account is in good standing.
This attester
can also perform rate-limiting,
to recognize if the client device
is following normal patterns,
or may have been compromised
or used as part of a farm of devices.
If the client can be validated,
the attester sends the request
for a new token to the issuer.
When the token issuer gets the request,
it doesn't know anything about the client.
But since it trusts the iCloud attester,
it signs the token.
The client then receives the signed token,
and transforms it
in a process called "unblinding"
so the original server can verify it.
And finally, the client presents
the signed token to the server.
The server can check
that this token is signed by the Issuer,
but it cannot use the token
to identify or recognize the client.
So how can you take advantage
of this technology on your servers?
There are three steps to adopting
Private Access Tokens on your server.
First, you'll need to select
a token issuer.
Second, your server will need to send out
HTTP authentication challenges
when you want to validate clients.
And third, your server will need
to validate the tokens sent by clients.
The token issuer you select
is a trusted provider
that can sign tokens
that your server validates.
This may be your existing
CAPTCHA provider,
your web hosting service,
or your content delivery network,
also called a CDN.
In the iOS 16 and macOS Ventura betas,
there are two token issuers
that you can already start testing with.
Fastly and Cloudflare are two CDNs
that have been developing
the Privacy Pass standards,
and have already made
their issuer services available.
Other CAPTCHA providers,
web hosting services, and CDNs
will also be able to run token issuers
that will work with Apple devices.
Issuers will be able to sign up
later this year at register.apple.com.
It's important that the use
of a specific token issuer
doesn't become a way to identify
what websites a client is accessing–
that would be a problem for privacy.
So each token issuer needs to be
a large service
that work with
at least hundreds of servers.
When a client accesses your server,
you can request tokens by sending
an HTTP authentication challenge
with the PrivateToken scheme.
To do this, you have two options:
Either you can work with your existing
CAPTCHA or fraud prevention provider
to build the challenge into their scripts,
so it is handled automatically for you,
or you can choose to send these challenges
directly from your server.
If you're doing this
as part of your website,
the challenge must come from
a first-party domain–
a subdomain of your main URL
and not a separate third-party domain
embedded on your site.
When clients return tokens to you,
you'll need to check their validity
using your issuer's public key.
You may also want to enforce checks
to prevent replay attacks,
where a client could try to present
a token multiple times.
Tokens are meant to be one-time use only.
You can prevent replay attacks
either by remembering
what tokens were sent previously,
or requiring that tokens sign
a unique value sent in your challenge.
Your site still needs to work
with legacy clients
that won't respond
to this authentication challenge.
So it's important that the authentication
should not block your main page load,
but instead be treated
as an optional way to trust a client.
Web servers that are accessed through
Safari and WebKit will work automatically,
but you can also use Private Access Tokens
within your app directly.
Private Access Tokens require iOS 16
or macOS Ventura
on a device that has
an Apple ID signed in.
This Apple ID is only used
for attestation,
and is not shared with the servers
that receive tokens.
Within your app, tokens are available
if you use WebKit or URLSession
to contact your servers using HTTP.
Then anytime your app receives
a challenge while it's in the foreground,
the system will automatically send a token
as authentication.
If you're using URLSession,
you don't need to do anything explicitly
to make Private Access Tokens work.
URLSession will automatically respond
to challenges
using the PrivateToken HTTP
authentication scheme.
However, if there's an error
in fetching a token,
such as if your app
isn't in the foreground
or the device doesn't have
an Apple ID signed in,
your app will receive
the 401 HTTP response
that included the token challenge.
This allows your app to know
that the token challenge was received,
and provides a chance to handle the error
correctly for your use case.
Make apps and websites better
experiences for everyone
by avoiding CAPTCHAs whenever
Private Access Tokens are available.
Go and enable your servers to
send token challenges and validate tokens.
And, in your apps,
use URLSession or WebKit
to automatically support
Private Access Tokens.
I'm looking forward to the CAPTCHA-free
experiences you will build.