♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hip music ♪
♪
Hi, I am Vidhi Goel,
and in this video,
I will talk about how to reduce
networking delays in your apps
and make them more responsive.
First, I will explain why
reducing latency is crucial
in making your apps responsive.
Next, I will go over a list
of things that you can do
in your app
and on your server to get rid of
unnecessary delays.
Finally, I will show what
you can do to reduce delays
in the network itself.
Network latency
is the time it takes for data
to get from
one endpoint to another.
It determines how quickly
content can be delivered
to your app.
All apps that use networking
can be affected
by slow network transactions
that result in
a poor app experience.
For example,
video calls can sometimes freeze
or become laggy,
which can interrupt meetings.
To address this,
people often call up
their service provider
to upgrade their bandwidth,
and yet,
the problem still exists.
To get to the root cause
of this problem,
you need to understand
how your app's packets
travel in a network.
When your app or framework
requests data from a server,
packets are sent
out by the networking stack.
It is often assumed
that the packets go directly
to the server with no delays
in the network.
But, in reality,
the slowest link of the network
usually has a large queue
of packets to process.
So, the packet from your app
actually waits behind
this large queue
until the packets ahead of it
are processed.
This queuing at the slowest link
increases the duration
of each round trip between
your app and your server.
This problem is aggravated when
it takes multiple round trips
to get the first response
for your app's request.
For example, the time to get
the first response packet
when using TLS 1.2 over TCP
is the duration
of each round trip
multiplied by four trips.
Given that each round-trip time
is already inflated
by queuing in the network,
the resulting total time
is simply too long.
There are two factors
that multiply together
to determine
your app's responsiveness:
the duration of each round trip
and the number of round trips.
Reducing these will lower
your app's latency,
and increase your app's
responsiveness.
There was a study
examining the impact
of increasing bandwidth
versus decreasing latency
on page load time.
In the first test,
latency is kept fixed
and bandwidth is increased
incrementally from 1 to 10Mbps.
At first, increasing the
bandwidth from 1 to 2Mbps
reduces page load time
by almost 40 percent,
which is great.
But after 4Mbps,
each incremental increase
results in almost no improvement
in the page load time.
This is why apps can be slow
even after upgrading
to Gigabit Internet.
On the other hand, the results
for the latency test show
that for every 20 millisecond
decrease in latency,
there is a linear improvement
in page load time.
And these results apply
to all network activity
in your apps.
Now, I will go over a few
simple actions you can take
to reduce latency and make
your app more responsive.
You can reduce
your app's latency significantly
by adopting modern protocols
such as IPv6, TLS 1.3
and HTTP/3.
And all you need to do
is use URLSession
and Network.framework APIs
in your app
and these protocols
will be used automatically
once they are enabled
on your server.
Since its rollout,
we have seen a constant increase
in HTTP/3 usage,
and within just a year,
20 percent of web traffic
already uses HTTP/3,
and it continues to grow.
Comparing Safari traffic
for different HTTP versions,
HTTP/3 is the fastest
of them all.
HTTP/3 requests take
a little over half the time
as compared to HTTP/1,
when looking at median
request completion time
as a multiple
of round-trip time.
This means your app's requests
will complete much faster.
When a device moves
from Wi-Fi to cellular,
it takes time to reestablish
new connections
and that can make
your application stall.
Using connection migration
eliminates those stalls.
To opt in, set the
multipathServiceType property
to .handover on your URLSession
configuration,
or on your NWParameters.
Enable this option and make sure
it works with your app.
If you design your own protocol
that uses UDP directly,
iOS 16 and macOS Ventura
introduce a better way
to send datagrams.
QUIC datagrams provide
many benefits over plain UDP,
the most important being
that QUIC datagrams
react to congestion
in the network
which keeps the round-trip time
low and reduces packet loss.
To opt in on the client,
set isDatagram to true
on your QUIC options
and set the maximum datagram
frame size you want to use.
After creating
the datagram flow,
you can send and receive on it
just like any other QUIC stream.
Now you know
what to do in your app
to reduce latency.
Next, I will explain
how servers impact
your app's responsiveness.
Despite often running
on top-of-the-line hardware,
it is possible that your server
actually becomes the reason
for slowness in your app.
We introduced the network
quality tool in macOS Monterey,
and you can use this tool
to measure buffer bloat in
your service provider's network
as well as on your server.
You need to configure your
server to act as a destination
for the network quality tool.
Once you have done that,
run the networkQuality tool,
first against
Apple's default server
and then against
your own configured server.
If the tool scores well
using the default server,
but not so well when talking
to your own server,
there may be room to improve
the responsiveness
of your server.
Now, I will show you an example
where we used this technique
to improve something that all
of you are doing right now --
streaming video.
You may have had the experience
where you skip ahead
to a different place in a video
and you end up waiting
a long time while it rebuffers.
So, we investigated
the reason for this slowness
in random access.
We used the network quality tool
to test the behavior
of a streaming server
and we found that the
responsiveness score was poor.
On the right side,
I streamed a WWDC video.
Then, I skipped ahead
in the video.
The screen
didn't display anything
while the video rebuffered.
After a few seconds,
the video showed up.
With the help of detailed output
from the network quality tool
on macOS,
we found that there was
huge queuing at the server.
So we took a look at
the server configuration.
Specifically we looked at TCP,
TLS, and HTTP buffer sizes,
which were configured to 4MB,
256KB, and 4MB, respectively.
The buffers were huge
because RAM is plentiful.
But just because
some buffering is good,
doesn't always mean
that more buffering is better.
Our responsiveness measurements
highlighted this exact issue --
a newly generated packet
was queued behind stale data
in these large buffers,
and this created a lot
of additional delay
in delivering
the most recent packet.
So, we reduced the buffer size
to 256KB for HTTP,
16KB for TLS,
and 128KB for TCP.
This is the config file
for Apache Traffic Server
which shows the options
that were configured.
TCP not-sent low-water mark
was set to 128KB
along with other options that
were enabled to lower buffering.
For TLS, we enabled
dynamic record sizes
and for HTTP/2,
we reduced the low-water mark
and buffer block size.
We recommend
using these configurations
for your Apache Traffic Server,
and if you are using
a different web server,
look for its equivalent options.
After making these changes,
we ran the network
quality tool again.
And this time we got
a high RPM score!
On the right,
I streamed the same video,
but this time
when I skipped ahead,
the video resumed instantly.
By getting rid of unnecessary
queuing at the server,
we made random access
much more responsive.
Regardless of how your app
uses networking,
these changes on your server can
make your app more responsive
and deliver
a better user experience.
That's how to improve your app
and update your server.
There is a third factor that
affects responsiveness greatly;
the network itself.
Apple introduced the
network quality tool in iOS 15
and macOS Monterey.
Since then, others have used
the same methodology
to develop
network quality tests.
Waveform has launched
a Bufferbloat test.
There's an open source
implementation
of the responsiveness test,
written in Go.
And Ookla has added
a responsiveness measurement
to their Speedtest app.
Ookla's app shows
round trip time in milliseconds,
and if you divide 60,000
by that number,
you get the number of
round trips per minute, or RPM.
You can use these tools
to measure
how well your own network
is performing.
The best way to understand
delays in a network
is with a delay-sensitive
application.
So, I will show you
my screen sharing experience
to a remote machine.
I set up network conditions
to mimic a representative
access network,
with traffic from other devices
sharing that network.
Here, I logged on to my remote
machine using Screen Sharing.
I clicked on different
Finder menus
but the display of each menu
was very sluggish.
To check how much
this interaction was delayed,
I launched an app that displays
time on my local machine,
and I launched the same app
on my remote machine.
Even though time on these
computers is synchronized,
my remote screen
didn't update regularly
and showed time delayed
by a few seconds.
The reason
for this delayed update
was the presence
of a large queue
at the slowest link
of the network
and packets from
the Screen Sharing app
were stuck in this large queue.
To solve this queuing issue,
Apple is working with
the networking community
on a new technology called L4S.
It is available as a beta
in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura.
L4S reduces
queuing delay significantly
and also achieves
zero congestion loss.
To keep a consistently
short queue,
the network explicitly
signals congestion
instead of dropping packets,
and the sender adjusts
its sending rate
based on the congestion feedback
from the network.
This makes it possible to keep
very low queuing in the network
without any packet loss,
and that will make your app
highly responsive.
Now, let's look at how L4S
improved Screen Sharing.
Here, I used the same machines
and the same network
except this time,
I enabled L4S.
When I clicked on
different Finder menus,
they opened immediately.
I launched the Time app
on both the machines.
And now, time on both
the remote screen
and the local machine
is almost perfectly in sync.
This technology is not just
for screen sharing.
L4S improves
all of today's apps,
and opens the door
for future apps
that wouldn't even
be possible today.
This chart plots the observed
average round trip time
of packets from
the Screen Sharing app
which was running
concurrently with traffic
from other devices
sharing the same network.
Comparing classic queuing
versus L4S
shows that there
is a massive reduction
in round trip time with L4S.
This is the primary reason
for the dramatic improvement
in my screen-sharing experience.
Test your app that uses
HTTP/3 or QUIC with L4S.
You can enable L4S in iOS 16
inside Developer settings
or on macOS Ventura
via a defaults write.
To test using a Linux server,
your QUIC implementation
needs to support accurate ECN
and a scalable congestion
control algorithm.
To ensure that you are ready
when L4S-capable networks
are deployed,
test your app
for compatibility with L4S,
and provide feedback with any
issues you might encounter.
Now you know that
reducing latency is crucial
to improve your app's
responsiveness.
So, adopt HTTP/3 and QUIC,
to reduce the number
of round trips
and for faster delivery
of content to your app.
Eliminate unnecessary queuing
on your server
to provide a more
responsive interaction.
Test your app's compatibility
with L4S by enabling it
in Developer settings
and provide feedback.
And finally,
talk to your server provider
about enabling L4S support.
Thanks for watching!
♪