♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello, I'm Sara Frederixon,
an engineer on the Health app,
and I'm here to talk to you
about using SwiftUI with UIKit.
Like many of you,
I work on an existing UIKit app.
For me, this is the Health app.
The Health app
has many visualizations
to help people understand
their health data,
but building these views
can be quite complex.
I've been interested
in taking advantage of SwiftUI,
so I worked with the UIKit
and SwiftUI teams
to learn how to integrate
both into the same app.
In this video,
I will teach you how easy it is
to start using SwiftUI
in your own UIKit apps.
First I'll cover the existing
UIHostingController,
which has some new updates
that add even more flexibility.
Next I'll dive into populating
SwiftUI views
with data that already exist
in your app,
and how to ensure
the SwiftUI views update
when that data changes.
Then, I'll talk about
some exciting new functionality
that lets you build
UICollectionView
and UITableView cells
using SwiftUI.
Finally, I'll walk through
the unique aspects of data flow
with collection and table views
when you're using SwiftUI
inside cells.
Let's get started by talking
about UIHostingController.
UIHostingController
is a UIViewController
that contains a SwiftUI
view hierarchy.
You can use a hosting controller
anywhere you can use
a view controller in UIKit.
This makes UIHostingController
an easy way
to start using SwiftUI.
Let's examine how
a hosting controller works.
A hosting controller
is a view controller,
which means it has a UIView
stored in its view property.
And inside that view
is where your SwiftUI content
is rendered.
Let's go through an example of
how to use a hosting controller.
Here, we create a HeartRateView,
a SwiftUI view.
We then create a hosting
controller with HeartRateView
as its root view,
and present it.
UIHostingController works with
all of the UIKit
view controller APIs.
Let's go through
another example.
We have the same HeartRateView
and hosting controller
as before.
Here we add
the hosting controller
as a child view controller.
Then we can position and size
the hosting controller's view.
When your SwiftUI content inside
UIHostingController changes,
it may cause the view
to need to be resized.
New in iOS 16,
UIHostingController
allows you to enable
automatic updates
of the view controller's
preferred content size
and the view's intrinsic
content size.
You can enable this using
the new sizingOptions property
on UIHostingController.
Let's go through an example.
To start, we make
our HeartRateView,
and create
the hostingController.
We use the new sizingOptions API
to tell the hostingController
to automatically update
its preferredContentSize.
Then, we set
the modalPresentationStyle
to popover.
Using the new sizingOptions API
ensures that the popover
is always sized appropriately
to fit the SwiftUI content.
Now that you're familiar
with UIHostingController,
let's talk about
how to get data into SwiftUI
from other parts
of your UIKit app,
and ensure that
your SwiftUI views update
when that data changes.
Here's a diagram
of your UIKit app,
It contains
an existing model layer
that owns and manages
your app's data model objects.
Your app also contains
a number of view controllers.
If you want start using SwiftUI,
you'll need a hosting controller
with a SwiftUI view inside
one of the view controllers.
You will want to populate
this SwiftUI view with data
that is still owned
by your existing model layer.
In this section, we're going
to focus on how to bridge data
across the boundary
between UIKit and SwiftUI.
SwiftUI offers a variety
of data flow primitives
to help you manage the data
in your app.
Let's go through
the different options.
To store data that is created
and owned by a SwiftUI view,
SwiftUI provides the @State and
@StateObject property wrappers.
Since we're focused on data
owned outside of SwiftUI,
these property wrappers
aren't the right choice.
So, I'm not going
to cover these in this video.
Watch
"Data Essentials in SwiftUI"
to learn more about data
owned by a SwiftUI view.
One way to handle data
external to SwiftUI
is to pass values directly
when you initialize your views.
Because you are
just passing raw data
that is not owned
or managed by SwiftUI,
you are responsible for manually
updating the UIHostingController
when the data changes.
Let's go through an example.
Here is a SwiftUI view
named HeartRateView.
This view has
a single property --
the heart rate beatsPerMinute
stored as an integer --
and it displays
the value as text.
We're displaying
this HeartRateView
by embedding
a UIHostingController
inside an existing
view controller
named HeartRateViewController.
We save a reference
to the hosting controller
so we can update
its root view later.
Remember, the SwiftUI
HeartRateView is a value type,
so storing it by itself
would create a separate copy,
and wouldn't allow us
to update the UI.
The HeartRateViewController
owns the data
used to populate
the HeartRateView.
This data is stored
in the beatsPerMinute property,
and when the beatsPerMinute
value changes,
we call a method
to update the view.
Inside of the update method,
we create a new HeartRateView
using the latest
beatsPerMinute value,
and then assign that view
as the rootView
of our hosting controller.
This is a simple way to get data
from UIKit into SwiftUI,
but it requires manually
updating the rootView
of the hosting controller
any time the data changes.
Let's go through some other
SwiftUI data primitives
to make these updates
happen automatically.
The @ObservedObject
and @EnvironmentObject
property wrappers
allow you to reference
an external model object
that conforms to
the ObservableObject protocol.
When you use
these property wrappers,
SwiftUI automatically updates
your view when the data changes.
We're going to focus on the
@ObservedObject property wrapper
in this video,
but you can learn more about
EnvironmentObject in the
"Data Essentials in SwiftUI"
video mentioned earlier.
Let's go through how to create
an @ObservedObject.
The first step
is to take a model object
that is owned by an existing
part of your app
and make it conform to
the ObservableObject protocol.
Next, we store the model
as an @ObservedObject property
in our SwiftUI view.
Connecting the ObservableObject
to SwiftUI allows it
to update the view when
one of its properties change.
Let's go back to our
HeartRateView example
and wire this up.
Our app has a class named
HeartData
that contains the property
beatsPerMinute.
We make it an ObservableObject
by conforming to the protocol.
Then we add
the @Published property wrapper
to the beatsPerMinute property.
This property wrapper
is what triggers SwiftUI
to update our views on changes.
In the HeartRateView,
we store the HeartData
in a property annotated with
the @ObservedObject
property wrapper.
In the body of the view,
we display the beatsPerMinute
directly from the HeartData.
Now, let's use these together
in our view controller.
Here is our
HeartRateViewController.
It stores the HeartData
ObservableObject in a property.
Because this property
is not inside a SwiftUI view,
we don't need to use
a property wrapper here.
The HeartRateViewController
is initialized
with a HeartData instance,
which is used to create
a HeartRateView
that becomes the rootView
of the hosting controller.
The diagram illustrates
how this comes together.
We fetch the current
HeartData instance,
which contains a heart rate
of 78 beat per minute.
Then we create a new
HeartRateViewController
with that HeartData instance,
which wires it up
to the SwiftUI HeartRateView.
After a few seconds,
when the next heart rate
data sample arrives,
the heart data's beatsPerMinute
property is updated to 94.
Because this changes
a published property
on an ObservableObject,
the HeartRateView
is automatically updated
to display the new value.
We no longer need to manually
update the hosting controller
when the data changes.
This is why ObservableObject
is a great way to bridge data
from UIKit to SwiftUI.
Next, let's talk about
using SwiftUI in collection view
and table view cells.
New in iOS 16
is UIHostingConfiguration,
which lets you harness
the power of SwiftUI
inside your existing UIKit,
collection, and table views.
UIHostingConfiguration
makes it easy to implement
custom cells using SwiftUI,
without needing to worry
about embedding an extra view
or view controller.
Before we dive deeper
on UIHostingConfiguration,
let's review
cell configurations in UIKit.
Cell configurations
are a modern way
to define the content, styling,
and behavior of cells in UIKit.
Unlike a UIView
or UIViewController,
a configuration is just
a lightweight struct.
It's inexpensive to create.
A configuration
is only a description
of a cell's appearance,
so it needs to be applied
to a cell to have an effect.
Configurations are composable,
and work with both
UICollectionView
and UITableView cells.
For more details, you can watch
"Modern cell configuration."
With that in mind, let's dive in
and start using
UIHostingConfiguration!
UIHostingConfiguration
is a content configuration
that is initialized
with a SwiftUI ViewBuilder.
That means we can start
writing SwiftUI code
to create views
directly inside it.
In order to render
the hosting configuration,
we set it to the
contentConfiguration property
of the UICollectionView
or UITableView cell.
Let's start writing
some SwiftUI code
in this hosting configuration to
build a custom heart rate cell.
We'll start by creating a label
with the text "Heart Rate"
and the image of a heart.
SwiftUI views
receive default styling
based on the context
they are used in.
But we can start
customizing the styling
using standard
SwiftUI view modifiers.
Let's make the image
and text pink with a bold font,
by adding the foregroundStyle
and font modifiers to our label.
Since we're just writing
regular SwiftUI code,
we can factor out our code
into a standalone view
anytime we want.
Here, we create
a new SwiftUI view
named HeartRateTitleView,
moved the code we had
into its body,
and then used
that HeartRateTitleView
in the hosting configuration.
As shown in the cell,
it produces
the exact same result.
Now we can start
adding more views
inside the HeartRateTitleView.
I've put the label inside
of an HStack with a spacer,
then added the current time
in a Text view next to it.
That's looking
pretty good so far.
Let's add some more content
to this custom cell
below the HeartRateTitleView.
To do this,
we'll insert a VStack
inside the hosting
configuration
so we can add more content
below the HeartRateTitleView.
Then we'll put
two Text views together
in a HStack to display 90 BPM
and then apply a few modifiers
to style them the way we want.
Just like we did before
with the HeartRateTitleView,
we can move this new code
into its own SwiftUI view.
Now the same code
is extracted into the body
of the HeartRateBPMView.
Our cell is looking great,
but I have an idea
for another thing we could add.
New in iOS 16 is
the Swift Charts framework,
which lets you visualize data
with beautiful graphs
in only a few lines of code.
Let's try using it to display
a small line chart
right inside the cell.
Using the new Chart view,
we create a small line chart
that visualizes
recent heart rate samples
and display that next
to the BPM view in the cell.
To generate the chart,
we pass in a collection
of heart rate samples,
and draw a LineMark that
connects all of the samples.
We can add a circle symbol
to indicate each sample
on the line
and apply
a pink foreground style,
to tint the chart to match
the HeartRateTitleView.
We're only scratching
the surface of what you can do
with the new
Swift Charts framework,
so be sure to check out
the video "Hello Swift Charts"
to learn more about it.
Not only does our finished
heart rate cell look awesome,
but it was easy to make
in just a couple of minutes.
That's how easy it is
to start building custom cells
with UIHostingConfiguration
and SwiftUI.
Let's talk about
four special features
that UIHostingConfiguration
supports.
By default,
the root-level SwiftUI content
is inset from the edges
of the cell,
based on the cell's layout
margins in UIKit.
This ensures
that the cell content
is properly aligned with
the content of adjacent cells
and other UI elements,
such as the navigation bar.
Sometimes, you may want to use
different margins,
or have the content extend
to the edges of the cell.
For these cases, you can change
the default margins
by using the margins modifier
on UIHostingConfiguration.
If you want to customize
a cell's background appearance
using SwiftUI, you can use
the background modifier
on the UIHostingConfiguration.
There are a few
key differences between
a UIHostingConfiguration's
background and its content.
The background is hosted
at the the back of the cell,
underneath your SwiftUI content
in the cell's content view.
Additionally,
while content is typically
inset from the cell's edges,
backgrounds extend
edge to edge in the cell.
Finally, when using
self-sizing cells,
only the cell content influences
the size of the cell.
Next, let's examine
two more special features
of UIHostingConfiguration
that you can use
when you have a cell
inside a collection view list
or table view.
In a list, the separator
below the cell
is automatically aligned
to the SwiftUI text
in your hosting configuration
by default.
In this example, notice how the
leading edge of the separator
is inset past the image
so that it aligns with the text
in the cell.
If you need to align
the separator
to a different SwiftUI view
in your hosting configuration,
use the alignmentGuide
modifier.
When inside a collection view
list or table view,
you can configure swipe actions
for a row directly with SwiftUI.
By creating your buttons inside
the swipeActions modifier,
you'll be able to swipe the cell
to reveal and perform
your custom actions.
Download the sample code
for this video
to find a complete example.
When defining swipe actions,
make sure your buttons
perform their actions
using a stable identifier
for the item represented.
Do not use the index path,
as it may change
while the cell is visible,
causing the swipe actions
to act on the wrong item.
When you're using
UIHostingConfiguration
in a cell, keep in mind
that the cell interactions
such as tap handling,
highlighting,
and selection
will still be handled
by the collection view
or table view.
If you need to customize
your SwiftUI views
for any of these
UIKit cell states,
you can create
your hosting configuration
inside of the cell's
configurationUpdateHandler,
and use the state provided
in your SwiftUI code.
The configurationUpdateHandler
runs again
any time
the cell's state changes,
creating a new
UIHostingConfiguration
for the new state
and applying it to the cell.
In this example, we use the
state to add a checkmark image
when the cell is selected.
Now that you're familiar
with UIHostingConfiguration,
let's discuss how to manage
data flow from your model layer
to a UICollectionView
or UITableView
filled with cells using SwiftUI.
Our goal is to build
this list of medical conditions.
In this example,
we're using a UICollectionView,
but everything we discuss
applies equally to UITableView.
Let's go through
the components involved.
Our app has a collection of
MedicalCondition model objects,
which we are going to display
in the collection view.
For each item
in this collection,
we want to create a cell
in the collection view
to display that
medical condition.
In order to do this, we'll
create a diffable data source
connected
to the collection view.
Then, we need to populate
a diffable data source snapshot
with the identifiers of the
MedicalCondition model objects
in the data collection.
It's important that the diffable
data source snapshot
contains the unique identifier
of each MedicalCondition,
and not the MedicalCondition
objects themselves.
This ensures that the diffable
data source can accurately track
the identity of each item,
and compute the correct changes
when new snapshots
are applied later.
By applying a snapshot
with these item identifiers
to the diffable data source,
it will automatically update
the collection view,
which will create a new cell
for each item.
Each cell is configured
to display one MedicalCondition,
using a SwiftUI view
in a UIHostingConfiguration.
Now that we're displaying cells
built with SwiftUI,
we need to handle updating
the UI when the data changes.
There are two different
types of changes
that we need
to handle separately.
The first type is when the
data collection itself changes.
For example, when items are
inserted, reordered, or deleted.
These changes are handled
by applying a new snapshot
to the diffable data source.
Diffable data source will diff
the old and new snapshots,
and perform the necessary
updates to the collection view,
causing cells to be inserted,
moved, or deleted.
Because changes to the
collection of data itself
don't affect anything
inside of cells,
you handle these types
of changes the same,
whether you build your cells
using UIKit or SwiftUI.
The second type of change
we need to handle
are when the properties of
individual model objects change.
These changes often require
updating the views
in existing cells.
Because the diffable data source
only contains item identifiers
in its snapshot,
it doesn't know
when the properties
of existing items change.
Traditionally, when using UIKit,
you would need to manually
tell the diffable data source
about these changes
by reconfiguring or reloading
items in the snapshot.
But when using SwiftUI in cells,
this isn't necessary anymore.
By storing
the ObservableObject model
in an ObservedObject property
in our SwiftUI view,
changes to published properties
of the model will automatically
trigger SwiftUI
to refresh the view.
This establishes a direct
connection between the model
and the SwiftUI view
inside of the cell.
When a change is made,
the SwiftUI views in the cell
are updated directly,
without going through
the diffable data source
or the UICollectionView.
When a cell's data changes,
it may cause the cell
to need to grow or shrink
to fit the new content.
But if the SwiftUI cell content
is being updated directly
without going through UIKit,
how does the collection view
know to resize the cell?
UIHostingConfiguration takes
advantage of a brand-new feature
in UIKit to make this work.
In iOS 16, self-sizing cells
in UICollectionView
and UITableView
are now also self-resizing!
This is enabled by default,
so that when you're using
UIHostingConfiguration
and the SwiftUI content changes,
the containing cell
is automatically resized
if necessary.
You can learn more
about how this new feature works
in the "What's New in UIKit"
video from WWDC 2022.
There's one more aspect
of data flow
that you may need to handle,
and that's sending data out
from a SwiftUI view
back to other parts of your app.
Once again, ObservableObject
has got you covered!
You can create a two-way binding
to a published property
of an ObservableObject.
Not only will data flow from the
ObservableObject into SwiftUI,
but SwiftUI can write back
changes to the property
on the model object.
Let's go through
a simple example
of creating a two-way binding
by making the text in our
MedicalCondition cell editable.
Here is our ObservableObject,
MedicalCondition.
It stores a unique identifier
in an ID property.
This is the identifier
used to populate
the diffable
data source snapshot.
And this published property
stores the text
of the medical condition.
Here's the MedicalConditionView
that displays the medical
condition text inside each cell.
Right now this text
is read-only,
so let's make it editable.
All we need to do is to change
the Text view to a TextField
and create a binding
to the text property
of our MedicalCondition
by adding a dollar sign prefix.
When you type
into the text field,
this binding allows SwiftUI
to write back changes
directly to
the ObservableObject.
That's really how simple it is
to set up two-way
data flow with SwiftUI.
UIHostingController
is a powerful way
to embed SwiftUI content
into your UIKit app.
Your SwiftUI view is rendered
inside the hosting
controller's view,
and you can use
the hosting controller
anywhere that you can use
a view controller in UIKit.
When using UIHostingController,
make sure to always
add the view controller
together with the view
to your app.
Many SwiftUI features, such as
toolbars, keyboard shortcuts,
and views that use
UIViewControllerRepresentable,
require a connection
to the view controller hierarchy
in UIKit to integrate properly,
so never separate
a hosting controller's view
from the hosting controller
itself.
For comparison, when you apply
a UIHostingConfiguration
to a cell,
your SwiftUI view
is hosted in the cell
without a UIViewController.
UIHostingConfiguration supports
the vast majority
of SwiftUI features.
But keep in mind
that SwiftUI views
that depend on
UIViewControllerRepresentable
can't be used inside of cells.
With UIHostingController
and UIHostingConfiguration,
you have two great ways
to incorporate SwiftUI
into your UIKit app.
SwiftUI integrates seamlessly
into existing UIKit apps
Use UIHostingController to add
SwiftUI throughout your app.
Create custom cells in
your collection and table view
using UIHostingConfiguration.
And take advantage
of ObservableObject,
so your data and UI
is always in sync.
Add SwiftUI to your app today!
Thank you for watching!
♪