♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Welcome to
"Use SwiftUI with AppKit."
I'm Ian, an engineer
working on Shortcuts.
In macOS Monterey,
Shortcuts came to macOS.
Shortcuts uses a lot
of SwiftUI on the Mac.
SwiftUI helps customize
the experience for the platform,
while sharing common views
with the apps
on iOS and watchOS.
In this video, I'm going to show
how you can start adopting
SwiftUI in your Mac app,
by looking at some examples
from Shortcuts.
First, I'll show you an example
of how to host
SwiftUI views in your app,
and then talk about
how to pass data
between AppKit and SwiftUI.
I'll also cover
hosting SwiftUI views
in the cells of a collection
or table view,
how to handle layout
and sizing of SwiftUI views
when they are embedded
in AppKit,
how to make
your SwiftUI views participate
in the responder chain
and be focusable,
and, finally, how to host
an AppKit view in SwiftUI.
Alright, I'll start with
how to host SwiftUI in AppKit.
In Shortcuts,
the main window contains
an AppKit split view controller
and the sidebar on the left
is written using SwiftUI.
The sidebar view is implemented
as a SwiftUI List,
and the list shows sections
with rows for all of the places
you can navigate to in the app.
The view keeps track
of which item is selected,
through the selected item
binding.
The possible items
that can be selected
are represented as cases
in the SidebarItem type.
In this case, since there's a
split view controller already.
To host this sidebar view,
we use a class from SwiftUI
called NSHostingController.
The SwiftUI sidebar view
is passed in
as the root view
of that hosting controller.
Since a hosting controller
can be used
like any other view controller,
here, we configure it
as a splitViewItem
and add that
to the splitViewController.
Now the sidebar is hosted
in the split view,
but for it to work
when the selection changes,
the right side of the split view
needs to show a different page.
Currently,
the selected item state
only exists within SwiftUI.
What we need to do is move that
to a place that can be shared
between the split view
and the sidebar.
A good way to do this
is to create a model object
that can be stored outside
of SwiftUI and contain the state
that needs to be shared.
I'll call this object
the SelectionModel.
Now, the sidebar can still
read and write the state
in the SelectionModel.
In code, the SelectionModel
is a class that conforms
to ObservableObject.
Being an observable object
lets SwiftUI reload the view
when the state stored
in the model changes.
It stores which sidebar item
is currently selected.
This property is published
so that the SwiftUI sidebar view
can update when
the selected item changes.
Whenever someone changes
the selection in the sidebar,
the model can show a new page
in the detail view.
Now that I've covered
how to host SwiftUI in AppKit,
let's move on to collection
and table cells.
When bringing Shortcuts
from other platforms to macOS,
there was already
an iconic SwiftUI view
built to display a shortcut
in a collection view cell
or a Home Screen widget.
On macOS, these same views
are displayed in the cells
of an NSCollectionView.
In a collection or table view
with lots of items,
each cell view is recycled
as you scroll,
showing different content
over time.
To make sure the cell reuse
is performant,
you need to avoid
adding and removing subviews
from the cells
as the user scrolls.
When displaying a SwiftUI view
in each cell,
use a single hosting view
and update it
with a different root view
when the cell's content
needs to change.
Here's all you need
to build a collection view cell
to host SwiftUI.
In the example here,
I'm building the cell
that displays a shortcut view.
Each cell contains an
NSHostingView to host SwiftUI.
Since cells are created
before they are configured
with any content,
this will start off as nil,
and will be set the first time
a shortcut
is ready to be displayed.
The displayShortcut method
is called by the data source
when configuring the cell
to display a shortcut.
This method creates
a SwiftUI ShortcutView.
Then, if there's already
a hostingView,
the rootView of that hostingView
is set to the new view.
Otherwise,
if it's the first time,
a newHostingView
is created and added
as a subview of the cell.
Here's the lifecycle of the cell
that's hosting SwiftUI.
First, the cell is initialized
and it starts with no subviews,
since there is not
a shortcut to display yet.
The first time
displayShortcut is called,
the hostingView is created with
the shortcutView to display.
This creates
a SwiftUI view hierarchy,
containing a VStack, an image,
a spacer, and two text views.
If this cell is then scrolled
off screen,
it will be potentially
dequeued by the system
and need to show
a different shortcut.
When this happens,
a new ShortcutView is created
and given to the HostingView.
Since the HostingView
was already displaying
a different shortcut view,
it will reuse the overall
structure of the view,
including the VStack
and the spacer,
and only update the image, text,
and background that changed.
Alright, next, let's talk about
layout and sizing.
Hosting controllers
and hosting views
have intrinsic sizes
based on the SwiftUI view's
ideal width and height.
SwiftUI automatically
creates and updates
Auto Layout constraints,
which the AppKit layout system
uses to size the view
appropriately.
Views are also flexible,
meaning they support
a variety of sizes,
between a minimum and a maximum.
SwiftUI creates constraints
for these as well.
When embedding SwiftUI
hosting views in your hierarchy,
you should apply your own
Auto Layout constraints
to the superview
or to other adjacent views.
Using the frame modifier
or other SwiftUI layout
will result in an update to the
constraints that are created,
such as overriding the width
to be a fixed size.
Since windows can be resized
by the user,
they have a minimum
and a maximum size.
When HostingViews are set
as the top-level contentView
of a window,
SwiftUI will automatically
update that window's minimum
and maximum size based on
the content being displayed.
And this lets windows
be resizable
either vertically,
horizontally, or both,
depending on the content.
SwiftUI views,
placed in hosting controllers,
also are sized based on the
content when presented modally.
For example, you can easily
place SwiftUI views
into an AppKit popover,
by presenting
a hosting controller
using the popover presentation
API on NSViewController,
as shown here.
You can also present
SwiftUI views as sheets,
using the presentAsSheet
method.
And finally, for a modal window,
you can use the
presentAsModalWindow method
to present a window that
blocks interaction until closed.
The window is sized
to fit the content.
In macOS Ventura,
there are new APIs
on NSHostingView
and NSHostingController
that allow you to customize
the constraints
that are automatically added.
By default,
hosting controllers and views
create constraints
for the minimum size,
intrinsic size,
and maximum size.
You may want to disable some of
these for performance reasons
if you want the view
to always be flexibly sized,
or the constraints
are already added
to surrounding views in AppKit.
For hosting controllers,
to let the ideal size
of the view
determine the preferred
content size,
you can enable the
preferredContentSize option.
When you start adding
SwiftUI views to your app,
it's important that they take
part in the responder chain
and focus system just like
other views in your app.
In Shortcuts,
our editor is implemented
as a SwiftUI View.
But the editor needs to handle
menu bar commands
defined in the main menu,
which is implemented in AppKit.
These commands include
cut, copy, paste, and others.
We implemented a few of our
own custom menu items as well,
for moving actions up and down.
In AppKit, your view hierarchy
makes up a chain of views
called "the responder chain."
The focused responder
is called the first responder.
When a menu item is selected,
the selector for that item
is sent to the first responder.
But if the first responder
doesn't respond
to that selector,
then the selector is sent
to each next responder,
until something
handles the selector,
or it reaches the app.
The equivalent to the first
responder in SwiftUI
is the focused view.
Focusable SwiftUI views
can respond to keyboard input
and handle selectors
sent to the responder chain.
Some views like text fields
are already focusable,
but you can use
the focusable modifier
to make other views
focusable too.
SwiftUI has a few modifiers
to handle common commands,
such as copy, cut, and paste.
These pass values
in and out of the pasteboard,
and it's an easy way
to let people transfer data
in and out of your app.
The shortcuts editor uses
the onMoveCommand
and onExit command modifiers
to handle the arrow keys
and escape keys.
The onCommand modifier
can be used to handle
any of the common selectors
from AppKit
or your own custom selectors
defined in your app.
Here, we handle the
selectAll command from AppKit
and the moveActionUp
and moveActionDown commands
defined in the Shortcuts app.
When testing focus and keyboard
navigability in your app,
make sure to open
Keyboard System Settings
and test with
Full Keyboard Navigation
turned both on and off,
since many controls are only
focusable when that's enabled.
There's a lot more you can do
to make your app work great
with the keyboard.
For example, there are APIs
such as FocusState
and the focused modifier
that let you programmatically
change which view is focused.
To learn more about focus
and the keyboard,
you should go watch
the "Direct and reflect
focus in SwiftUI" video.
Finally, let's talk about
hosting AppKit views in SwiftUI.
There are some instances
where Shortcuts
is hosting AppKit views
inside of a SwiftUI layout,
and you may need to host
AppKit views, too,
as you adopt SwiftUI
in your app.
One example is inside
of the SwiftUI shortcuts editor,
where there's an embedded
AppleScript editor view,
which is an AppKit control
shared with a few
other system apps on macOS.
SwiftUI provides two
representable protocols
that allow AppKit views
and view controllers
to be embedded within
a SwiftUI view hierarchy.
Like SwiftUI views,
representables are descriptions
for how to create and update
AppKit views.
Since many classes in AppKit
have delegates, observers,
or rely on KVO or notifications
to be observed,
the protocols also include
an optional coordinator object
that you can implement
to accompany your view
or view controller.
Here's the lifecycle
of the hosted object
and its coordinator.
We start with the hosted view
being initialized.
This happens when the view
is about to be displayed
for the first time.
The first thing SwiftUI
does during initialization
is make the coordinator.
This is optional,
but you can define your own type
and return it from
makeCoordinator
if you need it for delegation
or state management.
A single instance
of the coordinator
will stay around
for the lifetime of the view.
Second, either the makeNSView
or makeNSViewController method
is called.
This is where
you describe to SwiftUI
how to create
a new instance of your view.
The context contains the
coordinator that was just made,
if any, so here's a good place
to assign the coordinator
as the view's delegate
or other type of observer.
Once the view has been created,
the update view method
will be called
whenever the SwiftUI state
or environment changes.
Here, it's your responsibility
to update any properties
or state stored
in the AppKit view
to keep it in sync with
the surrounding SwiftUI state
and environment.
The update method
can be called often,
so the changes you make
to the view
should be
as minimal as possible.
You should check
for what has changed
and only reload the affected
part of the view
when changes are made.
When SwiftUI is done displaying
the hosted view,
it will be dismantled.
The hosted view and coordinator
will both be deallocated.
Before these are deallocated,
the representable protocols
give you an optional method
to implement,
where you can clean up
state if needed.
Alright, now that you know
the lifecycle
and are familiar with
the representable protocols,
I'm going to show you
how Shortcuts hosts
the custom script editor view
in the app.
The script editor is an NSView
called ScriptEditorView.
The code that's written
in the editor can be accessed
and modified through
the sourceCode property,
and the view can be disabled
to prevent changes
from being made.
The script editor
also has a delegate,
which is notified any time
someone modifies
the source code.
When hosting an AppKit view,
first think about where the
view will be placed in SwiftUI,
and what data needs
to be passed in and out.
In Shortcuts, this view
is placed into a container view
next to the compile button.
The compile button's handler
needs to access the source code
that's entered into the view.
The source code
is stored in SwiftUI
using the State property
wrapper.
The representable
will need to both read
and write to this state.
To build the representable,
start by creating a type that
conforms to NSViewRepresentable,
since it will host an NSView.
Add properties for each thing
that needs to be configurable
from SwiftUI.
For the source code
a binding is used,
which will read and write
the state stored in SwiftUI.
The first method you need
to implement is makeNSView.
Here is where you describe
how to create a new instance
of the view,
and where you should do any
one-time setup that's required.
Here, the delegate is set
to the coordinator.
I'll talk about the coordinator
more in a bit.
Next, implement updateNSView.
This will be called when
either the sourceCode changes,
or when the
SwiftUI environment changes.
Since the script editor
does a bunch of work
when the sourceCode property
is set,
we compare the value
already in the view,
and only set the property
if it changes
to avoid unnecessary work.
The context passed
to updateNSView
contains
the SwiftUI environment.
The isEnabled environment key
is passed to the isEditable
property on the script editor,
so editing is disabled
if the rest of the
SwiftUI view hierarchy is.
Whenever someone modifies
the source code in the view,
the source code binding
needs to capture the new value.
To do this,
we'll build a coordinator
that conforms to the
ScriptEditorViewDelegate.
The coordinator will store
the representable value,
which contains the source code
binding that it needs to update.
And in the
sourceCodeDidChange method,
the binding is set
to the new string value
from the view.
Finally, we need to tell
the SwiftUI representable
how to make and update
the coordinator.
First, you need to implement
the makeCoordinator method
to create a new coordinator.
Coordinators have the same
lifetime as the hosted view,
and like hosted views,
properties you add
to the coordinator
need to remain up to date
as the representable changes.
Since updateNSView is called
when the values stored
in the representable change,
here, the representable property
on the coordinator is updated.
Now that you know how to add
AppKit into SwiftUI,
and also add SwiftUI
into AppKit,
you should start integrating
SwiftUI into your app.
A great place to start
is in your sidebar,
or table
and collection view cells.
Make sure your views are sizing
themselves correctly
and handling common commands
and focus.
Thanks for your time,
and I can't wait
to see what you build
♪