[upbeat music]
Qiaoyu Deng: Hello.
Welcome to “Improve DNS security
for apps and servers.”
My name is Qiaoyu Deng.
In this video, we are going to talk about
why DNS is often not secure
and how to protect it using DNSSEC
and encrypted DNS with DDR.
First, let’s talk about
why DNS is not secure.
DNS is the phone book of the internet.
It translates domain names,
which are human readable and easy to
remember,
to IP addresses,
which are made for machines.
Other internet protocols,
such as TCP, TLS, and QUIC,
rely on having an IP address,
so everything starts with DNS.
Today, TLS is widely used
to secure internet communication.
That’s great,
but DNS, the foundational layer,
has some security issues.
DNS is historically not secure.
It was designed back in 1983
with few security considerations.
In the years since,
many DNS attacks have been created.
One example is DNS cache poisoning,
where the attacker
exploits flaws of DNS resolvers
and make them cache
incorrect IP addresses,
causing clients
to connect to malicious hosts.
This reveals one vulnerability of DNS:
it is unauthenticated.
Traditional DNS clients today
have no way to validate answers,
so they can easily be spoofed.
Another common attack is DNS sniffing,
where the attacker watches DNS traffic
between a client and a DNS server,
collecting the client's history.
This is a serious problem
for user privacy.
The reason this attack is possible is that
DNS traffic was originally unencrypted.
In order to be a secure starting point
for the protocols that build on top of it,
DNS needs to be both
authenticated and encrypted.
When we use DNSSEC to sign DNS response,
it provides authentication.
When we use TLS and HTTPS
to encrypt DNS resolution,
it ensures privacy.
Next, let’s talk about DNSSEC.
DNSSEC is a suite
of extension specifications
created by IETF.
Many DNS service providers
already support it,
but client support is still ramping up.
iOS 16 and macOS Ventura
now support client side DNSSEC validation.
DNSSEC ensures the authentication of data
by adding digital signatures.
It protects data integrity.
It authenticates denial of existence
when answers do not exist.
It also provides cryptographic
authentication.
DNSSEC protects data integrity
by attaching signatures in responses.
If a response is altered by an attacker,
the signature of the altered data
will not match the original one.
In that case, the client can detect
the altered response and discard it.
DNSSEC also asserts the existence
and nonexistence of records in a zone,
by using special types of DNS records
such as the NSEC record.
The NSEC record tells you
what the next record name is,
securely, in alphabetical order.
The names listed by it
are the ones that exist,
and any name not listed does not exist.
For example,
we have three NSEC records here.
The record set reveals that zone org
only has three record names,
A.org, C.org, and E.org.
Now, if there is an attacker
that says A.org does not exist,
the client can detect this attack.
A.org does exist
because it is listed
in the first NSEC record.
Likewise, if an attacker says
that D.org exists,
the client can also detect that,
because according to
the second NSEC record,
D.org is in between C.org and E.org
and no name should exist
in between the two names.
DNSSEC authenticates records
by establishing a chain of trust.
Here is an example.
A device wants to resolve www.example.org
with DNSSEC validation enabled.
It sends queries
asking for the IP addresses,
signatures, and keys.
With the responses,
the trust relationship can be built
from the IP addresses to key number 1.
Then the client sends queries
to the parent zone, org,
asking for the records that can be used
to authenticate key number 1,
so it can build the trust relationship
from key number 1 to key number 2.
So the device repeats
this process recursively,
until it has reached the root.
Now, if the root key,
which is key number 3 in the diagram,
can be trusted, the trust relationship
from the IP addresses
to key number 3 can be authenticated.
The hash of the root key is always
stored in the device securely.
In DNSSEC,
it is called the root trust anchor.
If the hash of key number 3
matches the pre-installed anchor,
a trust chain can be established securely.
With the trust chain,
the IP addresses of www.example.org
are now authenticated.
If you want to require DNSSEC validation
in your apps,
here are the things you need to do.
Support IPv6 for your domains.
In an IPv6-only environment,
IPv4-only addresses are translated
into synthetic IPv6 addresses.
If domains are signed,
synthesized addresses
cannot pass DNSSEC validation;
they are unreachable with DNSSEC enabled.
So make sure that
your domains support IPv6.
Make sure your DNS service provider
signs your domain with DNSSEC.
If you enable DNSSEC in your app
without signing your domain,
you will get no benefit,
but you will get additional DNS traffic
and extended resolution time
to attempt authentication
for your unsigned domain.
Once you have
the corresponding infrastructure support,
here is the code needed to adopt
DNSSEC for your apps.
If you are an NSURLSession client,
you can require DNSSEC validation
for your URL request.
Here is an example.
You will first create a default session
configuration.
Then you will require DNSSEC validation.
Next, you will create the session
with the modified configuration.
It enables DNSSEC for all URL requests
created from this session.
If you do not want to enable DNSSEC
for the entire session,
you can also do this at the request level.
First, create a session with
the default configuration
where DNSSEC validation is disabled.
Then enable it in the request.
Now, this session task
will only be started
when DNSSEC validation is completed.
If you are a Network.framework client,
you can also require DNSSEC validation
for your connections.
First, when you create
a parameters object,
require DNSSEC validation.
Then create the NWConnection
with the parameters object.
Now, when you start your connection,
it will only move into the ready state
when the DNSSEC validation has completed
and a connection to the validated
IP address has been established.
When DNSSEC is enabled,
only the validated addresses
will be used to establish a connection.
In HTTPS,
errors are reported through the APIs.
In DNSSEC, no error is returned
for the validation failure.
Receiving a response that fails validation
is equal to not receiving any response.
If there is a DNS provider
that tampers with the response,
the addresses will not pass
the authentication check,
so they will be discarded directly.
When the device joins a new network
where the DNS provider
is not tampering with responses,
the validation will make progress again
and the resolution will be back
to normal automatically.
Here are a few cases
that can cause DNSSEC failure.
When the original DNS response is altered,
the mismatched signature
will not pass the DNSSEC check,
causing a validation failure.
When the device is unable to reach
any pre-installed trust anchor
and unable to establish
a trust chain from it.
When the network does not support
the necessary protocols
required by DNSSEC,
such as DNS over TCP and EDNS0 option,
that carries the DNSSEC enablement bit.
When the signed domain
does not support IPv6,
the synthesized IPv6 addresses
provided by the internet service provider
will fail the validation.
So that’s how to authenticate
DNS responses with DNSSEC,
but if they are still unencrypted,
anyone on the network can see them.
Next, we will talk about
how to enable DNS encryption
automatically with DDR.
In iOS 14 and macOS Big Sur,
we introduced encrypted DNS
to help preserve privacy.
You can use NEDNSSettingsManager in an app
or DNSSettings in a profile
to manually configure encrypted DNS
system-wide.
You can also opt into
encrypted DNS for your app
using the PrivacyContext on NWParameters.
For more information, please watch
"Enable encrypted DNS."
New in iOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
encrypted DNS can be used automatically.
If your network supports Discovery of
Designated Resolvers, also called DDR,
DNS queries will automatically
use TLS or HTTPS.
To use encrypted DNS,
your device needs to know that
a resolver supports TLS or HTTPS,
and it may need to learn
a port or URL path as well.
Common mechanisms such as DHCP
or Router Advertisements
only provide a plain IP address.
DDR is a new protocol
developed in the IETF by Apple
working with other industry partners.
It provides a way for DNS clients
to learn this necessary information
by using a special DNS query.
When your device joins a new network,
it will issue a Service Binding query
for “_dns.resolver.arpa”.
If the DNS server supports DDR,
it will reply with
one or more configurations.
Then, the device uses this information
to set up an encrypted connection
to the designated resolver.
It verifies that the IP address
of the unencrypted resolver
is included in the TLS certificate
of the designated resolver.
This is done to ensure that
the unencrypted resolver
and the encrypted one
belong to the same entity.
If everything looks good, the device now
uses encrypted DNS by default.
DDR applies to a single network at a time.
Your device will use
encrypted DNS automatically
only if the current network supports it.
It's also important to note that
DDR does not work
if your DNS server's IP address
is a private IP address.
This is because such IP addresses
are not allowed in TLS certificates,
since their ownership cannot be verified.
In iOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
we also support the ability
to specify client authentication
when using encrypted DNS
for a configuration setup,
using NEDNSSettingsManager
or the DNSSettings profile.
Client authentication allows
encrypted DNS servers to be used
in enterprise environments
where servers need to validate clients
before allowing access.
You can now configure a client certificate
using the identityReference property
of NEDNSSettings.
This behaves just like client certificates
for VPNs.
These can apply to both DNS over TLS
and DNS over HTTPS.
This is the path to securing DNS.
Sign your domain with DNSSEC
and require DNSSEC validation in your apps
to authenticate your IP addresses.
Enable DDR on your network
so that the clients can switch
to encrypted DNS automatically
for better user privacy.
Adopt client authentication in enterprises
where better access control is needed.
I am looking forward to
a more secure DNS foundation
that you help to build in the future.
Thanks for watching!
[upbeat music]