♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Miranda Zhou: Hi,
my name is Miranda
and I'm an engineer
on the Sharing team.
Elana Stettin: I'm Elana
and I'm an engineer
on the Messages team.
Miranda: In this video,
Elana and I will be diving into
how to enhance collaboration
with Messages in your app.
I'll start with an introduction
of what the feature is.
You'll learn how to prepare
to adopt this feature,
and how to tie Messages
into the process
to start a collaboration.
Elana will explain
how to add collaboration
with Messages UI to your app,
and finally she will discuss
how to keep up to date
when the collaboration
is updated.
First, let me introduce
collaboration with Messages!
In iOS 16 and macOS Ventura,
we've added a new and easy way
to improve communication between
people who are collaborating.
Collaborators are able to tie
a document to conversations
by sharing via Messages.
Collaboration activity
is surfaced in Messages
conversations and in
ongoing FaceTime calls.
A customizable
Collaboration popover
is also provided to your app
to manage details
of the collaboration and connect
to the Messages conversation.
This builds on technologies
that you are already using,
such as the share sheet
and drag and drop.
Next, I'll go over the types of
collaboration infrastructures
we support,
and how to tie each of those
to Messages collaboration.
We support three types of
collaboration infrastructures:
CloudKit, iCloud Drive,
and whatever custom
collaboration infrastructure
you may be using today!
In this video,
I'll mainly focus
on the CloudKit
and iCloud Drive cases.
If you are using
a custom infrastructure,
watch the "Integrate your custom
collaboration app with Messages"
video for more details.
If you use CloudKit-based
collaboration,
we've provided a new API
to create an object
that the system
can recognize for collaboration.
This is based off
the macOS Sierra API
to start or manage a share
with NSSharingService.
Once you have
the collaboration object,
identify where in the app
you are showing UI
to start or manage the share.
You need to update
to the new API
to enhance your
collaboration with Messages,
as we will deprecate
the existing AppKit API.
The new collaboration object API
uses NSItemProvider.
NSItemProvider is used
by system services
to transport your app's data to
other processes on the system.
The provider requires
either the CKShare
for the collaboration item,
or a preparation handler
to create a CKShare
when collaboration starts.
Your app's CKContainer
is also required.
And finally, provide a
CKAllowedSharingOptions object
representing the access
and permissions options
for the collaboration.
The values of the options
are the same as the
NSCloudKitSharingServiceOptions
which were previously requested
from
NSCloudSharingServiceDelegate
methods.
Here's a brief overview
of what it looks like to create
a CloudKit collaboration object.
If the collaboration
is being started and you pass in
a preparation handler,
you need to both
create the share and save it
to the server in the handler.
If it's already started, just
pass in the associated share.
The CKAllowedSharingOptions
instance being registered
is using
a static standard property
which returns the default set
of allowed options.
CloudKit adopters can use that
or create a custom instance
of the class for a restricted
set of allowed options.
For those of you who might be
interested in adopting CloudKit,
CloudKit lets you use iCloud
as your app's database
without writing your own
server code.
You will also get a built-in
method of sharing parts
of that data
with other iCloud users.
For more details, watch the
"What's new in CloudKit" video.
If you're using iCloud Drive,
your object for collaboration
is simply your file URL --
we'll do all the work
to recognize it!
Once you have that,
identify the entry points
to start or manage collaboration
in your app
and prepare to replace them with
the new and improved versions.
For custom collaboration
infrastructures,
your collaboration object is
called SWCollaborationMetadata,
wrapped in new
NSItemProvider API.
Watch the "Integrate your custom
collaboration app with Messages"
video for details on
how to use this API
to update your collaboration UI.
Now you're ready to go.
Next, initiating
a collaboration.
There are two different ways:
through the share sheet
in its new collaboration mode,
and through drag and drop
to Messages,
either from your app
or from the Files app on iOS
and Finder on macOS.
The new share sheet
collaboration mode
can be identified
by an indicator in the header,
which also provides
a choice between collaboration
and sending a copy.
In order to have collaboration
in the share sheet,
give the share sheet
the collaboration object
you prepared earlier.
On macOS,
this collaboration indicator
is shown in a beautiful
new share popover!
The share popover
also includes a title and image
in the header, plus a row
of conversation suggestions,
and all the transports
we offered already.
For more details about this,
watch the WWDC22
"What's new in AppKit" video.
On iOS and Mac Catalyst,
show the share sheet using
the UIActivityViewController
class.
On macOS, show the share popover
using NSSharingServicePicker.
Pass the collaboration object
to UIActivityViewController
as an activity item to present
it with collaboration enabled.
And similarly, initialize
NSSharingServicePicker
with the collaboration object
to show it
with collaboration enabled.
CloudKit adopters
will need to take an extra step
to provide a title
and image for the headers.
On iOS, use existing API such
as UIActivityItemsConfiguration
or UIActivityItemSource
to provide
an LPLinkMetadata object
with a title and imageProvider.
Create your configuration
with your collaboration object,
then set the metadata provider
to return
your LPLinkMetadata object
for the item being shared.
Finally, initialize
UIActivityViewController
with that configuration.
On macOS,
we have a new API called
NSPreviewRepresenting
ActivityItem
for providing
the header metadata.
Refer to the
NSPreviewRepresenting
ActivityItem documentation
for more details.
To use NSPreviewRepresenting
ActivityItem,
first choose your title,
image, and icon.
The image represents
the item being shared,
while the icon represents
the source of the item
being shared --
for example, an app icon.
Create an NSPreviewRepresenting
ActivityItem
with your collaboration object,
title, image, and icon,
and initialize
NSSharingServicePicker
with that preview item.
On an exciting note,
the new SwiftUI ShareLink API
for the share sheet will also
support collaboration mode!
To adopt, the item you are
sharing must be represented
by Transferable, a new protocol
for sharing and data transfer.
CloudKit adopters provide
the share, container,
and options through
a CKShareTransferRepresentation
returned by your
Transferable item.
For more details,
watch the "Meet Transferable"
and WWDC22
"What's new in SwiftUI" videos.
Here's an example of how
a CloudKit adopter like Notes
would create a transferable
object to share with ShareLink.
The note provides a
CKShareTransferRepresentation,
which is constructed either
as its existing value
with an existing CKShare,
CKContainer,
and CKAllowedSharingOptions
value,
or as its prepareShare value
with a CKContainer,
CKAllowedSharingOptions value,
and a preparation handler
to create and save a CKShare
for the collaboration object.
For iCloud Drive adopters,
your file URL
is the Transferable object which
you share through ShareLink.
If you have a custom
collaboration infrastructure,
watch the "Integrate your custom
collaboration app with Messages"
video for how to return an
SWCollaborationMetadata object
from your transferable object.
Once you have
your Transferable object,
pass it
to the ShareLink initializer
as the item to share.
At the same time,
pass in a preview
with a title and image to
fill in the share sheet header.
One notable feature
of the share sheet
collaboration mode header
is the summary of the access
and permissions options.
Tapping this summary brings up
a view where collaborators
choose what access
and permissions options
to use when collaborating.
For CloudKit adopters,
this view shows
the set of options registered
in the collaboration object.
iCloud Drive adopters
show the standard set
of iCloud Drive options.
If you have a custom
infrastructure,
watch the "Integrate your custom
collaboration app with Messages"
video for how to specify
your custom options
and have them
show up in this view.
There's one more way
to start a collaboration,
and that's through
drag and drop.
A collaborator can simply drag
your document into Messages
and get the new
collaboration-enabled rich link
for the document in Messages.
This rich link
provides functionality
both for collaboration
and sending a copy,
and for selecting
collaboration options.
To adopt, provide your
collaboration object
through ShareLink on iOS 16
and macOS Ventura.
And that's how you prepare for
and initiate collaborations
with Messages.
Next, I'll hand it
over to Elana,
who will talk about taking your
app's collaboration experience
to the next level.
Elana: Thanks, Miranda!
Now that you know
how to get started,
I'll talk about
how to further integrate
our collaboration UI
into your app.
We've added these new features
to amplify the collaboration
experience.
The collaboration button is
placed in your app's navigation
and will show the group photo
of the associated
messages group.
There is also an active
participant count
to the right of the button
that will show when others
are present in the document.
When you tap
the collaboration button,
the new collaboration
popover appears.
The customizable popover
shows the overview
of the collaboration.
It also allows users
to initiate communication
with other participants
with just one tap.
This provides them the ability
to work together in real time
via Messages and FaceTime.
These UI elements are all
powered by a single class
in the SharedWithYou framework:
SWCollaborationView.
This view represents the
button view in the navigation.
All you need to do
is initialize
the SWCollaborationView
and we will take care
of the popover layout
and presentation for you.
To show custom content,
you'll provide a view
which will be added
to the popover.
Now, I'll go over the code to
create the SWCollaborationView.
Initialize
the SWCollaborationView
with an itemProvider.
The itemProvider contains
the CKShare
for CloudKit-based apps,
the fileURL
for iCloud Drive-based apps,
or the SW Collaboration
metadata
for custom collaboration
infrastructures.
Set the activeParticipantCount
property
on the collaboration view
to show the number
of active participants
on the document.
Then set the contentView
property
on the collaborationView
to provide the popover
with custom content.
The ContentView
is what makes the popover
completely customizable.
This is where you'll add
your own content to give users
a unique view of what is
going on in the collaboration.
For example, in Pages,
the ContentView contains
the Current Participants list
and the Participant Cursors
toggle.
Now, let's look at
the "manage" button.
For CloudKit
and iCloud Drive adopters,
this manage button
will bring up the manage UI,
where you can add
and remove participants
or change the share settings.
I'll talk more
about this shortly.
Customize the provided
button title by setting
the manageButtonTitle property
on the collaboration view.
If you do not set
this property,
the title will default
to "Manage Share."
If your app uses a custom
collaboration infrastructure,
include your own manage button
in the contentView.
One will not be
provided for you.
On Mac, make sure the button
has a transparent background
to adhere to Apple design
recommendations.
Finally,
create a UIBarButtonItem on iOS
as shown here,
using the collaborationView
as the custom view.
On Mac,
initialize an NSToolbarItem
using a UIBarButtonItem.
Then, add the bar button item
or toolbar item
to the ViewController's
navigationItem.
As I mentioned earlier,
CloudKit and iCloud Drive
adopters are provided
with a button
in the collaboration popover.
This enables you to manage
the share in the same way
you've always been able to.
Changes in the provided
manage UI are observable
by adhering to
the same delegate protocols
already used to observe changes:
UICloudSharing
ControllerDelegate
and NSCloudSharing
ServiceDelegate.
Now you have an understanding
of how to integrate
the new collaboration UI
into your app.
Next, I'll go over how
to observe and handle
updates to collaborations.
It is critical to know when
a share starts or stops.
For CloudKit adopters,
we've added a new protocol
called CKSystemSharing
UIObserver
to notify you of just that.
With this protocol,
you get callbacks corresponding
to when your CKShare
is saved or removed
without needing
the CloudKit Sharing UI.
I'll take you
through some code now.
Initialize an observer
using the CKContainer.
On the observer,
define a closure to be executed
when the CKShare
is saved and assign it
to the systemSharingUI
DidSaveShareBlock.
In the closure, if the Share
was saved correctly,
you'll get a success result --
indicating the share
was started --
and an associated
CKShare to work with.
If the save was unsuccessful,
you receive a failure result
and the associated error.
Here is the implementation
of the closure
for when the document owner
stops sharing.
In the success case,
the CKShare
has successfully been deleted.
In the failure case, you will
also get the associated error.
Starting and stopping shares
are not the only changes
you may care about.
Some changes, you might even
want to bubble up to users.
We've added API to enable you
to post notices
summarizing updates
to a collaboration,
right at the top
of the relevant Messages thread.
Collaborators are shown
what the update was
and who made the change.
To post a notice, retrieve
the SWCollaborationHighlight,
which is a
collaboration-specific
type of highlight
in Shared with You.
Use it to create an
SWCollaborationHighlight event.
Learn more about SWHighlights
and other SharedWithYou APIs
in the "Add Shared with You
to your app" video.
Watch this video before
beginning your work
to adopt notices.
I'll talk through posting
different notices
using a CloudKit app
as an example.
If your app uses a custom
collaboration infrastructure,
view the "Integrate your
custom collaboration app
with Messages" video
for detailed instructions.
To represent a notice,
we've introduced a protocol
called SWHighlightEvent.
Highlight events are
initialized with SWHighlights
retrieved from
the SWHighlightCenter API.
The supported event types
include a change event
for content updates or comments;
a mention event when a user
is mentioned in a collaboration;
a persistence event when content
is moved, renamed, or deleted;
and a membership event
when a participant is added
or removed from a document.
Here's an example showing
how to post a change event
when a collaboration
has been edited.
Using the highlight center API,
retrieve a collaboration
highlight using the CKShare URL.
Remember, this CKShare
is one you defined during
the collaboration initiation,
so your app should have
this available when
a content change is made.
Next, create a
HighlightChangeEvent instance.
The initializer
takes a highlight,
and a trigger enum value.
In this case,
we set the trigger type to edit.
Lastly,
post the notice for that event
to the highlightCenter.
The rest of the events
follow a similar format
with the sole exception
being the mentionEvent,
as it requires more information
to indicate which
user was mentioned.
You are able to post
this type of event
only if your app
supports user mentions.
Create the mentionEvent
by passing in the retrieved
highlight and the handle of the
mentioned CKShare participant.
This notice will only be shown
to the mentioned user.
Use the persistence event type
when content is moved,
renamed, or deleted.
Here, the renamed trigger type
is used to signify
the document name
has been changed.
Finally,
here is a membershipEvent.
For a membershipEvent,
use the addedCollaborator
or removedCollaborator
trigger type instead.
With mentionevents,
notices are posted to show
how the document
membership has changed.
However, we've also made it
possible to keep collaborators
on your shared documents
in sync
when the Messages group
membership changes.
For CloudKit and iCloud Drive,
this is simple:
we do the work for you.
When someone new is added
to the Messages group
with a collaboration,
the document owner
is prompted via a notice
to add them to the share.
The same goes for when
someone is removed.
For apps with custom
collaboration infrastructures,
there's a little more work
to be done.
You will need to adopt the
SWCollaborationActionHandler
API,
which you can learn more about
in "Integrate your custom
collaboration app
with Messages."
Now you know how to get started
with collaboration in Messages
and integrate it into your app,
whether you're using CloudKit,
iCloud Drive, or your own
collaboration infrastructure.
Prepare your app to initiate
collaborations by adopting
the new share sheet
and drag and drop APIs.
Integrate the new
collaboration UI
to provide a customized overview
of what is happening
in the shared document.
Once you have that set up,
go even further and adopt
notices to display changes
to the collaboration
from within the Messages thread.
Miranda and I can't wait to see
how your app takes advantage
of these new collaboration
features in Messages!
Both: Thank you for watching!
♪