♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Garrett,
an engineer on the
Authentication Experience team.
And in this video, I'm excited
to talk about passkeys,
a next-generation
authentication technology.
But first, I need to talk about
today's authentication
technology: passwords.
You're probably used
to signing in
to nearly every app
and website with them.
Passwords are really hard
to use securely.
All of us know
we're supposed to create strong,
unique passwords
for every account,
but not many people actually do.
As you're designing
your apps and websites,
there's this constant tradeoff
between keeping accounts secure
and designing a good experience.
And even if your apps and
websites do everything right,
issues like phishing
and password reuse
can still lead
to account compromise.
In macOS Monterey
and iOS 15,
we announced a developer
preview of the solution --
passkeys -- and got so much
great feedback.
In macOS Ventura and iOS 16,
we're excited to make passkeys
available to everyone.
Now is the time to adopt them.
With passkeys,
not only is the user experience
better than a password,
but also entire categories
of security problems,
like weak and reused
credentials,
credential leaks, and phishing,
are just not possible anymore.
And they're so easy to use.
Let me show you.
Let's start with our favorite
demo app, Shiny.
This app lets me see
one cute picture a day
and has a typical
password-based sign-in flow.
I can tap in the
user name field
and see an AutoFill suggestion
for my account.
I'll select that, sign in.
Then, I can fill in my password.
Then, I wait around
for a little bit
until an SMS message comes in
with my one-time code.
There it is.
And eventually, I'm signed in.
It took a few steps,
but with the help of AutoFill
and my password manager,
I was able to get there.
Now that I'm signed in, I'll add
a passkey to this account.
Account Management, Add passkey.
Here, I get the system sheet
for creating a passkey.
Continue.
Done!
In just a few taps,
my device has generated
a unique, cryptographically
strong key pair for my account
and stored it
in my iCloud Keychain,
so it will sync and work
across all of my devices
running macOS Ventura
and iOS 16.
Now that I have a passkey,
let me show you
how easy it is to use.
I'm going to sign out,
and I'm back at the same
sign-in form I used earlier.
I'm going to focus
the user name field like before.
Now that I have a passkey
saved for my account,
it shows up
in the QuickType bar.
All I have to do is tap it
and I'm signed in.
One step.
When saving the passkey,
I didn't have to come up
with a new password
or try to satisfy
any complexity requirements.
Each passkey
is generated by the system
and guaranteed to be strong
and only ever used
for a single account.
And when I'm signing in with it,
it can be shown
in the existing sign-in flows
I'm used to,
and it's a single tap to use.
And the system will take care
of only letting me use it
in the correct app or website,
with strong built-in
phishing resistance.
Of course, passkeys
work on the web too.
Here I am on Shiny's
website in Safari.
Just like on my phone, when I
focus the user name field,
my passkey is already there
and ready to use,
thanks to iCloud Keychain.
All I have to do is Touch ID
and I'm signed in.
That's it.
Apple's passkey implementation
is built on open standards.
We've been working
with other platform vendors
within the FIDO Alliance
to make sure
that passkey implementations
are compatible cross-platform
and can work on as many
devices as possible.
After upgrading my account
to use a passkey,
I'm still able to sign in to it
on my friend's PC.
Of course, my friend's PC
doesn't have the passkey
saved locally, but I can still
type my user name here.
When I press Sign In,
I get a sheet that's offering
to let me use my phone.
Then I get a QR code.
Let me scan that.
My phone recognizes
that this QR code
is for signing in
with a passkey.
When I select this option,
my phone and the browser
securely connect to each other.
Now I can just Continue,
and I'm signed in.
This cross-platform
sign-in experience
is a first-class system feature
that's part of the standards
behind passkeys.
On the surface,
it appears incredibly simple,
but this is not just a QR code.
Behind the scenes,
the devices are performing
a local key agreement,
proving proximity,
establishing an end-to-end
encrypted communication channel,
all to let you sign in
in a way that's easy
but maintains the strong
phishing resistance of passkeys.
It works great for allowing me
to sign in securely
to my account on any device.
Another important feature
for a password replacement
is the ability to share accounts
between two or more people.
To share a passkey
with someone else,
I can use AirDrop.
My partner and I also have an
account for Shiny that we share,
which I've already upgraded
to use a passkey.
With a passkey, the credential
isn't something I could type,
but I'm still able to share it
with people I trust.
On my phone, I'll open up
the account details.
Here are all of my accounts,
which use both passwords
and passkeys.
I can tap on our shared account
to pull up more details.
Here, I can get some information
about my saved passkey
or add a note to this account.
I can also share my passkey.
There's my partner's phone.
I'll go ahead and select that.
Now my partner
has the passkey too.
And that's how easy it is
to use passkeys everywhere.
I've just gone over the
experience of using a passkey.
Next, I'll talk about
what a passkey is
and some interface guidelines
when using them.
Then I'll show you
how you can integrate passkeys
into your existing sign-in flows
in your apps and websites,
by taking advantage of AutoFill,
followed by some
additional options
that can further streamline
your sign-in process.
After that, I'll go into
some more technical detail
about how passkeys work
and finally, discuss passkeys
and multifactor authentication.
First up,
designing for passkeys.
When it comes to talking
about passkeys,
first and foremost, passkeys are
replacements for passwords.
They're faster to sign in with,
easier to use,
and so much more secure.
Here are some guidelines
for how to refer to passkeys
in your apps and websites.
"Passkey" is a generic,
user-visible term.
This video focuses on
Apple's implementation,
but as I've just shown you,
other major platforms
have already started building
their own support for passkeys.
"Passkey" is also a common noun,
like "password."
In English, this means
it's lowercase
and gets pluralized
like "password" would.
I have a passkey for my account,
and I can go to Settings
to view all of my accounts
with passkeys.
On Apple platforms,
you can also use the SF Symbol
person.key.badge
and the .fill variant
to provide iconography
consistent with the system.
When it comes to offering
passkeys in your apps
and websites, you don't need
to design entire new interfaces.
The user name field is
the center point for most app
and website sign-in today.
Pretty much everyone
knows how to use it,
and many apps and websites
already take advantage of it
to tailor the sign-in experience
per account.
Now the user name field
has another big feature.
While passkeys
bring new paradigms
for how signing in works, the
transition away from passwords
needs to be smooth
and easy too.
You can now present passkeys
using AutoFill
as a first-class feature,
letting you drop them
right in to your existing
sign-in flows,
in an interface that's familiar
and people know how to use.
Presenting passkeys
with AutoFill
is the primary way
you should use them.
For more advanced uses though,
Apple platforms
also have a wide range
of additional UI options
for signing in with passkeys.
Here's how to get started
using passkeys
and presenting them
with AutoFill.
Passkeys are built
on the WebAuthentication --
or WebAuthn standard --
and use public-key cryptography.
Rather than having
a typable word or string,
unique cryptographic key pairs
are generated for every account.
You'll need to adopt WebAuthn
on your server back end
in order to perform
passkey sign-in.
Any standard WebAuthn
server implementation
should work with passkeys.
In apps on Apple platforms,
passkeys are part of the
ASAuthorization API family
in the AuthenticationServices
framework.
This is our API
for working with all kinds
of different credentials,
including passwords,
security keys,
and Sign in with Apple.
We've also added a few
new methods you can use,
like AutoFill support, to make
this API even more flexible
and let you fit it in seamlessly
in your existing sign-in flows.
To get started using
passkeys in your apps,
first, you'll need to set up
associated domains,
using the webcredentials
service.
You can find more
details about that
in the "Introducing Password
AutoFill for Apps"
and "What's new
in Universal Links" videos.
In your app's interface,
make sure your user name field
is using the user name
textContentTtype.
This lets the system know where
to offer passkey suggestions.
Once that's configured,
here's the code needed
to start an AutoFill-assisted
passkey request.
It's just a few simple steps
when you break it down.
As with any WebAuthn request,
you'll first need
to fetch a challenge
from your server.
Then create the provider
and the request.
ASAuthorizationPlatformPublicKey
CredentialProvider
is the
ASAuthorizationProvider
for working
with passkey requests.
In WebAuthn terms, assertions
are used when signing in,
so here, I'm creating
an assertion request
to sign in with
an existing passkey.
ASAuthorizationController
is what actually handles
the request.
Create an instance
with the passkey request
and configure its delegate and
presentationContextProvider.
And finally, call
performAutoFillAssistedRequests
to start the request.
While this request
is running in your app,
whenever a user name field
is focused,
the system will offer available
passkeys in the QuickType bar.
Make sure to start this request
early in your view lifetime
before a user name field
gets focused,
so passkeys are ready
when the keyboard appears.
When an item from
the QuickType bar is selected,
Face ID gets invoked,
then you'll receive
an ASAuthorizationController
Delegate callback
to complete the sign-in.
Nothing actually gets filled
in your text field.
When an authorization succeeds
for any credential type,
you'll get the
didCompleteWithAuthorization
callback.
The first thing you should do
is check the type
of the credential that you got.
In the case of passkey sign-in,
it will be an
ASAuthorizationPlatformPublicKey
CredentialAssertion.
The assertion object will
contain the fields needed
to verify the sign-in
on your back end.
You should read the values,
verify them with your server,
and complete the sign-in.
AutoFill-assisted passkey
requests are powerful.
With that small code change,
your app's sign-in flow
now offers a lot of flexibility.
The primary case, of course,
is to select
the passkey suggestion
from the QuickType bar
to sign in quickly
with that passkey.
This is what you should expect
to happen most often.
There are other options though.
The code I just showed you
also allows passkey sign-in
from nearby devices
with no additional changes.
You can tap the key icon
to bring up a view
that lists all available
passkeys and passwords
and get to the option to sign in
with a nearby device.
Then you can perform a
cross-device passkey sign-in.
In both cases,
if a passkey is used,
you'll receive the same
ASAuthorizationController
Delegate callback.
There's nothing special you need
to do to support this.
If a user doesn't have
any passkeys yet,
they can just use your login
form like they're used to.
They'll get password suggestions
in the QuickType bar,
or they can just type
in the fields.
If a password item is selected,
the credential will still be
filled in to your text fields,
and you can cancel
the running request.
We designed this API
to let you drop it
right in to your existing
sign-in flows
and make it super easy
for your users.
If someone that has already
upgraded to using a passkey
decides to enter
their user name anyway
instead of using
the AutoFill suggestion,
you should cancel
the AutoFill request
and use
ASAuthorizationController
to present a modal passkey
sign-in sheet.
From here,
it's still a single tap,
and you'll receive the same
ASAuthorizationController
Delegate callback.
Here's the code from before.
To switch this from an AutoFill
request to a modal request,
just swap this
performAutoFillAssistedRequests
method call
with a performRequests() call.
This will present a modal sheet
with all available passkeys
as well as the option to use
a passkey from a nearby device.
Those are the only code changes
you need in your app
to support passkeys.
The web platform also supports
both AutoFill-assisted
and modal passkey requests.
On the web, passkeys are used
via standard WebAuthn API,
which is also used
for security keys.
Just like in apps, adopting
AutoFill-assisted requests
allows signing in quickly
with just a Touch ID,
getting to all of your available
passkeys and passwords
or using a passkey
from a nearby device,
all with very little code.
First off, make sure to annotate
your user name field
on your webpage
with both the username
and webauthn
autocomplete detail tokens,
so that both password
and passkey suggestions
are shown in the right place.
Once that's done, here's
a typical WebAuthn sign-in,
in JavaScript.
In WebAuthn,
AutoFill-style requests
are invoked using
conditional mediation.
You should start by using
standard JavaScript
feature detection
to check if it is available.
If it is, you can proceed
making your request.
Just like with a native API,
you'll start by making a request
using a challenge
fetched from your server.
To make it
an AutoFill-assisted request,
add the mediation: "conditional"
parameter to your options.
Then, use navigator.credentials
.get to start the request.
The .get call
returns a promise.
If it resolves, you'll
receive an assertion object,
which you can send back
to your server to verify,
then complete the sign-in.
Like in apps, if someone
manually enters a user name
for an account with a passkey,
you should use the API
to present a modal
sign-in sheet.
To switch to a modal request,
all you need to do is remove
the mediation: "conditional"
parameter.
One thing to note
when using WebAuthn
is how Apple platforms handle
user verification -- or UV.
UV is a Boolean field
in a WebAuthn response
that indicates whether
the authenticator
attempted to verify
that the current user
is the owner of the device.
On Apple devices, a value of
one indicates that biometrics,
or a password
or passcode were used.
Apple platforms will always
require UV for passkeys
when biometrics are available,
so you don't have
to worry about that.
When making WebAuthn requests,
there's an option to specify
a user-verification requirement.
The default value is
userVerification: "preferred".
Always use the default value to
avoid creating a bad experience
on devices without biometrics.
Here are some additional notes
for using passkeys on the web.
When you make
AutoFill-assisted requests,
you should make them
early in the page lifetime,
just like in apps.
For modal WebAuthn requests,
you should trigger them
from a user gesture event,
such as a button click.
A modal request can be
triggered once per page load
outside of a user gesture
event, but WebKit may limit
subsequent calls
on that page if you do so.
AutoFill requests
are not modal,
so they don't require
a user gesture
and have a much longer timeout.
Finally, passkeys are
replacing Safari's legacy
platform authenticator.
Existing credentials
will still work
and still be bound to the
device they were created on,
but new platform credentials
will be created as passkeys.
They can be differentiated
from legacy credentials
during registration,
as passkeys will not provide
an attestation statement.
That's passkeys and AutoFill.
Next up, I'll go over some
additional platform features
that can further streamline
your sign-in experience.
In addition to the
AutoFill-assisted sign-in,
the ASAuthorization API
provides many more
useful features.
I'm going to cover three
additional features of the API
and when you might
want to use them.
Starting with passkey
allow lists.
When presenting
a modal passkey sheet
after a user
name is entered,
it's possible that there are
passkeys for multiple accounts
saved on the device.
All available passkeys will be
shown in the sheet by default.
You can use
a passkey allow list
to restrict which passkeys
are shown in the sheet,
so that only the matching
account is offered.
To add an allow list
to a modal request,
you'll first need
the user name.
You can use that user name
to fetch a list
of matching credential IDs
and turn it into an allow list.
A credential ID is a unique
identifier for a passkey.
A Webauthn server should have
a way to look up credential IDs
for a given user name.
From here, just proceed
with your request like before.
Now, on my device which
has three Shiny accounts
using passkeys,
the sheet only offers
the single account
I'm trying to use.
When making modal requests,
you should use an allow list
when you have additional
context about which account
the user is trying
to sign in with,
such as if they've already
typed in their user name.
Next up, I'll cover what happens
you make a modal passkey request
if there are no passkeys
saved on the current device.
This also applies
if you use an allow list
and none of the saved
passkeys match that list.
By default, when you make
a modal passkey request,
if there are no matching
passkeys available,
the modal sheet
will be displayed
and will immediately show
the QR code
for signing in with a passkey
from a nearby device.
This provides most
flexibility when signing in
and is the best option when you
know a passkey is being used.
But there's a new option
in the API to prefer credentials
that are immediately available
and fall back silently
with a delegate callback
if there aren't any.
This can be used to quickly
offer up existing credentials
when possible,
before even showing
a traditional sign-in form.
This modal request
using the default options
will fall back
to showing a QR code
if there are no matching
passkeys on the current device.
If you use the preferImmediately
AvailableCredentials option,
instead of
getting a QR code,
you'll receive a delegate
callback with an error.
If you receive
an ASAuthorizationError
with a code of canceled,
that means
either the user saw the sheet
and manually dismissed it,
or you passed preferImmediately
AvailableCredentials
and no credentials
were immediately available.
What you do from here
depends on the context
where you were
calling this from.
For example, if you were
using this option
as a way to test
for local credentials
before showing
your normal sign-in form,
this is where would trigger
showing your form.
If there's at least one matching
credential on the device,
the full modal sheet
will be displayed
regardless
of the options used.
Make sure you're also using
either AutoFill-assisted
requests or modal requests
with the default fallback
somewhere in your app,
so that the option to sign in
with a nearby device
is still reachable
if there are no passkeys
on the current device.
The last feature
of the ASAuthorization API
that I'll cover is making
combined credential requests.
In this example,
the app made a request
for passkeys, passwords,
and Sign in with Apple.
My device happens to have
three different credentials
for three different
accounts saved,
so they're all
presented here.
But a more likely scenario
is that someone would only
have a single account.
In that case, this same
combined credential request
will only offer one account
in the sheet.
Adding additional
credential types
to an existing ASAuthorization
request is really easy.
You just need to create
providers and requests
for the additional
request types,
then pass those new requests
to your controller.
Now, the modal sheet will
offer whatever credentials
are available from any
of these credential types.
You'll get the same
delegate callback
regardless of which
credential type is used.
You should check the type
of the credential you received
and finish the sign-in
as appropriate
for that credential type.
So that covers a few
of the more advanced features
of the ASAuthorization
API family.
Now, I'm going to dig in
to some more technical details
about how passkeys actually work
and what makes them so secure.
When you sign in
with a password today,
generally what's actually
happening
is after you enter
that password,
it gets hashed and salted, and
the resulting obfuscated value
is sent to the server,
which stores it.
Later, if you can produce
the same hashed salted value,
you're allowed into the account.
This means the server
is responsible
for storing this derivation
of your password,
which is highly valuable
to attackers.
If they can get it,
it's possible to figure out
what your password is
and gain access to your account.
Passkeys, however,
work very differently.
Rather than having a single,
typeable string,
a passkey is actually
a pair of related keys.
These keys are generated
by your devices,
securely and uniquely,
for every account.
One is public
and is stored on the server.
The other is private
and stays on your devices
even when signing in.
The public key
is not a secret.
It's just as public
as your user name.
The private key is what is
needed to actually sign in.
The server never learns
what your private key is,
and your devices keep it safe.
When you go to sign in,
the server sends your device
a single-use challenge.
WebAuthn allows many different
challenge-response algorithms,
but passkeys on Apple
platforms use standard ES256.
Only your private key
is capable of producing
a valid solution to
the challenge for your account.
Your device produces
this solution --
called a signature -- locally,
and only sends the solution
back to the server.
Your private key stays secret
and only on your devices.
The server then validates the
solution using your public key.
If the solution your device
provided is valid,
you're signed in!
A public key can be used
to check if a solution is valid
but is not able to produce
a solution itself.
This means
the server can be sure
that you have
the right private key,
without knowing what
the private key actually is.
And since the server doesn't
know any private keys,
it's a less valuable target
for attackers,
because there are
no user credentials to leak.
All of this cryptography
and key protection
is totally transparent
and performed by the devices.
Your customers never have
to know or think about it.
From their perspective,
passkeys are super simple
and just work, everywhere.
Passkeys can also be used
to sign in across devices
in a secure,
phishing-resistant manner.
Here's how that works.
There are two devices here.
The client, which is the
device or web browser
where I'm signing in,
and the authenticator,
which is the device
which has my passkey.
First, the client
shows a QR code,
which the
authenticator scans.
This QR code contains a URL
that encodes a pair
of single-use encryption keys.
Then, the authenticator produces
a Bluetooth advertisement
containing routing information
for a network relay server.
This local exchange
allows selecting a server
and sharing routing
information,
but also serves
two additional functions.
It performs an out-of-band
key agreement
that the server can't see,
so everything
going over the network
is end-to-end encrypted
and the server
can't read anything.
It also provides a strong claim
that these two devices
are in physical proximity.
That means a QR code
sent in an email
or generated on a fake
website won't work,
because a remote attacker
won't be able receive
the Bluetooth advertisement
and complete the local exchange.
So that's the local part.
Once the local exchange
and key agreement have happened,
the two devices connect
to a relay server
picked by the phone.
From there, they perform
a standard FIDO CTAP operation,
which is encrypted using
the keys from earlier,
so the relay server can't see
anything that's going on.
This whole process is
performed by the device
and the web browser.
The website is not involved
at any point
in the cross-device
communication.
Cross-device cross-platform
sign-in is a system feature
that just works anywhere
passkeys can be used.
So that's a more technical
look into how passkeys work
and how they can make such
strong security guarantees,
even across devices.
Next up,
multifactor authentication.
A common way to think about
authentication today
is in terms of factors.
Different factors
are strong or weak
against different kinds
of attacks,
and combining factors
can provide better
collective coverage.
But with passkeys, you don't
need to think like that anymore.
Here are some
of the most common methods
used to sign in today.
Passwords in your head
are vulnerable
to pretty much everything.
Password managers
are good at generating unique,
high-entropy strings,
may have local protections
against device theft,
and offer some hints
about phishing.
Adding an SMS
or time-based code
can help with theft or phishing
in some circumstances
but doesn't really
solve either.
With passkeys though,
every passkey is a unique,
device-generated key pair.
On Apple devices, they're
built on a strong foundation
of local device protections.
Passkeys also
completely eliminate
the human factor
from phishing.
And they can't be leaked
by an app or website server,
because the servers
don't have the private keys.
Adding factors to
a password-based sign-in flow
makes sense,
as together they can protect
against more types of attacks
than passwords alone.
But a passkey alone protects
against so much more
that it doesn't need
additional factors.
I'm looking forward to
a future without passwords.
Here's how you can get
started making that happen.
First off, you'll need to adopt
WebAuthn on your server,
if you haven't already done so.
Passkeys should work
with any standard WebAuthn
server implementation.
Once your server
is ready to go,
adopt our new API
in your apps and websites.
AutoFill-assisted passkey
requests can be dropped
right in to your existing
sign-in flows,
plus we have a range of more
advanced UI options as well,
if you need them.
And finally, transition your
users away from passwords.
Passkeys are
an industry-standard solution
to the convenience
and security problem
of securely signing in
to apps and websites.
By guiding your customers
to passkeys
and away from passwords,
you can give them
an incredibly quick and
convenient sign-in experience
while raising the security bar
for everyone.
Thank you.
♪