♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello, my name is Johnathan.
macOS developers submit
software to the notary service
in order to help protect
their customers
from malicious software.
Last year we introduced
a faster and simpler way
to submit apps for notarization
with the notarytool CLI
or command-line interface.
This year we are excited to
continue championing performance
and flexibility with
some major improvements
for your interactions
with the notary service.
In this session, we'll be
talking about three main topics.
First, we'll go through
important deadlines
for the migration from
using altool for notarization
to using notarytool.
Next, we'll discuss improvements
to the Xcode integration
with the upcoming Xcode 14,
bringing the submission speed
of notarytool to Xcode.
And finally, we'll talk about
a flexible new way
to interact with
the notary service,
a REST API, letting you expand
the places you can upload,
check the status of,
and review submissions.
Last year we introduced
notarytool,
a replacement for altool
for notarization.
Later in this talk,
I'll be discussing Xcode
moving to our updated backend
with Xcode 14.
With migration paths in place
for notarization
via altool and Xcode 13,
we're announcing the sunset date
for notarization
with these older methods
to be fall of 2023.
For help moving
from altool to notarytool,
please refer
to last year’s presentation
"Faster and simpler notarization
for Mac apps."
To highlight some specifics,
the notarytool CLI
will continue to work
past the fall 2023 deadline,
including the one
bundled in Xcode 13.
As always, however,
we do encourage you
to update to receive the latest
improvements and fixes.
Uploads to the notary service
using the Xcode 13 UI
will stop working
after that deadline.
Stay tuned to hear about
some performance improvements
in Xcode 14,
but largely you can expect
your workflow
to remain unchanged.
Finally, notarization
with all forms of altool
will stop working in fall 2023.
Again, please refer
to last year's WWDC presentation
for details on migrating
to notarytool.
Next, we'll touch on changes
to notarization in Xcode 14.
We've migrated
the notarization support
built into Xcode to use
the same reliable backend
as the notarytool CLI
we introduced last year.
Because of this,
we're happy to bring the same
roughly 4x performance increase
we announced last year
for notarytool to Xcode 14.
The best part is that,
besides updating,
you don't need to change your
project settings or workflows
to receive this
performance boost.
For the final topic
of this presentation,
we're excited to announce
a new service,
a REST API for notary.
This new service allows you
to interact more flexibly
with the notary service
in even more places.
To go over some
important concepts,
this new API
is intended to allow
for a more flexible interface
to the notary service.
As a JSON-based web service,
integration should be
fairly simple in most languages.
This API allows you
to upload submissions
from any place
with an internet connection,
including continuous
integration servers --
places where you might not
be running macOS today.
Additionally, other interactions
with the notary service
are also supported in this API,
such as retrieving
your submission history
or past submission details.
Our goal with introducing
the REST API
is to support submitting
software for notarization
from more platforms and to allow
for easier interactions
with notary
in automated systems.
This complements the current
methods of submission,
Xcode and notarytool,
where those can't be run today,
such as a Linux-based
continuous integration.
For example, imagine you want
your deployment pipeline
to submit your application
to notary
prior to distribution.
With this new API
and some basic scripts,
you can easily
automate the process.
Before I dive in,
one important topic
is authentication.
You can authenticate with
the API using JSON Web Tokens,
or JWTs, just like other
App Store Connect APIs.
For more details
on authentication
or the code I'm about to show,
please visit the REST API
documentation linked below.
In these snippets,
I'll assume you have a valid JWT
passed into the functions
as the token variable.
Let's walk through an example
of submitting files
to notary in Python.
This same basic flow
is applicable
in other programming languages.
There are two major steps
for uploading files to notary.
The first step
is to inform notary
that you wish to upload a file.
Included in this is some
basic information about the file
like name and SHA-256.
The response contains
information necessary
to upload the file and an ID
to track your submission
through our pipeline.
The second step actually uploads
the file for notarization
via Amazon S3.
You'll need to grab
your favorite S3 SDK.
For this example,
I'm going to be using
the boto3 library.
Here we use
the temporary credentials
returned in the previous call
to authenticate
and create a client.
We then use the client to upload
the file to the bucket
and object specified
in the first step's response.
Once uploaded,
the submission will proceed
though the
notarization pipeline.
This process should complete
in under 15 minutes
for most submissions.
After upload, you should confirm
the notary service
has successfully processed
your submission
prior to distribution.
There are, broadly speaking,
two approaches to this.
The first, and the simplest,
is checking the result
through the same API.
The other option is via
the webhook support
introduced with notarytool.
First, let's look at
the API approach.
Checking the status
of a submission to notary
is pretty straightforward,
You can make a request
with the submission ID
received during
the upload process
Part of the response
is the current status
of the submission,
which will remain "In Progress"
until notary is finished
processing it.
The status will then transition
to the final state
of your submission,
such as Accepted or Invalid.
Once the submission
is complete,
you can then use the API
to retrieve the notarization log
for this upload.
Please refer to the
Notary REST API documentation
for more details
on these endpoints.
Next, we'll talk about
the second approach
to getting your status:
a webhook.
In the webhook workflow,
the process is largely the same,
but this time you'll provide
a webhook URL
in the initial request
to upload.
Details on the format can be
found in the documentation
for the notary REST API.
As before, this will trigger
the notary service
to analyze your submission.
As the automated analysis
concludes, tickets are created,
and the final status is saved.
Once complete,
the notary service will call out
to the webhook URL provided.
The contents of this call
include the submission ID,
the team ID, and a signature
to verify it came from us.
On receiving that notification,
you can choose what to do next.
For example, you might notify
the original submitter
or begin an automated
distribution pipeline.
Compared to waiting
with notarytool,
this allows you to decouple
the system that uploads the file
from the system that automates
actions after notarization.
We're excited to see this new
REST API open the doors
to more integrations with
continuous integration systems
and other tools
to build software for macOS.
To wrap up,
as one more reminder,
the deadline to migrate
to using Xcode 14, notarytool,
or the REST API
directly is fall of 2023.
Finally, if you haven't yet
been able to use notarytool
in your deployment pipelines,
this is your chance
to jumpstart your automation
by trying the notary
REST API today.
You can find a link
to the documentation below.
Thank you, and I hope you enjoy
the rest of WWDC22
♪