♪ ♪
Hi, my name is Yi.
Hi, my name is Dominik.
And we are GPU software engineers.
Today, Dominik and I are going to talk
about the performance enhancements
and features we've added
to the Metal Ray Tracing API this year
to help you maximize the performance
of your ray tracing applications.
Ray tracing applications simulate
individual rays of light
bouncing around a scene.
This is used in games
and offline rendering to produce
photorealistic reflections,
shadows, global illumination, and more.
This requires simulating a lot of rays,
so performance is critical
for these applications.
Fortunately, Metal has
built-in support for ray tracing
optimized for all Apple devices.
Let's briefly review
how ray tracing works in Metal.
The Metal ray tracing API
is available from within shader functions
such as compute or fragment functions.
We start by generating some rays
which are emitted into the scene.
Next, we create an intersector object
and use it to check
for intersections between our rays
and the geometry in the scene.
A bit later,
I will describe some of the new features
we've added this year
to speed up the intersection search.
This process depends
on a special data structure
called an acceleration structure,
which also represents
the geometry in the scene.
I will also talk about several new
features and performance improvements
focused on acceleration structures today.
The intersector returns
an intersection result object
describing the primitive each ray hit.
The intersection result is used to produce
a color to write into the output image.
It can also be used
to produce additional rays
which go through the process again.
We can repeat this process
as many times as we'd like
to simulate light
bouncing around the scene.
If you want to learn more about
the basics of the Metal ray tracing API,
I recommend you review
our previous WWDC sessions.
We first introduced the Metal
ray tracing API at WWDC20,
and last year, we introduced new features
including support for motion blur.
Today, I'm going to talk
about three things.
First, I will tell you about new features
which enable you to improve
ray tracing performance
in your applications.
Next, I will talk about
improvements and features
we've added
to the acceleration structure API.
Finally, Dominik will tell you
about improvements
to our GPU tools for ray tracing.
This year, we've added three new features
aimed at either improving
ray tracing performance
or simplifying your code.
They are per-primitive data,
the ability to retrieve buffers
from intersection function tables,
and support for ray tracing
from indirect command buffers.
Let's start with per-primitive data.
Applications usually have data associated
with the primitive in their scene
such as vertex colors, normals,
and texture coordinates.
This year,
we've added the ability to store
small amounts of data for each primitive
directly in the acceleration structure.
This data can be accessed with fewer
memory indirections and cache misses,
improving performance.
This also reduces the need to store
complicated auxiliary data structure
which are typically required to look up
the data associated with your primitives.
Let's look at an example.
Alpha testing is a technique
used to add complexity
to transparent geometry
without increasing the triangle count.
In this technique, the alpha channel
of a texture mapped onto a triangle
is used to determine if the ray should
hit the triangle or continue further.
To achieve this,
you need to configure the intersector
to call your custom intersection function
when a triangle is hit by the ray.
The ultimate goal is to sample from
the texture associated with the triangle
and test if the alpha value allows the ray
to continue through the primitive.
To get there,
you need two pieces of information:
the texture object and the UV coordinates.
In a typical implementation
of alpha testing,
you would need to access
a number of intermediate buffers
in Metal device memory
in order to get this information.
First, you would store the texture
associated with the primitive
in some kind of material structure.
Several materials would be
packed into a buffer.
It would be impractical to store
material structure for every primitive,
as they may be pretty big
and there may be a lot of primitives.
Instead, you would want to store
just the material IDs
for each primitive in a buffer
and use them to look up the materials.
Next, to calculate UVs,
you need to load the UVs
for each vertex from another buffer
and interpolate them.
Finally, let's say you are
using instanced geometry.
You may want each instance
to have its own materials and UV mappings.
To support that, you would store pointers
to UV and Material ID buffers
in an Instance Data buffer,
adding yet another level
of indirection to your function.
This approach requires you to maintain
a fairly complex buffer setup
and involves many layers of indirection
to get to the data that you need.
This may also lead to cache misses
that would negatively affect
the performance.
Let's look at the code needed
to implement this diagram.
Then I will show you
how you can simplify it step-by-step
using per-primitive data.
This is the original implementation of
the alpha testing intersection function.
This function is invoked when
the ray hits an alpha tested triangle.
The function starts by loading
the instance data from the memory.
This is the buffer that contains pointers
to UV and material buffers
used by the instance.
Next, the function loads
the UV coordinates
from the UV buffer and interpolates them.
This is another memory load.
Then, the function loads
the material index from another buffer.
And finally,
the function loads the material
and samples the corresponding texture.
At this point, the function has
the alpha value it needs
and can compare it to the threshold.
Now, I will show you
how you can simplify this code
and improve its performance
using per-primitive data.
Instead of using
a complicated buffer setup
with multiple layers of indirection,
you can simply store only the data
the intersection function will need
for each primitive
directly in the acceleration structure.
In this example, you can create a struct
containing the texture and UV coordinates
for each primitive.
You provide this data when building
the acceleration structure
and the intersection function
simply receives a pointer
to that data
when a ray hits the primitive.
You can store anything you like
in the per-primitive data,
but keeping the size small will
help achieve the best performance.
I will start with the inputs
to the intersection function.
Having access to all of them gives you
a lot of flexibility
when it comes to the implementation,
but it can also increase
the register usage on the GPU.
With per-primitive data,
instead of all the buffers,
you only need to access
the primitive data pointer.
This is the data you store
directly in the acceleration structure.
In this case, each primitive has
its own texture object and UVs
for all of its vertices.
Next up are the loads from the global
material buffer and instance data buffer.
You won't need either of them.
Instead, you can do one load
from the per-primitive data pointer.
This is the only device memory access
needed in this function.
Next up are the UVs.
Instead of dereferencing a pointer
retrieved from the instance data,
you can simply access the data embedded
in the per-primitive data structure.
The change in the code is subtle,
but is important for performance,
as no additional
memory loads are involved.
Finally, there are
the material properties.
Since the only part of the material
needed is the texture,
you can encode the primitive's texture
directly in the per-primitive
data structure.
This means you don't need to access
the material
and material index buffers anymore.
You can simply use the texture directly
without paying the cost
of additional memory dereferences.
This is how much simpler
your intersection code can be
when using per-primitive data.
All the costly memory accesses
are replaced
with just one load
from the primitive data pointer.
On top of that, the code is
much simpler and easier to follow.
Next, I will show you
how to store the primitive data
in the acceleration structure.
You will need to do this before you can
access it from an intersection function.
You will need to set a few fields
in the acceleration structure
geometry descriptor.
First, set the Metal buffer
where all the data is stored.
Next, specify the size of the data
that will be stored for each primitive.
If your data is not tightly packed
in the buffer
or doesn't start
at the beginning of the buffer,
you can also specify
the stride and the offset.
Otherwise, these values default to 0
so you don't need to set them.
You have already seen
how you can use per-primitive data
in an intersection function.
It's simply passed
into the function as a pointer.
But that's not all–you have access
to this data wherever you need it.
That includes the final intersection
result returned by the intersector.
And if you are using intersection query,
the primitive data is also available
for both candidate
and committed intersections.
This means you can use per-primitive data
for shading
in addition to intersection testing.
Per-primitive data can
improve the performance
of both your intersection code
and your shading code
by reducing the number
of memory accesses and indirections.
In fact, we found
in one of our own test applications
that using per-primitive data resulted
in a 10% to 16% performance improvement.
We can't wait for you to try it out
and see what kinds of improvements
you can get
in performance and code quality.
This year, we've also added
another convenience feature
to the Metal shading language to help you
simplify your ray tracing kernels.
Applications often pass
the same set of bindings
to both their intersection functions
and their main ray tracing kernel.
For example,
our ray tracing sample code uses
an intersection function
to render spheres.
This intersection function
accesses a resource buffer
containing information about each sphere.
In order to pass this buffer
into the intersection function,
the app binds the buffer
to the intersection function table.
However, the main ray tracing kernel
also needs access to the resource buffer,
so the app binds the buffer there as well.
This year,
the Metal shading language allows you
to access the buffers
bound to intersection function tables.
With this new feature,
you can save the effort
of binding the buffer for the kernel,
and instead access it directly
from the intersection function table.
You can do this by calling
the get_buffer method
on the intersection function table,
providing its pointer type.
You can also access visible
function tables by their function type.
Indirect command buffers allow you to
encode GPU work independently on the GPU
and represent a fundamental element
of GPU driven pipelines.
To learn more about
indirect command buffers
and GPU-driven rendering,
we recommend you review
the "Modern rendering with Metal"
session from WWDC 2019.
Enabling ray tracing support
in an indirect command buffer is easy.
All you have to do is to set
the supportRayTracing flag
on the descriptor.
Indirect command buffers
dispatch graphics and compute functions,
so you can simply use ray tracing
from those functions as usual.
That's a rundown of all
the new features we've added this year
to help you get improved ray tracing
performance in your applications.
Next, let's talk
about acceleration structures.
We've implemented several
performance improvements
and added features focused
on building acceleration structures.
Let's recap what they are used for.
Acceleration structures
are data structures
which accelerate the ray tracing process.
They do this
by recursively partitioning space
so we can quickly find which triangles
are likely to intersect a ray.
To support building complex scenes,
Metal supports two types
of acceleration structures:
primitive and instance
acceleration structures.
Individual pieces of geometry
are represented
using primitive acceleration structures.
They can be something simple
like a plane or a cube,
or something more complex
like a sphere or a triangle mesh.
You can create more complex scenes
using an instance acceleration structure.
Instance acceleration structures
create copies
of primitive acceleration structures.
First, define transformation matrices
for each object in your scene.
Then, use the array
of transformation matrices
and primitive acceleration structures
to build
an instance acceleration structure.
That's how you can build a static scene
using acceleration structures.
Next, let's see how dynamic applications
like a game would use
acceleration structures.
Let's start at the beginning:
there are several tasks you need to do
when first launching a game
or loading a new level.
This includes the normal tasks
like loading models and textures.
With ray tracing, you also need to build
primitive acceleration structures
for all of the models which will be used.
We recommend that you build as many
of your primitive acceleration structures
as possible at load time
to save time in your main rendering loop.
You can use
an instance acceleration structure
to add or remove these objects
from the scene as needed.
Once your app is done loading,
it enters the main loop.
Every frame,
it renders the scene using a combination
of rasterization, ray tracing,
and post-processing.
However, since games are very dynamic,
you will probably need to update
some of the acceleration structures.
This typically includes refitting
a handful of deforming
or animated models
such as skinned characters.
Refitting an existing
acceleration structure is much faster
than a full rebuild, so we recommend
using it for cases like this.
You should also do a full rebuild
of the instance acceleration structure.
This is necessary since objects may have
been added or removed
from the scene since the last frame,
or they may have moved significantly.
Doing a full rebuild is fine in this case
since there's only one
instance acceleration structure
and it usually only contains at most
a few thousand objects.
This year, we've improved performance
for all of these cases.
First, acceleration structure builds
are now up to 2.3 times faster
on Apple Silicon.
Second, refitting is also
up to 38% faster.
This means that both load times
and per-frame overhead are reduced.
But it gets even better.
Some applications build hundreds
or even thousands
of small primitive
acceleration structures.
These small builds
don't do enough work individually
to fill up the GPU, resulting in
long periods of low GPU utilization.
Therefore, multiple builds are
now automatically performed
in parallel whenever possible
on Apple Silicon.
This results
in up to 2.8 times faster builds
when they run in parallel.
This further reduces load times.
And this doesn't just apply to builds:
it applies to all
of the acceleration structure operations
including compacting and refitting,
so your per-frame overhead
is reduced as well.
There are a few guidelines
you will need to follow
to ensure that you can benefit
from this optimization.
Here is an example that builds
an array of acceleration structures.
To build them in parallel,
you will need to ensure that you use
the same acceleration structure
command encoder for many builds.
Additionally, builds which use the same
scratch buffer can't run in parallel.
Therefore, you will want to ensure
that you are looping through a small pool
of scratch buffers rather than using
the same scratch buffer for each build.
Those are all the performance improvements
we've made to building
acceleration structures.
We've also added three new features
to make building acceleration structures
easier and more efficient.
They are support for additional
vertex formats, transformation matrices,
and acceleration structure allocation
from heaps.
Let's start with vertex formats.
A common performance optimization
is to use quantized
or reduced precision formats
for vertex data,
resulting in lower memory usage.
This year, you can build
acceleration structures
from a wide range of vertex formats.
This includes half precision
floating point formats,
two component vertex formats
for planar geometry,
and all the usual
normalized integer formats.
Previously,
acceleration structures have required
three component,
full-precision floating point vertex data.
In this example,
the application has vertex data
in a half precision vertex format.
This data needs to be unpacked
and copied into a temporary buffer
just to build the acceleration structure.
With the new vertex formats feature,
acceleration structure builds
can now consume vertex data
in any of the supported formats,
eliminating the need to create
a temporary copy.
Setting the vertex format
couldn't be simpler.
All you need to do is set the property
on your geometry descriptor.
Next, let's talk about
transformation matrices.
This feature complements
the new vertex formats,
so that you can pre-transform
your vertex data
before building
the acceleration structure.
For example, you might want to use them
to unpack complex meshes
stored in a normalized format.
Let's consider
the Red Panda model in this scene.
To normalize the geometry to use
one of our compressed formats,
you take the mesh, calculate its bounds,
and then scale them
to a zero to one range.
You can then use one of the normalized
integer vertex formats to store the mesh,
reducing the amount of space
it takes up on disk and in memory.
At runtime,
you provide a matrix that will scale
and offset each vertex
to the final position.
Applying that matrix
retrieves the original model.
Now let's walk through
how to set up acceleration structure
passing a transformation matrix.
You start by creating
the transform buffer.
One way of doing this is to create
an MTLPackedFloat4x3 object
containing the scale
and offset transformation matrix.
Then, create a Metal Buffer
big enough to hold the matrix.
And finally,
copy the matrix to the Buffer.
Next, set up the acceleration structure.
First, create
a triangle geometry descriptor.
Then, specify
the transformation Matrix Buffer.
And finally the Buffer Offset.
That's all you need to do to set up
the transformation matrix.
These matrices can also be used
to combine simple acceleration structures
to improve ray tracing performance.
Let's see an example scene.
Here, the boxes and the spheres
are all relatively simple meshes.
This presents an opportunity
to optimize the acceleration structure
for this group at the front of the scene.
Focusing on
the instance acceleration structure,
there is an overhead for each instance
that your rays hit.
There is a cost for transforming the ray
and then switching from the instance
to the primitive acceleration structure.
This occurs more often
with overlapping instances.
To reduce the instance count,
you can generate
a single primitive acceleration structure
that contains
both the boxes and the sphere.
To do this,
you can create a geometry descriptor
for each object,
each with its own transformation matrix.
The resulting primitive acceleration
structure is a single instance
in the instance acceleration structure
and contains the boxes and sphere.
This should result in a better
performing acceleration structure.
Let's see how to set this up in code.
You start with the descriptor
that defines the sphere geometry.
Next, set the vertex buffer,
index buffer, and other properties
as usual
for a primitive acceleration structure.
The difference is, you also specify
the transform buffer
that contains the transformation matrix
used for the copy of the sphere.
For the boxes,
you have multiple geometry descriptors
sharing a vertex and index buffer.
You just need to specify different
transform buffers for each copy.
Finally, when creating the descriptor
for the primitive acceleration structure,
add all the geometry descriptors.
This will result
in a primitive acceleration structure
that you can instance into the scene
with an identity transform.
This primitive acceleration structure
will take less time to build
than separate acceleration structures
and will be faster to intersect.
Finally, heap allocation
of acceleration structures has been
one of our most requested features.
With this feature,
you now have more control
over acceleration structure allocation.
It also allows you to reuse
heap memory between allocations,
avoiding expensive buffer allocations.
Heaps can also help improve performance
by reducing calls
to the useResource: method when using
instance acceleration structures.
Going back to the example scene,
the instance acceleration structure
references
primitive acceleration structures
indirectly.
This means that each time you want to use
an instance acceleration structure
with a command encoder,
you need to call useResource: method
for each primitive acceleration structure.
For large scenes,
this could require thousands of calls
to useResource: each time you use
the instance acceleration structure.
Knowing that you have
so many useResource: calls,
you could call useResources:
to reduce the number of API calls,
but you still need to maintain
an array of your acceleration structures
and Metal still needs to loop
through the array.
Instead, you can allocate
all of these primitive acceleration
structures from the same heap.
When you want to use
the instance acceleration structure,
you can simply make a single call
to the useHeap: method
to reference all
of the primitive acceleration structures.
We saw a small performance improvement
in one application
simply by replacing the calls
to useResource:
with a single call to useHeap:.
Let's see how you can allocate
an acceleration structure from a heap.
You can directly allocate an acceleration
structure by calling a method on the heap
that takes the acceleration structure
descriptor as the input.
If you are not allocating
using the descriptor,
the Metal device determines
the size and alignment requirement
for allocating
the acceleration structure from a heap.
You can get this information
from the Metal device
by providing the descriptor
or acceleration structure size.
Once the final size is determined,
you can allocate the acceleration
structure from the heap.
There are a few things to remember
when using heaps.
First, remember to call useHeap:
to make all of the acceleration structures
in the heap resident
for the duration of the ray tracing pass.
Second, by default, Metal doesn't track
resources you allocate from a heap.
You can either opt-in
to resource hazard tracking,
or you can manually manage
your own synchronization.
You can use MTLFences to synchronize
across command encoders
and MTLEvents to synchronize
across command buffers.
Those are the new features
and performance improvements
in the Metal ray tracing API this year.
Next, Dominik will talk about improvements
to Xcode's Metal tools
that will boost your productivity
when developing ray tracing applications.
Dominik: Thanks, Yi.
There are a lot of enhancements
to the Metal tools in Xcode 14,
but here, I would like to highlight
just a few
that are especially useful
when developing ray tracing applications
Starting with the Metal debugger,
I'll talk about improvements
to the Acceleration Structure Viewer,
Shader Profiler, and Shader Debugger.
Then I'll round it up
with the runtime Shader Validation.
First, let's take a look
at the Acceleration Structure Viewer.
The Acceleration Structure Viewer in
the Metal Debugger enables you to inspect,
in great detail,
all of the geometries and instances
of all the meshes that make up
your acceleration structure.
Xcode 14 now supports
debugging acceleration structures
with primitive or instanced motion
and a new highlight mode
for visualizing primitives
with an inspector for per-primitive data.
Let's see them in action.
If you are using
acceleration structures with motion,
you now have a scrubber in the bottom bar
for viewing your acceleration structure
at different points in time.
On the right of the scrubber
is a "play" button.
You can use it to play the animation
back and forth in a loop.
Now let me show you
how to inspect individual primitives
in your acceleration structure.
This is especially useful if you are
using the new per-primitive data API.
And so there's a new highlight mode
just for this.
Primitive highlight mode gives you access
to all primitive data...
And allows you to select specific
primitives for detailed inspection.
In the left sidebar,
you can find arrows next to the data rows.
Clicking on an arrow will reveal a popover
that displays the corresponding data
for the primitive.
These additions
to the acceleration structure viewer
ensure you have full access,
down to each primitive,
to all of the components
that make up your acceleration structure.
Next, let's talk about improvements
to the Shader Profiler.
The Shader Profiler gives you insights
into the performance of your shader,
providing per-pipeline
execution timing costs,
and on Apple GPUs, it provides
more granularity at the source level,
showing the execution costs per-line
distributed across instruction categories.
In Xcode 14,
profiling GPU captures has been updated
to support intersection functions,
visible functions, and dynamic libraries.
Here we have a ray tracing kernel
using an intersection function.
You can now view
the per-line profiling results
inside of the intersection function.
This includes a breakdown
of the instruction categories
that contribute to the cost.
Profiling visible functions
works the same way.
And similarly,
detailed profiling information
is now available for shader code
from linked dynamic libraries.
With these additions,
you now have the full breakdown
of the performance of your pipeline,
down to each line of code.
Moving on to the Shader Debugger.
The Shader Debugger provides
a unique
and incredibly productive workflow
for debugging the correctness
of your shader code.
Just like with the Shader Profiler,
we've also extended support
to enable debugging of Linked functions
and Dynamic libraries.
Here we have a ray tracing kernel
that calls out
to a linked visible function passed in
through a visible function table.
You are now able to follow
the execution of a kernel
all the way
into your visible function code
to verify that the code behaves
as you expect it to.
Again, the same applies
to debugging dynamic libraries.
You are also able to jump into
and out of any executed dynamic libraries
that are linked to your pipeline.
With these additions, you now have
a complete picture
of your shader execution
across linked functions
and libraries in your pipeline.
Now, before you capture
and jump into the Shader Debugger,
it is often a good idea to enable
Shader Validation at runtime.
Shader validation is a great way
to diagnose runtime errors on the GPU,
catching issues
such as out-of-bound memory accesses,
null texture reads, and more.
To enable Shader Validation in Xcode,
all you need to do is to go
to the "Edit Scheme" dialog,
select the "Run" action,
and under the "diagnostics" tab
tick the "Shader Validation" checkbox.
And you are all set to go.
In Metal 3, we have added
Stack Overflow detection
which will help you quickly find issues
that would otherwise result
in undefined behavior.
I'll quickly elaborate
on the function stack in Metal shaders
and the problem of Stack Overflow.
The call stack is a region
in device memory
where Metal stores the values of local
data used in your shader functions.
If the called function is
not known at compile time,
Metal needs your help in estimating
the amount of memory required
for the stack.
An example of a call to a function
that is unknown at compile time
may be a ray tracing
intersection function.
If you are using
custom intersection functions,
maximum call stack depth should be
set to 1, to allocate space for it.
This is the default value, so there is
nothing more that you need to do.
However, if you are using Function Tables
to call into a Visible function,
this is another example of a function call
unknown at compile time.
If you perform such a call
from an intersection function,
like in this example,
your call stack will be two levels deep.
Another example are calls
to dynamic libraries
and calling a local function
using a function pointer.
In this example, our call stack has
four levels with nested calls
to different types of functions
that cannot be resolved
when the shader is compiled.
To properly configure Metal
to allocate the right amount of memory,
you need to specify a maximum
call stack depth of 4 yourself.
The important thing to remember
is that when the value
of the max Call Stack Depth is set
too low for your program,
Stack Overflow can happen,
resulting in undefined behavior.
But if you are running
with Shader Validation enabled,
such situations will be caught early,
and you will see information in Xcode
about where the Stack Overflow occurred.
You can then go and fix your shader code,
or adjust your maximum call stack depth
in the pipeline descriptor.
All of these new improvements
to the Metal tools in Xcode 14
ensure you have an even more
complete picture and insight
into the performance and correctness
of your ray tracing applications.
For more on how to get the most
out of the Metal tools for debugging
and profiling,
check out these other sessions
This session has been all about
maximizing Metal ray tracing performance
for your applications.
We talked about
how you can squeeze out more performance
and simplify your code using new features
such as per-primitive data.
We also described
optimization techniques and features
that make building accelerations
structures faster and more convenient
than ever before.
Finally, we covered all the new
enhancements to the Metal tools
in Xcode 14 that will provide you
with deeper insight
during your development.
Thanks for watching.