♪ ♪
Welcome to Profile and
Optimize Your Game's Memory.
I'm Jack Xu (许) from GPU Software team
at Apple.
We're joined by my colleague Seth Lù (陆).
In the last few years,
our teams have been working
with game developers like you
to understand
and improve game memory together.
Today, we want to share our learnings,
so you can also have a head start
when you debug your game's memory
and create awesome games
with the best player experience.
We're going to break down memory usage in
your game, from both CPU and GPU objects.
Plus, analyze allocations in your game,
actual use on physical memory,
and references between objects.
Because there are many facets of memory,
our developer tools also reveal
memory mysteries from different angles.
We'll take a guided tour,
and experience how we use all of them,
including Xcode, Instruments,
and command line tools in Terminal.
In today's guided tour, we will begin
with a prelude to understand game memory.
And start to profile memory
and memory growth,
where Seth will tell us about Instruments.
After taking the temporal approach with
Instruments, we will further our journey,
and analyze the memory graph of your game
using tools in Xcode and Terminal.
These workflows focus on
the current state of memory use,
and the breakdown
of the total game memory.
Finally, Seth will share
how you can use Metal Debugger
to optimize Metal resources,
which is a somewhat standalone,
yet core area in game memory.
Now, let's start rolling
with understanding game memory.
When you launch your game from Xcode,
such as the Modern Rendering
with Metal sample code,
you can open this Memory Report
in Xcode's debug navigator.
It is your first view on the game's
current and recent memory usage,
and its impact level on the system.
The number on the gauge shows you
the current memory use of the game.
An important first step
in memory debugging
is to understand what this number means.
To put it in one line,
actual memory use in your game
is not the same as allocations.
Actual memory use is on physical memory.
While allocations
is the memory requested by the game,
on the virtual memory address space.
And different kinds of allocations
are naturally calculated separately.
When your game allocates memory,
those new allocations do not immediately
nor directly take up space
on physical memory.
On the contrary, they will reserve some
space on virtual memory address space,
which the system provides
for each process.
And when the program actually
uses this allocation later,
will the system prepare space
on physical memory.
Allocations of the same kind
are grouped into categories,
and sparsely occupy
the virtual address space.
These categories may include:
the program's executable binary;
all the libraries and frameworks;
the stack, providing storage
for local and temporary variables
as well as some function arguments;
dynamic memory regions also known as heap;
including class instance storage
and memory the program manually allocates;
regions mapped from read-only resources
such as game asset files;
and of course, Metal objects in your game,
such as buffers, textures,
and pipeline state objects.
And these categories are made of regions.
Under the hood, memory operations
work at the granularity of memory pages,
which are 16 kibibytes each
on modern Apple devices.
This means each region takes up
one or more pages,
and is at least 16 kibibytes large.
As the game continues,
the state of its memory keeps evolving;
new objects get allocated,
old items get destroyed,
the regions keep changing.
But only used pages on the regions
are on physical memory,
which the system diligently charges
to your game,
as to any other apps.
Memory pages in your game
can be one of three kinds:
dirty, compressed, and clean.
Let's check out what they are.
Dirty memory pages includes memory
that your game has written to.
This includes memory allocations in heap,
and frameworks, once your game modifies
those variables or symbols.
On devices with Apple silicon,
accessed Metal resources
also fall into this category,
this is because CPU and GPU share
the same pool of fast unified memory.
However, if some dirty pages
are not used for a long time,
the system might reduce
their presence on physical memory
by compressing these pages
or storing them on flash or disk,
which we call swapping.
This will allow the device
to run more apps and services.
Later, when your game asks
for these pages again,
the system will decompress
or page in them from disk.
Note, your game will still get charged
for their uncompressed size.
For clean memory pages,
they include read-only files
mapped from disk,
such as texture or audio assets,
and frameworks loaded into the process.
The system can empty or reload them
from disk at any time,
so they don't count towards
your game's memory footprint.
However, they may be resident on memory,
and excessive use will slow down
the system and your game.
It's usually the most interesting
to look at the first two parts,
which combined, we call memory footprint.
And the system uses this
to enforce memory limit.
In some terminologies,
people say "dirty memory"
when they mean memory footprint,
as dirty is the opposite of clean.
But don't worry, when things become fuzzy,
we will call out which one we mean.
So now you know how memory works,
and how system charges it to the game.
Besides this Xcode memory gauge,
you can find memory footprint
in many places on the system,
including the Activity Monitor app on Mac.
And some Apple platforms use it
for app memory limits.
Your game can also use this metric
to guide its memory use.
There are useful APIs to query
current footprint and available memory.
Here's a quick look.
To get available system memory
for your iOS, iPadOS or tvOS game,
call os_proc_available_memory,
which is in os/proc.h header file.
And for memory footprint
on any Apple platform,
you can get it via proc_pid_rusage,
with process ID from "get pid",
"rusage_info_current",
which is version 6 at the moment,
and the data store.
And retrieve its physical footprint or
lifetime max physical footprint property.
To recap, in this first section,
we reviewed some concepts about memory.
Allocations in your game happen
on virtual memory address space,
and they will take up physical
memory space as 16 kibibyte pages,
once they're accessed by your game.
Memory footprint is the primary
and universal metric on Apple platforms
to determine your game's
actual memory use.
Memory footprint contains dirty,
compressed, and swapped pages.
It includes both CPU and GPU objects
on Apple silicon.
And it's used for
memory limit enforcement.
Your game can call system APIs to
get its footprint, and available memory.
Now that you know how memory works
behind the scenes,
let's find out how it looks in your game.
Let me hand over to Seth,
to tell you more.
Seth Lù: Thanks, Jack.
Now, let's get started with capturing
the memory growth for a game.
And I'll continue to use
the Modern Renderer sample project.
When you run a game from Xcode,
the Memory Gauge shows you
the memory footprint over time.
However, you can get a much more detailed
look at the memory use
by profiling the game in Instruments.
Because oftentimes a game could
allocate a lot of memory at launch time,
you may want to begin profiling
from a new game launch
instead of attaching to an existing run.
From Xcode,
to quickly begin profiling your game,
press and hold the run button,
then choose "Profile".
This will automatically bring you
to Instruments.
The Instruments app includes
a collection of profiling tools
that record different aspects
of the system
and visualizes the recorded data
on a timeline.
New this year is the Game Memory template
that can help you better understand
the memory growth in your Metal game.
This template comes with the Allocations
and Metal Resource Events instruments
to record memory allocations with history,
VM Tracker to record memory footprint,
Virtual Memory Trace
to record virtual memory activity,
and Metal Application and GPU
to record Metal-related events.
And in this demo, I'll highlight
the first three instruments:
Allocations, Metal Resource Events,
and VM Tracker.
But first,
let's record a trace for the game.
You can press the record button here
to start recording.
And later, to stop recording,
you can press the same button
or simply quit the game.
While Instruments is recording
the Modern Renderer,
let me show you an alternative way
to record a trace.
The xctrace command allows you
to programmatically perform recordings,
which may be useful
in automation workflows.
Additionally,
you can specify the device name
to choose an iPhone,
iPad, or Apple TV as the target.
Now that I have captured
an Instruments trace,
let's first take a look at Allocations.
The Allocations instrument gives you
a detailed view of memory allocations,
their sizes, and object reference counts.
However, it doesn't include
private Metal resources.
The Statistics view displays
all heap allocations and anonymous VM.
The All Heap Allocations include malloc'ed
buffers which may contain objects,
and All Anonymous VM includes
interesting VM regions that may be dirty.
And we'll see in a moment that some
Metal resources belong to this category.
Now, let's take a look
inside All Heap Allocations.
Usually, the larger allocations
are more interesting for optimization.
To find the single largest allocation, you
can click on the Size table column
to sort the allocations by size.
For an allocation,
you can click on this arrow
to see the reference count changes
for Swift and Objective-C objects.
And with this large allocation selected
in the list,
there is the stack trace of
the allocation history in the inspector.
Clicking on the button allows
hiding the system libraries or frameworks.
And here, according to the stack trace,
the allocation happened
when Modern Renderer loaded the assets.
Double clicking on the frame
can also bring you to the source code.
Now, let's go back and take a look inside
the "All Anonymous VM" category.
In Metal games, you may find
a lot of allocations in the IOAccelerator
and IOSurface categories.
Allocations in IOAccelerator
correspond to Metal resources.
From the stack trace, you can see this
allocation happened while loading assets.
Allocations in IOSurface
correspond to drawables.
And here, the stack trace shows
the MetalKit view requested the drawable.
The Allocations instrument, by default,
visualizes the allocation size.
However, it also comes with
alternative looks.
You can on the arrow button
in the Allocations track
to customize the display mode
to visualize Allocation Density.
This will update the graph to show you the
amount of allocations performed over time
and reveal spikes for memory allocations.
These spikes may be sources
of memory growth.
So the data shown in Allocations
is quite low-level.
To get a better understanding
of the allocated Metal resources,
let's move on to Metal Resource Events.
The Metal Resource Events instrument
is designed around Metal resources.
In the Resource Events view,
you can find a history of Metal resource
allocations and deallocations.
Here, you could also identify
the Metal resources by their labels
which you can specify programmatically
through the Metal API.
And similar to the Allocations instrument,
you can find a stack trace for
the allocation history in the inspector.
This instrument also adds the Allocation
and the Deallocations track
under the Metal device.
They help visualize the density of events.
So far,
Allocations and Metal Resource Events
can help understand memory allocations.
However, allocations don't always
translate to memory footprint.
So let's move on to VM Tracker
to investigate the actual memory use.
The VM Tracker instrument
shows the non-compressed dirty
and compressed or swapped memory.
The Dirty Size represents
the non-compressed dirty memory.
And the Swapped Size represents
the compressed or swapped memory.
In this recording, there's no compressed
or swapped memory use
from the Modern Renderer.
The detailed Summary view
shows the VM regions.
And in the "mapped file" region,
you may find some memory-mapped resources
like your game assets.
Here, Modern Renderer maps
the bistro asset file into memory.
So that's a brief overview
of the Allocations,
Metal Resource Events
and VM Tracker in Instruments.
To quickly recap
how you can profile memory growth:
First, choose the Game Memory template,
and then, record and analyze the trace.
Sometimes, you may repeat this process
a few times
when reproducing or verifying
memory growth patterns.
We hope the new Game Memory template
can help you better understand
the memory allocation
or footprint growth in your game.
And please check out these other videos
to learn more about using Instruments.
Now, back to Jack.
The game Memory template
looks really cool,
and it's going to be so useful
to help with understanding changes
of memory use over time.
In addition, you might also want
to capture the memory state of the game
at a given time, so you can dig deeper
into that memory state
and examine it through different lenses.
And for that, we have memory graphs
and a suite of tools.
Memory graph is a file
to efficiently store a complete snapshot
of your game's memory state,
including object creation history,
references,
and any compression or swapping.
You can take a snapshot anytime you want,
such as when an issue occurs,
or a pair of those,
before and after an issue happened
for comparison.
To spice things up,
let's use a cookbook analogy
on how to analyze memory
with memory graphs.
It includes an ingredient
and a preparation part.
For the Ingredients, well,
you would need your game;
something called Malloc Stack Logging;
and, a captured memory graph.
It's quick to configure
Malloc Stack Logging
and to capture a memory graph.
Malloc Stack Logging records allocation
information in the game process.
You can find it in Scheme settings.
Choose the Run action,
go to Diagnostics,
and tick the Malloc Stack Logging
checkbox.
In case you wonder what the two
options are;
All Allocation and Free History
keeps track of all objects
even after they are deallocated.
The logging data may take up more memory,
but it's useful for debugging issues
such as fragmentation.
On the other hand, Live Allocation Only
discards deallocated objects
from its history, so it's lighter.
In this case,
I'm only investigating references,
which are on live objects,
so I can pick this option.
In fact, most of the time,
Live Allocation Only will be
your recommended option.
Alternatively, you can set environment
variable if not launching from Xcode.
Check out the malloc manual page
for some additional recording modes.
After that, also prepare a memory graph.
Just click on
the debug memory graph button
in the debug area.
Xcode will take a memory snapshot,
process it, and enter the memory debugger.
Xcode Memory Debugger provides intuitive
perspectives into the game's memory use.
Let's take a minute to explore the view.
On the left side,
Debug Navigator gives you
a hierarchical list of object instances.
On the right, File Inspector provides
useful information
such as memory footprint,
uptime, and capture date.
In the middle area
shines the memory graph view
where you have the selected object
from the left,
and how references connect to this object.
I'll come back to this graph in a bit.
And the File menu gives you the option
to save this memory graph
for future analysis,
or to easily share with your team.
For a Mac game,
you can also capture a memory graph
with the leaks command line program,
using process ID or name.
This means you could do it remotely
in a secure shell,
so the cursor stays in the game,
in case your game is running fullscreen
and needs to stay in focus.
So that's what you'll need
to start memory graph analysis.
Now it's time to examine this memory graph
using Xcode Memory Debugger,
plus some versatile command line tools
in Terminal,
to find out allocations,
footprint, and even more.
A good first step
is to break down memory use by categories.
The footprint program does just that.
Footprint uses information in the memory
graph to recreate this high level summary.
Typically, you will want to first focus
on the larger categories.
For game memory graphs such as this one
from the Modern Rendering sample code,
IOAccelerator is usually the largest one.
As Seth said, it includes Metal resources.
Here, heap allocations go to several
MALLOC_(prefixed) categories,
since the system groups heap allocations
to size pools to improve performance.
These objects may come from many places,
such as third-party plugins,
or libraries, where your game does
sound effects or physics simulation.
Here's a memory graph
from an awesome Apple Arcade game,
Manifold Garden,
created by William "Cheer" Studio.
I'm glad they allow me to show you
the game's memory usage.
If your game uses a game engine,
like Manifold Garden using Unity,
or a custom allocator
on top of memory map,
that memory would be shown as
untagged VM_ALLOCATE like this.
Here's a pro tip: on Apple platforms,
your game can use
up to 16 app-specific tags,
so you can have more clarity
when drilling down memory usage.
It's as easy as a one line change.
First, make the tag
from one of 16 options.
Then replace the minus one with
this new tag as the "file descriptor",
when calling "em map".
Check out "em map's" manual page to learn
how tags and categories are defined.
If you use "mach VM allocate",
include the same flag in
the flag argument when allocating.
In the world of footprint program,
the dirty size also includes swap
and compressed,
so think of it as total charged
for each category.
That's a brief idea of the composition
of current memory use,
and how it makes up the footprint.
Some of this memory is less used
and become compressed or swapped.
They might be sources of memory savings.
The next step is to find out
how much compressed
or swapped memory the game uses,
and optimize.
For this, you can run the memory graph
with vmmap.
It gives you dirty and swapped sizes,
instead of two combined.
This dirty column includes
currently not swapped
or compressed regular dirty memory,
while the swapped column includes
the original size
of compressed or swapped memory.
The system adds these two columns together
to determine footprint.
But since content in the swapped size
column isn't used as often,
it is a good indicator
for what to look for
to optimize your game's memory.
Oh, by the way,
here is the allocation size,
with the virtual size column.
And the resident size includes clean pages
such as executables
and memory mapped files.
Conveniently, vmmap shows
heap allocations with a separate table.
At the bottom of its output,
vmmap groups heap memory by zones.
These zones reflect their usage
or lifecycle in your game.
Because I turned on MallocStackLogging,
allocations on the heap
are in the tool's zone.
Otherwise,
they would be in two default zones:
MallocHelperZone and DefaultMallocZone,
based on the allocation size.
And usually you could skip smaller system
utility zones such as QuartzCore zone.
Also, if you suspect fragmentation,
indicated by high fragmentation size
or percentage,
like dozens or hundreds of megabytes,
the WWDC 2021 session covers more
about fragmentation issues.
And running vmmap
without dash dash summary,
or to use vmmap in standard mode,
shows each vm region within
those categories line by line.
Just like how the virtual address space
looks like, as we discussed earlier.
So with vmmap, you can distill less used
dirty memory from actively used ones.
And typically,
there are also a good amount
of dynamic allocations of various sizes,
or malloc'd heap memory usage in the game.
They need a special look.
Heap tool groups malloc'd resources
by their classes,
and sorts them by instance count.
These classes are determined in
C++ with a VTable,
Objective-C, or Swift.
We are using the —quiet argument
to skip the header about some metadata.
New this year, heap is more intelligent
at identifying object types.
It uses information recorded
by Malloc Stack Logging
to present the caller
or responsible library,
so a huge non-object
is a thing of the past.
And here is the memory graph
from Manifold Garden again.
In this example,
it is revealed for the first time
how much heap usage is taken up
by plugins like FMOD Studio,
and game components
such as GameAssembly.dylib.
So now you can be more informed
on how the memory is spread out.
And it also hints which direction to go
for getting more info on these objects.
In this example,
the developer can open FMOD Studio
to fine tune the soundtrack
and sound effects in the game,
or go to Unity to look for
game code optimizations, and so on.
Sometimes,
sorting by class total size
rather than class instance count
is more helpful.
In the memory graph
of the Modern Rendering sample project,
the top contributor is a class
using over 258 million bytes.
To continue looking for larger objects
in the Modern Rendering sample,
use heap to sort objects by class
total size with —sortBySize,
and list all objects
with —showSizes,
rather than a summary of each class.
And, there is one object of
NSConcreteMutableData
in Bytes Storage with a size
of 255 million bytes:
that looks like one worth looking at.
Next, I want to find out what it is.
And I want to know
its address for a start.
I add —address and enter
the pattern NSConcreteMutableData
followed by wildcard–
dot star,
and a size filter in the bracket
to only list objects
10 megabytes large and upwards.
And here is the address of the object.
I'll use it in the following steps
for more in-depth analysis.
So that's heap tool, with improved
object identification for instances.
So far, you've seen three tools
to understand
what objects are using memory in the game,
and they all provide different views.
What I showed was just one workflow.
Depending on
the particular memory patterns,
or technologies used in your game,
you can use them
in any way that suits your needs.
With discoveries for objects
that we are not quite sure
of their existence,
the next step is to get its origin,
which is its allocation call stack.
In the case of the 200 million bytes
object in Modern Rendering,
I use the —callTree mode
and pass in its address to malloc_history.
Together with additional invert argument,
I can focus on functions
closest to the allocation.
And voila.
Here is the back trace of the allocation.
Similarly, Xcode Memory Debugger shows
the allocation history of an object too
in the inspector.
Just select an object,
click on the Memory Inspector,
and there it is.
As another example,
pass in VM_ALLOCATE
as the class pattern
instead of an address,
to check for anonymous VM usage
in your game or plugin,
such as debugging a custom allocator.
Whether using Xcode or malloc_history,
you can know the allocation back trace,
and decide if you want to dig deeper,
including setting a breakpoint
at the line, for a start.
And last but not least, it's also helpful
to investigate object references.
Memory graph always records
object references,
even when MallocStackLogging
is not enabled for various reasons.
We've used leaks before to capture
a memory graph outside of Xcode.
Leaks does more.
It checks for all references
in the memory graph,
and that is why it knows about leaks
and retain cycles.
Leaks gets this tree of references
to the object
by using the trace tree argument
and the object address from heap.
However, because this is a rather
large tree in this example,
there is a somewhat better way
to view it than in Terminal.
With Xcode 14,
we redesigned the memory graph view
to show both ingoing and outgoing edges
of the selected object.
It even has a new
neighbor selection popover,
to choose the edges
you want Xcode to draw.
This is going to greatly improve
productivity
when trying to understand object
references in complex game states.
After exploring around for a little bit,
I'm pretty sure the texture manager
is what is accessing this object.
For your game,
consider using leaks tool
and the memory graph view to find
important object reference relationships,
to learn how these objects
are accessed in the game.
So that how to view and find out
important references
of an object using leaks or Xcode.
Please check out leaks' manual page,
and Xcode help
for more usage of these tools.
In this memory graph analysis cookbook,
each step uses some specific tools.
All of them work together to complete
the analysis on a memory graph.
To summarize, the first thing
is to enable MallocStackLogging
when you expect to capture and analyze
memory with a memory graph.
Then capture a memory graph
with Xcode for your game,
or alternatively use leaks tool
for your Mac game.
Next, find large and troublesome objects.
Footprint, vmmap, and heap tools
provide breakdown of memory,
both on a high level and in details.
With malloc_history, you can find out
where objects are allocated
and leaks can analyze object usage
or references.
These previous sessions
include in-depth walkthroughs
as well as demos
of more usage of these tools.
Until now, we have deferred probing
into Metal resources.
Well, now is the time.
To tell you more, here's Seth.
Hi again!
In games, Metal resources
can use a big chunk of memory.
But there are ways to optimize
their memory use.
Here I've summarized a list
of memory savings
that you can use when optimizing
the Metal resources in your game.
We'll take a look at how Metal Debugger
can help you with auditing the resources
and learn some advanced techniques
for further reducing your game memory.
Metal Debugger is the one stop shop
for debugging your Metal games.
After taking a GPU frame capture,
you can find a summary page.
This provides you with some general stats
about the captured workload.
In the lower half of the page,
there is a list of insights
divided in four categories.
Insights in the "Memory" category
suggest memory savings for your game.
There aren't many memory insights
particular for this trace;
we can save just a few megabytes
of memory after addressing these insights.
However, there may be more memory savings
specific to your game.
To get a more complete picture of
the memory used by Metal resources,
you can use the Memory Viewer
from clicking on the Show Memory button.
The Memory Viewer offers you a full list
of resources captured from the game.
The upper half shows
different categories for filtering.
You can quickly use this to
look up resources, say, textures.
And in the lower half,
the table displays just the textures.
Let's take out the filter for now.
The resource table has a collection
of columns to help you optimize your game.
And I'd like to highlight a few columns
that may help you quickly identify
some interesting resources.
The Insights column is similar to
what we just saw on the summary page.
You may quickly view all the resources
with insights
when sorting the table by this column.
And clicking on an insight icon
will reveal a popover
explaining the finding
and providing some possible actions.
Right next to this column
is Allocated Size.
You can sort by this column
to see the largest resources.
It may be useful to audit if some
resources actually make good use
of their memory size.
For example, some textures may be resized
to smaller resolutions
and some models loaded in buffers
may use a lower poly count,
given that doing so won't affect
the visual quality of the game.
There are some alternative ways
to save texture memory
that I'll mention in a minute.
Another interesting column here
is Time Since Last Bound.
You can sort the resources by this column
to find which haven't been used recently.
If a resource is never used,
it may be a good idea to double check
if it's worth loading the asset.
For a resource
that hasn't been bound for a while,
you may consider releasing it
if it won't be used again in the future.
Alternatively, you can set
its purgeable state to volatile.
A Metal resource may be in
one of the three purgeable states:
non-volatile, volatile, and empty.
By default, resources are non-volatile.
By setting the purgeable state
to volatile,
Metal may evict the resource from memory
in case of high memory pressure
in the system.
Once the resource is empty,
the system will no longer charge it
towards the game's footprint.
When your game needs the resource again,
check if the content's still there,
and reload if needed.
Consider only using volatile
for infrequently used resources,
so the purgeable state
doesn't work against you.
So those are some of the general notes
for all resources.
And now,
let's take a closer look at textures.
Not all columns are shown by default
in Memory Viewer.
Right clicking on the table header
will allow showing and hiding columns
like texture's Pixel Format.
You may get different amount of savings by
optimizing the pixel format for a texture.
Many textures in a game could use
a 16-bit half precision pixel format
to reduce memory use and bandwidth.
In cases when you need a texture
with a single alpha component,
you may avoid multiple color channels.
And lastly, some read-only textures
may benefit from block compression
for lower memory use.
For block compressed pixel formats,
there are options such as ASTC and BC.
Additionally, since A15 Bionic,
you can use lossy compression for textures
and render targets
to save memory while preserving
quality wherever possible.
Please check out these previous
videos for more details.
And those are some of the memory savings
you can quickly discover
from using Memory Viewer.
But there are a few additional techniques
you may take
to further optimize your game.
If a texture is only used by single pass,
you can set its storage mode to memoryless
to save memory and bandwidth.
Memoryless textures work well
for temporary render targets,
like depth, stencil,
or multi-sampled textures.
Otherwise, if the texture
is only used by the GPU,
you can set its storage mode to private,
or else shared or managed.
As a reminder, managed mode is not needed
on Apple silicon Macs,
just like on iPhone and iPad.
Here's an example case.
The game has
a Depth32Float_Stencil8 texture.
The depth texture is used across passes,
but the stencil texture's content
is discarded
and won't be used later in the frame.
So instead,
the game could use two textures
and make the stencil texture memoryless,
to save memory and bandwidth.
Lastly, I'd like to mention another
technique that might be interesting to you
for making the most out of the memory
in your game.
You may use aliased resources
from a heap
if your game doesn't use them
at the same time.
They can share the memory backed
by the same allocation.
But be extra careful when synchronizing
the accesses to those resources.
You can check out
the "Go bindless with Metal 3" talk
to learn more about using resources
allocated from a heap.
So that wraps up our checklist
of memory savings.
And I hope this checklist will help you
audit the Metal resources in your game.
To learn more about using
Metal Debugger for optimizing
your game memory,
please check out these other WWDC talks.
And back to you, Jack.
Thank you, Seth.
Today, we took a guided tour
and explored many interesting things
you can do to understand and improve
your game's memory usage.
First, memory footprint
is the primary metric
in understanding your game's memory usage,
and it includes dirty plus compressed
and swapped memory.
Then, we experienced powerful
memory debugging tools.
Seth showed us how Instruments
empower memory profiling
with useful telemetry tracks.
The new Game Memory template
is exactly tailored for this job.
After that, I presented memory graph
to store a snapshot of game memory state.
There are flexible and powerful
command line programs
to analyze memory graphs for objects,
references, and allocation history.
Improvements in the heap tool
and redesigned Xcode Memory Debugger
will supercharge game memory analysis.
Lastly, Seth shared
a memory savings checklist
for Metal resources,
and how Metal Debugger
can help answer questions
about Metal resource usage in your game.
You could also learn more
from other WWDC sessions,
documentation, and manual pages.
We are constantly advancing
our best and most flexible tools for you.
So why not try them out?
They may just be what you are looking for.
And don't hesitate to share with us
any feedback you may have,
via any channels
such as the Feedback Assistant.
Have fun in your memory journey,
and thanks for watching.  ♪ ♪