[upbeat music]
- Hi! I'm Kent and I'm an
engineer on the CloudKit team.
I'm excited to introduce
a new library that you can use
to access CloudKit.
First, I'll cover
how to configure this new library.
And then you'll learn
how to manage your schema,
as well as how to access
user data with CKTool JS.
Let's begin!
CloudKit is a persistence technology
that lets you store your app's data
in iCloud within containers.
By using CloudKit in your app,
you can also have your data
stay up to date across devices
and on the web.
For building your apps,
you can access iCloud storage using
the CloudKit framework on Apple platforms
or CloudKit JS on the web.
To implement automation and tooling,
Xcode provides cktool for use on macOS.
And now you have a new way to automate
changes and interact with iCloud,
using CKTool JS.
CKTool JS lets you perform
the same operations
as the cktool command-line utility
introduced in Xcode 13
and supports similar use cases.
In fact, CKTool JS is used to
implement features in CloudKit Console
such as adding record types
and querying records.
With CKTool JS,
you can manage your app containers
and perform schema operations,
such as resetting and applying
updates to your schema.
This is something that you couldn't
do from JavaScript before.
CKTool JS lets you fetch existing
records using their unique identifier
or through complex queries.
And it lets you create new records
and update them.
CKTool JS ships with strict
type definitions for TypeScript.
These type definitions enable
compile-time checking
that flags incorrect
usage of the client library
and it enables code completion
in supported IDEs.
You'll find editing CKTool JS
code easier because of this.
Additionally,
this new library ships with support
for both Node.js
and browsers out of the box.
CKTool JS is distributed
as a set of npm packages,
which allows you to integrate it as
part of your JavaScript build pipeline.
Doing so enables features such
as tree-shaking and bundling.
You can also
track updates to these packages
because their release history
is transparently available from npm.
The following packages are part
of the CKTool JS distribution.
Note that these packages
are within the @apple scope
and follow the convention of using
cktool. at the start of the name.
The main package that you'll use
is cktool.database.
To enable communication with iCloud,
you'll also need to use one other package
for your target platform,
cktool.target.nodejs
for Node.js
or cktool.target.browser
for web browsers.
cktool.database automatically
pulls in three more packages--
cktool.core, cktool.api.base,
and cktool.api.database.
Since CKTool JS communicates directly
with iCloud, it must first be authorized.
Depending on the operation
that you want to call,
you'll either need
a management token or a user token.
Both kinds of tokens are
obtainable from CloudKit Console.
Management tokens are used to
access management operations
and are scoped to a team and user.
Such operations include enabling schema
import and export, schema validation,
and resetting the container to production.
User tokens are scoped to teams
and containers and enable access
to private user data
within those containers.
To learn how to obtain these
authorization tokens as well as
continuous integration with CloudKit,
check out
"Automate CloudKit tests with cktool and
declarative schema" from WWDC21.
Any time you want to use
CKTool JS in your scripts,
you'll first need to configure it for use.
But before
I dive into configuring CKTool JS,
I'll do a quick review of what
makes up a CloudKit schema.
In CloudKit,
data is stored in a structured way.
Data that has the same kinds of
values are stored together as records.
Records are instances of record types,
and the properties of a record
that a record type describes
are known as fields.
In addition to your user-defined fields,
CloudKit adds system fields
such as recordName,
which is the ID of the record.
I'll use examples from a coin collection
app I've been working on.
I want to store a collection of countries,
so I have a record type
to describe what kinds of properties
I need to store for them.
I'm storing names and ISO codes,
and I'm naming the record type,
"Countries."
ISO codes uniquely identify a country,
so it's important
to include them in my record type.
I create some records of
type Countries to store this information
along with their names.
I also have a record type
for coins of particular countries,
and I want to relate them to one another.
The Coins record type stores the
relationship from a coin to its country.
Record types and relationships
combine to make a schema.
I can consider the current
state of these elements
to be the current version of my schema.
As you develop your apps,
you'll evolve your schema,
and over the lifetime of your app,
you'll likely have several versions of it.
While my app's schema describes
the structure of the data
I want to store in iCloud, my app
container is where that data is stored.
A container has a unique identifier
and is associated with a developer team.
There are two environments to keep
in mind when working with CloudKit.
The development environment
is a safe place to make changes
without disrupting users.
This is where you should be testing
and developing changes to your schema.
When users interact with your app,
they'll be interacting with
the production environment.
The production environment
contains the live data for your app.
Now that I've reviewed
how CloudKit stores data,
I'll cover how to configure CKTool JS.
Because CKTool JS talks with iCloud,
you'll need to gather
a few pieces of information
so that it knows how to work
with the right container
and that your script
is authorized to do so.
You'll need your team ID
and the container ID
for the container you want to work with.
You'll need a management token
in order to work with schemas,
and if your script will access data,
you'll need a user token as well.
All these values can be
obtained from CloudKit Console.
You'll also need to specify which
environment, development or production,
your script will run in.
I'll use development
as an example going forward.
Anytime you configure CKTool JS for use,
you'll need these values.
For my examples,
I'm writing scripts for Node.js.
You import objects and functions
from CKTool JS in order to use them.
In this case, you can import these
symbols using CommonJS require statements.
Once you've gathered
your configuration information,
you'll create objects
to hold that information.
To store your auth tokens,
you create an object
to hold your management token and,
if you have one, your user token.
Since teamId, containerId
and environment are common values
that are passed to CKTool JS, you can
create an object to hold these values.
You instantiate a Configuration
object that tells CKTool JS
how to talk with iCloud by using the
createConfiguration factory function.
createConfiguration is platform-specific.
In this case, it'll return an
appropriate configuration for Node.js,
since that's the function that
was imported from the target package.
You then pass the configuration object
and the security object declared earlier
to initialize an API object.
API objects contain asynchronous methods
that allow you to talk to iCloud.
You've now completed the steps
to use CKTool JS in your scripts.
Let's learn about how you
can use CKTool JS
to manage your container's schema.
In my app,
I want to store information such as
an American dime issued in 2007.
This coin
is composed of copper and nickel
and the value stamped on it
is 1/10th of an American dollar.
After thinking
about how to store this data,
I decided to store information
about the coin's composition
as records separate from
the other details about the coin.
So I store the copper percentage
for the dime
and its nickel percentage
in separate records.
I identified two record types
that I want in my container's schema.
Coins, which stores its country reference,
issue year, and nominal value.
And a Components record type
that stores a reference to a coin
it describes
and the material
and its percentage in the coin.
Now that I've determined
the schema for my app,
I can create a text file in
CloudKit Schema Language to describe it.
The convention is to use the
.ckdb extension for your schema file.
For more information about
CloudKit Schema Language,
refer to "Integrating a Text-Based Schema
into Your Workflow" documentation article.
The schema file you create for your
container can be applied using CKTool JS.
Before you apply a new schema,
you'll typically reset the
container's development schema
to match the one in production.
You can do this with the
resetToProduction method.
You call this method by passing
the defaultArgs object
that you declared earlier.
If your schema isn't in production,
all record types are deleted.
Otherwise,
this will revert the development schema
to the state
of the production environment.
Note that this is an asynchronous call,
so this method returns a promise object.
CKTool JS has methods that let you
export and import your container's schema.
The exportSchema and importSchema
methods let you do this
and are named from
the perspective of the container.
So you download a schema to be exported
from the container using exportSchema,
and you upload a schema to be imported
into the container using importSchema.
Together, these allow you
to manage your schema's evolution.
You can create a help function
to apply the schema to the container.
First, import the File object
from CKTool JS,
then import the fs and
path modules from Node.js.
Now define an asynchronous
function that will do the following:
It reads the schema file's
contents into a Node.js buffer.
It creates
a CKTool JS File instance for upload.
Finally, it uploads the file's contents
to the server using importSchema.
Note that the defaultArgs object
that was declared earlier
is passed to importSchema.
Now you can put it together.
Because resetToProduction and the
helper function used to import a schema
are asynchronous, you need to ensure
that they run in the correct order.
To do that you chain the promises.
If an error occurs,
the promise will reject.
In addition to the management
capabilities that CKTool JS has,
it also allows you to work
with reading and writing data.
Field values that are used in
CKTool JS records
are type and ranged checked
on the client side
before they're sent to the server.
If the value passed in
is not the right kind of value
or is outside of
the allowed range of the value,
an exception will be thrown.
For large numbers that can't be
represented natively in JavaScript,
there are CKTool JS types
that are used instead.
For example,
to coerce a number to a CKTool JS Int64,
you use the toInt64 function.
To coerce a number to
a Double floating point value,
you use the toDouble function.
If you're writing TypeScript,
the compiler will flag
incorrect value type usages if these
coercion functions are not used.
Field values in CKTool JS records
are created using field
value factory functions.
For a coin issued in 2007,
I'd pass that value
to the makeRecordFieldValue.int64
factory function
in order to create a record field value
that contains an Int64.
In general, if a factory function
can't create a record field value
from the value passed in,
it'll throw an exception.
Here, I've created an object
to hold common values
that I send to methods
that work with records.
Since containerId, environment,
databaseType and zoneName
are often required, I'm including those
in this databaseArgs object.
To query for records,
I use the queryRecords method.
To make this easier,
I create a helper function
that finds a country matching
its unique 3 character ISO code.
In this case, I pass the contents
of the databaseArgs object,
in addition to
a body that contains the query.
For the query object,
I'm specifying the recordType value
as well as a single filter object.
The filter object describes a
query where the country's isoCode3
is equal to the one
this function is seeking.
If successful,
the collection of found records
will be in the
response.result.records property.
I return the
first object from this collection.
To make converting raw values into
field values that createRecord can use,
I have a helper function called
makeCoinFieldValues to do this.
For each raw property for my coin
that I want to convert to field values,
I call the appropriate
RecordFieldValue factory function.
For the country field, however,
I need to create a reference.
I use the passed-in country
record name to make a reference
from this coin record
to the corresponding country record.
Here, I create a helper function
that takes coin record field values
and sends the
createRecord request to the server.
In this function,
I'm passing the content of databaseArgs
declared earlier and a body.
The body dictionary contains
the recordType and field values.
If successful,
response.result.record is returned.
Before calling the helper function,
I need to fetch the correct
country record that will be
referenced from this coin.
I use the country query function
defined earlier.
I then call coinCreateRecord by
passing it a field values dictionary
which is created with the
makeCoinFieldValues helper function
that I wrote earlier.
The raw coin values are passed
to that helper function.
This will asynchronously create
the record and return the new record.
To update a record,
use the updateRecord method.
I create a helper function that
updates a coin matching the record name
with the fields passed to this helper.
I then call updateRecord with the contents
of the databaseArgs object, recordName,
and a body that contains the record type
and the new record's field values.
If successful,
the updated record will be in the
response.result.record property,
which I return from the helper function.
To update the coin record I created
earlier, I call this helper function
passing in its record name
and field values to update.
The field values are created
with makeCoinFieldValues.
To delete a record, I call the async
deleteRecord method on the API object.
I pass in the contents of
the databaseArgs object
as well as the recordName
of the record to delete.
I hope you've enjoyed
getting to know CKTool JS.
Try it out for yourself:
Configure CKTool JS for your automation
and tooling purposes.
Reset and import your schemas
as well as read and write
your data using JavaScript.
For usage of CKTool JS in
continuous integration scenarios,
check out
the CloudKit sample repo on GitHub.
And for more detailed documentation, check
out CKTool JS on developer.apple.com.
Thanks for joining me today,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC22.