♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Kevin Ferrell: Hi,
my name is Kevin,
and I'm an engineer working on
the new PushToTalk framework,
which enables a walkie-talkie
system experience
for apps on iOS.
Later I'll be joined
by my colleague Trevor
to talk about how you can
enhance voice communication
in your apps
with this new framework.
First, I'll introduce
the PushToTalk framework
and explain how it fits
into your app.
Next, we'll go over
how to configure your app
for PushToTalk.
After that,
Trevor will walk through
how to transmit and receive
audio using the framework.
Finally, Trevor will wrap up
with best practices
for enhancing
the Push To Talk user experience
while preserving battery life
for your users.
I'll get started
by introducing key features
of the new PushToTalk framework.
The PushToTalk framework
enables you to build
a new class of audio
communication app on iOS
that provides a walkie-talkie
style experience for your users.
Push To Talk apps have many uses
in fields where rapid
communication is essential
such as health care
and emergency services.
To provide a great
Push To Talk experience,
users need a way
to quickly access
audio transmission features
while also being able to see
who is responding to them.
At the same time,
a Push To Talk app
must be power efficient
to ensure that users
can maintain all-day battery
life while using the app.
The PushToTalk framework
provides you with APIs
to utilize a system UI
that users can access
anywhere on the system
without having to directly
launch your app.
The system UI allows a user
to quickly activate
an audio transmission,
which will launch your app
in the background to record
and stream audio to your server.
The system provides transparency
to users
by showing who's speaking
when your app plays audio
from your server.
The PushToTalk framework
accomplishes this
by introducing
a new push notification type
that notifies your app when new
audio is available for playback.
When your app receives
this notification,
it is launched in the background
so that it can stream
and play audio.
The PushToTalk framework
is designed to be compatible
with existing end-to-end
communication solutions
and backend infrastructure.
If you've already implemented
a Push To Talk workflow
in your app,
it should be easy for you
to integrate
the PushToTalk framework
into your existing code.
The framework allows
your app to implement
its own audio encoding
and streaming process
to transmit audio between users.
This provides flexibility
in how audio transmission
is handled by your app
and enables compatibility
with other platforms.
Finally, many Push To Talk apps
rely on wireless
Bluetooth accessories
to trigger audio recording
and transmission.
Your apps can continue to
integrate with these accessories
using the CoreBluetooth
framework
and can trigger audio recording
in PushToTalk.
If you are building your first
Push To Talk app,
keep these integration
considerations in mind
as you begin architecting
your code.
Before we begin
walking through the code
for the new
PushToTalk framework,
we want to demonstrate
how the Push To Talk experience
can work in your app.
Trevor and I have built
a demo app
to show how PushToTalk works.
To start,
I'll tap the join button
to connect to
a Push To Talk session,
which we call a channel.
Once I'm joined to the channel,
I can transmit and receive audio
to other members of the channel.
Trevor and a few
of our colleagues
have joined the same channel
so that we can communicate
throughout the day.
I can transmit audio
directly from the app
using the microphone button,
but the PushToTalk framework
allows me to access
the transmit feature
from anywhere in the system.
When there is an active
Push To Talk channel,
a blue pill will appear
in the status bar.
Tapping that pill
shows the system UI.
The system UI displays the name
of the Push To Talk channel
that I've joined
and an image provided by the app
to help users
quickly identify the channel.
I can transmit audio
to the channel
by pressing and holding
the Talk button
and then waiting for
the system chime to indicate
that I can begin speaking.
[CHIME]
Hey, Trevor.
Are you ready to cover
your WWDC slides? Over.
Trevor Sheridan: When my device
received Kevin's message,
it displayed a notice that
contained his name and image,
providing transparency into
who I'm receiving messages from.
Once I launch the system UI,
I can quickly respond
to Kevin's message
or leave the channel without
having to stop what I'm doing.
I don't want to leave Kevin
waiting, so I'll reply now.
[CHIME] Hey, Kevin.
I'll be ready in a few minutes.
Over.
Kevin: The PushToTalk system UI
can also be accessed
from the Lock Screen so a user
can receive and respond
to messages without
having to unlock their device.
[CHIME] OK, see you soon!
Over. [CHIME]
Now that we've discussed
how PushToTalk works,
we'll review how to integrate
the framework in your own app.
There are a few modifications
that you need to make
to your Xcode project to support
the PushToTalk framework.
First, you need to add the new
Push To Talk background mode.
This enables your app
to run in the background
when responding
to Push To Talk events.
Next, you must also add
the Push To Talk capability
to your app to enable
the framework features.
The push notification capability
is required to allow APNS
to wake your app
in the background
to play received audio.
Finally, your app must request
recording permission
from the user and include
a microphone purpose string
in its Info.plist file.
Now we're ready to begin
integrating the code.
The first step in
the Push To Talk workflow
is to join a channel.
The channel represents
and describes
the Push To Talk session
to the system.
Your app interacts with channels
through a channel manager.
The channel manager is the
primary interface for your app
to join channels
and perform actions
like transmitting
and receiving audio.
When you join a channel,
the Push To Talk system UI
becomes available and your app
receives an APNS device token
that can be used throughout
the life of the channel.
You must join a channel before
you can begin transmitting
and receiving audio.
The first step is to create
a channel manager
using the class initializer.
This initializer requires
that you provide
a channel manager delegate and
a channel restoration delegate.
Multiple calls
to the initializer
result in the same shared
instance being returned,
but we recommend that
you store the channel manager
in an instance variable.
It is important to initialize
your channel manager
as soon as possible
during app start up
in your ApplicationDelegate's
didFinishLaunchingWithOptions
method.
This ensures that the channel
manager is initialized quickly
so that existing channels
can be restored
and push notifications
will be delivered to your app
when it launches
in the background.
Now we're ready
to join a channel.
When someone joins
a channel from your app,
you must provide a UUID
to identify the channel
and a descriptor that describes
the channel to the system.
The same UUID will be used when
interacting with the manager
throughout the life
of this channel.
The descriptor includes
a name and an image.
Providing a unique image
to represent the channel
makes it easier for your users
to identify the channel
when interacting
with the system.
Your app joins a channel by
calling the requestJoin method
on the channel manager.
Note that it is only possible
to join a channel
when your app is running
in the foreground.
When your app joins a channel,
the channel manager delegate's
didJoinChannel method
will be called.
This delegate method
is your indication
that your app
has joined the channel.
In addition,
the delegate's
receivedEphemeralPushToken
method will be called
with the APNS push token
that can be used
to send Push To Talk
notifications to this device.
This token will only be active
for the life of
the Push To Talk channel.
Keep in mind that APNS
push tokens are variable length
and that you should not hardcode
their length into your app.
It is possible for the
channel join request to fail,
such as when attempting
to join a channel
when another channel
is already active.
If this occurs,
the error handler will be called
and the error will indicate
the reason for the failure.
When the user leaves a channel,
the delegate's didLeaveChannel
method will be called.
Your user may leave the channel
as a result of either
your app requesting to leave
programmatically
or the user can tap
the Leave Channel button
in the system UI.
The channel manager delegate
has an associated
LeaveChannel error-handling
method that will be called
if the request to leave
the channel fails.
PushToTalk supports
restoring previous channels
whenever your app is relaunched
after being terminated
or after a device reboot.
In order for the system
to accomplish this,
you must provide a channel
descriptor to update the system.
Here we have a helper method
that will fetch
our cached channel descriptor
in our restoration delegate.
In order to keep the system
responsive,
you should return from this
method as quickly as possible
and should not perform any
long-running or blocking tasks
such as a network request
to retrieve
your channel descriptor.
Throughout the lifecycle
of your Push To Talk session,
you should provide updates
to the descriptor
whenever information
about the channel changes.
You should also inform
the system about changes
to your network connection
or server availability
using the service status object.
Here we're updating
the descriptor for the channel.
You can call this method
whenever you need to update
the channel name or image.
In this example,
we are providing an update
to the system to indicate
that the app's connection
to its sever is in
a reconnecting state.
This updates
the system UI accordingly
and prevents the user
from transmitting audio
if the service status is
connecting or disconnected.
Once a connection
is reestablished,
you should update
the service status to "ready."
Now let's review
how to send and receive audio
using PushToTalk.
[CHIME] Trevor, are you ready
to walk through
the rest of the API?
Over.
[CHIME] Trevor: Yep.
Send them over. Over.
[CHIME]
Now that we've seen
how to configure
the PushToTalk framework,
let's explore how to transmit
and receive audio.
A core capability
of the PushToTalk framework
is to allow your users
to quickly transmit audio.
Users can begin
audio transmission
from within your app,
or from the system
Push To Talk UI.
If your app supports
Bluetooth accessories
through CoreBluetooth,
you can also begin transmission
in the background
in response to a peripheral's
characteristic change.
When transmitting,
the PushToTalk framework
unlocks the device's microphone
and activates
your app's audio session
to enable audio recording
in the background.
Let's review this process
in detail.
To begin transmission from
within your app, you can call
the requestBeginTransmitting
function.
This can be called whenever your
app is running in the foreground
or when reacting
to a change
of a Bluetooth peripheral's
characteristic.
If the system is not able
to begin transmitting,
the delegate's
failedToBeginTransmitting
InChannel method will be called
with the reason
for the failure.
For example, if the user has
an ongoing cellular call active,
they will not be able to begin
a Push To Talk transmission.
To stop transmitting,
call the channel manager's
stopTransmitting method.
To handle failures when
attempting to stop transmitting,
such as when the user
was not in a transmitting state,
the channel manager delegate
has an associated
failedToStopTransmitting
InChannel method.
Whether you begin transmission
from within your app
or if the user starts
from the system UI,
your channel manager delegate
will receive
a "Did begin transmitting"
callback.
The transmission source
will be passed to the method
and indicate whether
the transmission
was started
from the system UI,
the programmatic API,
or a hardware button event.
Once transmission begins,
the system will activate
the audio session for your app.
This is your signal that
you can now begin recording.
You should not start or stop
your own audio session.
When transmission ends,
your channel manager delegate
will receive
the end transmission
and audio session
deactivation events.
Keep in mind that while
your transmission is active,
your audio session may be
interrupted by other sources,
such as phone
and FaceTime calls
for which you need to handle
within your app.
The PushToTalk framework
also allows your app
to receive and play audio
from other users
while in the background.
This process relies on a new
Apple Push Notification type
that is specific
to Push To Talk apps.
When your Push To Talk server
has new audio
for a user to receive,
it should send the user
a Push To Talk notification
using the device push token
you received
when joining the channel.
When the push notification
is received by your app,
it must report an active speaker
to the framework,
which will cause the system
to activate
your app's audio session
and allow it to begin playback.
The new Push To Talk
notification
is similar to other
notification types on iOS
and there are specific
attributes that you must set
to enable delivery
to your Push To Talk app.
First, the APNS push type
must be set to "pushtotalk"
in the request header.
Next, the APNS topic header
must be set
to your app's bundle identifier
with a ".voip-ptt" suffix
appended to the end.
The push payload
can contain custom keys
that are relevant to your app,
such the name
of an active speaker
or an indication
that the session has ended
and the app should leave
the Push To Talk channel.
The body of the "aps" property
can be left blank.
Additionally, like other
communication-related
push types,
Push To Talk payloads should
have an APNS priority of 10
to request immediate delivery
and an APNS expiration of zero
to prevent older pushes
that are no longer relevant
from being delivered later.
When your server sends
a Push To Talk notification,
your app will be started
in the background
and the incoming push
delegate method will be called.
When you receive
a push payload,
you will need to construct
a push result type
to indicate what action
should be performed
as a result
of the push notification.
To indicate that
a remote user is speaking,
return a push result
that includes
the active participant's
information,
including their name
and an optional image.
This will cause the system
to set the active participant
on the channel
and indicate that the channel
is in receive mode.
The system will then activate
your audio session,
and call the
didActivateaudioSession
delegate method.
You should wait for this method
to be called
before beginning playback.
If your server decides
that a user
should no longer
be joined to a channel,
it may indicate this
in the push payload,
for which you can return
a leaveChannel push result.
It's important to note
that you should return
a PTPushResult from this method
as quickly as possible
and not block the thread.
If you are attempting to set
the active remote participant
and do not have their image
stored locally,
you can return
an activeRemoteParticipant
with only the speaker's name.
Then download their image
on a separate thread,
and once the image is retrieved,
update the
activeRemoteParticipant
by calling
setActiveRemoteParticipant
on the channel manager.
When the remote participant
has finished speaking,
you should set the
activeRemoteParticipant to nil.
This indicates to the system
that you are no longer
receiving audio
on the channel
and that the system should
deactivate your audio session.
This will also update
the system Push To Talk UI
and allow the user
to transmit again.
Now that we've covered
the basics
of how to integrate PushToTalk
into your app,
let's review some best practices
for optimizing
the user experience
and preserving battery life.
The PushToTalk framework
provides a system UI
for users to begin
a transmission
and leave a channel from
anywhere within the system.
Additionally, it is flexible
and allows you to implement
your own custom
Push To Talk UI
when your app
is in the foreground.
The PushToTalk framework
utilizes shared system
resources.
Only one Push To Talk app
can be active
on the system at a time,
and Push To Talk communication
will be superseded
by cellular, FaceTime,
and VoIP calls.
Your app should handle
PushToTalk failures gracefully
and respond accordingly.
As mentioned earlier,
the PushToTalk framework
handles activating
and deactivating
your audio session for you.
However,
you should still configure
your audio session's category
to play and record
when your app launches.
The system provides
built-in sound effects
to alert the user that
the microphone is activated
and deactivated
when transmitting.
You should not provide
your own sound effects
for these events.
It is also important
for your app to monitor
and respond to AVAudioSession
notifications,
such as session interruptions,
route changes,
and failures.
Your Push To Talk app
can be affected
by these audio session events
just like any other audio app
on the system.
It's important
to optimize your app
to preserve battery life.
The PushToTalk framework
provides your app
with background runtime
when needed,
such as when transmitting
and receiving audio.
When your app is not being used
by the user,
it will be suspended by the
system to preserve battery life.
You should not activate
or deactivate
your own audio sessions.
The system will handle
audio session activation for you
at the appropriate times.
This ensures
that your audio session
has the proper priority
within the system
and can be suspended
when it is not being used.
Your Push To Talk server
should use the new
push notification type
to alert your app that there is
new audio to be played,
or that the Push To Talk
session has ended.
For more information
about improving
the battery life in your app,
refer to the
"Power down: Improve battery
consumption" session.
When your Push To Talk app
is in the background
and the app is not
transmitting or receiving audio,
it will be suspended
by the system.
When your app is suspended,
any network connections
will be disconnected.
You should consider adopting
Network.framework
and QUIC to reduce
the steps needed
to establish a secure
TLS connection
and improve initial
connection speed.
Network.framework
has built-in support for QUIC.
Check out the
"Reduce networking delays for
a more responsive app" session
for more information
about how to use QUIC.
The PushToTalk framework
enables you to build
robust and power-efficient
walkie-talkie style
communication experiences
within your apps.
If you already have an app
that implements
a walk-talkie style experience
on iOS,
you should begin updating
your existing app
to use the new API.
If you're implementing
a new walkie-talkie app,
you should use
the PushToTalk framework now.
Finally,
please submit feedback
as you begin testing
the new framework
and integrating it
with your app.
Thank you
and have a great WWDC!
Over and out!
♪