♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Alex Young,
and I'm an engineer
on the iCloud developer
experience team.
CloudKit is an easy way
to create great experiences
by allowing users
to effortlessly synchronize data
between devices.
CloudKit Console helps to make
this even easier by providing
tools that let you work with
your app's schema and data.
I'm going to share several
updates to CloudKit Console
that will help you
understand and debug
your application's
schema and data.
First, I'll walk through
how to use hidden containers,
then dive into a new way
you can view records
using iCloud accounts,
and finally,
there are some great updates
for working with shared zones.
It's common to create lots of
containers while in development,
and only focus
on a few later on.
You can better organize this
with the new
hidden containers feature.
In CloudKit Console,
you can choose
which containers
are hidden or visible.
Hidden containers
aren't just hidden
from the lists
inside the Console,
but also across
all developer tools,
including Xcode.
Even better,
when a container is hidden,
it applies at the team level,
which means all of your test
and prototype containers
no longer clutter
your teammates' views.
I'll open the Console and use
this new functionality now.
Once you're signed in
to the Console,
open the container selector
from the top-level navigation.
Then click Manage Containers.
This displays a new menu
that allows you to toggle
the visibility of every
container in the current team.
For people with several teams,
you can switch between them
using the account menu
in the top right.
Then you can go on
to hide containers
in your other teams as well.
Here's the container
from WWDC21,
which isn't needed anymore.
I can hide it, like this.
And if you refresh
the container list in Xcode,
you'll see the containers
are now hidden there too.
I'll tell you about
a new addition to the Console
that lets you view data
as iCloud accounts
instead of your
developer account.
This is called Act As iCloud.
Sometimes, it can be difficult
to understand why certain users
are experiencing trouble with
data in their private databases.
Now you have the ability
to sign in
as a separate iCloud account
to view private data.
When you're logged in
with an iCloud account,
CloudKit Console's query tools
work as you'd expect
from the perspective
of that account.
This helps you debug
development and production
issues on behalf of your users.
I'll demonstrate
this in the Console
to illustrate how it works.
This query was performed
using my developer account.
I'm going to switch
to an iCloud account
to show how
the query results change.
First, navigate to the
Act As iCloud account menu item.
This will open a dialog
that allows you to sign in
as an iCloud account.
When I sign in, the context of
the Console is going to change.
Now you'll see a banner
at the top of the page.
All subsequent operations
will be performed
using the iCloud account instead
of your developer account.
You can query records
and view zones,
but you cannot perform
schema operations.
As you can see,
the results of this query
are for my iCloud account,
not my developer account.
Switching to another
container or environment
will stop acting
as the iCloud account.
You can also click
the button in the banner
to stop the Act As session.
Remember, acting as an iCloud
account applies to records,
not schema,
so this feature only works
in the data parts
of the Console.
Attempting to access schema
will halt the Act As session.
This feature helps you
to better understand
how your data
is used in production
and investigate data-related
bugs more effectively.
Encrypted fields
remain unreadable to you
when acting as another account.
Only the original user who
owns the data can decrypt it.
This is by design
and helps iCloud
maintain a high level
of security and privacy
and ensures
that sensitive data stays safe.
Next, I'll show you how
to share zones in the Console.
CloudKit sharing is a safe way
to securely share records
between users of your app.
This is sharing done securely,
using permissions
that allow your app
to determine a participant's
read and write access.
Participant access
is further controlled
by defining shares
as public or private.
Zone sharing works by applying
rules to every record in a zone.
A shared zone
has a CloudKit share record
that contains the options
for accessing each record
in the zone.
Shared zones cannot have
existing shared records.
The standard public
and private zone sharing options
are supported by shared zones.
A public shared zone
makes every record visible
to everyone who has
the share code.
Anyone with the short share code
can join this share.
This is ideal for records
that should be easy to share
between users
without strict access control.
Private shared zones have
an additional layer of security
because members must be
in the participant list
to join the share.
CloudKit Console
has several new tools
for creating and viewing
zone shares,
to help you
better understand shared zones
and work with them during
development and production.
Let's create a zone share now
so you can learn how it works.
Navigate to Zones, then select
a zone that you want to share.
Click the Configure zone
wide sharing... button
in the details view.
This shows a form
that lets you decide
if you want a public
or private share.
Public zones have
an additional permission option
for creating read-only
or read/write shares.
For private shares,
the permissions are defined
at a participant level.
I'm going to create
a private share, like this.
Once the zone is shared,
you will see a short unique ID
that can be sent to participants
to join the share.
Shared zones can be joined
in the console
by using the Accept Shared
Record menu option
found in the Records page.
Now any record created
in this zone
will be automatically shared.
Now that you've seen these
updates to CloudKit Console,
go and tidy up your container
lists by hiding containers,
try out Act As iCloud
so you can see records
with different iCloud accounts,
and try out zone sharing
for easier sharing
of multiple records.
We hope these tools
enable you to better understand
your schema,
debug issues in your apps,
and make CloudKit
a little easier to work with.
Thanks, and have a great WWDC.
♪