♪ (Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music) ♪
♪
Praveen Sharma: Hi.
My name is Praveen,
and I'm from the Prototyping
team here at Apple.
Kai Kang: Hi. My name is Kai
and I'm from
the Video Engineering team.
Praveen: Over the past few years
Apple has enabled
powerful new ways for people to
bring the world into their apps.
Last year,
we introduced Object Capture,
which takes in photos
of real-world objects,
and using the Photogrammetry API
in RealityKit,
turns them into a 3D model
ready for use in your app.
Previous to Object Capture,
we released
the Scene Reconstruction API
which gives you
a coarse understanding
of the geometric structure
of your space
and enables brand-new
augmented reality use cases
in your apps.
This year, we are
very excited to announce
a brand-new framework called
RoomPlan.
RoomPlan allows you
to scan your room
using your LiDAR-enabled
iPhone or iPad.
It generates a parametric 3D
model of the room
and its room-defining objects
which you can use in your app.
Let's take a look at what
a RoomPlan scanning experience
looks like.
RoomPlan uses sophisticated
machine learning algorithms
powered by ARKit to detect
walls, windows, openings,
and doors, as well as
room-defining objects
like fireplaces, couches,
tables, and cabinets.
With our RoomCaptureView API,
which uses RealityKit to render
scanning progress in real time,
you can easily integrate
a scanning experience
into your app.
And when you are
finished scanning,
RoomCaptureView presents
the final post-processed results
for you to use however
best fits your use case.
For the first time, without
the complexities of implementing
machine learning
and computer vision algorithms,
people can now interact with
their room in brand new ways.
For example, interior design
apps can preview
wall color changes
and accurately calculate
the amount of paint
required to repaint a room.
Architecture apps can now
easily allow someone to preview
and edit changes to their room's
layout in real time.
Real estate apps can now
seamlessly enable agents
to capture floor plans
and 3D models of a listing.
And e-commerce apps
can engage customers
through product visualization
in their physical spaces.
These are just a few examples of
applications RoomPlan enables,
and you'll be surprised
to see how simple it is
to integrate RoomPlan
into your app.
Let's take a look.
There are two main ways
you can use RoomPlan.
The first is our out-of-the-box
scanning experience
which allows you to seamlessly
integrate RoomPlan
into your app.
The second is our data API
which enables your app
to use the live
parametric data from a scan
however best suits
your use case.
With both of these APIs,
we recommend some best practices
to help you achieve
the best possible scan results,
which we'll go over in the last
section of this presentation.
First, let's talk about
the scanning experience
that you can bring into your app
using our new
RoomCaptureView API.
RoomCaptureView
is a UIView subclass
that you can easily place
in your app.
It handles the presentation of
world space scanning feedback,
real-time room model
generation,
as well as coaching
and user guidance.
Let's take a closer look
at the design elements
presented during
a RoomCaptureView-based scan.
During an active
RoomCaptureView session,
animated lines outline detected
walls, windows, openings,
doors, and room-defining objects
in real time.
The interactive 3D model
generated in real time
at the bottom
of the RoomCaptureView,
gives you an overview of your
scanning progress at a glance.
Finally, text coaching
guides you
to the best possible
scanning results.
Let's take a look at how you can
start using RoomCaptureView
in just four easy steps.
First, we create
a RoomCaptureView reference
in our ViewController.
Second, we create a reference
to our RoomCaptureSession
configuration object.
Third, we start
our scan session,
passing in our configuration
to the capture session's
run function.
And finally, our application
tells the capture session
to stop scanning.
Optionally, your app can adhere
to our RoomCaptureViewDelegate
protocol and opt out of
post-processed results
and their presentation
or handle the post-processed
scan results
once they have been presented.
For example, you can export
a USDZ of the results
by calling
the export function available
on the provided
CapturedRoom data struct.
And that's how simple it is
to integrate RoomPlan
into your app.
We are so excited to see
what you make with this API.
Now my colleague Kai will talk
about RoomCaptureSession
and RoomPlan's Data API.
Kai: Thanks, Praveen.
In this section, we will
walk you through the Data APIs
that provide you the access to
the underlying data structures
during scanning and can help
you build a custom visualization
of the scanning experience
from ground up.
The basic workflow
consists of three parts:
scan, process, and export.
For scanning, we will cover
the basics of how to set up
and start the capture session,
as well as display and monitor
the capture process.
Then we'll look at how
your scanned data is processed
and the final model is received
for presentation.
Finally, we'll discuss
how you can generate and export
the output USD file
which can also be used
in your USD workflows.
Now, let's look into
the Scan step in detail.
We will use
the RoomCaptureSession API
to set up the session
and display the progress
as we continue scanning.
Let me show you in code.
Here's a simple RealityKit app
as an example.
To start, simply import RoomPlan
into your Swift project.
In the ViewController
of your app,
you can have a custom type
to visualize the results
and to initiate
a RoomCaptureSession instance.
Additionally, RoomCaptureSession
provides a handle
to the underlying AR session so
that your apps can draw planes
and object bounding boxes
in the AR view.
RoomCaptureSession
adopts the delegate pattern.
In your ViewController class,
you can assign
the ViewController itself
as the captureSession's
delegate.
This would allow
the ViewController
to get real-time updates
from the RoomCaptureSession.
Theses updates include
3D models and instructions
in order to guide people
during the capture.
To get these updates,
your ViewController
needs to conform to the
RoomCaptureSessionDelegate
protocol and implement
two methods.
The first one is
captureSession(_ session:
didUpdate room:) method
in order to get the real-time
CapturedRoom data structure.
Your visualizer can use it to
update AR view of the 3D model,
which provides
real-time feedback to people
on the progress.
We will dive into
the CapturedRoom structure
more in a later part
of the talk.
This method will be called
when we detect updates
to the captured room.
The second method is
captureSession(_ session:
didProvide instruction:).
This method provides you
with an instruction structure
which contains real-time
feedback.
Your visualizer can use
the instruction
to guide people during the scan.
Let's go through
the instructions
that this API provides.
These instructions include
distance to the objects,
scanning speed,
lighting adjustment to the room,
as well as focusing on
specific areas of the room
that have more textures.
These instructions will be
provided during the scan
in order to guide people
with real-time feedback.
Next, we will move on
to the process part.
In this section, we will use
the RoomBuilder class
to process the scanned data and
generate the final 3D models.
To process the captured data,
the first step is to initiate
a RoomBuilder instance
in your ViewController class.
Next, in order to receive
the sensor data
after the capture process,
your app needs to implement
the captureSession(_ session:
didEndWith data: error:) method.
When the RoomCaptureSession
is stopped, by calling
the stop() function in your app,
or due to an error,
this function will be called to
return a CaptureRoomData object
and an optional error.
Finally, to process
the captured data,
we call the roomBuilder's
async roomModel(from:) method
with the await keyword.
The method runs asynchronously
to process the scanned data
and build the final 3D model.
It utilizes the Swift
async/await function
that we introduced
in last year's WWDC.
Within just a few seconds,
the model will be available
for the final presentation
in your app.
Now, let's dive into the details
of the CapturedRoom
data structure
and how you can export it
to use in your app.
At the top level,
there is CapturedRoom
which consists of
Surfaces and Objects.
Surface contains unique
attributes to represent curves
such as radius;
starting and ending angles;
four different edges
of the surface;
and architecture categories of
wall, opening, window, door.
Object contains
furniture categories
such as table, bed,
sofa, etc.
Surface and Object share
some common attributes
such as dimensions;
confidence, which gives you
three levels of confidence
for the scanned surface
or object;
the 3D transform matrix;
as well as a unique identifier.
Let's see how they are
represented in code.
The CapturedRoom structure is a
fully parametric representation
of the elements in the room.
It contains five properties
including walls, openings,
doors, windows,
and objects in the room.
For the first four elements,
they are represented
as the Surface structure
which represents 2D planar
architectural structures.
On the right, you can see
the various properties
of Surface we covered earlier.
The last property is an array
of 3D objects in the room,
and they are represented
as cuboids.
On the right, you can see the
various properties of Object.
Here is the list of object
types we support in RoomPlan.
These include a variety
of common furniture types
such as sofa, table,
chair, bed, and many more.
Finally, the export function
allows you to export
this CapturedRoom
into a USD or USDZ data
for your existing workflows.
Here is an example to show
how you can directly open
the USD output in Cinema 4D
to browse and edit
the hierarchical data structure
of the room, as well as
the dimensions and location
of each room element or object.
You can also leverage your
existing USD and USDZ workflows
to add renders
of the captured room
into a variety of applications
such as real estate, e-commerce,
utilities, and interior design.
So far, we covered
the scanning experience
and underlying RoomPlan APIs.
We'll now go through
some best practices
to help you get good results
with RoomPlan.
We will cover
the recommended conditions
that allow for a good scan,
room features to look out for
while selecting a room,
as well as a few scanning
and thermal considerations
to keep in mind.
RoomPlan API supports most
common architectural structures
and objects
in a typical household.
It works best
for a single residential room
with a maximum room size
of 30 feet by 30 feet
or around 9 by 9 meters.
Lighting is also important
for the API
to get a clear video stream and
good AR tracking performance.
A minimum 50 lux or higher is
recommended for using the API,
which is typical for
a family living room at night.
For the hardware, RoomPlan API
is supported on all
LiDAR-enabled iPhone
and iPad Pro models.
There are
some special conditions
that can present a challenge
for the API.
For example, full-height mirrors
and glass pose a challenge
for the LiDAR sensor
to produce the expected output.
Even high ceilings could exceed
the limit of the scanning range
of the LiDAR sensor.
Also, very dark surfaces could
be hard for the device to scan.
There are some considerations
to get better scanning results.
First, for applications that
have high accuracy requirements,
preparing the room
before scanning
can enhance the quality
of the scan.
For example,
opening the curtains
can let more natural light in
and reduce window occlusions,
which works best
for daytime scans.
Closing the doors
can reduce the chance
of scanning unnecessary area
outside of the room.
Following a good scanning
motion is also very important
to achieving good
scanning results with the API.
And that is why we provide the
user instruction delegate method
in order to provide feedback
on textures, distance, speed,
and lighting conditions
to people during the scans.
Another thing to keep in mind
is battery and thermals
of the device.
We have done many optimizations
on RoomPlan API
to ensure a good
scanning experience.
Nevertheless, it's best
to avoid repeated scans
or single long scans
over 5 minutes.
These could
not only cause fatigue
but also drain out the battery
and create thermal issues
which might in turn impact
the user experience of your app.
There is a lot
that we covered today.
We introduced a brand-new API,
RoomPlan.
It provides an intuitive
scanning experience
to capture your rooms,
powerful machine learning models
to understand the environment,
as well as a fully parametric
USD output format
for easy integration
in your apps.
For guidance on how to better
design and implement
your new RoomPlan experience,
please check out
the related talks below.
Praveen: It's time for you
to try RoomPlan in your app.
We can't wait to see what you
can create with this new API.
Kai: Thanks for watching!
♪