♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hello, I am Teja, an engineer on
the iOS System Experience team,
and in this session, you'll get
to meet Focus filters.
Focus was introduced in iOS 15,
macOS Monterey and watchOS 8.
It is a way for people to
concentrate on what's important
by configuring system behavior
for a period of time.
Focus is enabled by simply
going into Control Center
and selecting from either a
system Focus or a custom Focus.
During the time
that a Focus is enabled,
notification behavior
can be customized.
For example, during Work Focus,
someone may want
to only allow notifications
from their coworkers
or only allow notifications
for a select few apps
that are relevant to work.
For each Focus, system behavior
can be configured
and scheduled in Settings.
iOS 16 and macOS Ventura
enhance the Focus feature
with Focus filters.
I'll start by introducing you
to Focus filters
and how they behave.
Then, I'll go over how to define
a Focus filter in your app.
After that, I'll cover what it
means to act on a Focus filter.
And finally, I'll cover how
your app can provide
additional context
back to the system.
Focus filters
are a way for someone
to customize app behavior based
on the currently enabled Focus.
There are some great examples
of system apps
that have adopted Focus filters.
The Calendar app allows people
to filter which calendars
should be visible by default
when a Focus is enabled.
This is what my calendar
normally looks like.
And as you can see,
I have a mix
of work and personal
calendar events.
I can configure
a Focus filter for Calendar,
during the Personal Focus, to
only show my personal calendar.
After setting up
the Focus filter,
this is what my calendar
looks like.
Calendar has indicated
that this is filtered by Focus
and provided a way
to toggle the filtering.
Now I won't be overwhelmed
with my work calendar
when trying to enjoy
some personal time.
The Mail app's inbox
can be filtered
to show only relevant mailboxes
during a Focus.
Mail notifications
are also filtered
to show only the relevant
notifications prominently.
This means
that I can set up Mail
to only deliver work-related
Mail notifications
during the Work Focus
and prevent
personal mail notifications
from interrupting me.
There are many reasons
why your app may want
to implement Focus filters.
Perhaps your app
manages multiple accounts,
and it's appropriate
to associate a Focus
with a particular account.
Apps with large amount of data
may need to filter content
for the Focus.
If you would like
to help your users
avoid getting distracted
while focused,
you can do this
by reducing badge counts,
in-app alerts,
and notifications
to what is salient
for the enabled Focus.
Regarding appearance, your app
may want to surface a theme
or a layout based
on the enabled Focus.
Fundamentally, if your app
can surface different content
based on context, you may be
able to employ Focus filters
to enhance user experience.
Let me explain
how Focus filters work.
Your app defines what can be
customized by a user per Focus,
and this is done
using an AppIntent.
The system will expose what
can be configured per Focus.
UI to configure properties
defined by your AppIntent
will be exposed in Focus
settings as a Focus filter.
Users can configure your app
to behave a certain way
by navigating to Focus settings
and configuring Focus filters
for your app.
Now, I'm going to go over
how you can incorporate
Focus filters
into your codebase.
There are a few parts
to defining your Focus filter.
The first is implementing
SetFocusFilterIntent.
This indicates to the system
that your app
is interested in having
custom settings per Focus.
The second step is defining
your app's parameters.
These will represent what can
be configured within your app
by the user.
The final step is to set
the display representation,
so your Focus filter
appears in system settings
with the correct content.
This way, users are aware
of what is configured.
I'll dive into some code.
The first thing you need to do
is import AppIntents
and define a struct that
implements SetFocusFilterIntent.
This is your Focus filter.
Setting the title
and description
will help users discover
what your Focus is all about.
Focus filters appear
in a grid view in Settings.
Before your Focus filter
has been configured,
it will be surfaced
to the user with this look.
The icon here
is your app's icon,
the primary text
is your app's name,
and the secondary text
will match the title variable
that you set
in your Focus filter.
When the user taps in
to configure your filter,
the same content is displayed.
This time, the system also
includes the description string
that you've provided,
for additional context.
Both the title and description
strings are static,
and they are read by the system
at the time that your app
is installed.
When defining your Focus filter,
you'll have to specify
what a person can customize
by providing a series
of properties that are decorated
as parameters.
When specifying a parameter,
you must give it a name
and a data type.
Parameters can be
of a standard data type
such as Bool, string,
float, etcetera.
If you have a custom data
type that you would like
to have configured,
you can make it an entity,
which will allow you
to decorate it as a parameter.
To learn more about entities
and App Intents,
watch the
"Dive into App Intents" session.
When defining your Focus filter,
you will only specify
the data type and name
for each parameter.
It is up to users to configure
the value of the parameter
that would apply
during each Focus.
Parameters can be
marked as optional,
which means that they do not
have to be configured.
Parameters that are not optional
should provide default values.
In code, you specify
a parameter --
or an optional parameter --
by defining a variable
of the type you want
in your Focus filter
and decorating it
as a parameter.
Here, I've created a required
Bool parameter that represents
whether my Focus filter
should always use Dark Mode.
I've set its default to false.
I've also created
an optional string parameter
that represents a user's status
message during this Focus.
Lastly, I've included
an optional account parameter
that is an entity
defined by my app;
it contains information
about a particular account.
The title, which is set on all
three of these parameters,
is displayed in Settings
to describe the parameter
to the user.
In Focus settings,
once a user configures
your app's Focus filter,
it'll be presented
in a similar grid
to what I showed earlier.
But this time,
because the filter
has already been configured,
the content is dynamic
in order to reflect
what has been configured.
The icon here is
still your app's icon.
The primary text
and the secondary text
can be customized using the
display representation property
on your FocusFilterIntent.
The primary text should
represent what parameters
have been configured,
such as Select Account,
Set Status, etcetera.
The secondary text should
represent what the parameters
have been configured to,
such as Work Account or Working.
In my code, I set
the display representation
to be generated dynamically.
Since account and status
are optional parameters,
they only get included
in the dynamic primary
and secondary texts
if they are actually set.
Since alwaysUseDarkMode
is a required parameter,
it is always included in
the primary and secondary texts.
OK, you have now
defined your Focus filter,
so users can go
into Focus settings
and customize certain values
for a particular Focus.
But how can your app know
what someone has customized?
And how can your app
update itself accordingly?
It has to act on a change
from the system.
When a Focus change occurs
and the system has determined
that it's important for your app
to know about this change,
it will deliver this information
to you in one of two ways.
If the app is running,
you will receive a call
to the perform method
in your FocusFilterIntent,
if you've implemented it.
If the app is not running,
you can implement an extension
that will get spun up.
Again, if you've
implemented perform
in your FocusFilterIntent,
that will get called
in your extension.
Since perform can get called
on either your app
or your extension, not every
app needs an extension.
Typically, if your app
is only updating its own view
in response
to a Focus transition,
then implementing perform
just in the app would suffice.
If your app's widget,
notifications or badges
would need to change
based on the Focus transition,
then you may want to consider
implementing an extension.
Basically,
if your app would want
to update anything
outside its own views,
you would need
to implement the extension.
For the rest of this session,
I may refer to "your app"
but that can mean either
your app or your extension
depending on this context.
To respond to a Focus filter,
implement the perform function,
access the populated values
for parameters
provided via Settings,
and then use these values
to update your app's
views and behavior.
Your implementation
of perform is called
when the system
determines that your app
needs to respond
to a Focus transition.
Perform is also called
when the system determines
that the previously delivered
values are no longer relevant.
In this case,
your Focus filter parameters
are configured
with the default values.
When perform is called
on your app's Focus filter,
the values of all the parameters
will be filled out
to match what was configured
in Settings.
The values of the named
parameters can be read
by calling
self."name of the parameter."
In this example,
at the end of perform,
I update my app
with the data I received.
Sometimes, you may need to query
the current Focus
filter parameters.
In my case,
since my filter is called
ExampleChatAppFocusFilter,
I access ExampleChatAppFocus
Filter.current.
Now that your app is able
to act on a Focus filter,
the next step is to take
the user experience further
by providing additional context
about how your app behavior
has changed back to the system.
By providing additional context,
you can influence
your app behavior
outside your app's views.
Examples of this include
notifications filtering
and setting your app's
notification badge count.
One way you can give
the system information
is via the App Context object.
This is an object
that can be returned
as part of the result
of the perform function.
Or you can return
the App Context at any time
in your Focus filter
and force the system
to get the updated value
by calling invalidate.
When a Focus filter is active,
your app may have
additional context to determine
if a particular notification
should not interrupt the user.
To pass along this information,
your app must set
the filterPredicate property
in the AppContext.
This filter predicate
works in conjunction
with a new string property
called filterCriteria
on the UNNotification.
If the filter criteria on the
notification does not match
the filter predicate,
the notification is silenced.
To set the filter predicate
from your FocusFilterIntent,
include it in your App Context.
Say the device has
the Personal Focus enabled
and the user has set it up so
that only the personal account
is selected;
in this case, I set up
the filter predicate
to be the personal account's
identifier.
If the incoming notification is
not from the personal account,
it should not interrupt
the user.
Here, when I'm configuring
this notification,
I set the filterCriteria to be
the work account's identifier.
This is because I know
this notification
is being sent
to the work account,
and I expect that this
notification would be silenced
because the account identifier
does not match the predicate
that I had just set,
which only matched with the
personal account's identifier.
This example is
for a local notification
but filter criteria can also
be set on the JSON payload
of a remote notification.
Another way to provide
the system additional context
is by updating your app's
badge count to reflect
what is important during
the currently-enabled Focus.
This prevents distractions
for your users.
There is a new API
in UserNotifications
for this purpose.
On UNUserNotificationCenter,
you simply call setBadgeCount
with an unsigned integer that
represents the new badge value.
Now, you know how
to provide additional context
to filter notifications
or set the badge count.
Remember, the goal
of this feature is to surface
what is most relevant to a user
when they are focused.
Sometimes this requires
minimizing unrelated content
to prevent distraction
when a Focus is enabled.
For next steps, I encourage you
to start considering
what parts of your app would
benefit from a Focus filter,
determine which properties
can be configured,
set up your app and your
extension to process this,
and then take it a step further
by assessing whether
to provide additional context.
That's it for Focus filters!
Thank you for joining in
on this session
and have a great rest of WWDC.
♪