♪ ♪
David Stites: Hi, and welcome
to "Evolve Your Core Data Schema."
My name is David Stites and I am
an engineer on the Core Data team.
In this session,
I am excited to talk to you
about how to update and migrate
the Core Data schema in your app.
The agenda for this session is to learn
what schema migration is
and why your app has to perform it
after updating its data model,
how to migrate the existing schema,
and how CloudKit
and schema migration interact.
First up, what is schema migration
and why your app must migrate
when you update your data model.
As your application evolves, it may become
necessary to change your data model.
Updating the data model requires
that those changes are materialized
in the underlying storage schema.
Consider this data model.
It has an Aircraft entity
with two attributes,
type and number of engines.
These attributes are reflected
in the underlying storage.
If I add
a number of passengers attribute,
I need to add the corresponding storage.
After migration, the changes are
fully reflected in the underlying storage.
Without migrating the changes
in the underlying storage,
Core Data will refuse
to open your persistent store
as the freshly-changed model doesn't
match the model used for storage.
Attempting to open an incompatible store
will result in an error
with the code NSPersistentStore-
IncompatibleVersionHashError.
If you receive this error,
it should be an indication to you
that a migration is required.
Now that I've explained
what schema migration is
and why it's essential
to evolving your app,
let me tell you
how migration is accomplished.
Core Data has built-in
data migration tools
to help keep your app's data storage
up-to-date with the current data model.
Collectively, these tools are
referred to as "lightweight migration."
Lightweight migration is
the preferred method of migration.
Lightweight migration automatically
analyzes and infers the migration
from the differences between the source
and destination managed object models.
At runtime, Core Data looks for the models
in the bundles returned
by .allBundles and .allFrameworks methods
of the NSBundle class.
Lightweight migration then generates
a mapping model
to materialize the changes you've made
in your app in your database schema.
Using lightweight migration
requires the changes to the data model
to fit an obvious migration pattern.
Lightweight operations
involving attributes include
adding an attribute,
removing an attribute,
making a non-optional attribute optional,
making an optional attribute non-optional
and defining a default value,
and renaming an attribute.
If you want to rename an attribute,
set the renaming identifier
in the destination model to the name
of the corresponding attribute
in the source model.
The renaming identifier is found
in the Xcode Data Model Editor's
property inspector.
For example, you can rename
the Aircraft entity color attribute
to paintColor.
The renaming identifier
creates a canonical name,
so set the renaming identifier
to the name of the attribute
in the source model, unless that attribute
already has a renaming identifier.
This means you can rename
an attribute in version 2 of a model,
and then rename it again in version 3.
The renaming will work correctly
going from version 2 to version 3,
or from version 1 to version 3.
Lightweight migration can also
handle changes to the relationships
without breaking a sweat.
You can add a new relationship
or delete an existing relationship.
You can also rename a relationship
by using a renaming identifier,
just like an attribute.
In addition,
you can change relationship cardinality,
for example,
migrating from a to-one to a to-many,
or a non-ordered to-many
to an ordered to-many, and vice versa.
If you guessed that entities are
also eligible for lightweight migration,
you're right.
You can add a new entity,
remove an existing entity,
and rename entities.
You can also create
a new parent or child entity
and move attributes up and down
within the entity hierarchy.
You can move entities
into or out of a hierarchy.
You cannot,
however, merge entity hierarchies.
if two existing entities do not
share a common parent in the source,
they cannot share a common parent
in the destination.
Lightweight migration is controlled
by two options keys:
NSMigratePersistent-
StoresAutomaticallyOption
and
NSInferMappingModelAutomaticallyOption.
The presence of these two keys
set to a true value
when the store is added to the persistent
coordinator will cause Core Data
to perform lightweight migration
automatically if it detects
the persistent store no longer matches
the current model.
If you're using NSPersistentContainer
or NSPersistentStoreDescription,
these options are set
automatically for you
and you don't need to do anything.
If you're using an alternative API
such as NSPersistentStoreCoordinator
.addPersistentStore
(type:configuration:at:options:),
lightweight migration can be requested by
setting and passing an options dictionary
with the keys set NSMigratePersistent-
StoresAutomaticallyOption
and NSInferMappingModelAutomaticallyOption
to a value of YES.
Core Data will perform
lightweight migration automatically
if it detects the persistent store
no longer matches the current model.
Here’s how this works in code.
First, I'll import CoreData
and create a managed object model.
Then, I'll create
a persistent store coordinator
by using the model I just created.
Note the options dictionary
I created and that I'll pass
when I add the store
to the persistent coordinator.
Lastly, I'll add the store
to the coordinator
where migration will occur
automatically if necessary.
Regardless of whatever API you use,
the changes to your data model can be made
directly in the same model
that is shipping with the application.
There is no need to create a new version
of the model to make changes.
If you want to determine
in advance whether Core Data can
infer the mapping model between the source
and destination models
without actually doing the work
of migration,
you can use NSMappingModel
.inferredMappingModel method.
The method returns the inferred model
if Core Data was able to create it.
Otherwise, it returns nil.
Sometimes, combined changes to the schema
may exceed the capabilities
of lightweight migration.
I’m going to describe to you
how to deal with that problem
and still use lightweight migration.
Returning to our previous example model,
suppose that we've previously added
an attribute called “flightData” that uses
external storage for binary data,
indicated by the file path
stored in FLIGHT_DATA.
Further, suppose there is a need
to change that attribute
to store data internally
and remove the external storage.
Checking to see if this migration
fits any of the capabilities
of lightweight migration,
it is discovered that it doesn't.
On the face of it,
it appears that we're stuck,
unable to make this change.
However, fear not!
Lightweight migration can still be used
to perform more complex,
non-conforming migrations,
albeit in multiple steps.
The goal becomes
to decompose the migration tasks
that aren't eligible
for lightweight migration
into a minimum series of migrations that
are eligible for lightweight migration.
Generally, if the original model is A
and the objective model is B,
but model B has changes
that aren't eligible
for lightweight migration,
a bridge can be created by introducing
one or more model versions
that decompose those changes.
Each of the models introduced
will have one or more operations
that is within the capabilities
that compose the non-conforming changes.
This results in a series of migrations
where each model is now
lightweight migrateable
but equivalent
to the non-conforming migration.
Returning to my example
that wasn't eligible
for lightweight migration,
our original model is model A.
I will start decomposing the task
by introducing a new model version, A prime,
and add a new attribute
"tmpStorage" that will be used
temporarily to store data
that is imported from the external files.
Next, I will import the data
from the external files
into our new attribute.
The code to import this data is separate
from the functionality provided
by Core Data.
The execution of this import
is interposed between migrations.
Once the data has been safely imported,
I'll create another new version
of the model A double-prime from A prime.
In A double-prime, I will delete
the old external storage attribute
while simultaneously renaming
the new attribute.
Each of these steps described is within
the capabilities of lightweight migration.
Intuitively, an event loop could be built
that opens the persistent store
with the lightweight migration options set
and iteratively steps through each
unprocessed model in a serial order,
and Core Data will migrate the store.
If you perform app-specific logic
during your migrations,
such as how I imported data from
external files in the previous example,
that logic must be "restartable"
in the event the migration is interrupted
due to the process terminating.
If your app uses Core Data and CloudKit,
there are some important points
you should keep in mind
when designing your data model
in Core Data.
To pass records between a Core Data store
and a CloudKit database,
they require a shared understanding
of the data model.
You define this model
in the Core Data model editor.
That model is subsequently used
to generate the CloudKit schema.
The generated schema is created initially
in the Development environment,
and then promoted to Production.
You should be aware that CloudKit
doesn't support all the features
of a Core Data model.
As you design your model,
be aware of the following limitations
and create a compatible data model.
For example, unique constraints
on entities aren't supported.
Undefined and objectID attribute type
aren't supported as attribute types.
And relationships must be optional
and have an inverse relationship.
In addition, CloudKit does not support
the deny deletion rule.
As you're developing your app, you'll be
using the Development environment.
The CloudKit schema can be
modified freely in this environment.
However, after you promote
your schema to Production,
the record types
and their fields are immutable.
While lightweight migration handles
many different scenarios,
CloudKit is more restricted
in what it supports.
Many of the lightweight operations
I described earlier are unsupported.
Specifically,
what is supported in CloudKit is
adding new fields to existing record types
and adding new record types.
You cannot modify or delete
existing record types or fields.
Consider these restrictions
when modifying the model schema.
When it comes time to update
your data model,
keep in mind that lightweight migration
only materializes schema changes
in the local store file.
Regardless of whether a particular store
is used with CloudKit,
migration will only change
the store on disk
and does not make changes
to the CloudKit schema.
You still need
to materialize those changes
in the Development database
by running the schema initializer
and then promoting
those changes in Development
to Production using the CloudKit Console.
Keep in mind that users of your app
will be using old versions
as well as new versions.
The latest version of the app
will of course know
about any new additions to the schema.
Old versions of the app won't know
about the new fields or record types.
Since CloudKit schema is
essentially additive,
give consideration to the effects
of schema migration
to devices running
older versions of your app.
For example, one common pitfall
is forgetting to update old fields
that the older versions of your app use
but newer versions don't.
Here are some strategies
to migrate CloudKit schema.
The first option is to incrementally add
new fields to existing record types.
If you adopt this approach, older versions
of your app will have access
to every record a user creates,
but not every field.
A second option is
to version your entities
by including a version attribute,
and then use a fetch request to select
only the records that are compatible
with the current version of the app.
If you adopt this approach,
older versions of your app
won't fetch records that a user creates
with a more recent version,
effectively hiding them on that device.
The last strategy is to create
a completely new container,
using
NSPersistentCloudKitContainerOptions,
to associate the new store
with a new container.
Be aware that if the user has
a large data set,
uploading the data set to iCloud
could take an extended period of time.
Whatever method you use,
take care in designing your data model.
Be sure to consider
cross-version compatibility issues
and test different versions
of your data model together.
Now that we've
thoroughly discussed data models,
migration, and CloudKit,
I am going to demonstrate this in action.
As you may have guessed, I'm a pilot.
I've created a small app
to log my flight time.
Here is the data model for that app.
I have a single entity called “LogEntry”
and have added a number of attributes,
such as aircraft type,
flight duration, origin, destination,
and tail number to allow me to log
the required experience information.
When I run this application
for the first time,
Core Data will create the store
and materialize the schema in that store.
Before I run the application,
I am going to turn on
the com.apple.CoreData.SQLDebug
and the com.apple.CoreData.MigrationDebug
environment variables.
This will cause Core Data
to log the steps it is taking.
With these arguments in place,
I will run the app.
As the app launches, Core Data is
logging the steps that it is taking:
creating the file,
creating the metadata for the store,
and materializing the schema.
SQLite created the table ZLOGENTRY
with our schema in it.
This can also be confirmed
by looking at the store file
using the sqlite3 command line tool.
Here, I have the LogEntry table,
and it has the corresponding columns
to the attributes I created
in the data model.
Now I'm going to make
some lightweight changes.
I'm adding some new entities,
Aircraft, Pilot, and Airport.
This will help me normalize the schema.
I am changing some of the attributes in
the LogEntry entity to be relationships.
For example, destination and origin move
from being string attributes
to being an Airport to-one relationship.
The Airport entity
also has two new attributes,
icaoIdentifier and faaIdentifier.
The type attribute is promoted
to a new entity; Aircraft
and I am adding two new attributes,
tailNumber and registrationNumber.
On LogEntry, I am creating a to-one
relationship to an Aircraft from LogEntry.
Lastly, I added a Pilot entity
that has name and certificate ID.
Each log entry will be
related to a Pilot entity.
Now that I've completed my changes
to the data model,
I'm going to run the app again.
Oop! I received an error running the app.
Inspecting the code, it is
NSPersistentStore-
IncompatibleVersionHashError.
That error means that my current model
no longer matches the schema
for the model in the store.
I need to migrate the store schema.
I can do that in one of three ways.
Using the first method, I can convert
my code to use an NSPersistentContainer
as the lightweight migration options
are automatically set for me.
Using the second method,
I can use NSPersistentStoreDescription,
as, again, the lightweight migrations
options are automatically set for me.
Lastly, using the third method,
I can manually set
the lightweight migration options
on an options dictionary
and pass that dictionary
to the coordinator when opening the store.
I think I'll go with the first option,
using an NSPersistentContainer.
Now that I have converted the code
to use an NSPersistentContainer,
I will launch the app and again observe
that Core Data is migrating the schema
in the store file.
Again, this can be confirmed
using the sqlite3 command line tool.
Note the new schema was materialized
by Core Data automatically,
using lightweight migration.
What could be easier?
Before ending my demo,
I wanted to show option number 3.
Recall in this option,
I am manually setting
the lightweight migration options
on an options dictionary
and then passing that dictionary
to the coordinator when opening the store.
The end result is the same
in that the store is migrated
to the new schema.
When you make changes to your data model,
use lightweight migration to help you.
Lightweight migration is very flexible
and easy to use
for the vast majority
of data model changes.
If you have more complex data models,
break that model down
into ones that are composed
of lightweight changes.
Lastly, if you use CloudKit with your app,
carefully consider the implications
of the data model changes.
Thoroughly test any data model changes.
I hope you've found
this information useful
and that you'll consider updating
the model in your project
to build some awesome new features.
Thanks for flying with me,
and have a great WWDC.