♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Kacey.
You may have come across
Universal Scene Description,
or USD, already.
You may have interacted with
USD files in augmented reality.
Or you may have converted assets
from other formats to USD.
But what's really inside
of a USD file?
USD is an important technology
with unique features,
so let's take a look
under the hood
and explore the fundamentals
of USD together.
We'll learn what USD is,
introduce some
basic USD concepts,
learn how to compose scenes
with USD,
and get an understanding
of the USD file formats.
First, what is USD?
USD was developed
by Pixar Animation Studios
to enable them to create
the complex movies we love,
and it is widely used
across the film, entertainment,
and other industries.
It's extensible by design
and is rapidly emerging
as a collaborative,
key workflow technology.
It's an open source project
built on decades
of production experience
in the film industry
and is increasingly
being adopted for games,
simulation, AR, manufacturing,
and e-commerce.
There are three
core aspects to USD:
the scene description
specification, the API,
and the rendering system.
Your application interacts
with USD using the API.
The rendering system
provides support
for visualizing the scenes
with different renderers.
Apple has multiple different
rendering systems for USD.
Check out the "Explore USD tools
and rendering" session
to learn more about it.
In this session,
we focus on the scene
description specification
which states how
scene data is described,
how it is organized,
and how it is represented
in a file format.
Fundamentally,
these USD files contain data
describing how a scene
should look.
Rendering applications
interpret the data,
and produce an image
on the screen.
For example,
at last year's WWDC session,
we created this USD scene
and rendered it in Octane.
Now let's dive into
the fundamental concepts
and learn about the data
behind the render.
To keep things simple,
we will use
a text USD representation
USD has a lot of cool features
we'd love to talk about,
but for the sake of time,
we will focus on
the essentials features
that you may
most commonly encounter
while working with USD
such as stage, prim, and layers,
just to name a few.
Let's start with the stage.
Imagine we are attending
a play in a theater.
As audience members,
we observe the stage
to watch the actors perform,
notice the environments,
lighting, and the props.
This is a good analogy
to how a stage works in USD.
A stage is a scene graph,
or a data structure,
that organizes
graphical information
in a hierarchical way,
where all the scene elements
come together.
A stage is a composition
of one or more layers,
which are typically files
containing scene information.
In general,
a stage is made up of prims,
which are the primary
container objects of a scene.
Prims can contain other prims
to create a hierarchy
of scene elements.
Let's check out an example.
On the left,
we have a sample USD layer
and on the right, we see
a preview visual representation
of the stage.
We see two prims:
a sphere and a cube.
Each prim has a certain type
that defines what it represents
on the stage.
There are many
different types of prims
that make up a stage such as
meshes, lights, and materials.
For this example,
the sphere prim
has a type called "Sphere,"
and the cube prim
has a type called "Cube."
But this brings up
a good question.
How does USD know
what these prim types mean?
USD knows this
through the use of schemas.
Schemas are structured data
that define the role
of a prim on the stage.
They provide meaning
to common scene concepts
like geometry,
materials, and more.
For this example,
here is a schema definition
of a sphere.
It defines that every sphere
has a radius
and a bounding box extent.
With the existing schemas,
USD gives you a rich foundation
of built-in types
to describe your scenes.
Custom schemas enable you
to extend USD even further.
You can provide your own schemas
that represent your custom data
for your own use cases
and workflows.
Schemas don't need to have
a visual representation.
They can just be data
you want to have in the stage
in a structured, meaningful way.
For example,
here, I've created a new schema
called "WWDC."
It defines that a prim
that has a title
and a year associated with it,
and here is a prim
called "WWDC22"
that uses the schema.
It has set the year to 2022
and the title is set
to "Call to code."
The year and the title
are called the "attributes"
of the prim.
Prims can have many
different attributes.
Each attribute has a type
and a value.
Attributes can also have
default values authored
so they don't have to be
explicitly defined
in the prim
that uses the schema.
Going back
to our Sphere schema,
you can see how we've defined
default values
for the radius
and extent attributes.
In this layer,
we have a single Sphere prim.
Since the Radius attribute
is not set,
it derives its value
from the Sphere schema:
a default radius of one.
We can be explicit though,
and set the radius attribute.
The sphere still looks the same
because this value matches
the default value of one
that is set in the schema.
Now let's add a second sphere,
and set the radius to 0.5.
We can see that
it's indeed half the size
of the other sphere.
Attributes, prims, and stages
can also contain metadata,
which are key-value pairings
of information
that can provide auxiliary data
for parts of a scene.
Metadata is set
at the level where it applies.
Metadata that affects
the whole stage
and all prims in it
is set at the stage level.
Metadata that is specific
to a single prim,
is set on the prim.
Attributes can also
have metadata.
For example, here is some
typical stage metadata.
metersPerUnit defines the scale
units for the scene.
upAxis defines which
of the X, Y, or Z axes
is considered the up direction
for the camera in the scene.
doc strings store
useful documentation
for workflow tracking purposes.
Now that we have defined
these basics,
we can already start
making use of USD.
Let's see how
the pancakes scene can be done
using just these concepts.
In our layer,
we create a transform prim
called "Pancakes."
We then add a transform prim
called "Blueberry_01"
that is a child
of the Pancakes prim.
Within the Blueberry_01 prim,
we include the Mesh prim.
The Mesh prim holds
the geometry for the blueberry
and binds to the materials.
Let's complete
the rest of the asset
by adding the other prims.
Here is our completed
pancake scene,
using just these basic concepts.
These fundamentals
can get you far,
but in production-centric
projects,
we need to collaborate
with many different team members
and organizations.
USD has a lot of features
to address this need
in what is called "composition."
Composition enables
the creation of a stage
from separate units
of scene description.
This allows for the efficient
reuse of 3D elements
in a scene
that enables collaboration
and fast iteration.
We will discuss the most common
types of composition:
layering, references, payloads,
and variantSets.
But let's do it in a fun way.
Fancy a game of chess?
Let's build out
a chess set scene.
In the scene,
we will use a catalog of assets
in a catalog layer,
which will refer
to our chess pieces.
We will then arrange these
pieces on the chessboard
in a layout layer
to get our final result,
which is viewable
with the ChessSet layer.
We'll first need to get
our chess pieces
In chess,
there are six main pieces:
the pawn, rook, bishop,
knight, queen, and king.
We will use these assets,
created with Object Capture,
to build a complete chess set.
Let's start by bringing in
our pieces to our stage
using a USD concept,
referencing.
Referencing is when a prim in
a stage refers to another prim
in either the same stage
or a different layer
without copying the data.
This helps minimize
duplication of data
and allows for the data
to be updated separately
by different people
and applications.
Let's reference our pawn asset
into our scene.
In our catalog layer,
we define a prim called "Pawn".
So far it doesn't have any data
and so our stage is still empty.
Next, we add a reference
to the Pawn.usda layer.
This brings in the pawn asset,
and we can see it
in the catalog layer.
But how does USD know
which prim it should bring in
from the file you reference?
We can specify this prim
with the defaultPrim metadata.
The defaultPrim metadata
is defined on the stage
and specifies which prim
should be referred to
when using this scene
on another stage.
We recommend always authoring
a defaultPrim for USD assets.
Let's check our pawn asset
to make sure
the defaultPrim is authored.
We can see the defaultPrim
metadata at the stage level
in our asset.
Great.
Alternatively, if the
defaultPrim is not authored
or you wish to refer to a prim
that is different
from the defaultPrim,
you can specify the path
to the prim
in the referencing
layer explicitly,
anywhere in the hierarchy.
Paths in USD are used to
identify elements on a stage.
The prim path is a unique
identifier for a prim.
For example, on this stage
we see three prims.
The World prim
has a prim path of /World.
The Pawn and Knight prims
are considered children
of the World prim.
Thus the path to the Pawn prim
would be /World/Pawn,
and the path to the Knight prim
would be /World/Knight.
With that in mind, we can
explicitly set the prim path
to the Pawn prim
in our reference here.
For larger scenes,
it can be expensive
to load all
the scene information at once.
For this, USD allows
for the deferred loading
of scene description
onto a stage
with a type of reference
called a "payload."
It is recommended to use
payloads when referencing
large data sets,
such as complex geometry,
or other large scene graphs
representing props
or characters.
We'll convert these asset
references to payloads instead,
so we can choose to defer
the loading of the chess pieces.
If we choose
not to load the payloads,
our scene appears empty
when initially opened.
Once we enable
the loading of payloads,
we can see
all of our pieces again.
Now that we have our pieces
in the scene,
we can start laying them out
on the chess board.
We can do this
on yet another layer
using the USD concept
of layering.
With layering,
layers can be stacked,
similar to popular image editing
software packages
such as Photoshop
or Affinity Photo.
Prims in a layer
that are above another layer
are considered stronger
and can add or override data
in the lower layers.
As you can see,
the pieces are currently
in their wrong places
But don't worry,
we can use layering
to make nondestructive
modifications to other layers.
This is perfect for us
to move our pieces
to the right positions without
editing our catalog layer.
Let's see how this can be done
We start by creating a new stage
called ChessSet
which will be our final scene.
It contains metadata
called "sublayers"
at the top of the layer.
Here we bring in our pieces
with the catalog layer.
Next, we create a new layer --
Layout.usda --
which we use to move our pieces.
This layout layer will contain
the positions
of our chess pieces.
Let's override the position
of our pieces in the scene.
We'll start with Pawn_01.
We modify
the pawn asset's position
by changing
its translation attributes.
Let's check out
how this updates our scene.
Here we have our chess set again
without our layout layer,
so the pawn is still
in its original position.
Once we add our layout layer,
the pawn has been moved
to its expected position
on the chessboard.
Let's do the same
for the other pieces
and move them
to their correct locations.
We position our other
chess pieces
the same way
we position the pawn.
Here's how we did it
for Pawn_02.
And then again
for Pawn_03, and so on.
We finished the changes
to the layout layer,
and now we have the chess pieces
set in their correct location.
We have half
of our chess set built.
We use layers to bring in our
assets with the catalog layer
and use the overrides
to place them on the board
with the layout layer.
All that is left
is setting up the pieces
for the opponent side.
One thing to note is that
our opponent's pieces
are a different color.
Instead of making
a new set of assets,
we can update
our chess piece assets
using another USD concept,
variantSets.
VariantSets allow
for the dynamic swapping
of discrete alternatives
on the stage.
The variants contained
in a variantSet
can be different materials,
geometry,
or anything that
can be represented in USD.
Switching between
different variants on a stage
is nondestructive.
We will setup variant sets
to switch between
different materials
for the chess pieces.
In our Pawn asset, we add
a variantSet called "color"
so we can switch between
different colors for the pawn.
Now we add two variants
to our variantSet:
Dark using the dark material and
Light using the light material.
Finally, we set
the default variant to specify
which one to use when we load
the pawn onto the stage.
Now, we are back
in our catalog layer.
We've set up all the pieces
on the board,
but they are all using
the light material.
That is because
the default variant
is set to the light material.
Let's change the variant
of one of the pawns
to the dark material.
We set the variant to Dark.
We can see that one of the pawns
on the opponent's side
is now dark.
Let's apply this change
to the other pieces as well.
Finally, we completed
our chess set.
There's one more USD concept we
can use to optimize our scene:
scene graph instancing.
Scene graph instancing allows us
to reuse parts of scene graph
on a stage many times
to represent anything
that contains
more than one of something
such as foliage, furniture,
or in our case, chess pieces.
Using scene graph instancing
provides both memory
and performance improvements
in your applications.
To use scene graph instancing,
we can specify the instance
metadata on a prim
or part of a scene graph.
All prims that are instanced
are candidates
to share the same scene graph.
Let's add support for prim
instancing in our scene.
In our catalog file, we will add
the metadata "instanceable"
to the chess piece prims
and set the value to true.
By adding this metadata,
USD will now treat these assets
as potentially instanceable
prims that share the same data,
rather than duplicating the data
for each prim.
Our chess set
still looks the same
but it's now more performant
and memory efficient.
And with this, we're done
with our chess set!
It looks great, and we exercised
a lot of USD features.
Layering, referencing, payloads
and variantSets
are just some of the types
of composition that USD defines.
There is a specific
strength order
in which USD composes
the scene graph
to ensure consistent
scene representation.
More information
about composition
and the order acronym LIVRPS
can be learned
in Pixar's USD documentation.
In this session,
we talked about
what's inside of USD files.
Now let's talk about
the files themselves
and how they might
appear on disk.
There are several types
of USD files.
USD files containing
readable ASCII text
had the .usda extension.
We have been using these files
the whole time in this session.
A more compact and efficient
binary representation
is the crate format,
which has the .usdc extension.
You may also have files
with the .usd extension.
These could either be ASCII text
or binary crate files.
Lastly, USD has a packaging
format which can contain
multiple USD files
and associated auxiliary files,
like textures, in an
uncompressed zip archive
with the .usdz extension.
Today we learned about some
of USD's fundamental concepts:
stage, layers, prims, schemas,
attributes, and metadata.
We used these concepts
to build a chess set
and made use of referencing,
payloads, the defaultPrim,
prim paths, layering,
and instancing.
And finally, we discussed
the different USD file formats:
.usda, .usdc, .usd, and .usdz.
We encourage you to learn more
about these concepts
with Pixar's USD documentation
and take full advantage
of USD's capabilities
in your applications.
Thank you!
♪