[spacey music]
Anne: Hello, and welcome!
I'm Anne Hitchcock,
and I'm a watchOS software engineer.
Today, I want to show you
how to create a productivity app
on watchOS.
Since the introduction of SwiftUI
and Independent Watch apps in watchOS 6,
you've been able to do more
in your Watch apps.
Each year, SwiftUI on watchOS gets
more capabilities.
At the same time,
watchOS has gotten new features,
like the keyboard,
that let you build whole new kinds of apps
for Watch.
I'd like to show you how to knit together
some of those features
to build an app to track
a list of things to get done.
We're going to create a new Watch app,
add a simple list of items to display,
Let people add items to the list,
and then edit the items.
As we add these features,
we'll talk about common app
navigation strategies in Watch apps
and how to pick the correct one.
We'll share items with a friend
to share the load.
Then we'll add a chart to our app
to help us spot productivity trends
and keep us motivated.
And we'll use the Digital Crown to make
our chart scrollable
to show a larger data range.
Let's get started by creating
a new app.
Create a new project in Xcode.
In the watchOS tab, choose App
and click Next.
After choosing a product name,
you have a couple of choices.
The most important one
is whether to create a Watch-only App
or to create a Watch app
with a companion iOS app.
Let's talk about what makes
a great Watch app
and when you want a companion iOS app.
Great Watch apps enable quick interaction,
like the interface in Workout
that allows you to start
your favorite workouts quickly.
No one wants to stand around,
holding up their arm,
tapping through to try to find something.
Great Watch apps make it easy
to access important information
and features.
Great Watch apps focus
on the essential purpose of the app.
For example, the Weather app displays
the forecast for today,
relevant current conditions,
and a simple 10-day forecast.
Focus on the essentials in your app
so people can easily find the information
and actions they need.
A great Watch app is designed to be used
independently of the companion iPhone.
The Contacts app, for example,
synchronizes with your phone,
but doesn't require your iPhone
to be nearby
to access contact information
on your Apple Watch.
There are many reasons you might also want
a companion iOS app for your Watch app,
including providing a historical record
of data captured by Apple Watch
or detailed analysis of trends,
as in the Fitness app.
Since our app has a focused feature set,
quick interaction, and limited data,
we're going to create a Watch-only app.
At this point,
I want to spend a few minutes
talking about the targets that
are created.
If you've built a Watch app in the past,
your project has two targets for Watch:
a WatchKit App target with a storyboard,
assets, and perhaps
some localization-related files,
and a WatchKit Extension target
with all of your app code.
These dual targets are a holdover
from the early days of watchOS,
and there really isn't a good reason
for multiple Watch targets anymore.
Starting in Xcode 14, new Watch apps
have a single Watch app target.
All of the code, assets, localizations,
and Siri Intent and Widget extensions
associated with your Watch app
belong in this target.
The great news is
that single-target Watch apps
are supported back to watchOS 7!
You can simplify your project structure
and reduce confusion and duplication
while still supporting customers
who aren't running
the latest watchOS.
If you have an existing app
with a WatchKit Extension target,
it will continue to work,
and you can continue
to update your app using Xcode
and publish your app
through the App Store.
If you already have a Watch app that uses
the SwiftUI lifecycle,
transitioning to a single target is easy
using the migration tool in Xcode 14.
Select your target and choose
Validate Settings
from the Editor menu.
The target collapsing option
will be offered
if your deployment target
is watchOS 7 or later.
If you haven't already made the leap,
now is a good time to start the process
of converting your app to use
the SwiftUI life cycle
to enjoy the simplicity
of a single-target Watch app
and all of the features of SwiftUI.
The targets aren't the only thing
we simplified in Xcode 14!
We've also made it a lot easier
to add an icon for your app
by only requiring
a single 1024x1024 pixel image.
The app icon image will be scaled
for display on all Watch devices.
Be sure to test with your app icon
on devices on the home screen,
in notifications,
and in the settings for your app
in the Watch app on the iPhone.
You can add custom images
for specific smaller sizes if necessary.
For example,
if your app icon has details in the image
that get lost at smaller sizes,
you can add specific icon images
for those sizes
with the image details removed.
Now let's add some functionality
to our app
by adding a list of task items.
We'll start by creating a data model
for our list of tasks.
The ListItem struct
will be Identifiable and Hashable,
and we'll give it a description
to display.
Then, create a simple model to store
our data
and publish the array of list items.
And finally, add the model
as an environment object
so our views can access our model.
Now let's create a List in SwiftUI
with our data model.
Since there are no tasks yet,
when we preview this,
we get an empty list.
We need to do something about that.
We should give people a way to add
some tasks to their list.
We'd like to add a Button
that people can tap
to add a new item to the list.
Text field link, new in watchOS 9,
lets you invoke text input options
from a button,
and offers several styling options
to make it feel right at home in your app.
You can create a TextFieldLink
with a simple string
or use a Label for a more custom button.
Modify the button's appearance
with view modifiers,
including foregroundColor,
foregroundStyle,
and buttonStyle.
We'll create an AddItemLink view
to encapsulate the styling and behavior
of the TextFieldLink
we're using in our app.
We'll use a custom label for the button,
and when someone enters text,
we'll add the new item to our list.
Now that we've decided
to use TextFieldLink
to add a button to add a new list item,
we need to think about where to put
the TextFieldLink.
When adding actions to lists
in Watch apps,
we have a couple of options.
Use a button, navigation link,
or TextFieldLink
at the end of the list
for primary actions in short lists.
Adding an action as an item
at the end of a list
is a good choice for a primary action
in a short list of items
like the list of cities in World Clock.
However,
if you anticipate a long list of items,
people will have to keep scrolling
to the end of the list
each time they want to do the action.
For commonly used actions
with longer lists, use a toolbar item.
To add a toolbar item,
add the toolbar modifier to the list,
and use your action view as the content.
This will add a single toolbar item
to the list
with automatic toolbar item placement.
While I'd like to think I'll always keep
my to-do list short,
I'm fairly sure that I won't.
So I'm going to put the text field links
in a toolbar item
to make it easy to access.
Let's take a moment to review
what we've accomplished.
We've created a model for our list items,
stored it as an environment object,
created a list to display the items,
and added a text field link
to add new items.
Creating an item with only a description
is simple, but it isn't very useful.
We're going to need
to mark the item as complete,
and we might want a way to set a priority
or add an estimate of the amount of work
for a task.
To do this, we'll add a detail view.
Before we do this, I want to review
the options for app navigation structure
in SwiftUI on Watch.
Hierarchical navigation is used for views
with a list-detail relationship.
Starting in watchOS 9,
use the SwiftUI NavigationStack
to create interfaces
with this type of navigation structure.
Page-based navigation is used for views
with a flat structure,
where all of the views are peers.
A great example of page-based navigation
is the in-workout view of the Workout app,
where people can easily swipe
between the workout controls, metrics,
and playback controls
during a workout.
A full-screen app has a single view
that uses the entire display.
This is generally used for apps like games
and other apps
that have a single main view.
For a full-screen view,
use the ignoresSafeArea modifier
to extend your content
to the edges of the display,
and the toolbar modifier
with a visibility value of hidden
to hide the navigation bar.
A modal sheet is a full-screen view
that slides over the current view.
It should be used for important tasks
that should be completed
as part of the current workflow.
It's important to differentiate
when to use a hierarchical flow
versus when to use a modal sheet.
Mail uses a hierarchical style
to display the list of messages
and show each message or thread
as a detail view.
There are actions you can do
from the message detail,
but there is nothing you must do
before returning to the list.
If you go back to the list,
and tap New Message,
Mail uses a modal sheet to show
the New Message view.
A modal sheet is the right choice
because you need to fill in the details
of the new message, or cancel,
before continuing.
To display a modal sheet,
create a property to control
the sheet presentation state.
Set the property based on an action in
the user interface,
and use the sheet modifier
to display the custom modal sheet content
when the presentation state property
is true.
To add custom toolbar items
to the modal sheet,
add a toolbar with your items.
Note that your toolbar items should use
modal placements
like confirmationAction,
cancellationAction,
and destructiveAction.
We're going to use the modal sheet
for our detail view
because we're editing an item
and we want to focus on this single task
until we've finished and tapped Done.
To learn more about navigation in SwiftUI,
including more details
about NavigationStack
and programmatic navigation,
check out "The SwiftUI cookbook
for navigation."
Now that we've decided how to navigate
to our detail view,
we'll update our list item struct.
We have new properties to store
estimated work,
creation date, and completion date.
Let's give people a way to view and edit
these details.
We'll create a detail view
with a TextField to edit the description
and a toggle to mark the task as complete
or not.
But what should we do
with the estimated work?
We know the values will all be numbers,
and we can specify a range
of valid values.
Beginning in watchOS 9,
we can use the Stepper.
The Stepper is a great option
when you want to provide granular control
to edit sequential values.
You can specify a range
of values and optionally provide a step.
You can also use the Stepper to edit
logically sequential,
but not necessarily numeric values.
For example, maybe we want to note
the estimated stress level for an item.
We could create an array of emoji
to indicate the stress level,
then create a Stepper,
binding the value to the selected index
in the stress level emoji array
and setting the range to the range
of emoji indices.
Stepping through the values
increases or decreases
the stress level we're estimating
for the item.
Preparing a WWDC session is fun,
but sharing great Watch app development
with all of you is a party.
When I have stressful items on my list,
or just a lot of items on my list
that are making me feel stressed,
I'd like to share an item from my list
with a friend
to ask for help.
We're going to add a button
to our detail view
to allow people to share an item
using the share sheet.
I want to be able to tap a button
on my detail view
to share the item,
pick from a list of friends
to ask for help,
edit my message, and send it.
To do this, we're going to use a new tool
available to us in SwiftUI on watchOS 9:
ShareLink.
We can share our list item by creating
a ShareLink with our item.
We can optionally customize
the initial text of the message
with a subject and message.
And provide a Preview
to display in the Share Sheet
when someone shares the item.
You can use ShareLink to share
from your SwiftUI app
in iOS, macOS, and watchOS.
Be sure to check out "Meet Transferable"
to learn more details and options
for ShareLink.
Now that I can track when I completed
items
and call for help to get things done,
I'd also like to add a chart
to see my productivity.
I've chosen to use a bar chart
because I have a single data series
and distinct data values.
A bar chart will clearly show
this data on a Watch display
as long as I limit the amount of data
I display at one time.
We're going to start by adding
the chart view
to our app's navigation structure.
I've chosen
a page-based navigation strategy
because there is
no list-detail relationship
between the item list and the chart.
Someone can swipe between the list
and the chart at any time.
To add the page-based navigation
for our list and chart,
let's start by creating an ItemList struct
to encapsulate the list view.
I moved the entire content
of the content view
to this new item list.
Encapsulating the item list here
will allow us
to have simple, easy-to-read tab view code
in the content view.
We also need to create a struct
for our chart view.
I'll temporarily put in a placeholder
so we can focus
on our navigation structure
before we build our chart.
Now we'll set up a content view
with a page-style tab view with 2 tabs:
the item list and the chart.
Since we've set up
our navigation structure,
let's talk about how to build this chart.
I know I could use a SwiftUI Canvas
and draw a chart,
but starting in watchOS 9,
we have an easier answer: Swift Charts.
Swift Charts are also available on iOS,
macOS, and tvOS,
so you can reuse your charts anywhere
you're using SwiftUI.
We'll aggregate the data we want to chart
and then let Swift Charts display it
for us.
For our chart, we want to show the number
of items completed by date.
We'll create a struct
to store the aggregate data for the chart.
Then we'll write a small method
to aggregate our list item data
into chart data elements.
Display a simple chart by specifying
the data to display
and defining the series from the data.
We're using the date as the x-value
and the number of items completed
as the y-value.
To achieve the appearance I want
on my Watch display,
I'm customizing the x-axis
using the Chart's chartXAxis modifier.
I'm specifying a format style
for the axis value labels.
I also don't want vertical gridlines,
so I omitted an AxisGridLine mark.
I'm also customizing the y-axis using
the chartYAxis modifier.
I specify a gridline style that looks
good with my chart on Watch.
I'm formatting the axis value labels
as integers
and omitting the top label
to prevent it from being clipped
at the top of the chart.
To learn more about the amazing things
you can achieve with Swift Charts,
check out "Hello Swift Charts"
and "Swift Charts: Raise the bar."
Our chart looks pretty good,
but I'd like to show a little more data
but still keep a great Watch experience,
so I'm going to make it scrollable.
To accomplish this, we're going to use
a new digitalCrownRotation modifier
that allows us to set a callback
for digital crown events,
and we're going to implement
a custom scrolling behavior for our chart.
Let's get ready to add
the digitalCrownRotation modifier
by adding some properties to store
the state
as someone scrolls across the chart.
The highlightedDateIndex
is the index of the data point
for the current scroll position.
We'll store the crown offset
so we can display
the current crown position
as the person is scrolling
across the chart.
This is an intermediate value,
on or between data points,
while the crown is moving.
To keep track of whether
someone is actively scrolling,
we'll store the the idle state.
We'll use this information
to add a little animation
as crown scrolling stops and starts.
Now that we have the properties
to store values,
we can add
the digitalCrownRotation modifier.
We'll bind the detent value
to the highlightedDateIndex property.
In mechanical terms,
a detent is a mechanism
that holds something in a position
until enough force is applied to move it.
For instance, when I open my car door,
there is a "stop" position
where the door will settle.
I can push a little harder
and open the door wider to another "stop."
To close it, I need to pull hard enough
to overcome the resistance
to pull it out of the "stop."
Otherwise, it will spring back
into that resting position.
This is a detent.
The stop for the car door
helps us understand detent in this API.
The detent is the resting notch position
of the crown on your view.
In the handler for the onChange callback,
we'll set the value for isCrownIdle
to false,
since we know that the crown is scrolling,
and we'll set the crownOffset value
to the current value
to let us show the current position
on the chart during scrolling.
In the handler for the onIdle callback,
we'll set the value for isCrownIdle
to true.
Now we can display the position
of the crown
as we scroll on the chart.
To do this, we can use
the RuleMark from Swift Charts.
A RuleMark is
a straight line on your chart.
You can use it to display
a horizontal or vertical line,
to display a threshold, for example,
or to display a sloped line.
We're going to create a RuleMark
with the crown offset date value
to display the current location
of crown scrolling.
Just to make this look a little better,
I'd like to have
the crown position line fade
when the crown stops moving.
It's simple to animate this
using the isCrownIdle property we added.
We'll add a property to store the opacity
for the color we're using
in the foregroundStyle for the RuleMark.
And add an onChange modifier to the chart
to animate
the crownPositionOpacity value change
when the isCrownIdle value changes.
Then update the foregroundStyle
for the RuleMark to use the opacity.
To display the value next to the bar
on the chart as we scroll,
we can add an annotation to the BarMark.
We'll position the annotation
on the top leading side of the bar
when it's the last bar.
Otherwise, we'll position it
on the top trailing side.
Let's take a moment to see
what we've accomplished
with just
the digitalCrownRotation modifier,
the RuleMark in Swift Charts,
and a simple SwiftUI animation.
The final step to creating
our custom scrollable chart
is adjusting the data range for the chart
as someone scrolls.
Create a property to store
the visible range.
Create the chartData variable to provide
the data in the range to the chart.
When the highlightedDateIndex changes,
call a method to check the chartDataRange
and update it if necessary.
As someone scrolls across the chart using
the Digital Crown,
the chart will scroll to display
the available data.
Now we've finished implementing
all the features we had planned.
To learn more
about the new SwiftUI features
available in watchOS 9,
check out "What's New in SwiftUI."
As you're planning your Watch app,
or your new Watch app features,
think about what makes
a great Watch app experience.
While you're designing your app,
consider your app navigation strategy
to ensure that your app is easy
and intuitive.
And use SwiftUI for simpler
and richer development options.
Keep building great Watch apps.
And remember,
because of you, there's an app for that!
[spacey music]