♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Mindy
and I'm an engineer
on the Photos team.
Today, I'll be going over
how to access
Photos change history
in your apps.
PhotoKit provides
a rich set of APIs
for accessing and updating
photos, videos, and albums
stored in the photo library.
PhotoKit is designed for apps
that require a deep level
of Photos access
and integration
for managing or editing photos,
custom cameras,
or apps that give people a way
to browse their photo library
in a unique way.
These types of applications
may want to monitor
how the photo library
changes over time
to closely mirror
the Photos experience.
Let's say I've created
a social hiking app
that allows people
to share and edit photos
of hiking trips with friends.
When someone launches the app,
the app gathers photos
from the start and end timestamp
of their latest hiking workout
to generate a collage
of their experience
on the mountain.
The collages stay in sync
with the selected photos
from the photo library.
If someone receives
hiking photos
from a friend,
for instance,
the app will generate new
collages using these updates.
Up until now,
in order for the app
to discover
newly inserted assets
and changes to previous
hiking collages,
the app would need to perform
a series of fetches.
To determine which assets
were inserted,
the app can fetch assets
with a date created later than
the last app launch date.
Determining asset updates
and deletions is trickier.
The app would need to refetch
every asset in every collage
and check
the modification date
to determine asset updates,
but this could bring up
false positives,
as the asset modification date
can be set by internal
Photos processing activities.
Deletions in the photo library
are more difficult to track,
as all tracked assets
need to be fetched and diffed
for assets that were not
returned with the fetch.
In total, this means that
there are three separate checks
that need to be done
each time the app is launched,
which can be especially costly
if the app is displaying
large quantities of assets.
Instead of performing different
fetches and checks
for uncertain results,
what if there was a way
to know exactly what changed
in one unified API call?
Well, I'm excited to say
that we've done just that!
The new change history API
allows for an easier way
to track offline updates
to the photo library.
Change history consists
of a timeline of changes
such as insertions, updates,
and deletions
to the photo library.
In this example timeline,
there are a variety of asset,
album, and folder changes
in the change history
from the past three days.
Using this timeline,
how can you determine
which changes have happened
in the last two days,
or the last time
you launched your app?
You can now use
a persistent change token
that represents
the state of the photo library
at a given point in time.
This token can be persisted
across app launches,
and it can be used to fetch
changes to the photo library
that have occurred
since that token,
including third-party app
changes.
Note that if your app
is in limited library mode,
only changes for user-selected
PhotoKit objects
will be returned.
This change token
is local to the device
and is cheap to access
from a persistent change
or photo library instance
at any time.
This new API is available
on every platform
that supports PhotoKit:
macOS, iOS, iPadOS, and tvOS.
As your app is running and
working with the photo library,
you can store a persistent
change token within the app.
Later, you can use the token to
fetch the photo library changes
that have occurred since.
For each persistent change,
you can grab
the change details
for three types
of Photos objects:
asset, asset collection,
and collection list.
So what does this look like
in code?
You first use the last stored
change token
to fetch the persistent changes.
Next, you enumerate
through the persistent changes
and grab the change details --
in this case, of type "asset" --
for each persistent change
object.
These change details
provide information
on which local identifiers
were updated, deleted,
and inserted
into the photo library
since the change token.
After processing these changes,
you can store the last
change token for future use.
Let's compare and contrast
the new persistent history API
with the existing
change observer APIs.
PHChanges deal with active,
in-memory fetch results
and are used to record live
changes to the photo library
while your app is running.
Persistent history,
on the other hand,
records long-running changes
to the photo library,
and can be used
to report changes
from when your app
is not active.
You can use both
or either of these APIs
depending on the requirements
of your app.
Going back to the hiking app
example,
I'd like to now use
the persistent history API
to track asset changes
in order to create
and update hiking collages.
First, I'll use the last
stored change token
and fetch
the persistent changes.
Next, I'll iterate through
the persistent changes,
grab the relevant
asset change details,
and process the inserted,
updated,
and deleted identifiers.
Now I need to identify
library changes
that affect the app
from the change history,
as the app doesn't need
all of the information
returned from fetching changes.
It's important for the app
to know which assets
were added to the photo library
for new hiking workouts,
and updated and deleted assets
referenced in previous
hiking collages.
I've already identified
the three sets
of inserted, updated, and
deleted asset local identifiers
from enumerating through
the persistent changes.
How do I now update the app
to reflect this?
Using the insertedIdentifiers
set,
I can determine which assets
were added
between hiking timestamps
by fetching the inserted assets
and checking
their creation dates
against each hike
start and end date.
The updated assets may now
have adjustments applied,
so I can use the new
hasAdjustments API
to check if I need to redraw
the asset in the UI.
I can use the deleted asset
local identifiers
to determine which collages
need to be regenerated.
Now I've handled all of the
offline photo library changes
and my app is up to date.
Here are a few things
you should keep in mind
when using the new
change history API.
First, determine what changes
are important to you
and your app, and only check
for those changes.
Consider performing
one large fetch request
of updated and inserted assets
instead of multiple smaller
requests to improve performance.
Photo libraries can change a lot
due to processing
and sync activity
under the hood,
so you may end up
enumerating through
a large amount of changes,
especially if your app
is not frequently launched.
Because of this,
we recommend
that you ask for change history
on a background thread
to not block the UI.
There are two types of errors
that can occur
when fetching
persistent history.
If the change token
is older than the available
history of changes,
the expired change token error
will be returned.
In some cases,
the persistent change
cannot be relied upon
to completely reconstruct
the changes that occurred,
and will return an error that
change details are unavailable.
In these instances,
we recommend
refetching tracked objects
in the photo library
to ensure your app
is up to date.
Before we wrap up,
there are a few more
new PhotoKit APIs
I'd like to share with you.
PhotoKit now supports
accessing cinematic videos
by media subtype
and smart album.
There are also
two new error codes.
If the photo library bundle
is in a File Provider
sync root directory on macOS,
the library can become
corrupted,
and an error will be returned
when trying to perform changes.
If an asset resource
cannot be found
due to network issues,
the resource request
will now return a network error.
Please check
the developer documentation
for all of the latest updates.
Lastly, be sure to check out
this year's session
on the Photos picker,
as it is the easiest way
to work with and access Photos.
We're so excited for you to use
the new change history API
and all of the great new
features in PhotoKit.
Thank you!
♪