♪ ♪
Adam: Hi, my name's Adam
and I'm an engineer on the SharePlay team.
I'm excited to talk to you
about what's new in SharePlay
and how you can adopt it in your app.
To start, we'll talk about some new APIs
for starting SharePlay from your app.
Next, we'll get into some exciting
GroupSessionMessenger updates.
Finally, some best practices around
implementing a SharePlay experience.
Starting SharePlay from your app.
We heard your feedback and we delivered,
As of iOS 15.4 you can now leverage new
API to allow your app to start SharePlay
without an existing FaceTime call.
So let's see what that looks like.
So now all we have to do
is find our favorite SharePlay app.
Let's say the Music app.
And we'll find a song that
we want to SharePlay,
like Viral Hits,
and press and hold it.
Now in the contextual menu,
you'll see that we now have
a new SharePlay button.
So I'll go ahead and press that,
and it brings up the people picker.
So we can select Sue
and start a FaceTime call.
And, as you can see,
we now have a pill here
with the staged activity.
So if Sue joins,
we can go ahead and start,
and we'll have group session.
Well, I thought that was all pretty cool,
but let's break that down
into some more detail.
Here we have the ability for users
to start SharePlay from share sheet,
and you may be wondering
what you need to do for this to work.
Well, the answer is that
if your app is entitled for SharePlay
then you get this button for free
with our zero adoption flow,
but this isn't the optimal user experience
since the user won't be able to start
the GroupActivity through system UI
and will, instead,
need to re-interact with your app
to pick the content to SharePlay.
So let's see how you'd adopt
our new APIs for your app.
The answer is, it's as simple as
registering your GroupActivity
on NSItemProvider
and then providing the ItemProvider
to the share sheet.
Want to still offer the SharePlay button
but not display it as prominently?
No problem.
You can tune the behavior
with allowsProminentActivity
on the UIActivityViewController.
Just set allowsProminentActivity
to false.
Or what if you have a piece of content in
your app that doesn't support SharePlay?
Well, while we'd love for everything
to support SharePlay,
you can make SharePlay not show up
in the share sheet
by telling UIActivityViewController
to exclude the SharePlay activity type.
And if you want to place a button
directly within your app,
then you can use our new API
GroupActivitySharingController
to create our UIViewController
and then, just present it!
Once someone
presses your in-app experience
and starts a FaceTime
or SharePlay session,
they'll then be presented with the ability
to activate the staged GroupActivity.
Once activated,
your app will receive the GroupSession.
And don't worry if you're saying
to yourself "Wait, Adam,
did you just say 'Staged GroupActivity'?"
Why, yes. Yes, I did!
But let's hold onto that thought
and dive deeper into that later
when we're talking about best practices.
For now, let's see how we can adopt this
in our DrawTogether app.
This is our DrawTogether app.
It's the same app
from our previous WWDC talk from 2021
"Build custom experiences
with Group Activities,"
so if you haven't seen it already,
I highly recommend checking it out.
Now that you've gone ahead and seen that,
you'll remember there weren't
any share buttons in our app,
but we did have a SharePlay button
when you were eligible for
a GroupSession.
Let's go ahead and modify that behavior
so that even when
isEligibleForGroupSession is false,
we show the button and, now, allow
the user to start a SharePlay session.
And now we can go ahead
and see it in action.
Let's go ahead
and go to our ControlBar code.
Now, as you can see here,
we have an ‘if’ statement
that makes sure
that we don't have a group session
and that we're eligible
for a group session.
So let's go ahead
and remove the latter statement,
and move it down here.
And now what we have to do
is register a new variable
so that we know when to present
our GroupActivity sharing controller.
So we'll have a new variable up here,
and now let's handle when that variable
changes to true.
And we have to have a wrapper now
so we can present the GroupActivity
sharing controller in SwiftUI.
And now, finally, all we have to do
is have an 'else' statement
to set isSharingControllerPresented
to true
if we're not eligible for a GroupSession.
And now we can see our code in action.
So we'll go ahead
and go to the DrawTogether app.,
and you can see,
we have our SharePlay button.
So we can now press it,
and we're given the people picker.
And now we've got a great experience
for starting SharePlay from your app.
But that's not the only update we made.
So now let's talk about some of the
GroupSessionMessenger updates we've made.
We've got two exciting new updates
in our GroupSessionMessenger.
For the first update,
you may have run into this magical number.
It's the payload size you're able to send
over the GroupSessionMessenger.
Well, not anymore.
We've now made it so that the payload size
is four times larger at 256KB.
With this change,
your app doesn't need to worry
about breaking up your message
into smaller messages.
You can simply send your message
and focus on building a great experience.
And if that didn't excite you enough,
then I'm sure our next update will.
Unreliable messaging.
As part of the GroupSessionMessenger,
you can now choose
your messages' reliability.
This allows you to choose
between reliable or unreliable messaging
depending on your desired experience.
All we have to do
is leverage the new initializer
on GroupSessionMessenger
that allows us to specify
the MessageReliability.
Now that we understand how to use the API,
what about the experience?
When would we want to use
unreliable messaging?
Well, that's a great question
People are performing real-time actions
on FaceTime and SharePlay.
So let's imagine that we have
three people in a session.
Amy, Brian, and Chris.
They're all joined into a session
and synced
so as time progresses so does our movie.
But what happens
if Amy wants to do something
relevant to the specific time
that they're at in that moment?
Well, if you use reliable messaging,
then we guarantee that messages
will be received on all the devices,
but that doesn't mean
that they'll be received
at the time that they're expecting it.
For example,
Chris received the message,
but Brian has the message dropped
the first time
and receives it properly after that.
But remember, the movie is still playing.
So now we get to where Amy intended
the message to be reflected
and Brian doesn't have it.
He receives it later,
but at that point, it's too late.
Well, this is a perfect case
for unreliable networking.
It allows you, the developer,
to know what information
needs to be reliably received
on the other side
and what information doesn't.
This is an important concept to understand
when designing protocols
that have the user experience
deeply affected by latency.
Unreliable messages are using UDP
and have less latency and overhead
with each message involved
and, as a result of that,
you'll have a more real-time experience
when sending messages through them.
So now let's talk about how we're going
to use this for our DrawTogether app
You may remember this screen
from WWDC '21,
especially with my beautifully drawn
smiley face.
Let's dive a bit into what happens
when you're drawing
your smiley face on the screen.
In our app we have some code
that listens to a GestureRecognizer
and then we sent messages
each time we noticed a change.
This meant that as we were drawing
our smiley face,
we were constantly sending new messages
for each point
our GestureRecognizer gives us.
That's a lot of messages!
Well, we can now change our protocol
to use unreliable messaging
to make a more seamless
drawing experience.
What we'll do here is make it so that
each time we receive an update
from our GestureRecognizer,
we'll send our newly added point
using unreliable messaging.
Once the gesture is complete,
we'll then use reliable messaging
and give all of the points so a client can
catch up with any points that they missed.
This allows us to take advantage
of the lower latency
provided by unreliable messaging to have
a more immediate drawing experience.
So let's see how we would do this
in code.
So first let's go to our messages file.
And we'll go ahead and define
our new message type.
As you can see, this new message type
is pretty much the same as our old one,
but this time, will contain all
of the points for our stroke.
Now we'll go over to our canvas file.
And we need to set up a handler function
to handle the new message
that we're gonna get.
And let's go ahead and create
our unreliable messenger.
First, we'll create a variable.
And now, let's just initialize it.
Now we'll listen
for the finished stroke message.
And mark the previous message
as unreliable messenger as well.
But we need a way to send the message.
So we'll go up to finishedStroke.
And we'll go ahead and send
our new message type.
And let's change our old function
for sending all of the points
to use the unreliable messenger.
And now we can see our code in action.
So we go over to the DrawTogether app
and we can see how seamless it is.
And that's it!
And now, as promised,
let's talk about some best practices
for your SharePlay implementation.
You may remember this term from earlier:
Staged GroupActivity.
What does that term mean for your app?
Well, let's talk through a scenario.
Let's say that the device
on our left, "Adam",
starts SharePlay
with the device on our right, "Brian".
But Adam is trying to resume the show
they were watching.
So when someone activates
the staged GroupActivity,
we want to jump into that resumed show
at a specific time,
rather than starting over.
This poses a problem because
"Adam" knew we had 11 minutes remaining
in the show,
but Brian's device didn't.
This means that if Brian's device
activated the staged GroupActivity,
the show may start over.
So what can we do here?
It really depends on your app
and experience.
So let's walk through some ideas.
For the playback case,
we'll want to have each device
contribute its initial playback state
to the others in catch-up.
This means that since Adam's device
knew the playback state was 23 seconds,
when he joins the session,
he'll tell all the other devices
his intended playback state,
and they'll use that
as the source of truth.
This same principle applies to any
experience you create using SharePlay.
Each person that joins a session
should contribute
their understanding of the session
to the others.
This is because sessions are peer-to-peer
and ownerless.
So let's talk a bit more about that.
Ownerless sessions
are a hard concept to grasp,
but they're important when
designing a proper SharePlay experience.
In this case, Adam, on the left,
wants to hand off his session
to his Apple TV.
This results in his phone dropping off
the GroupSession and his TV joining.
But what happens
if we had ownership implemented?
Well, the owner dropped off, so...
And remember, this isn't just for TVs.
In iOS 16 we now have
FaceTime handoff.
So Adam goes ahead and hands off his iPad,
and well, same thing.
Boom
And that isn't all.
We just talked about some examples
of a user flow
where someone tries to move the session
from one device to another,
but there's other cases to think about.
Okay, don't worry, we'll keep it short
with just one more example.
This screen may seem a little familiar.
It's the FaceTime HUD.
But what happens
if we click the SharePlay button?
We're now presented with a button,
End SharePlay,
that allows you, you guessed it,
end SharePlay.
This allows you
to end SharePlay for everyone,
essentially the system calling .end()
on the GroupSession
on your application's behalf.
This means that no matter how careful
you are about not calling .end()
unless that device is the owner,
the system is still able to call .end()
on the GroupSession on your behalf.
So remember,
while it may be a hard concept to grasp,
making sure that your application
doesn't have a sense of ownership
means that it'll, overall,
result in a much better experience.
Now that you've listened
to the whole session,
go and adopt our new APIs for starting
SharePlay from within your app,
and explore ways for your app
to communicate
in new, low latency, ways
using unreliable messaging.
We love hearing from you all,
so please continue to file feedback
using the Feedback Assistant.
I hope you enjoyed
all the changes that we've made
and we look forward to seeing all
the amazing experiences that you build.
If you haven't already,
check out our other WWDC talk,
"Make a great SharePlay experience".
Or, if you're looking for
some amazing enhancements we've made
around media playback,
check out "Display ads
and other interstitials in SharePlay".
If you have any questions, please find us
at the GroupActivities labs
and challenges.
As always, thank you all for tuning in,
and have a great WWDC.
We can't wait to see what you build.