♪ ♪
Jake: Hi, my name's Jake.
I'm an engineer on the AVKit team,
and welcome to Creating
a Great Video Playback Experience.
In iOS and iPadOS 16,
we've built a completely new media player
from the ground up
bringing a whole new look and feel,
designed to keep the focus
on the content
and fit within a broader spectrum of apps.
We've also built in
many novel interaction models
that make using this new media player
feel even more intuitive and seamless,
and we think you're are gonna love it.
In this session, we'll take a deep dive
into the new system media player.
We'll learn how to design
amazing playback experiences.
We'll see some exciting new visual
intelligence features
coming to macOS and iOS.
I'll introduce
an all new interstitials experience
coming with the new media player
and go over some new APIs
we're bring over from tvOS.
And lastly,
we'll go over a new feature in AVKit:
selectable playback speeds.
For tvOS 15.0
we redesigned the system player,
bringing a whole new look and feel,
as well as a host of new features
and usability improvements
to the system player.
Well, we heard your requests.
I'm happy to say, we've revamped
the iOS system player as well.
We've completely redesigned
the native media player,
adopting the look and feel
of the tvOS player,
but reimagined for a touch first device.
We've removed the chrome
across the board,
allowing the interface to feel native
within broader spectrum of apps
and bringing a more modern feel
to the player.
Let's dig deeper into some
of the changes we've made.
First, we've brought the play/pause
and skip controls front and center
to make them even easier to interact with.
We've also adjusted the skip interval
from 15 seconds down to 10
making it easier to track how far
you've jumped with consecutive skips.
Next, we made some significant
improvements to the usability
of the timeline as well.
We're removing the slider knob
marking the timeline's current position.
Instead, the timeline can now
be interacted with
from anywhere along the slider.
Drags no longer needs to begin
at the current time marker.
This makes it even easier to find
exactly where you want to go.
We've also replaced
the video aspect control
with a more intuitive
pinch to zoom gesture,
which I'll show in a moment.
And of course, the new UI looks great
for portrait content as well.
On iPadOS, the player
integrates seamlessly into the system
with full support for keyboards,
trackpads,
mice, game controllers, and much more!
We also added a number of new ways
to interact with the controls
that make navigating the content
and some common interactions
even easier and more intuitive.
Let's take a look at these.
First, we've added a new way
to change the video's fill aspect.
You can now use a pinch gesture
to move through the available zoom levels.
Pinching in will bring the video within
the safe area of the display.
Pinching out will zoom the video
in to fully fill the display.
Next, we stream lined one of
the most common interactions,
play/pause.
You can now tap the center of the display,
even while the controls are hidden
to play and pause the video.
And lastly, we've added a new way
to navigate through the media timeline.
You can now scroll through the timeline
from anywhere over the video
using the same interactions
we all know and love in scroll views.
As you begin to scroll
through the video frames,
the interface drops away,
leaving only the most relevant UI,
allowing the focus to stay on the content.
We've also brought over some new features
from the tvOS player.
AVPlayerViewController now supports
displaying a content title,
subtitle, and description natively
from within the fullscreen UI.
You can provide strings for each of these
by passing AVMetadataItems
to an existing AVKit API.
Let's see how this is done.
By default, the title, subtitle,
and content description will be pulled
from the media's metadata.
However, the values in the media
can be overridden if needed
through the externalMetadata API
on AVPlayerItem.
A title can be added
by creating an AVMetadataItem
with the identifier commonIdentifierTitle
and adding it to the playerItems
externalMetadata property.
Titles should be short and descriptive
to avoid cluttering the UI.
Similarly, here we've added a subtitle
by creating an AVMetadataItem
with the identifier
.iTunesMetadataTrackSubtitle.
The subtitle will be displayed
above the content title
and should be a few words
describing the content.
Lastly, a description can be added
with the identifier
.commonIdentifierDescription.
This will display a chevron
to the right of the title and subtitle.
Selecting the title will display the info
panel containing the content description.
The description should be a few sentences
with more info about the content.
Tapping anywhere
will dismiss the info panel.
So to wrap up,
we've revamped the iOS system player
with an all new look and feel, with new
streamlined touch first interaction models
as well as a host of other improvements.
Using AVPlayerViewController in your app,
you'll have the full support
of the system player–
support for Picture in Picture,
SharePlay, Visual Analysis,
Native Catalyst Support,
New hardware and feature support,
and much, much more.
And of course, all of this
you get with just a few lines of code.
Now, let's talk about how you can design
amazing playback experiences in your apps.
When we set out to redesign
the system media player,
we took a step back
from what we had built in the past
and what we had built for other platforms
and we asked ourselves,
"What makes for a good user experience?"
We wanted to share this process with you;
how we've gone about designing
the new players,
why we designed them the way we did,
and what we think defines
an amazing media experience.
We think there are three things
that make a media experience great.
The experience should be intuitive.
It should feel easy, familiar, natural,
even if you've never used it.
It should be tightly integrated,
both within your app and with the system.
And lastly, it should be content forward.
At the end of the day,
people are there to experience the media
and your apps and designs
should reflect that.
Now let's dig deeper into these three,
starting with making your experience
intuitive.
Oftentimes, when an app feels intuitive
it can be hard to put your finger on why.
You just know it when you see it.
So what actually makes an interface
or an experience feel intuitive?
And how can you design for it?
We think it starts with familiarity.
When you can draw on your past experiences
to help understand something new,
that's intuitive.
When you don't need an explanation
of how it works
or even need to think about how it works–
it just works exactly as you expect.
Every one of us builds experiences daily
interacting technology and the real world.
Both of these are great sources
of experiential familiarity
and is often where we started when
designing the new system media players.
There are many types of experiences
to draw intuition from,
but I want to focus on two;
the two that we most often relied on
when designing the system media players.
Platform paradigms
and the real world.
The first comes from our experiences
using technology every day.
Years of using TV remotes tells you
that the arrow keys
move focus left and right.
Similarly, tapping a volume button on
a touch first device will mute the audio.
These interactions feel intuitive
because they're familiar.
You can use these types of familiar
interactions in your media experiences
to help make your apps feel
more intuitive,
engaging, and even natural to use.
Conversely, finding unfamiliar
or unexpected interactions
can be confusing
and sometimes even frustrating.
Let's look at some examples where we drew
on this type of platform familiarity
in the system players.
A great example of this
is the presentation and dismissal model
of the iOS system player.
The player animates its presentation
in from the bottom,
giving a subtle hit that the player
can be dismissed by pushing it back down.
We see this model used extensively
across our touch first devices.
For example, the now playing UI in Music
presents from the mini bar at the bottom
and can be dismissed
with an interactive swipe downwards.
In some cases though,
we may draw on experiences
not from our understanding of technology,
but from everyday life.
These types of experiences
come from the real world.
Millions of years of evolution
have helped us develop
a deep instinctual understanding
of natural processes.
You can tap in to this understanding
to help build familiar and intuitive
experiences in your software.
A great example of this is our new
scrolling gesture in the iOS player.
Similar to rolling a toy car
across a table,
each swipe over the video has momentum,
continuing the movement of the timeline
past the direct interaction
until the timeline slowly comes to a stop.
The momentum here alone
builds an association
with real world moving objects.
This association helps you discover
the subtle depths of the interaction.
Just like the toy car,
I can make it go faster
by pushing it harder,
or pushing it several times in a row.
And if I grab it, it stops.
It feels natural because it is natural.
And the best part about this is,
if you use the system players,
your app will feel intuitive.
All the natural interactions
we've built and inherit intuition
and familiarity people have
with the system player,
all of the design paradigms
optimized in a way
that tvOS, iOS, and macOS users
will understand natively–
all of this you get
with just a few lines of code.
Building an intuitive design is one aspect
of making your media experience great,
but without all the features
and integration points people expect,
your app can inadvertently pull focus
away from the content.
This leads us to the second crucial aspect
of an amazing media experience–
tight integration.
When an experience is tightly integrated,
all the functionality,
features, and devices
people expect to work just work.
And importantly, they work in a way
that's consistent with their expectations.
As people use their devices,
they become accustomed
to relying on the features
of the platform.
For example,
pulling down the Control Center
and seeing your content populated
in the Now Playing media controls,
or responding to a notification
while watching a TV show,
and having the video continue smoothly
into Picture in Picture.
Building this tight system integration
into your app
is key to making your experience
feel seamless.
Your app should feel like
a native part of the system
and we work hard to provide you with
the tools needed to make that possible.
This includes things like
CoreSpotlight integration
to make your content searchable,
Now Playing info so your content
can appear in the system media UIs,
MediaRemote commands allowing your app
to respond to things like
the play button being pressed
on a keyboard or TV remote.
We even provide the ability to integrate
your media directly into the TV app,
delivering your content
to an even wider audience.
In addition to making your apps
feel native,
it's important to provide
all the features that people love.
Features like AirPlay, SharePlay,
and Picture in Picture.
We think people will expect these features
and providing them
enhances the experience in using your app.
People will use your app
across many devices
and even more input formats.
Providing support for all these is crucial
in ensuring your experience
is accessible to everyone.
This is particularly important on tvOS,
where supporting all available remotes
is critical
to ensuring everyone can use your app.
This is one reason we always recommend
using the system media player on tvOS.
Your apps should ensure a fluid experience
with all TV remotes, keyboards,
trackpads, game controllers,
and headphone controls.
Additionally,
you should ensure your app's UI elements
are drawn within the screen's safe area
to avoid collision with rounded corners
or notches in the display.
We recognize building support
for all of these integration points,
features, and hardware configurations
can be daunting.
This is why we built
AVPlayerViewController,
so with just a few lines of code,
anyone using your app
can have an amazing media experience.
And all of this leads us, lastly,
to the most important aspect in designing
a media experience;
making it content forward.
This should be the primary goal
in your design,
and is what we considering the defining
aspect of a great media experience.
When your app feels intuitive,
when all of the integration points
and all features people expect
just work,
you bring your content into focus,
and everything else
fades into the background.
There are a few things
you should keep in mind, though,
specific to designing your content.
Make sure you provide
all of the appropriate metadata,
both in your interface and to the system.
Providing this info helps give context
to your media
and allows the system to provide
better experiences
in Control Center and the Lock Screen.
This includes things like
a title and subtitle,
a description, thumbnail,
season and episode information,
or start and end dates for live streams.
Always keep your media
in its original aspect ratio.
This allows the system
to position your videos on screen
in the correct location.
Letter boxing your content
can lead to experiences like this
or this.
Make sure to include support for
the latest media standards where possible.
For example, HDR and Dolby Atmos.
And lastly, make sure to include
audio and subtitle tracks
for multiple languages
so your media is accessible
to as many people as possible.
If there is one thing to take away
from this section of the talk,
it's that you should keep the focus
on your content.
We've built the system media players,
provided through AVPlayerViewController,
to make that goal as easy as possible
for you as a developer.
Now, let's go over some new features
we've added to AVPlayerViewController,
starting with the new
visual intelligence features.
In this example, we have a video paused
on a frame with a code snippet in it.
Long pressing the code snippet
will select it.
You can then copy and paste it
directly into playgrounds to try it out.
This works great for macOS as well.
Hovering your cursor over
the same code will show the I-beam
indicating the text is selectable.
You can then use your cursor
to highlight it
or use CMD+A to Select All.
We're introducing a new API
to go along with this functionality.
Available in AVPlayerViewController
on iOS and AVPlayerView on macOS,
allowsVideoFrameAnalysis
will toggle this feature.
This will be enabled by for all apps
linking against the new SDKs.
While allowsVideoFrameAnalysis
is set to true,
and once the media is paused,
AVKit will begin analyzing the current
video frame after a set period.
Note that we will not analyze frames
while scrolling,
for performance reasons,
or for FairPlay protected content.
In general, we think people will expect
this functionality in most situations.
However, there are some instances
where you may want to disable
visual analysis
as is appropriate in your application.
For example, in performance critical
applications,
such as a collection view of videos,
or in cases where interaction
with the video is not expected,
like splash screens.
For more info on how to integrate the
visual intelligence feature set
into your apps,
see our related talks on VisionKit.
Next, let's take a look some improvements
we made to interstitials.
Up until now,
interstitials were only supported
in AVPlayerViewController on tvOS.
Well, I'm happy to announce we're bringing
the same level of support to iOS as well.
Interstitials,
either in the stream or defined locally
through AVPlayerInterstitialEvents,
will now be marked along the timeline.
When the timeline hits a marker,
we'll begin playing the interstitial.
If your interstitials are already
fully defined within your HLS playlist,
you'll get this behavior automatically–
no adoption required.
If not, or if you app requires
some more custom behavior,
we're introducing some new API as well.
AVInterstitialTimeRange is being brought
over from tvOS to iOS.
These will be populated automatically
into the AVPlayerItem property,
interstitialTimeRanges,
which is also being brought over
from tvOS.
When using an HLS stream,
an AVInterstitialTimeRange
will be synthesized
for each interstitial in the stream.
When creating interstitial events locally
through the AVFoundation API,
an AVInterstitialTimeRange
will be synthesized
for each AVPlayerInterstitialEvent.
Unlike on tvOS however,
interstitialTimeRanges
is a read-only property.
Interstitials will either need to be
defined within the HLS stream
or through AVPlayerInterstitialEvents.
For those migrating
their support from their tvOS apps,
this is in essence equivalent to setting
translatesPlayerInterstitialEvents to yes.
We're also bringing over two
delegate methods from tvOS as well.
These can be used to know
when an interstitial has begun
or ended playback.
Let's see how we can use these to APIs
to add a skip button
for a pre-roll ad on iOS.
First, we'll create an
AVPlayerInterstitialEventController
for the primary media's player.
Next, we'll create an interstitial event.
We'll define some restrictions for it.
These restrictions prevent seeking
within the interstitial
and prevent skipping past
the interstitial.
Then we'll add the interstitial
to the event controller.
And lastly, we can implement the new
willPresentInterstitial delegate callback
to bring up an ad skip button
after a set interval.
And once the button is pressed,
we'll cancel the interstitial.
It's that easy.
Note that when adding any custom
UI elements to an AVPlayerViewController,
such as this ad skip button,
always make sure to add to them
as subviews
of the contentOverlayView.
To learn more about how
you can integrate your interstitials
right into your HLS playlists
or how you can use
the AVFoundation interstitials API,
check out our related talks on exploring
HLS dynamic pre-rolls and mid-rolls.
Now we'll go over a new feature we've
added this year across all our platforms;
native support for playback speed control.
Both AVPlayerView
and AVPlayerViewController
can now optionally show a playback speed
menu using some new API we've added.
We're making this available
on macOS, iOS, and tvOS.
Let's take a look at what this looks like.
On tvOS, you'll see a new control
in the transport bar.
Selecting the control will display
a list of the available playback speeds
to choose from.
On iOS, this menu will appear
in the transport control overflow menu.
And similarly, on macOS, the control
will appear in the overflow menu.
All apps linking against the new iOS,
macOS, and tvOS SDKs
will get this functionality automatically
with no additional changes required.
However, depending on your use case,
some applications may want to modify
the list of speeds,
programmatically select a speed,
or disable the menu entirely.
To accommodate these use cases,
we've added some new APIs
to AVPlayerView
and AVPlayerViewController.
Let's take a look at these.
First, we've added a new class in AVKit–
AVPlaybackSpeed.
AVPlaybackSpeeds represent
user selectable speed options
in a playback UI
and they have three properties.
A rate value, defined on initialized,
which will be set on the player
when the playback speed is selected.
A localized name,
used to represent the playback speed
within the accessibility system
For example,
a speed of 2.5 might use a localizedName
of "Two and a half times speeds."
And a localized numeric name.
This value is synthesized
from the rate property
and will be the String displayed
in the playback speed menu
If your app requires a custom
playback speed menu
external to the player,
use this string to represent the speed.
Lastly, AVPlaybackSpeed defines a list
of system default speeds
that should be used whenever possible.
You can use AVPlaybackSpeed in conjunction
with some new API on AVPlayerView
and AVPlayerViewController to adapt
this feature to fit within your app.
The speeds property allows defining
a custom list of playback speeds.
By default this property will be set
to the AVPlaybackSpeed
systemDefaultSpeeds list.
Setting this to an empty list
will hide the menu.
The selected speed property will return
the speed that's currently active.
And lastly, the selectSpeed function
allows programmatic selection
of the current speed.
Note that you should only
use this function
in response to explicit selection of
the speed outside of the player UI.
Never implicitly override
the chosen playback speed.
Let's take a look at an example.
Here we're creating
a AVPlayerViewController
and presenting it.
By default this will use the system
provided list of playback speeds.
You can add a new speed to the menu
by creating an AVPlaybackSpeed
and appending it to the list of speeds
in AVPlayerViewController.
We can also disable the menu
by setting an empty list of speeds.
It's as easy as that.
Note though, you should always call
AVPlayer play() to begin playback.
Never start playback
by calling setRate:1.0,
as the selected rate might not be 1.0.
And with that,
I'd like to wrap up the session.
We saw the new
redesigned iOS system player.
We heard how you can design
amazing playback experiences of your own.
We saw some cool
new visual intelligence features,
and went over our new interstitials
and playback speed APIs.
I hope you enjoyed the session
and look forward to seeing
these features in your apps.
Enjoy the rest of the conference.