♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
Hi there.
Welcome to this year's WWDC.
My name is Stella.
And I'm Alex.
Stella and I work together
on the many parts of USD at Apple.
Today we'll explore with you
updates to USD tools and rendering.
Take it away, Stella!
USD is a foundational technology
that, with the growing and deepening
integration into content creation tools,
is enabling more and more ways
of creating assets and content,
rendering for games, AR, film,
and the web,
all with USD at the center.
Today, we will focus on two parts
of the ecosystem: tools and rendering.
Let's start with updates to our USD tools.
We'll then show you how your assets
look even better
with new lighting in AR Quick Look,
take a deep dive into USD rendering,
and last but not least,
show you how to integrate Hydra.
Let's get started with USD Tools
in the Apple ecosystem.
We'll cover USDZ Tools,
Reality Converter,
and then follow up
with additional tools and frameworks
that can help you create USDZ content.
USDZ Tools is a package
that contains essential
command line USD Python tools
to help you generate,
validate, and inspect USDZ files.
The package also includes a converter
called usdzconvert
that creates USDZ files
from other major 3D file formats.
The Python scripts give you powerful tools
for automation and batch processing.
Also, they are a great way
for you to explore USD and learn
how to use the API.
This year, we're bringing you
Python 3 and Apple Silicon support.
We've also upgraded the USD version
to give you simple access
to new USD features
and performance improvements.
On top of that, we added
great new features to usdzconvert.
You can now convert OBJ files
with materials to USDZ
with the useObjMtl flag.
We also added support
for points and lines from GLTF files,
and scene time
for animations from FBX files.
To display all usdzconvert options
and ways to customize your conversion,
just type "usdzconvert --help"
on the terminal.
This will show you all the options
you can use with usdzconvert,
such as adding copyright information
or providing the diffuseColor
or normalMap for your 3D model,
and much more.
Alternatively, if you prefer a UI editor
for your workflow
over using the command line,
we also have Reality Converter,
which is built using the USDZ tools
and provides the same capabilities
as usdzconvert,
but in an editor window,
making it easy to convert, view,
and customize USD content on MacOS.
Simply import common 3D file formats,
such as OBJ, GLTF, and FBX,
to view the converted USDZ result.
This year, we've also improved the UI
to streamline your workflow.
You can select the texture to view
more information...
Customize material properties
with your own textures...
Add copyright or edit file metadata...
And choose classic or new lighting,
which we'll get into more details
later in the session.
You can even preview
your USDZ object
under a variety of lighting conditions
with built-in options
and adjust exposure accordingly
On the asset side, we added a new feature
to let you choose texture quality
while exporting a USDZ file.
By default, the textures are exported
in their original, uncompressed size.
But, if you prefer to reduce the size
of your USDZ files, you now have
the option to compress textures
to the JPEG format.
In this example, we used object capture
to scan this chess piece
in high resolution.
In order to reduce the file size
without losing mesh detail,
we used RealityConverter to export
the model with compressed textures.
The visual difference
is hardly noticeable,
and we got a whopping 80% reduction
in the resulting file size!
Here is more exciting news:
RealityConverter can now fix issues
with your USD assets automatically!
It will correct mismatched attributes
and connection types,
fix a stage with multiple top-level prims
and a missing default prim,
update deprecated attributes,
and add missing stage metadata.
We've also added universal binary support
so now it runs natively on Apple Silicon.
Now, what if you want to create
3D models from scratch?
Last year, we launched Object Capture
as a RealityKit API on macOS,
which provides an innovative way
to create USDZ assets.
You can then use Reality Composer
to compose a scene with multiple assets.
This year, we are bringing you
RoomPlan API,
which lets you create parametric 3D scans
of your room.
I highly recommend you
to check out these 3 sessions.
Together, these technologies make it
easier than ever
for anyone to create
immersive AR experiences.
All these tools we covered today
are available for you to download
right now
on our AR Creation Tools
page on the Apple developer website.
Please check them out!
Next, let's take a look+
at AR Quick Look's new lighting.
AR Quick Look is the built-in,
system-wide AR viewer on iOS
which enables you to place 3D USDZ objects
in your physical space,
like on a table, a wall, or a floor,
and interact with them
with simple touch gestures.
You can even make interactive scenes
built with Reality Composer
and save them to a USDZ file
which you can share with others
on iMessage, Mail, Notes, and more.
We constantly strive to make AR Quick Look
rendering more realistic, and this year,
we are introducing improved lighting
in AR Quick Look,
which is brighter, with enhanced contrast
and improved shape definition
to make your assets look even better.
Here is an example of AirPods Pro
in object mode
with classic and new lighting.
The AirPods Pro look great
in both lighting conditions,
and you will notice
the new lighting option
offers brighter color,
higher contrast, and more highlights.
Now let's place the AirPods Max
on the desk to view it in AR mode
with new lighting!
Stunning, isn't it?
So how do you apply
the new lighting to your assets?
It's really simple.
You just have to pick the lighting
that works best for your content
by setting the new preferredIblVersion
metadata in your USDZ file.
Here we have set the value
of the preferredIblVersion to 2,
which will indicate AR Quick Look
to use the new lighting system.
Let's understand this in more detail.
The preferredIBLVersion metadata
can hold values of 0,1, and 2.
An asset with preferredIblVersion set to 0
will use the system default lighting.
If set to 1, it will continue
to use the classic lighting.
A value of 2
will give you the new lighting.
This means you can easily update
your current assets to the new lighting
as well!
We recommend that you make
an explicit choice and set this metadata
in all of your assets.
To do that, you can either use
usdzconvert
with the flag preferrediblversion.
For example,
here is how to use the flag to convert
the fire hydrant OBJ file
to USDZ with the new lighting.
Or you can use Reality Converter,
which will now use
the new lighting by default.
But if you want
to use the classic lighting,
there is a new option
in the Property Panel.
Here we preview the AirPods Max asset
with both the classic and new lighting.
This provides an easy way
to compare the differences.
By clicking the lighting icon,
the applied lighting
will also be highlighted
for your reference.
Lastly, for assets without this metadata,
AR Quick Look will determine
the lighting version automatically
based on the file's date-time stamp.
If the asset was created after July 1st,
2022, it will use the new lighting.
Older assets will continue
to use the classic lighting
so they don't change how they look.
Now, I'll hand it over to Alex
for USD rendering.
Thanks, Stella.
We've already seen a lot
of rendered USD assets today.
Now we'll explore what makes USD rendering
and Hydra a great choice
for your 3D content creation pipeline
and how you can integrate it
in your own applications.
First, let's take a step back
and talk about rendering in general.
A renderer takes a collection
of 3D models, cameras, and lights as input
and uses them to generate an image.
There are many different renderers,
and each one of them
is built for a specific purpose
and optimized for a different use case.
Some renderers are designed
for real-time applications
like rendering a character
in a game or an AR scene.
Others take much longer but produce
a more photorealistic image,
for example, producing visual effects
for a Hollywood movie.
All renderers make choices
about their features and are unique.
Different USD renderers
for different use cases
also exist on Apple platforms.
We're adding documentation
about these different renderers
to developer.apple.com.
It will help you understand
the differences between them,
explain which USD features
they support,
and provide guidance on how to author USDs
that work best for you.
One of the renderers on Apple platforms
is RealityKit,
which features
a photorealistic rendering system,
optimized for interactive augmented
reality experiences,
and is used in AR Quick Look.
It is the primary renderer of USDZ files.
Another option for USD rendering on macOS
is Pixar's open-source renderer, Storm.
It is optimized
for production-grade assets
and designed for real-time preview
of large-scale scenes.
It's a great technology for you
to visualize and iterate on assets
as they flow
through your content creation pipeline.
Storm uses a technology called Hydra.
Hydra is a core aspect
of the USD open source project.
So next, let's understand Hydra
and its connection to Storm.
We start with this diagram from earlier.
Here, we use Storm as the renderer.
The input is usually called
"the scene graph,"
and Storm produces a preview render of it.
But what if you want to generate
a photorealistic image of the same scene
using a different renderer?
That's exactly what Hydra is made for.
Instead of tightly coupling
the scene to the renderer,
Hydra acts as an abstract layer
in between them
to transport data from scenes
to renderers.
This allows you to easily swap out
your renderer
based on your needs at any time
without any changes to your scene graph.
For example, you might use Storm
and Pixar's RenderMan.
In your content creation pipeline,
you can use Storm for fast renders
and quick iteration,
and then switch to RenderMan
to produce
the final image when you're ready.
The same goes for the scene graph.
Your input to Hydra can be
a USD scene graph or a different one.
This allows you to leverage
the same renderer in multiple applications
even if each one of them has their own,
totally different scene graph.
The interfaces which connect
Hydra with scene graphs and renderers
are called delegates.
Scene graphs are connected
to Hydra via Scene Delegates,
and Renderers are connected
to Hydra via Render Delegates.
And that is Hydra for you!
Foundry's Nuke 13 is already
using Hydra to render the viewport,
enabling Nuke artists on macOS
to have better quality
and an interactive experience
in Nuke's 3D system.
This is achieved by using
Hydra with a custom scene delegate
and Metal-accelerated Storm.
We are excited to share that
we've worked with Pixar Animation Studios
to publicly release Metal
accelerated Storm to open source.
It is ready for you to use in USD 22.05.
Now that we've seen the power of Hydra,
let's go through
a Hydra sample application
with the typical use case
of a USD scene graph
and Storm as renderer.
It will get you started with using Hydra
to build content creation tools
and 3D workflow applications.
Our sample application, HydraPlayer,
is very simple but powerful.
It renders a USD file with Storm
and lets us move the camera around it.
And we're excited to make HydraPlayer
a public sample project
to get you started right away!
It is available in the session resources
and comes
with full instructions in the readme.
I encourage you to pause this video now,
download the project, and then follow
along as we walk through it.
In your Xcode project,
you will find 4 classes:
The AppDelegate, Camera,
Renderer, and View Controller.
The AppDelegate is basically
your root object
and manages interactions with the system.
The camera class is
a simple representation
of the USD scene camera
to make it easy
to translate the user input.
The renderer class will handle
all our interactions with USD and Hydra.
Last but not least,
the ViewController handles our user input.
Before we can build and launch
HydraPlayer, there are three things to do:
prepare the environment, use Rosetta
on Apple Silicon Macs,
and download and build USD & Hydra.
So let's get started.
First, we prepare
our development environment.
Make sure you have Xcode,
Python, and CMake installed.
Now let's open up a terminal
for the other two steps.
If you are on an Apple Silicon Mac,
you need to run under Rosetta
while USD is transitioning
to fully support arm64.
To do this, use the arch command.
Once your environment is ready,
we have to download the USD
and Hydra source code.
Both live in the same GitHub repository
at PixarAnimationStudios/USD.
Now that we have the code,
we can build it.
USD comes
with a convenient Python build script.
We add the flags "generator Xcode"
and "no-python"
and specify
where we want to install USD to.
Let's put it next to the source code
at "USDInstall."
Once USD finished building,
we are ready to build HydraPlayer!
Let's go back to this diagram
one more time and use it to identify
key parts of HydraPlayer
to check out in detail.
We'll look at how to load the 3D models,
how to set up the camera,
and set the scene light.
Then we'll learn how to get
our scene graph to Storm
and finally, how to produce
an image for the application window.
So let's get started with loading
our 3D models from USD.
In viewDidAppear in our ViewController,
we create a file picker
with an NSOpenPanel
when the view appears the first time.
Once a file has been selected,
the renderer
can start setting up our scene
and load the USD file.
Loading the file is very simple
with the USD API.
We simply open
the USD stage at the file path.
That's it.
We have our file loaded.
Next, we set up our camera.
In our code, this is straightforward.
In setupCamera,
we first create a new scene camera.
Then we calculate the world size
and center based on our scene.
Next, move our camera at a good distance
and then focus on the center.
This way, our camera
captures the whole scene.
Great, now we have our camera set up.
Next, lighting.
We keep it easy and create
one simple ambient light
and set its position to match
the camera, and that's it.
And with that, we have our full scene
with 3D models, a camera and a light!
We can now pass our scene to Storm.
First, we need to initialize
our render engine.
Here, we create a new UsdImagingGLEngine,
which is the class name of Storm.
The most important parameter here
is the rootPath.
It points the engine to our USD stage
with our 3D models.
To learn more about the other parameters
and UsdImagingGLEngine,
please check out
Pixar's USD API documentation.
Next, we set our camera
in our engine
and set our lighting setup.
And last but not least,
we define how we want Storm to render
by setting render parameters.
For example,
we want to render a transparent background
so that the rendered image
works nicely with our app color scheme.
Important for scenes with animation,
this is also where we specify
the time code.
Now we're ready to render an image!
We've already done all the
necessary setup,
so the render command is
just one line of code.
We get the result and display it
in our window, and there we are!
We're rendering the USD toy plane!
And actually,
we're rendering not just one plane.
HydraPlayer can easily render
thousands of animated assets
with tens of millions of triangles.
If you haven't already,
check out the resources for this session,
download the sample project,
and have fun exploring it further.
Together we explored updates
to Apple's USD tools
that make them more powerful and make
your assets look even better.
We learned about Hydra's features
and went
through the HydraPlayer sample project
to see how you can integrate it
into your own applications.
To find out more
about important concepts of USD,
check out the session
"Understand USD fundamentals.
Thank you.
♪ ♪