♪ ♪
Ahmed Badr: Hello and welcome.
My name is Ahmed and I am part
of the Display and Color Technologies team
at Apple.
Today, I would like to talk about some of
the new features and enhancements we made
in the Advanced Video Quality Tool,
or short AVQT.
Let me start with a quick recap.
So what's AVQT?
AVQT is a command line executable
that we first released in WWDC 2021.
It's a full reference video quality metric
that assesses the quality of videos
with potential compression
and scaling artifacts.
It attempts to mimic
how people rate the quality of videos.
AVQT supports all AVFoundation-based
video formats, both SDR and HDR.
This includes HDR10, HLG,
and Dolby Vision.
There are three key attributes
that are unique to AVQT.
First, AVQT achieves high correlation
with how people rate videos.
This applies to all content types
such as animation, natural scenes,
and sports.
Second, AVQT comes with
impressive processing speeds,
thanks to AVFoundation and Metal
that AVQT relies on
for video decoding and processing.
Third, AVQT is designed to accommodate
different viewing setups.
The same video can result
in different experiences
depending on the viewing setup.
This can be configured
in AVQT through factors
such as display resolution,
display size, and viewing distance.
To learn more about AVQT,
please check our 2021 video
titled "Evaluate videos
with Advanced Video Quality Tool."
In the WWDC 2021 video
where AVQT was announced,
we presented the impressive
processing speeds it achieves on M1 Macs.
Since then, Apple processors
got more capable and AVQT got faster.
Here are the processing speeds
on the new family of M1 processors.
On M1 Ultra, AVQT evaluates a 2-hour,
HEVC-compressed 4K movie in 20 minutes.
This is six times faster than real time.
For a full HD movie
with a similar duration,
AVQT processes the video
in less than 11 minutes.
This is more than ten times faster
than real time.
You can now evaluate more videos
in the same amount of time.
Next, let me introduce
the new features and enhancements
that we added to AVQT this year.
You can now visualize
the quality of your video using AVQT
without any extra steps.
The latest version of AVQT produces
HTML-based reports
with interactive plots and diagrams
showing analysis of the quality
of your videos.
These reports can easily be generated
by adding the new ‘visualize’ flag.
You can easily identify
sections in your video
where quality did not meet
the expectation.
You can also share AVQT reports
with other colleagues.
They don't need to have AVQT
or any other tool installed.
They can just open the report in Safari.
So let me show you how to create
an interactive report
and how to use some of its features.
I will start by showing the help menu.
We added a new argument, ‘visualize,’
which you can use to create reports.
Here's an AVQT command that evaluates
the quality of a test video that I created
by compressing a segment
from last year's WWDC presentation.
You can then add the visualize argument
and it will also create a report.
Once it's done, you will see the location
of the HTML report file
printed to standard out.
This file can simply be opened in Safari.
The table on the left shows information
about the analyzed videos.
The one on the right includes
settings and parameters used
while evaluating the videos.
This figure shows both frame-level
and segment-level AVQT scores over time.
If you're interested
in a specific interval,
you can simply zoom in
to get more details.
Hovering over the plot will give you
more information about that point,
such as time,
AVQT score, and index of the frame
or segment that this score belongs to.
To zoom out to the home view, you can
double-click anywhere in the figure.
A pie chart is also included
that shows the distribution
of the AVQT frame scores
of the analyzed video.
It shows the percentage
and number of frames
in each of the five quality categories,
"Bad," "Poor," "Fair,"
"Good," and "Excellent".
The figures on the bottom
are similar to those on the top
except that they show PSNR scores.
We hope this feature will help
summarize the quality of your videos
as well as identify issues, if any.
Here's another feature that I am
excited to tell you about.
You can now specify the time windows
from your reference
and test videos to be evaluated.
This enables focusing on a specific scene
or multiple scenes in your video.
It also allows for comparing videos
that are not temporally aligned.
We added four new command-line
arguments to help you accurately specify
the beginning and end of the video
sections you are interested in analyzing.
Let me show you an example
of how to use the time window feature.
Here's the video
I evaluated in the previous demo.
This time, I am interested
in evaluating a single scene of the video.
Here's how I can accomplish this.
In Quicktime Player, I will start
by seeking to that scene.
It's this one.
Clicking here shows the frame index.
I will use the arrow keys
to get to the first frame in the scene.
It's 270.
I will repeat the same steps to find
the last frame in the scene.
It's frame 486.
Now, let's evaluate this scene in AVQT.
The first part of the command
is the same as before.
I will then add the start and end frame
indices I got from QuickTime Player
using these four newly-added
command line arguments.
I now have the AVQT score for this scene.
Running this command is faster
than processing the whole video
and then only looking
at the scores of that scene.
We believe this adds
to the flexibility of AVQT.
Speaking of flexibility,
we also extended the support
of raw YUV formats in this version.
AVQT supports
all AVFoundation video formats.
Besides that,
it also supports raw YUV videos.
This enables scoring videos
that were never compressed,
such as a raw camera feed.
It's also useful when evaluating
videos that are compressed
and decoded outside the ecosystem.
This year, we extended the support
for raw YUV to include a total
of 20 formats with a wide range
of chroma sub-samplings and bit depths.
It's worth noting that `reference-fourcc`
and `test-fourcc` flags
are now deprecated.
We replaced them
with two separate sets of flags,
one for chroma-subsampling
and another for bit-depth.
This feature will allow you
to evaluate more videos
without the need of pre-processing.
Since AVQT was
first released in WWDC 2021,
there has been
a growing interest in the tool.
We received
numerous comments and requests.
One of the most common requests
is to add support for Linux.
Today, we are glad to announce
that AVQT is now available on Linux.
We understand that this will allow people
to evaluate content stored in the cloud
or compressed in Linux-based servers
without the need to move the videos.
Together with the macOS version,
we are also releasing a beta version
of AVQT for Linux that supports
a wide range of Linux distributions.
It can be easily deployed as it doesn't
require any external dependencies.
It's essentially plug and play.
To learn more about the supported
Linux distributions and versions,
please refer to the README file
in the AVQT package.
The Linux version of AVQT is
designed to have the same look
and feel of the macOS version.
It uses the same naming
of the command line flags
and produces output files
of the same format.
The Linux version supports
all 20 raw formats that are included
in the latest version of the macOS tool.
The viewing conditions parameters are not
available in the Linux beta version
but will be enabled in the future.
To wrap up,
here are a few important takeaways.
AVQT is a perceptual video quality tool
that we released in WWDC 2021.
It's available for download
on the developers’ portal.
If you haven't tried the tool,
go ahead and use it.
This year,
we added several enhancements to AVQT.
You can now visualize AVQT scores
of your videos in an interactive
HTML-based report that you can
share with your colleagues.
You can also use the new
‘Time Window’ feature to focus
on the quality
of specific scenes in your video.
And finally, for those of you
who have videos in the cloud
or use Linux-based video encoders,
AVQT is now available on Linux.
Thank you very much.