♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Welcome to "Efficiency awaits:
Background Tasks in SwiftUI."
I'm John Gallagher, an engineer
on the watchOS Frameworks team.
In this talk, we'll learn
about a new SwiftUI API
for handling background tasks
using Swift Concurrency
and in a consistent way
across all of Apple's platforms.
We'll begin by describing
a sample app called Stormy,
an app for taking photos
of the sky on stormy days
which makes use
of background tasks.
Then, we'll dive into how
the app uses background tasks
and how background tasks work
under the hood.
Next, we'll learn how to handle
those background tasks
using a new API in SwiftUI.
And finally, we'll review how
the API uses Swift Concurrency
to make handling background
tasks easier than ever.
The new API is shared
across watchOS, iOS, tvOS,
Mac Catalyst, and Widgets,
including iOS apps
running on the Mac,
which means the concepts
and patterns you learn
handling background tasks
for one platform
can apply to work you do
on others.
Utilizing Swift Concurrency,
the new API reduces the need
for deeply nested completion
handlers and callbacks
as well as much of
the mutable state
which was frequently
a side effect.
Swift Concurrency's
native task cancellation
helps applications gracefully
complete tasks in a timely way
to avoid being quit
in the background by the system.
For people who like to keep
their head in the clouds,
we're going to build
an app called Stormy
that will remind users
to take photos of the sky
when it's stormy outside.
The app will show a notification
at noon on stormy days
requesting that the user
takes a picture of the sky.
When the user
taps the notification,
they'll take a photo of the sky
to upload to their profile
for future admiration.
We're going to upload
this photo in the background.
The app will send
another notification
when the upload has finished.
Let's dive in to how background
tasks can let us do this.
In this diagram,
we'll examine at a high level
how the notification
will only get sent
on stormy days
utilizing background tasks.
We'll represent foreground
application runtime
with the bar on the left,
background application runtime
with the bar in the middle,
and the system is represented
on the right.
When our app is first launched
to the foreground by the user,
we can take
our first opportunity
to schedule a background app
refresh task for noon.
Then, when the user leaves our
app and the app is suspended,
the system will know to wake
our application again
in the background
at the time we scheduled.
We scheduled our task for noon,
so that's when system will
wake the app in the background
and send a background app
refresh task.
With this background runtime,
we need to figure out
whether it is stormy outside,
and if it is,
send a notification to the user.
To start, we'll make a network
request to a weather service
to check the current weather.
With the URLSession
scheduled for background,
the application can suspend
and wait for the network request
to complete.
When the background
network request
for weather data completes,
our application will be given
background runtime again
with a new URLSession
background task.
With the results of the weather
data request in hand,
our application knows
whether it is stormy outside
and can choose
whether to send a notification
prompting the user
to take a photo of the sky.
Now that our work for
that URLSession task is done,
the system can once again
suspend the application.
Let's dive into the details
of a single background task
and see how it works.
To do that, we're going to take
a closer look at the lifecycle
of a single app refresh
background task.
Let's zoom in here a little bit.
First, the system
will wake our application
and send it an app refresh
background task.
Then, still in the background,
we make a network request
to check whether
it is stormy outside.
Ideally,
our network request completes
within the allotted background
runtime our application has
for app refresh.
When we get
the network response,
we'd like to post
the notification immediately.
With the notification posted,
we've completed everything we
needed to do during app refresh
and the system can suspend
the application again.
But what about when our
network request for weather data
doesn't complete in time?
If an app is running low
on background runtime
for the current task,
the system signals the app
that the time is running low,
giving us a chance to handle
this situation gracefully.
If applications do not signal
that they've completed
their background work
before runtime expires,
the application may be quit
by the system and throttled
for future
background task requests.
In this case, we should make
sure that our network request
is a background
network request,
which will allow us to complete
our app refresh task immediately
and get woken again
for additional
background runtime
when the network
request completes.
With our background
URLSession scheduled,
the system can suspend
the application again.
Now, let's dive into how the
BackgroundTask API in SwiftUI
can help us build Stormy.
To begin,
we'll need a basic application.
Then, we'll write a function to
schedule background app refresh
for noon tomorrow.
First, we create a date
representing noon tomorrow.
Then, we create
a background app refresh request
with an earliest begin date
of noon tomorrow
and submit it to the scheduler.
This is what tells the system
to wake our application
tomorrow at noon.
We'll want to call this function
when the user
first opens the application
and requests daily
storm notifications at noon.
We can register
a handler corresponding
to the background
task we scheduled
by using the new background task
scene modifier.
When the app receives
a background task,
any blocks registered
with this modifier
that match the background task
received are run.
In this case, we used
the appRefresh task type
which can be scheduled
in advance
to provide our application
with a limited amount of runtime
in the background
at a desired date.
Using the same identifier
for the request
and the handler
in the background task modifier
lets the system identify
which handler to call
when the corresponding task
is received by your application.
In order for us to be sure that
we are scheduled again
for tomorrow,
we'll start our background task
by calling
the scheduleAppRefresh
function we just wrote
to schedule background runtime
again for tomorrow at noon.
Now that our background runtime
at noon is recurring,
we make our network request
to check whether
it is stormy outside
and wait for the result
using the await Swift keyword.
Then, if our network request
has returned
and it is indeed stormy outside,
we await sending
the notification to the user
prompting them to upload
a photo of the sky.
When the body
of our closure returns,
the underlying background task
assigned to our application
by the system
is implicitly marked
as complete,
and the system can suspend
our application again.
Here, using Swift Concurrency
has let do potentially
long-running operations
in our background task
without the need
for an explicit callback
for when the work
has completed.
Many APIs
across Apple Platforms,
such as adding a notification,
already support
Swift Concurrency
for asynchronous operations.
Here, the notifyForPhoto
async function
can be implemented
in a straightforward way
using the asynchronous
addNotification method
found on
UserNotificationCenter.
Let's dive in to how Swift
Concurrency and async/await
do some heavy lifting for us
and make it easier than ever
to handle background tasks.
Let's write the asynchronous
isStormy function
that we've been referencing.
This async function is going to
need to make a network request
checking the weather outside.
To start, we'll get
the shared URLSession
and instantiate a request
for weather data.
URLSession has adopted
Swift Concurrency
and has a method for downloading
data from the network
that can be awaited
from async contexts.
With the network response
in hand,
we can read the weather data
and return our result.
But what about
when our application
can't complete
the network request
before our runtime expires?
Recall that in this case,
we wanted to make sure that
we had set up our URLSession
as a background session
and to ensure that it will send
launch events to our application
using a URLSession
background task.
Back to our code.
We had used
the shared URLSession.
Instead, we should create
a URLSession
from a background
configuration with
the sessionSendsLaunchEvents
property set to true.
This tells the system that some
network requests should run
even when the app is suspended
and to then wake the app
for a URLSession background task
when that request completes.
Note that this is especially
important on watchOS
as all network requests made by
apps running in the background
on watchOS must be requested
through background URLSessions.
We're not quite done though.
Recall that when our background
task runtime is expiring,
the system will cancel
the async task
that is running
the closure provided
to the background task
modifier.
This means that
the network request made here
will also be cancelled when our
background runtime is expiring.
To respond to and handle
that cancellation,
we can use the
withTaskCancellationHandler
function built
in to Swift Concurrency.
Instead of awaiting
the result directly,
we place our download into a
withTaskCancellationHandler call
and await this as well.
The first block passed to
withTaskCancellationHandler
is the async procedure
we'd like to run and await.
The second onCancel trailing
closure is code that will run
when the task is cancelled.
Here, when the immediate
network request is cancelled
due to our runtime expiring,
we promote the network request
to a background download task,
on which we can call resume,
triggering the background
download that will persist
even when our app is suspended.
This code is not making the
underlying network request twice
as we're using the same
URLSession to back both,
and URLSession will deduplicate
any in-process requests
under the hood.
Finally, we need to ensure
that our application is set up
to handle a launch
from a background URLSession.
We can use the background task
modifier again,
but this time with
the URLSession task type.
By using the same identifier
for the background URLSession
configuration we made earlier,
we can ensure
this block is only called
when that specific URLSession
produces a background task.
We've taken a dive into
the new unified SwiftUI API
for handling background tasks
and discovered how Swift
Concurrency makes it easier
than ever for us to manage task
completion and expiration.
For more information
about Swift Concurrency,
check out the
"Meet Async/await in Swift" talk
from WWDC 2021.
And to learn more about
concurrency in SwiftUI,
we recommend "Discover
Concurrency in SwiftUI,"
also from WWDC 2021.
Thanks for watching
"Efficiency awaits:
Background Tasks in SwiftUI."
♪