♪ ♪
Bob: Hi, I'm Bob Whiteman,
Senior iOS Device Management Engineer.
It is my pleasure to share with you
an important new security feature
for managed devices in enterprise
and education environments.
Let's start by reviewing
the device security landscape.
Your users need to access
organization resources,
such as websites,
application servers, and databases.
And there's attackers who also
want to access those resources.
The classic model for securing resources
is perimeter security.
You draw a security boundary
around an intranet,
and stand up a firewall or VPN
that permits legitimate clients
and rejects threats.
But this model hasn't kept up with the way
people interact with modern organizations.
Cloud service providers put resources
outside the perimeter.
Threats can start
from inside the perimeter.
And threats can spoof legitimate clients
to penetrate the perimeter.
A more modern security model
does not trust a network perimeter.
Instead, each resource performs
its own trust evaluation.
This is a core principle
of zero trust architecture.
You can think of trust evaluation
as a function:
the input is posture information
about the client,
and the output is the decision
to grant or deny access.
It's critical to get
trust evaluation right.
A false negative gets in the way
of user activities,
or worse, a false positive allows
an attacker to access your resources.
And that means having accurate
posture information is also critical.
Let's investigate
common components of posture.
You use all available information about
the client and its request:
who is making the request,
what device they're using,
where they are, and so on.
Trust evaluation may use different details
within the posture
for accessing different resources.
Accessing a low-security resource
may only require the user's identity,
but accessing critical infrastructure
may require evaluating all posture items.
It's up to the organization
to decide which details are relevant.
One central element of posture
is the user's identity.
This indicates who is making the request.
Apple devices provide several technologies
to support user identity,
such as the Extensible Single Sign On
feature,
including the built-in Kerberos extension,
to facilitate user authentication
for apps, websites, and accounts.
And the new
Enrollment Single Sign On feature
lets an app facilitate
user authentications during and after
the enrollment process
of User Enrollments.
But this session isn't about
user identity,
it's about device identity.
This element of posture indicates
which device is making the request.
The UDID that the device reports
in each MDM communication
is the primary way that your MDM server
knows which device it's managing.
The DeviceInformation query
also provides to the MDM server
attributes of the device,
including the serial number.
A managed device often communicates
with other systems inside the organization
aside from the MDM server.
So, often the MDM server configures
the device with client certificates
that declare the device's identity
to those other systems.
These methods of identifying a device
have served us well,
but they amount to trusting that the
device is the one that it claims to be.
As the landscape has changed,
with devices more distributed
than ever before,
our security needs have evolved.
To address this,
I'm excited to share a powerful new method
for proving a device's identity,
Managed Device Attestation.
With Managed Device Attestation, a device
provides strong evidence about itself
when making a request.
It improves posture information,
so trust evaluations based on that
are more accurate.
In short, Managed Device Attestation
means legitimate devices
reliably access resources,
and attackers are thwarted.
This release brings
Managed Device Attestation for iOS 16,
iPadOS 16, and tvOS 16.
This session we'll start with an overview
of the new attestation features,
explain the benefits
of using attestations,
and then dive into
the implementation details.
First, what are attestations?
An attestation is a declaration of a fact.
If you trust the entity making the claim,
you accept that the fact is true.
In software, an attestation is a fact
that is cryptographically signed.
This is usually an X.509 certificate.
If you trust the signer,
you accept that the fact is true.
For Managed Device Attestation,
the facts are the identity
and other properties of a device,
and the signer is Apple.
Accepting the accuracy of these
device facts requires trusting Apple.
However, it doesn't require trusting
every line of code ever written by Apple.
It only requires trusting
the Secure Enclave
and Apple's attestation servers,
which access Apple's manufacturing records
and operating system catalog.
And if you keep your data
on Apple devices at all,
you're implicitly trusting those.
Here's how we're bringing the power
of attestations to managed devices.
Managed Device Attestation offers two ways
to use attestation certificates.
We've enhanced
the DeviceInformation MDM command,
which makes the benefits of attestation
available to the MDM server.
And we've added support for the Automatic
Certificate Management Environment,
or ACME, protocol
by adding an ACME profile payload,
which makes the benefits of attestation
available
throughout the organization's
infrastructure.
For DeviceInformation attestation,
the MDM server issues a DeviceInformation
query and specifies some new keys.
The device obtains an attestation
from Apple’s servers
and returns it to the MDM server.
Then the MDM server
evaluates the attestation.
But be careful.
DeviceInformation attestation declares
to the MDM server,
"A device exists with these properties."
It does not prove that the device the MDM
server is currently communicating with
is that same device.
For that,
you need ACME payload attestation.
ACME payload attestation
provides the strongest proof
of the identity of the device.
When you install a profile
containing an ACME payload,
the device requests a certificate
from an organization ACME server.
This is very similar
to installing a SCEP payload.
The device provides an attestation
to the ACME server.
Based upon this strong proof
of the identity of the device,
the ACME server issues
a new client certificate
that the rest of
your organization's servers trust.
These two new features use
attestation certificates
to prove several things:
the device is genuine Apple hardware;
the device is a specific device;
the device has certain properties;
and a private key is bound to the device.
And it proves to different servers
that they are communicating
with the same device.
How do these attestations benefit you?
Attestations are primarily
a security feature,
so I'll describe some of the threats
and how attestations mitigate them.
First, a compromised device
lies about its properties,
so Apple attests to the properties.
Even if the OS is compromised,
that doesn't affect the reliability
of the attestation.
It only requires the Secure Enclave
to be intact.
Or a compromised device provides
an outdated attestation of properties
that have since changed.
A nonce in the attestation ensures
that the facts are up to date.
ACME payload attestation
mitigates other threats.
A compromised device
sends a different device's identifiers
when communicating with the MDM server.
So Apple attests device identifiers in
a way that's tied to the client identity
that the device uses
to authenticate its TLS connection.
This proves to your MDM server
and other organization servers
which device they are communicating with.
Or, an attacker extracts a private key
from a legitimate device
and uses it to make requests,
spoofing the legitimate device.
Apple attests that the private key
is protected by the Secure Enclave,
which has exceptionally strong protections
against exporting
or importing private keys.
Last, an attacker hijacks
a certificate request
to get a certificate authority to issue
a certificate for a different device.
Apple attests the identity
of the requesting device
in a way that ties it to the certificate
request,
so the certificate authority
only issues certificates
to the legitimate device.
Attestations give you security benefits
that mitigate several threats.
So how do you use them
in your environment?
Let's get into the details of how to
implement Managed Device Attestation.
First, there are the enhancements
to the DeviceInformation command.
An MDM server can issue this command
to a managed device.
The request includes a list of properties
that the server wants to know.
We've added a new property,
DevicePropertiesAttestation.
Adding it to the Queries array
means the MDM server
is requesting an attestation.
To ensure that the attestation is fresh,
the MDM server can use
the DeviceAttestationNonce key.
This appears at the same level
in the request as the Queries key.
This key is optional.
Its value is a data object,
with a maximum size of 32 bytes.
Here's an example
that requests attestation.
The Queries array contains
the DevicePropertiesAttestation key,
and there's a 32 byte nonce.
When obtaining the attestation
is successful,
the response contains
a DevicePropertiesAttestation key.
Its value is an array of data objects.
Each element in the array
is a certificate in a certificate chain.
This is an example response.
The leaf certificate
appears first in the array,
and it contains device properties
in custom OIDs.
The first two OIDs are device identifying
properties, serial number and UDID.
They are omitted from the certificate if
the MDM enrollment is a User Enrollment.
The remaining OIDs are anonymous,
and available for all enrollment types.
sepOS version refers to the version
of the operating system
that runs on the Secure Enclave.
And the presence of the correct value
in the nonce OID
proves that the certificate
was just generated.
When the MDM server
receives an attestation
it must carefully validate it,
in the following order.
It verifies that the cert chain is rooted
with the expected
Apple certificate authority.
The Apple certificate authority
is available
from the Apple Private PKI Repository.
It verifies that the nonce
in the leaf certificate matches the nonce
in the DeviceInformation request,
if one was specified.
And then it parses out the remaining
OIDs and evaluates their values.
Generating new attestations uses
significant resources on the device
and Apple's servers,
so there's a rate limit on how often new
attestation certificates can be requested,
currently one new attestation
every seven days.
You request a fresh attestation
by specifying a new nonce.
Omitting a nonce indicates
that freshness is not a concern,
so the device can return
its most recent attestation instead.
And if the nonce is specified
and matches that cached attestation,
the cached attestation is returned.
When the MDM server validates
the nonce in an attestation,
it should detect a mismatched nonce
and determine whether that was expected
due to caching or not.
But don't request a new attestation
every seven days
just because that's the rate limit.
Doing that will only delay how quickly
your MDM server discovers changes
in device properties,
not to mention waste resources.
Instead, monitor for relevant changes
in the other DeviceInformation properties,
such as the OS version.
When one of those changes,
then request a fresh attestation.
This ensures the attestation is updated
as quickly as possible after a change,
rather than waiting
for the rate limit to expire.
And, just in case the device is compromised
and lying about these other properties,
slip in the occasional random request
for a fresh attestation
to keep the device honest.
Requesting an attestation may fail.
When that happens,
the device still responds
but some information is omitted.
Either the DevicePropertiesAttestation
field is omitted from the response,
or an expected OID
or its value is omitted.
There are many potential reasons
for a failure:
the device experiences a network issue
reaching Apple's attestation servers.
No server is up 100% of the time,
so there may be an issue
with Apple's attestation servers.
Or the device hardware or software
may be compromised,
or it's not even genuine Apple hardware.
In these last three cases,
Apple's attestation servers
refuse to issue an attestation
for properties that they cannot verify.
The different causes
of a failed attestation
range from a harmless network glitch
to an active attack.
Unfortunately,
there is no trustworthy way
for the MDM server
to know the exact cause.
This is because the only source
of information about the failure
is the device itself, which may be
a compromised device that's lying.
So how should an MDM server
interpret a failure?
Don't always assume the worst
when attestation fails.
If you have a zero trust architecture,
here's how you would likely handle it.
The organization calculates a trust score
for the device,
with a failed or unexpectedly stale
attestation lowering that score.
A lowered trust score
triggers different actions,
such as denying access to services,
flagging the device
for manual investigation,
or remediating by wiping it
and revoking its certificates.
This ensures an appropriate response
to a failed attestation.
Let's move on to implementing
ACME payload attestation.
Installing an ACME payload
involves several steps.
I'll describe the different participants
in the process, then each of those steps.
We start with an iPhone, iPad or Apple TV.
In most cases this is managed
by an MDM server.
There's an ACME server.
This implements the ACME protocol,
RFC 8555,
so it can issue client certificates from
an organization certificate authority.
And there's Apple's attestation servers
that issue the attestations.
The first step is for the MDM server
to install a profile
containing an ACME payload.
The payload specifies properties
of the key the device will generate,
properties of the certificate
that the device will request,
and how to request the certificate
from the ACME server.
To start installing the profile,
the device generates
the requested type of key.
In order to use attestations,
the key must be hardware-bound.
While the ACME payload supports RSA
and various sizes of keys,
in order to get a hardware-bound key,
you must use ECSECPrimeRandom.
Your best choice is
a ECSECPrimeRandom 384 bit key
because that's the highest security
hardware-bound key.
Once the key is created, the device makes
initial contact with the ACME server.
The device requests the DirectoryURL,
which specifies the URLs to use
for the rest of the process
of communicating with the ACME server.
Then the two systems create an account
and an order.
The server offers
the device-attest-01 validation type.
Then, the ACME server generates a nonce
and sends it to the device
in the token field.
The ACME protocol was initially used
to issue server certificates.
Here however,
the validation type we use
was introduced in an IETF draft
specifying an extension
of the ACME protocol
for receiving attestations
and issuing client certificates.
Attestation is optional.
When the payload specifies attestation,
the device requests an attestation
from Apple.
This is nearly identical
to the DeviceInformation attestation.
It uses the same OIDs,
and device-identifying OIDs are omitted
for User Enrollments.
But there's a few differences.
The nonce is hashed using SHA-256
before embedding it in the attestation.
The nonce comes from the ACME server,
not the MDM server.
And the private key that matches
the attestation leaf certificate
is the one the device just generated.
The attestation certificate
matches the private key,
however that certificate can't be used
for any purposes besides attestation.
So the device requests from
the ACME server another certificate
matching the private key,
and this cert is good for TLS.
The device provides
a certificate signing request
containing the certificate request
properties from the payload.
It provides the attestation chain.
And it provides the ClientIdentifier
from the ACME payload.
Typically this is used like a ticket
that is good for the issuance
of a single certificate,
to prevent repeated requests.
The ACME server must carefully validate
the request
before issuing a certificate,
in this order.
It must verify that the ClientIdentifier
is valid and unused.
The attestation certificate must chain up
to the correct Apple CA.
The public key in the attestation
leaf certificate must match the CSR.
The nonce must match the SHA-256 hash of
the one that the ACME server sent earlier.
And then the ACME server can evaluate
the remaining OIDs.
And remember that attestations may fail.
The ACME server should carefully consider
a failure when issuing a certificate,
just like we reviewed with a failed
attestation in the DeviceInformation case.
From here, things rapidly finish up.
The ACME server issues
a client certificate
from the organization CA
and returns it to the device.
The ACME server is the final authority
for client certificate issuance.
It can choose to honor or override
the properties in the CSR
such as the SubjectAltName.
The device stores
the certificate in the keychain,
and this completes the installation
of the ACME payload.
Let's tie all this together.
How do servers know
the device communicating with them
is the one it claims to be?
The device uses the same private key
in multiple ways:
when getting an attestation from Apple,
when getting a client certificate
from the ACME server,
and when using TLS
to communicate with other servers.
Because the key is hardware-bound,
we know all these actions were performed
by the same device.
And we have an attestation certificate
which describes that device.
Combining these,
organization servers now have confidence
in the device's identity
when granting access.
Just like with the certificate
and SCEP payloads,
other payloads in the profile
can reference the ACME payload
in order to use the certificate.
Use it for MDM, Wi-Fi, VPN,
Kerberos, Safari.
All these systems benefit
from attestation.
A device can have up to 10 ACME payloads
that use attestation
installed at the same time.
Note that hardware-bound keys
are not preserved
when a managed device's backup
is restored,
even when restoring to the same device.
And if you do nothing else
with Managed Device Attestation,
use an ACME payload
for the MDM client identity
so the MDM server can be sure
which device it's managing.
Let's wrap up.
You use Managed Device Attestation
to remediate multiple classes of threats.
You leverage DeviceInformation attestation
to improve the device identity component
of posture for better trust evaluation.
And, you can now prove a device's identity
as it accesses organization resources
using ACME attestation.
We look forward to your implementation
of Managed Device Attestation.
Together, we'll improve the security
of your device deployments.
Thank you, and have a great WWDC.