[upbeat music]
Justin Rennell: Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Justin, and I'm an engineer
on the Apple Music development team.
Today I’m going to give an introduction
to MusicKit with a focus
on the fundamentals
of using Apple Music API.
In this session, I’ll provide an overview
of MusicKit client frameworks
and how they integrate
with the Apple Music API web service.
I'll explain how to get access
as a developer and specific details
about using Apple Music API, including:
Requesting content and resources,
using limits and pagination to work
with large resource collections,
and how to find content in the catalog
with the search endpoint.
Finally, I'll provide a look
at some personalized features available
for Apple Music subscribers and how
to provide access to them in your apps.
I'll start with a brief introduction
to MusicKit and Apple Music API.
MusicKit was first announced
at WWDC in 2017.
Since then, we have made improvements
that make integrating
with Apple Music easier and continue
to add support
for additional functionality.
MusicKit is a combination
of client frameworks
and the Apple Music API.
Used together,
they make it possible to add
Apple Music functionality to your apps.
You can discover
and fetch content from Apple Music,
including artists, albums,
playlists, and more,
with functionality to search the catalog
and browse popularity charts.
With the user’s consent,
MusicKit and Apple Music API let you
authenticate subscribers
to play available content
and provide access
to personalized features,
including their music library,
recommendations,
and recently played history.
MusicKit client frameworks
provide the APIs needed
to authenticate subscribers
and start and control
playback on a device.
Client frameworks are available
for apps on Apple platforms,
web applications using JavaScript,
and Android applications
using the available SDK.
MusicKit on Apple platforms
has everything you need
to integrate Apple Music into your apps.
Subscribers can authenticate
or sign up within your app
to start and control playback
and access other personalized features.
Available APIs accelerate calls
to discover and access content
from Apple Music with native support
for resources and pagination.
Many of the topics covered later
about accessing and making requests
to Apple Music API directly
are handled by MusicKit
on Apple platforms automatically.
Developers writing apps
for Apple platforms are encouraged
to watch the session
"Meet MusicKit for Swift"
for an introduction to those APIs
and the session
"Explore more content with MusicKit"
for more functionality.
MusicKit on the Web makes it easy
to bring Apple Music
to your applications using JavaScript.
You can discover Apple Music content,
let subscribers sign in
to access personalized features
and play content directly on your website.
Full access to Apple Music API
gives you the power
to create unique music experiences.
MusicKit provides a collection
of built-in web components,
including a full-featured media player.
These components
make it easy to get started
and have the flexibility
to customize for your experience.
MusicKit for Android
lets you integrate Apple Music
into your Android applications.
Support for authenticating
Apple Music subscribers,
controlling content playback,
and full access to Apple Music API allows
you to build a rich music experience.
Apple Music API is the common
JSON web service that provides access
to discovery features
and Apple Music catalog content.
Authenticated subscribers can
access personalized features,
including their Music Library,
Recommendations,
and Recently Played history.
Next, I'll explain how to get access.
To make requests to Apple Music API,
you will need a Developer Token.
For applications on Apple platforms,
you can take advantage
of automatic token management
by enabling the MusicKit service
for your app.
This service can be found
in the App ID section
of the Apple Developer portal shown here.
For applications on other platforms,
you can obtain a Developer Token
by enrolling as a MusicKit developer
on the Apple Developer portal.
From there, you can request
and download a private key.
You will need to generate
a JSON Web Token and sign it
with your downloaded private key.
A JSON Web Token is split in two parts.
The first part is required headers,
including the signing algorithm "alg,"
which must be ES256,
and the key identifier "kid,"
which is included as part
of your private key download.
The second part of the token is claims.
Apple Music API has three required claims:
issuer ID “iss,”
which is your team ID that can be found
in the memberships section
of the Apple Developer portal,
issued at time "iat,"
which is represented by the number
of seconds since the Epoch,
and an expiration time "exp."
This is in the same time format
as the issued time.
Tokens can be generated
to expire a maximum of six months
from when they were issued.
For web applications,
we encourage providing an origin claim,
which will issue a token valid
for your website only.
A valid,
signed token must be supplied
in the authorization header
for all requests to Apple Music API.
With the MusicKit service enabled
for your applications on Apple platforms,
this will be done automatically.
MusicKit on the web must be configured
with a token you generate
to make requests to Apple Music API.
More information about generating
JSON Web Tokens can be found
in the Apple Music API documentation.
Now I will show you how to request
resources using Apple Music API.
Resources model Apple Music content,
such as artists, albums,
songs, playlists and more.
Each has its own corresponding type.
Resources can be fetched
from Apple Music API endpoints
through discovery features like search
or by using their identifiers.
Here is an example request URL
to fetch a playlist resource
from the API using its identifier.
Apple Music API
is hosted at api.music.apple.com.
The path of the URL
uses a RESTful pattern
and represents the location
for a resource or feature.
The first element in the location
is the version of the API,
which is currently version 1.
New versions may become available
when significant changes are introduced.
Versions maintain backwards compatibility
with existing calls,
even as enhancements to resources
and new features are made available.
For requests
within the Apple Music catalog,
the next section in the location
represents the specific catalog
to fetch from.
Apple Music is
a worldwide streaming service,
and content can differ between regions,
which we refer to as storefronts.
For information about storefronts
and content availability,
watch the session titled "Cross reference
content with the Apple Music API."
In this example, I will fetch
a playlist from the catalog
in the United States storefront,
denoted
by the two-letter country code “us.”
The final part of this location
is the resource’s identity,
represented by its type "playlists"
followed by its identifier.
Since Apple Music is available
in many regions,
support for localization is possible
using the optional language
tag query parameter "L."
Here, I am specifying
the language tag "en-US" for English.
To fetch content localized in Spanish,
I could specify the tag “es-MX.”
To keep things simple,
I will not specify a language tag
in these examples,
which results
in the storefront’s default localization.
The storefronts
that Apple Music is available in
and their supported localizations
can be found by accessing
the storefronts reference endpoint.
More detail can be found
in the Apple Music API documentation.
Here's a look at making
a GET request for a playlist.
This returns
a resource collection response
with a "data" array
containing the playlist resource.
Resource objects indicate the identity
of the content with an ID value and type.
The combination of ID and type represent
the unique identity of a resource.
The href value indicates the location in
the API where the resource may be fetched.
In this case, note the location
is the same as the path we requested.
The metadata values for the content are
found in the resource's attributes map.
Direct connections to other resources,
such as this playlist curator and tracks,
are found in the relationships map.
Here is a closer look
at the attributes map,
which contains the metadata values
for the playlist.
I'll walk through an example
of using some of these attributes
in the widget on the right,
which uses the playlist's name,
curator name, and description attributes.
playParams is a common attribute
on many resource types
that indicates when the content is
available to stream for subscribers.
This can be used to determine
if play control should be enabled,
as content without playParams is
not available for playback.
Artwork is another common attribute
for many resource types
that contains values for the maximum width
and height for the image,
alongside a url
where the image can be loaded from.
At Apple,
developer feedback is very important
and helps us improve our APIs
and services for everyone.
This year,
we're happy to announce the addition
of one of our most requested features.
Artist artwork is now available
in Apple Music API,
making plain silhouettes
a thing of the past.
All new and existing apps
can add support for these images
by looking for the artwork attribute
added to artist resources.
Artist artwork can be loaded the same way
as artwork for other content types.
Here is an abbreviated example
of an artwork url for the playlist
we were looking at earlier.
Artwork urls contain "w," width and "h,"
height tokens, highlighted in blue.
To load artwork using this URL,
replace these tokens
with the desired resolution
for your display.
Since playlist artwork is square,
I will use the same resolution
for both width and height.
Here is an example of requesting
a resolution of 400 by 400,
at 300 by 300, and at 200 by 200.
The images scale for display
at each resolution,
and the file sizes are reduced
for smaller images.
All resource types have a set
of default attributes
that represent the common
or basic metadata for that resource.
Some resources have additional attributes
that may be fetched,
known as "extended attributes."
These extended attributes can be requested
by using the extend query parameter.
For instance,
tracks on Apple Music playlists
are either songs or music videos.
If you'd like to know the types
of tracks a playlist contains,
you can request
the trackTypes extended attribute.
Extended attributes appear
in the resource’s attributes map
alongside their default attributes.
If a playlist's tracks are music videos
rather than songs,
perhaps you would customize
the play button to inform the viewer.
Taking a look now
at the relationships map shows a couple
of direct connections
from this playlist to other resources.
Many resources have
automatic relationships
that will be returned
when requesting some content directly.
The automatic relationships
for a playlist are its curator and tracks.
Relationships are named
to indicate what the connection is,
such as the curator for this playlist.
They have an href location where
the relationship may be fetched directly
and a data array
for the related resource collection.
For playlists, the curator relationship
is automatically related,
meaning only the identity
of the related resources will be present.
This allows for easily linking to
this resource using its identity or href.
Since a playlist already contains
the curator's name as an attribute,
there may be no need
to include other metadata
for the related curator resource.
The identity of the resource could be used
to make the curator name a link,
letting people navigate to the curator to
discover additional content if they wish.
If you want to show additional information
for the curator with the playlist,
such as its artwork, you will need
to fetch the curator's metadata.
Use the include parameter
to specify the relationships
you want related resource metadata for.
Some resource types have
additional relationships not included
by default that can also be requested
with this parameter.
Note that including relationships
can increase the size of responses
and negatively impact
the speed of your app.
Many useful values that may
be desired from related resources
can be found directly as attributes
on the original resource.
For the best performance,
we recommend including
only the relationships
and metadata needed in the response.
Detailed information for resource types
and their available attributes
and relationships can be found
in the Apple Music API documentation.
For more about extended attributes,
relationships,
and special relationships called views,
watch the session “Explore the catalog
with the Apple Music API.”
Revisiting the relationships
for the example playlist,
the tracks for the playlist
are automatically included,
meaning the attribute metadata
for the related track resources
appear in the response.
The attributes for the related tracks
can be used to display a track list
for the playlist using their artwork
and other metadata
shown in the widget on the right.
In the previous section,
I showed an example
of fetching a playlist resource
from the catalog with its tracks.
In this section,
I'll explain how to handle relationships
with a large number of resources.
The related resources for a relationship
appear in its data array.
When the number
of related resources is small,
all of the resources will appear
in a single response.
Relationships with more related resources
than appear in a single response
must be fetched
in multiple parts called pages.
I'll use the tracks relationship
for a large playlist as an example.
Only the first 100 tracks
of a playlist are included by default.
If a playlist has more than 100 tracks,
then the additional tracks
must be fetched in subsequent pages.
Here is an example response
for a playlist with over 100 tracks.
The href and resource collection data
for the tracks relationship appear
in the response as was seen earlier.
Since this playlist has more tracks
than were included in the response,
a next location appears
as a sibling to the data.
The next location represents
where the remaining resources
in the collection can be fetched.
Fetching the next location
makes a direct relationship fetch
and returns the relationship's
resource collection data
starting from the provided offset.
The default limit for the relationship
will apply to each page.
You may select your own page size
by supplying a limit parameter.
The page size limit
can be between one
and the specific relationship's
maximum page size,
which can be found in the documentation.
If the resource collection
for the relationship
contains additional resources
past the ones returned in the page,
a next location will continue
to appear as a sibling to the data.
When the resource collection is exhausted,
a next location will not be present.
Note that next locations do not reflect
the selected page size for the request.
You will need to supply a limit parameter
on each request if you wish
to use a different page size
than the default.
Always use the next location
from the response
to page over resource collections.
Trying to calculate your own offset
can result in issues
with invalid locations
or duplicate results.
In the next section,
I will show how to search fof content
in the Apple Music catalog
using Apple Music API.
Apple Music API provides functionality
to find content in the catalog
using a search term.
A search request resembles
a catalog resource request
with /search as the location
and the search term as a parameter.
You can specify which content types you're
interested in with the types parameter
and the maximum number of results
to include for each type using a limit.
When more results are found
past the requested limit,
pagination can be used
to continue the search.
Here's the response to a search
for albums and songs with the term “pop."
The search endpoint returns a response
with a results object containing a group
for each requested type
with matching content.
For this request,
matches were found for albums and songs.
The response also includes a meta object
containing a recommended order
for the result groups based on relevancy.
This may be helpful
if you're building a search experience
that handles
multiple content types at once.
Each result group has and href
where the results were fetched from
and a resource collection data array
containing the matching resources
of the relevant type
for the search term.
If more matches for
a result group are available,
the group will contain a next location
where additional matches may be fetched.
Requesting the next location
returns more results for the selected type
starting from the offset.
In the last section,
I’ll discuss accessing
personalized features in Apple Music API.
Apple Music API and MusicKit
provide access
to features personalized
to a specific user.
These features let you add support
for subscribers to view
and search for content
in their Apple Music library,
including the ability to add content
they enjoy and create new playlists.
Personalized Recommendations
can be surfaced
based on individual music tastes.
And you can let people rediscover
music they've been listening to recently
to pick up where they left off
or provide entirely new experiences.
Personalized features are available
for people
with an active subscription
to Apple Music.
To support these features,
you must first authenticate the person
with your app using MusicKit
and request permission
to access their music data.
When permission is granted,
a Music User Token will be available.
This token is added to Apple Music API
requests in the music-user-token header
and is used to authenticate access
to personalized data.
A Music User Token is specific to your app
and the device the user authenticated on.
This token must not be shared
across devices,
as permission is granted
for a single device at a time.
A token may become invalid based
on changes to a person’s subscription
or password,
or if they revoke access to your app.
It may also expire with time.
Authentication can be refreshed
by prompting them to sign back in
and grant permission for your app.
Note that this token is managed
automatically by MusicKit
on Apple platforms
and MusicKit on the Web.
Please see the documentation
for the framework you're using
for more details.
In today's session,
I showed how you can integrate Apple Music
into your apps using MusicKit
and Apple Music API,
a quick look at the platforms with support
for MusicKit client frameworks,
and how to use Apple Music API to access
and find content in the catalog,
and some personalized features
available for subscribers.
For more on this year's updates
to MusicKit on Apple platforms,
check out the session
"Explore more content with MusicKit.”
Thank you for watching,
and we hope you enjoy the rest
of this year's WWDC.
[upbeat music]