♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Meng Yang: Hi,
my name is Meng Yang,
an engineer from GPU Software
here at Apple.
Today I am going cover
a few advanced topics
about ScreenCaptureKit
and how it can take
your app's screen sharing
experience to the next level.
Later, my colleague Drew
will demonstrate
this exciting new API in action.
Screen capture is at the heart
of screen sharing applications
such as Zoom,
Google Meet, SharePlay
and even popular game streaming
services like Twitch,
which have become the new norm
of how we work, study,
collaborate, and socialize
over the past few years.
ScreenCaptureKit
is a brand-new,
high-performance
screen capture framework
built from ground up
with a powerful feature set.
The rich set of features
includes highly customizable
content control that allows you
to easily pick and then choose
any combination
of windows, applications,
and displays to capture.
Ability to capture
up to the screen content's
native resolution
and frame rate.
Dynamic stream property controls
like resolution,
frame rate, pixel format.
And these controls
can be modified on the fly
without recreating the stream.
Capture buffers that are
GPU memory-backed
to reduce memory copies.
Hardware-accelerated
content capture, scaling,
pixel and color
format conversion
to achieve high-performance
capture with reduced CPU usage.
Last but not least, support for
both video and audio capture.
Before getting started,
this talk assumes
you are already familiar
with the basic concepts,
building blocks,
and workflow of
how the framework works.
Please visit the intro session
"Meet ScreenCaptureKit"
to learn more.
In this session,
I am going to talk about
how to capture and display
a single window.
Next, how to add screen content
to full display capture.
How to remove content
from display capture.
I will then show you a few ways
to configure the stream
for different use cases.
And last, you will see a demo
of how ScreenCaptureKit
transformed the screen
and audio capture experience
of OBS Studio, a popular
open source screen capture app.
Now, let's start
with the first example,
and probably
the most common use case:
capture a single window.
This example is going to cover
how to set up
a single window filter;
what to expect
from the stream output
when the captured window
is being resized, occluded,
moved off-screen, or minimized.
You will also learn
how to use per-frame metadata
and how to properly display
the captured window.
Let's dive in.
To capture a single window
that's independent
of which display it's on,
you can start by using
a single window filter
and initialize the filter
with just one window.
In the example here,
the filter is configured to
include a single Safari window.
The video output includes just
that window and nothing else.
No child, pop-up,
or other windows from Safari
will be included.
ScreenCaptureKit's audio capture
policy on the other hand
always works at the app level.
When a single window filter
is used,
all the audio content
from the application
that contains the window
will be captured,
even from those windows that are
not present in the video output.
Now let's take a look
at the code sample.
To create a stream
with a single window,
start by getting
all available content to share
via SCShareableContent.
Next, get the window you want
to share from SCShareableContent
by matching the windowID.
Then, create a SCContentFilter
with the type
desktopIndependentWindow
with the specified SCWindow.
You can further configure
the stream to include audio
as part of the stream output.
Now you are ready
to create a stream
with contentFilter
and streamConfig.
You can then add a StreamOutput
and start the stream.
Let's take a look
at the stream output next.
In the example here, the source
display is on the left
and the stream output
is on the right.
The stream filter includes
a single Safari window.
Now I am going to start
to scroll the Safari window
that's being captured.
The stream output includes
the live content
from the single Safari window
and is updating at the same
cadence as the source window,
up to the source display's
native frame rate.
For example, when the source
window is constantly updating
on a 120Hz display,
the stream output
can also achieve
up to 120 fps update.
You might wonder what happens
when the window resizes.
Please keep in mind
that frequently changing
the stream's output dimension
can lead to additional
memory allocation
and therefore not recommended.
The stream's output dimension
is mostly fixed
and it does not resize
with the source window.
Now let me start to resize
the source window
and see what happens
to the stream's output.
ScreenCaptureKit always
performs hardware scaling
on the captured window so it
never exceeds the frame output
as the source window resizes.
How about windows that are
covered by other windows?
When the source window is
occluded or partially occluded,
the stream output
always includes
the window's full content.
And this also applies
to the case
when the window
is completely off-screen
or moved to other displays.
And for minimized windows, when
the source window is minimized,
the stream output is paused,
and it resumes when the source
window is no longer minimized.
Next, let's move
to audio output.
In this example here,
there are two Safari windows
with audio tracks,
and the window on the left
is being captured.
The video output includes
just the first window,
and the audio tracks
from both Safari windows
will be included
in the audio output.
Let's take a look and listen.
♪ Electronic dance music ♪
Chef: And I wrote down
my favorite guacamole recipe.
It calls for four avocados.
Meng: With the stream
up and running,
your app receives a frame update
whenever there's
a new frame available.
The frame's output
includes IOSurface
representing the captured frame
and the per-frame metadata.
I'd like to spend some time
talking about metadata.
I am going to show you
examples of metadata
that can be quite useful
for your app.
And these include dirty rects,
content rect,
content scale, and scale factor.
Let's start with dirty rects.
Dirty rects indicate
where the new content is
from the previous frame.
In the example here, the dirty
rects are being highlighted
to illustrate the regions
of frame updates.
Instead of always
encoding the entire frame,
or calculate the delta between
two frames in the encoder,
you can simply use
dirty rects to only encode
and transmit the regions
with new updates
and copy the updates
onto the previous frame
on the receiver side
to generate a new frame.
Dirty rects can be retrieved
from the output CMSampleBuffer's
metadata dictionary
using the matching key.
Now let's move to content rect
and the content scale.
The source window to be captured
is on the left
and the stream output
is on the right.
Since a window can be resized,
the source window's
native backing surface size
often doesn't match
the stream output's dimension.
In the example here,
the captured window has
different aspect ratio from the
frame's output and is bigger.
The captured window is scaled
down to fit into the output.
A content rect, which is
highlighted in green here,
indicates the region of interest
of the captured content
on the stream output.
And the content scale
indicates how much the content
is scaled to fit.
Here the captured Safari window
is scaled down
by 0.77 to fit inside the frame.
Now you can use the metadata
just discussed
to correctly display
the captured window
as close to its native
appearance as possible.
First, let's start by cropping
the content from its output
using the content rect.
Next, scale the content back up
by dividing the content scale.
Now the captured content
is scaled to match one-to-one
in pixel size
as the source window.
But how is the captured window
going to look
on the target display?
To answer that question,
I would like to start
by describing
how scale factor works.
A display's scale factor
indicates the scale ratio
between a display
or window's logical point size
and its backing surface's
pixel size.
A scale factor 2, or a 2x mode,
means every one point onscreen
equals four pixels
on the backing surface.
A window can be moved
from a Retina display
with scale factor 2,
such as in the example here,
to a non-Retina display
with scale factor 1
while being captured.
With scale factor 1,
each one logical point onscreen
corresponds to one pixel
on the backing surface.
In addition,
the source display might have
mismatched scale factor
from the target display
where the captured content
will be displayed.
In this example,
a window is being captured
from a Retina display on
the left with a scale factor 2
and to be displayed on a
non-Retina display on the right.
If the captured window is
displayed as-is without scaling
on the target
non-Retina display
with one point
to one pixel mapping,
the window will look
four times as big.
To fix this, you should
always check the scale factor
from the frame's metadata
against the scale factor
of the target display.
When there's a mismatch, scale
the size of the captured content
by the scale factor
before displaying it.
After scaling, the captured
window on the target display
now appears to be the same size
as its source window.
Now let's take a look
at the code,
and it's quite simple.
Content rect, content scale,
and scale factor
can also be retrieved from
the output CMSampleBuffer's
metadata attachment.
You can then use these metadata
to crop and scale the captured
content to display it correctly.
To recap, a single window filter
always includes
full window content
even when the source window
is off-screen or occluded.
It's display
and space independent.
The output is always offset
at the top-left corner.
Pop-up or child windows
are not included.
Consider using metadata
to best display the content.
And the audio includes tracks
from the entire containing app.
Now that you have just learned
about how to capture
and display a single window,
let me move to the next class of
display-based content filters.
In this next example,
you will learn to create
a display-based filter
with windows or apps,
and I will demonstrate
some differences between video-
and audio-filtering rules.
A display-based inclusion filter
specifies which display
you want to capture
content from.
By default,
no windows are captured.
You can choose the content
you want to capture by window.
In the example here, a Safari
window and a Keynote window
are added to the display filter.
The video output includes
just these two windows
placed in a display space
and the audio output
includes all the soundtracks
from Keynote and Safari apps.
This code sample demonstrates
how to create
display-based filters
with included windows.
Start by creating a list
of SCWindows
using SCShareableContent
and windowIDs.
And then, create
a display-based SCContentFilter
with a given display
and a list of included windows.
You can then create a stream
using the filter and
configuration in the same way
as a desktop independent
window and start the stream.
With the stream up and running,
let's take a look
at the stream's output.
The filter is configured
to include two Safari windows,
menu bar, and wallpaper windows.
If a window is moved off-screen,
it will be removed
from the stream output.
When a new Safari window
is created,
the new window doesn't show up
in the stream output
because the new window
is not in the filter.
The same rule also applies
to child or pop-up windows,
which do not show up
in the stream's output.
If you want to ensure
that child windows
are included automatically
in your stream output,
you can use a display-based
filter with included apps.
In this example, adding
the Safari and Keynote apps
to the filter ensures that
the audio and video output
from all the windows and
soundtracks from these two apps
are included in the output
Window exception filters
are a powerful way
of excluding specific windows
from your output
when the filter is specified
as a display with included apps.
For example,
a single Safari window
is removed from the output.
ScreenCaptureKit enables
audio capture at the app level,
so excluding audio
from a single Safari window
is the equivalent
to removing audio tracks
for all Safari apps.
Although the stream's
video output
still includes a Safari window,
all the sound tracks
from Safari apps are removed
and the audio output
includes just the soundtrack
from Keynote.
In the code example here,
we change the SCContentFilter
to include a list of
SCRunningApplications
instead of SCWindows.
If there are individual windows
you want to further exclude,
build a list of SCWindows and
then create an SCContentFilter
using the list of SCApplications
with the list of excepting
windows to exclude.
Let's take a look at what the
stream output looks like now
when new or child windows
are created
by specifying included apps.
This time, Safari app and system
windows are added to the filter.
A new Safari window
is now automatically included
in the stream output
and the same rule applies
to child and pop-up windows.
This can be quite useful
when you are doing a tutorial
and want to demonstrate
the full action
including invoking pop-up
or new windows.
I have just demonstrated
how to add content
to the stream output
through a few different ways.
My next example will show you
how to remove content
from the stream output.
This example
includes a test app
that emulates
a video conferencing app
that contains a preview
of the display being shared.
Because the test app recursively
shows itself in the preview,
it's creating the so-called
mirror hall effect.
Even during full display share,
it's common for screen sharing
applications to remove its
own windows, capture preview,
participant camera view
to avoid the mirror hall effect,
or other system UIs
such as notification windows.
ScreenCaptureKit provides you
with a set of exclusion-based
filters that allow you
to quickly remove content
from display capture.
An exclusion-based display
filter captures all the windows
from the given display
by default.
You can then start to remove
individual windows or apps
by adding them
to the exclusion filter.
For example, you can add
the content capture test app
and Notification Center to the
list of excluded applications.
To create
a display-based filter
excluding a list
of applications,
start by retrieving
SCApplications to exclude
by matching bundle ID.
If there are individual windows
you'd like to cherry-pick
back to the stream output,
you can also build
an optional list of
excepting SCWindows.
And then use a given display,
the list of applications
to exclude,
and a list of excepting windows
to create the content filter.
Let's take a look at the result.
The content capture
test app that's causing
the mirror hall problem
and the notification windows
are both removed
from the stream output.
New or child windows
from these apps
will be automatically
removed as well.
If these removed apps
include any audio,
their audio will be removed
from the audio output.
We've just seen how
to capture a single window,
how to add and remove windows
from a display filter.
Let's move
to stream configuration next.
In the next few examples,
you will learn about
different stream properties
you can configure,
how to set up the stream for
screen capture and streaming,
and how to build a window picker
with live preview.
Let's start with
configuration properties.
These are some of
the common stream properties
you can configure, such as
stream output dimensions,
source and destination rects,
color space, color matrix,
and pixel format,
whether to include cursor,
and frame rate control.
We will take a look at each
property in details next.
Let's start
with output dimension,
which can be specified
as width and height in pixels.
The source display's dimension
and aspect ratio
doesn't always match
the output dimension.
And when this mismatch happens
while capturing a full display,
there will be pillar or
letterbox in the stream output.
You can also specify a source
rect that defines the region
to capture from and the result
will be rendered and scaled
to the destination rect
on the frame output.
ScreenCaptureKit supports
hardware accelerated
color space, color matrix,
and pixel format conversion.
Common BGRA and YUV formats
are supported.
Please visit our developer page
for the full list.
When show cursor is enabled,
the stream output includes
a cursor prerendered
into the frame.
This applies
to all system cursors,
even custom cursor like
the camera-shaped one here.
You can use
minimum frame interval
to control desired
output frame rate.
For example,
when requesting 60 fps,
set the minimal interval
to 1/60.
You will receive frame update
no more than 60 fps,
and no more than
the content's native frame rate.
Queue depth can be specified
to determine
the number of surfaces
in the server-side surface pool.
More surfaces in the pool
can lead to better frame rate
and performance, but it results
in higher system memory usage
and potentially
a latency trade-off,
which I will discuss
in more details later.
ScreenCaptureKit accepts
queue depth range between
three to eight with a default
queue depth of three.
In this example here,
the surface pool is configured
to include four surfaces
available for ScreenCaptureKit
to render to.
The current active surface
is surface 1
and ScreenCaptureKit is
rendering the next frame to it.
Once surface 1 is complete,
ScreenCaptureKit sends
surface 1 to your app.
Your app is processing
and holding surface 1,
while ScreenCaptureKit
is rendering to surface 2.
Surface 1 is now marked
as unavailable in the pool
since your app
is still using it.
When surface 2 is complete,
it's sent to your app
and ScreenCaptureKit
now renders to surface 3.
But if your app is still
processing surface 1,
it will start to fall behind
as frames are now provided
faster than they
can be processed.
If the surface pool contains
a large number of surfaces,
new surfaces
will start to pile up
and you might need to consider
starting to drop frames
in order to keep up.
In this case,
more surfaces in the pool
can potentially lead
to higher latency.
The number of surfaces
left in the pool
for ScreenCaptureKit to use,
equals the queue depth
minus the number of surfaces
held by your app.
In the example here,
both surface 1 and 2
are still held by your app.
There are 2 surfaces
left in the surface pool.
After surface 3 is complete
and is sent to your app,
the only available surface
left in the pool is surface 4.
If your app continues to hold
on to surface 1, 2, and 3,
ScreenCaptureKit will soon
run out of surfaces to render to
and you will start to see
frame loss and glitch.
Your app needs to finish
and release surface 1
before ScreenCaptureKit starts
to render the next frame
after surface 4
in order to avoid frame loss.
Now your app releases
surface 1 and it's available
for ScreenCaptureKit
to use again.
To recap: there are two rules
your app needs to follow
in order avoid frame latency
and frame loss.
To avoid delayed frame,
you need to be able to process
a frame within
the MinimumFrameInterval.
To avoid frame loss,
the time it takes your app
to release the surfaces back
to the pool must be less than
MinimumFrameInterval
times QueueDepth minus 1,
after which ScreenCaptureKit
runs out of surfaces to use,
enters a stall, and will
start to miss new frames.
Now that you've seen
the various properties
you can configure,
let's dive into some examples
to configure the stream for
screen capture and streaming.
Some screen content
includes videos, games,
or animations that
are constantly updating
and that requires
higher frame rate.
While others include
mostly static text
like the keynote window,
which prioritize higher
resolution over frame rate,
you can live-adjust the
stream's configuration based on
the content being shared
and the networking condition.
In this code example,
you are going to see
how to configure the capture
to stream 4K, 60-fps game.
You can start by setting
the stream output dimension
to 4K in pixel size.
And then, set the output
frame rate to 60 fps
by setting the minimum
frame interval to 1/60.
Next, use pixel format YUV420
for encoding and streaming.
Set the optional source rect
to just capture
a portion of the screen.
Next, change the background
fill color to black,
and then include a cursor
in the frame output.
Configure surface queue depth
to five for optimal frame rate
and performance.
Last, enable audio
on the output stream.
All the stream configurations
you've just seen
in the previous example can be
dynamically changed on the fly
without recreating the stream.
For example, you can live adjust
some properties such as
output dimension, dynamically
change the frame rate,
and update stream filters.
Here's an example to switch
the output dimension
from 4K down to 720p.
And downgrade the frame rate
from 60 fps to 15 fps.
You can then simply call
updateConfiguration
to apply the new settings
on the fly
without interrupting the stream.
In the last example,
I'd like to walk you through
building a window picker
with live preview.
Here is an example
of what a typical window
picker looks like.
It's common for web conferencing
screen sharing apps
to offer users an option
to choose the exact window
to share.
ScreenCaptureKit provides
an efficient
and high-performance solution
to creating large number
of thumbnail-sized streams
with live content update,
and it's simple to implement.
Let's break it down to see
what it takes to build
a window picker like this
using ScreenCaptureKit.
To set up the picker,
you can start by creating
one single window filter
for each eligible window
that your app
allows the user to pick
with desktop independent window
as the filter type.
Next, set up the stream
configuration
that's thumbnail-sized, 5 fps,
with BGRA pixel format
for onscreen display, default
queue depth, no cursor or audio.
Use single window filter and
the stream configuration here
to create one stream
for each window.
To do this in code,
you can start by getting
the SCShareableContent
by excluding desktop
and system windows.
Next, create a content filter
of type desktop independent
window for each eligible window.
Then, move to
the stream configuration part.
Choose an appropriate
thumbnail size --
in this example,
it's 284 by 182 --
and then set the minimum
frame interval to one over five.
With a pixel format of BGRA
for onscreen display,
disable audio and cursor
since we don't need them
in the preview.
And set queue depth to three
because we don't expect updates
that are too often.
With the stream content filter
and the configuration created,
you are now ready
to create the streams.
Create one stream
for each window,
add stream output
for each stream,
and then start the stream.
Last, append it
to the stream list.
This is the window picker
with live preview
created using the sample code
we saw earlier.
Each thumbnail is live updating
and then backed
by an individual stream
with single-window filter.
With ScreenCaptureKit,
you can easily build
a live preview picker like this,
that allows you
to concurrently capture
so much live screen content
simultaneously, without
overburdening the system.
Now let me hand it over
to my colleague, Drew,
who's going to give you
an exciting demo about
OBS adoption
of ScreenCaptureKit.
Drew Mills: Thanks, Meng.
Hi, my name is Drew, and I'm a
Partner Engineer here at Apple.
OBS Studio is an open source
application that allows users
to manage recording
and streaming content
from their computer.
It contains an implementation
of ScreenCaptureKit
that we worked with the project
on integrating this spring.
ScreenCaptureKit was easy
to implement thanks to utilizing
similar code to OBS's existing
CGDisplayStream-based capture.
The ScreenCaptureKit
implementation demonstrates
many of the features discussed
in the "Meet ScreenCaptureKit"
session.
This includes:
capturing an entire desktop,
all of the windows
of an application,
or just one specific window.
ScreenCaptureKit has
lower overhead than OBS's
CGWindowListCreateImage-based
capture.
This means that when capturing
a portion of your screen,
you are left with more
resources that you can use
for producing your content.
Let's dive into a demo
to see what we've
been discussing in action.
On the left, there is
a worst case example
of OBS's Window Capture.
This capture uses the
CGWindowListCreateImage API,
and has significant stuttering.
In our testing, we saw frame
rates dip as low as 7 fps.
Meanwhile, the ScreenCaptureKit
implementation on the right
has a much smoother result,
providing an output video
with significantly
smoother motion.
In this case, delivering 60 fps.
All while OBS uses up
to 15 percent less RAM
than Window Capture.
And while OBS's CPU utilization
is cut by up to half
when using ScreenCaptureKit
instead of OBS's Window Capture.
Let's look at the other
improvements
that ScreenCaptureKit
has to offer OBS users.
I'm still trying to track down
all of the Gold Ranks
in Sayonara Wild Hearts.
I want to show off
my best run,
so I've been
recording my gameplay.
Thanks to ScreenCaptureKit,
I can now capture
direct audio stream
from the game,
so when I get
a notification on my Mac,
it won't ruin my recording's
audio or video.
And this is possible
without having to install
any additional
audio routing software.
♪
Now, using all
of the enhancements
provided by ScreenCaptureKit
on Apple silicon,
I can stream games like
Taiko no Tatsujin Pop Tap Beat
from my Mac to popular
streaming services.
A new constant bitrate option
for Apple silicon's
hardware encoder
means that I can encode
my streaming content
for services requiring constant
bitrate without significantly
impacting my game's performance.
Now, thanks to
ScreenCaptureKit's
lower resource usage
and encoding offloading,
I have even more
performance available
for the content that matters.
Back to you, Meng.
Meng: Thank you, Drew.
Through the demos and examples,
you learned about advanced
screen content filters.
Several ways to configure the
stream for different use cases.
And how to use per-frame
metadata and correctly display
the captured content.
Some best practices to help you
achieve best performance.
And finally, Drew showcased
the significant capability
and performance improvement
ScreenCaptureKit brought to OBS.
I can't wait to see
how you redefine your app's
screen sharing, streaming,
and collaboration experience
using ScreenCaptureKit.
Thank you for watching!
♪