♪ ♪
Hi, my name is Thalia,
and today we will learn what's new
in SF Symbols.
A symbol is one of the most effective
single pieces of graphic communication.
If you ever want to represent a feeling,
an object,
an action, or a concept,
symbols are an excellent way to do so.
Symbols are used frequently
and consistently,
becoming second nature to us.
Without relying on them,
we will find it very difficult
to navigate our surroundings.
As a result, they become
an essential part of interface design,
as symbols are an excellent way
to aid in communication.
A symbol can also bring many benefits
by being a means of interaction,
being space-efficient,
enhancing the aesthetic appeal,
and engaging us by being user-friendly.
What is so great about a symbol
is that it can transcend many languages.
They can be universal.
As a result, symbols can unite people
in communicating shared ideas,
helping engage with others on a deeper
level than is possible with just words.
At Apple, we care deeply
about making the user interface
and the overall experience better.
That's why we created SF Symbols,
an extensive library of iconography
designed to integrate seamlessly
with San Francisco, the system font,
providing a powerful
and flexible design resource
for creating experiences
on all Apple platforms.
SF Symbols is designed
with typography in mind.
It has awesome features
like different weights, scales,
outlined and filled variants,
encapsulated shapes, and alignments.
To learn more about these features
and when it's best to use them,
check out last year's video
from WWDC to get you up to speed.
Today, we will take a look
at the new repertoire
and the new categories in "New symbols."
In "Rendering modes," we will review
the benefits of adding colors to symbols,
and we have a new configuration to
help make the symbol's behavior automatic.
We have a new exciting feature
called "Variable Color."
Here we will explore the use of color
to make a symbol more dynamic.
And finally, we have a more efficient way
of annotating symbols.
We will learn more about it
in "Unified annotations."
So let's get started.
The SF Symbols library
keeps growing each year,
with newer categories
and symbols to choose from.
There are some great additions for Home,
including lights, blinds,
windows, and doors.
We even have light switches
and power outlets.
There are new furniture and appliances.
And new health symbols.
And this year, our fitness figures
are available for you to use.
We have expanded
the library's currency symbols.
And we have many new objects
to choose from.
And, of course,
we keep expanding our localized symbols,
with new ones covering different scripts
and right-to-left writing systems.
There are over 700 new symbols
to choose from,
making SF Symbols a library
of more than 4,000 unique symbols.
That is amazing.
With all these new additions,
we wanted to help you navigate
through all the symbols
in the SF Symbols app,
so we've added five new categories
that we think will be super helpful:
Camera & Photos,
Accessibility,
Privacy & Security,
Home, and Fitness.
And remember that in the app,
you can always create your own collection
with a selection of symbols
that best suits your needs.
Now, let's have a quick reminder
about the different rendering modes.
As you may know, in SF Symbols,
there are four rendering modes
to choose from,
each one providing a greater control
over how color is applied to a symbol.
Monochrome is the most neutral
of all the rendering modes.
It gives a uniform and consistent look,
and it is the rendering mode
that most closely reflects
the typographic nature of SF Symbols.
Hierarchical is the rendering mode
that provides a subtle emphasis
while having a single color hue
drive the overall aesthetic.
We can apply depth by highlighting
the most important shape of a symbol
or differentiate the foreground
and background elements.
That way, we create a visual hierarchy
by emphasizing
the essential part or parts of a symbol.
Palette uses two or more contrasting
colors to give elements of a symbol
more prominence and versatility,
allowing for the symbols to be customized
to integrate with the color palette
of the environment.
Palette helps the symbols
have a contrasting and unique look
without sacrificing the overall aesthetic.
And Multicolor is the rendering mode
that represents the intrinsic
or native color of a symbol.
This rendering mode uses a range of colors
that can be applied to a symbol
to describe the appearance of an object
in the physical world,
or it can use colors
to emphasize the meaning
that the symbol is trying to convey.
You can use Multicolor when
the symbols are very prominent in the UI,
as it will help create a color narrative
that will relate to the symbol forms.
Until now, if you didn't explicitly
specify a rendering mode,
you would get Monochrome by default.
But this year,
we've made it easier to display symbols
in a rendering mode that best highlights
each symbol's unique characteristics.
Symbols now feature
a preferred rendering mode,
which can vary between symbols.
And we call this behavior
Automatic Rendering.
When selected, it provides
the preferred rendering mode configuration
for each symbol
without having to specify it manually.
For example, when Automatic is selected,
the camera filters symbol
will opt into Hierarchical,
as it is the rendering mode that conveys
a more precise visual representation
by highlighting the opacities
that reference the translucency
of the physical camera lenses and filters.
Here's another example.
When Automatic is selected,
the SharePlay symbol participates
in the Hierarchical rendering mode.
This behavior lets the person's shape
stand prominently in the foreground
while the waves play a secondary role
in the background.
Again,
this emphasizes the symbol's concept,
as the SharePlay feature
is mainly a way to share
and connect with friends and family.
In most cases,
Automatic will be the best way to go.
But you always have to be aware
of the context.
For example, the AirPods Pro symbol
will render as Hierarchical
when Automatic is selected.
But in this context,
the symbol is very small
and has low contrast
when presented on this background.
Remember that rendering modes
can still be explicitly specified
for a uniform appearance
across symbols in a particular context.
So in this case,
Monochrome will be the best choice
as it is more legible
and has fewer details at small sizes.
So always make sure to specify the most
suitable rendering mode configuration.
The different rendering modes
apply color to symbols
to present visual solutions
for a wide range of circumstances.
Color is a powerful tool,
and we can explore it even further.
Some symbols are more dynamic in nature.
If we analyze their visual representation,
we can notice two main characteristics:
first, their paths or shapes convey
varying levels of strength,
and second,
they rely on color to communicate
their status changing over time.
This year,
we're expanding the use of color
by introducing a new feature
called Variable Color.
We've arranged the symbol's vector paths
into layers
and organized those layers
in sequential order,
creating a new method of
distributing color through these layers.
This allows us
to convey different levels of strength
or communicate a sequence over time,
which is dictated by the nature
of the design of the symbol.
One important thing to know is that,
in Variable Color,
some symbols have all paths
participating in the sequence,
but for other symbols,
only some of the paths may opt-in.
Let's look at a few examples.
With Variable Color,
we want the paths representing the iPhone
to opt-out of the variable sequence,
and we want to highlight the paths
representing the radio waves.
This will help differentiate the stages
that describe the levels of strength
of the radio signal of the phone.
It's important to know that we define
how we want to group the paths.
For example,
it wouldn't make much sense
to highlight the waves
from left to right in this case.
So instead, we can group the paths
following the sequence
that best conveys
the radio signal strength:
we have the two smaller waves
in one layer,
and we have the two bigger waves
in a different layer.
And as mentioned, the phone does
not participate in the variable sequence.
This time, let's look at a symbol
that we are very familiar with.
In most cases, this symbol is paired
with a built-in slider
that syncs with the states
represented in the symbol.
The waves highlight their paths
following a sequence
dictated by the user
controlling the slider,
increasing or decreasing the volume level.
Like in the iPhone example,
we have a path that doesn't participate
in the sequence,
which is the shape illustrating
the speaker,
and we have paths
that do participate in the sequence,
which are the three waves
that define the volume's strength:
low volume, mid-volume,
and high volume.
These paths are organized into layers,
and the selected layers opt-in
to the Variable Color feature.
We represent their strength
with percentage values:
0% is entirely off,
anything above 0%
will highlight part of the symbol,
and the whole symbol will be fully
highlighted as the value approaches 100%.
One important thing to know
is that Variable Color
is not meant to create depth;
instead, it's meant to highlight
a sequence of steps or stages
that the symbol can represent.
For example,
let's imagine I need a symbol
to represent people's capacity
inside a room.
This symbol looks great for that.
Let's look at it in more detail.
We don't want to highlight
just one part of the symbol.
Instead, we need to think of the symbol
as a sequence or a range.
My goal is to cover different states:
the room is empty,
the room has few people in it,
the room is half-full,
and the room is at full capacity.
So now, when I opt into Variable Color,
I can easily see
the graphic representation
of the different states
I'm trying to convey.
And there are no limits to how
many paths can opt into the feature.
There can be just one or many.
You decide what is the design strategy
that best suits your needs.
If you want to represent the strength
level of shapes that follow a sequence,
like waves, rays, ellipsis, and layers,
you can do so with Variable Color.
Variable Color is opacity based
and it's available in all rendering modes.
This year, we have made annotations for
custom symbols faster and easier to use
by creating a unified layer
structure across all rendering modes.
I love baking,
and I was thinking of designing an app
with cupcake-only recipes.
I wanted to create my own custom symbols,
so I've designed a set
that will cover my needs.
This will be an excellent opportunity
to show you how to annotate symbols
with the unified layer structure approach
and how to annotate symbols
that participate in Variable Color.
Let's use these two as an example.
Before we start annotating,
there are a few things to consider:
we need to keep the hierarchy in mind
and make sure we outline the z-order.
The z-order refers to the order
of the paths in a symbol along the z-axis.
There are also two new concepts
you need to be aware of:
Draw and Erase.
These are used to help define the way
a layer renders.
For example,
here we have the paths of a symbol
representing a square
overlapping a circle.
When selecting the layers
containing the square,
if we choose the Draw option,
the layer will draw the paths
contained in that layer.
If we choose the Erase option,
the layer will erase the path
containing the layer,
affecting how the symbol is rendered.
Now, let's start annotating the cupcake.
As a first step, we need to organize
the paths in layers
to create the desired hierarchy.
If I analyze it closely,
I can see four main shapes:
the frosting, the cupcake base,
the badge, and the plus.
You can add as many paths as needed
to a layer.
So in this case,
the frosting will be defined
by a layer with three different paths,
and the rest of the layers will be defined
by just one path each.
Organizing the shapes in this way
allows us to have more flexibility
when annotating one structure
for all rendering modes.
Now we have all the information
we need in one place
to customize the symbol as needed.
Now we can start annotating
all rendering modes.
Let's look at Multicolor first.
I already have the shapes set up,
so I just need to choose the right colors.
Red Velvet is my favorite flavor,
so I'll choose white for the frosting
and red for the cupcake base.
Now I will follow the same logic
that SF Symbols defines
for the plus badges in Multicolor:
green for the badge
and white for the plus.
Okay, this is looking great so far.
Now, let's focus on the badge.
This is where the unified annotation
approach is more apparent.
We already defined Multicolor.
Now let's look at Hierarchical
and Palette.
Because of the use of hierarchy
in this rendering modes,
I would expect the badge to be Primary,
which will render it white
on a black background, like this one.
Now I need the plus shape
to erase part of the badge.
This is where the Erase selection
is helpful.
I will be able to see the badge
rendered as desired
by erasing a part of a shape
when the layers overlap.
Finally, I just need
the Monochrome annotation.
Because there is no added complexity
in this rendering mode,
I will follow the same logic,
making the plus shape
erase part of the badge shape.
I'm almost done now.
I just need a few extra details.
For Hierarchical and Palette,
I just need to annotate
the rest of the cupcake shape
as Secondary.
For Palette, I will choose a color
to give a bit of contrast.
And for Monochrome,
I just need to make sure
I have the remaining shapes
opting into Draw.
That's all I need.
The cupcake is ready and customized
for all rendering modes.
Now let's look at the kitchen timer.
The paths represent the time passing,
and since this is a sequence,
it's a great candidate
to participate in Variable Color.
We can use the same strategy
to annotate this symbol,
but instead of grouping
the timer paths in one layer,
we need to split them
with each in its own layer.
This is because
we need to organize the shapes
to allow us to recreate the sequence
that will help us communicate
the different states of the symbol.
And remember that Variable Color
works in all rendering modes.
If you want to learn more about
the new Variable Color feature
and the SF Symbols app,
check out Paul's talk
"Adopt Variable Color in SF Symbols.”
You can find the new beta version
of the SF Symbols app,
where you can explore
the new unified annotation approach
and access the hundreds of new symbols
and fantastic new features.
Check out developer.apple.com/sf-symbols.
From Automatic Rendering behavior
to the Variable Color dynamic nature,
SF Symbols are an extremely powerful tool
to use
when implementing symbols in your UIs.
And this year,
SF Symbols is even more powerful,
with features that define
a spectrum of expression.
Thank you for joining today.
I hope you enjoyed learning
about what's new in SF Symbols.