[upbeat music]
- Hello and welcome.
My name is Marco Giordano,
and I'm with the GPU Software
Engineering team here at Apple.
In this session I'll talk to you about
how to scale workloads
across Apple M1 GPUs.
If you work on complex compute
workloads and want to know how to
take full advantage of Apple silicon
hardware and achieve great scaling,
this talk is the one for you.
I will start by discussing
compute scalability concepts
and how applications can naturally scale
performance across the M1 GPU family.
And then, I'll share
step-by-step "how-tos"
and talk about what tools are available
to maximize compute scaling
for your workloads.
Let's start by understanding
what scalability is
and why it is important
for your workload.
The Apple M1 GPU was designed
from the ground up to scale
and to let your workload achieve excellent
performance across the entire SOC family.
The same GPU supporting all Metal 3
features scales from your 8-core iPad
all the way to your 64-core Mac Studio.
To take advantage
of the high level of scaling,
having an app optimized for M1
is a great starting point.
Many prominent pro apps have already
been optimized for Apple M1
and have been experiencing
excellent scaling across all devices.
For example, here we have
Affinity Photo and DaVinci Resolve--
photo and video editors from
the post-production industry.
These apps are achieving great scaling.
Let's define what scalability really means
and how you can achieve "ideal" scaling.
GPU workload scalability
is the capacity to improve performance
with an increased number of GPU cores.
The chart on the right
shows application speed-up
with an increasing GPU cores count.
Linear proportion improvement
is considered ideal.
However, while working on your app,
you might notice a type of scaling
which hits a plateau and scales with
diminishing returns,
or doesn't scale at all
due to gaps in the GPU timeline.
Or you might see another type scaling
where the performance improves
but not uniformly across the stack
where the workload
is hitting some GPU limiters,
like here, between 24 to 32
or 48 to 64 cores.
Your goal is to get as close as
possible to linear scaling,
and I will show you
the tools and techniques
to identify bottlenecks and
achieve the result you want.
In the next section I will discuss the
approaches to maximize GPU scaling.
For every workload, you should
first identify where the bottleneck is.
Workloads can be limited either by
computation or bandwidth.
During the optimization process,
you might end up
bouncing between one and the other.
If you are computational-bound,
you might try to shift some of the load
to leverage memory
to reduce computation, or vice versa.
Bottlenecks can shift when you scale up.
One good solution could be
using Apple frameworks
like MPS or MPSGraph.
if you can leverage their primitives,
we made sure every compute kernel
runs best on all the hardware.
However, you
can't replace everything with MPS,
so it is critical to profile
and understand your workload.
I will first cover three items
that can help minimize GPU gaps:
Improve your work distribution,
eliminate GPU timeline gaps,
and atomics operation considerations.
Then I will explain
how to optimize for GPU limiters
by first investigating the effect of
compute grid shapes
and memory layouts of your workload
and finally by looking
at a specific example in Blender Cycles.
Start by focusing on minimizing GPU gaps.
This kind of scaling can be the result
of the GPU not being fully utilized,
with gaps in the GPU timeline
where the hardware is idle.
Let's see if we can improve scaling by
investigating work distribution.
Small workloads
usually do not saturate the whole GPU,
and kernel synchronization has its cost,
so both can prevent proper scaling.
It is very important to understand how
the workload gets mapped to the hardware,
so let's talk about it.
A workload is dispatched in the form
of a 3D grid of threadgroups.
Threadgroups are uniformly
distributed to the GPU cores
and have access to threadgroup memory,
which is limited in size,
but very fast, local to the GPU core.
A single threadgroup is further
broken down into SIMD-groups,
which are also known as waves or warps
in other compute dialects.
Checking the "threadExecutionWidth"
on the compute pipeline state object
will return the SIMD width,
and on all Apple GPUs,
it is equal to 32.
Threadgroups can have up to
1024 threads per threadgroup
and threads can share up to
32K of threadgroup memory.
To keep the GPU busy,
there should be enough work to do
on all the GPU cores.
Here is an example of a grid to dispatch.
Threadgroups are dispatched
to GPU Clusters
and distributed among GPU cores.
If there are too few threadgroups,
the workload
won't fully saturate the machine.
Here's how to fix this.
Start by computing
how many threads the workload produces
and roughly see if the dispatch
will saturate the whole machine.
For relatively complex kernels, 1K to 2K
concurrent threads per shader core
is considered a very good occupancy,
so take 1 to 2K threads per GPU core as
a rule of thumb.
Now you can compute if you have enough
work to fully saturate the hardware.
The table here shows the lowest
recommended number of threads
to saturate different SOCs.
Another thing to consider
would be avoiding
using unnecessarily large
threadgroup sizes.
Making threadgroups smaller will map
the load to the hardware more uniformly.
Using larger threadgroups might prevent
a more uniform distribution,
leading to imbalance in the GPU cores.
It's best to use
the smallest multiple of the SIMD width
that maps well to your workload.
By using smaller threadgroups,
the GPU has more opportunities
to better balance its workload.
Please always check your
kernel runtime performance
with Xcode or Instruments GPU Tools.
In this GPU capture, for example, there is
a kernel performing some computation.
Occupancy is pretty low,
which is unexpected.
The compiler statistics show
that max theoretical occupancy,
which is new in Xcode 14, is 100%.
This indicates there might not
be enough threads--and indeed,
we can see the algorithms starts
to dispatch fewer and fewer threads,
not saturating the machine anymore.
Low occupancy
might have several other causes.
To get all the details, check the
Metal Compute on MacBook Pro Tech talk.
OK, now that workload
is correctly distributed,
it's time to make sure the GPU
is always busy.
Under-utilizing the GPU
never leads to ideal scaling,
and the worst case
of under-utilizing is keeping it idle.
The GPU can be idle
because of GPU timeline gaps.
Consider this example.
Here is a workload
using only 50% of the GPU
due to work serialization
between CPU and GPU.
In this case, overall task duration
is the sum of CPU and GPU work
with no overlaps.
Doubling the GPU cores makes
the GPU track complete faster,
but the CPU track is not affected.
Overall performance increases only by 33%,
far from ideal scaling.
If the GPU cores are doubled again,
the workload is even faster on the GPU,
but overall latency is reduced by
only 60% compared to the original time!
So GPU cores scaling brings
diminishing returns in such cases.
This is far from ideal.
Let's fix it!
This Instrument trace from a M1 pro
shows big GPU timeline gaps,
and this will clearly prevent
proper scaling.
On M1 Ultra the same workload
is indeed a bit faster,
but the GPU idle time became higher
and the workload is not scaling well.
The big gaps are caused by
CPU synchronization
using the waitUntilCompleted
on the command buffer.
After changing the waiting logic
and removing serialization,
the GPU became fully utilized,
which is great.
Comparing the workload scaling
before and after,
we can state that the scaling
became much closer to the ideal scaling.
In the previous example,
it was possible to remove
CPU/GPU synchronization altogether,
however this is not always the case,
due to your application nature.
There are other approaches you can take
to reduce idle time.
Use MTLSharedEvents to signal the CPU,
pipeline more work,
consider using GPU-driven encoding,
and using concurrent dispatches.
So let's discuss those approaches
to minimize GPU timeline gaps.
Some of them might fit your workflow.
Waiting on the CPU for GPU completion
leads to not ideal scaling.
If your application
is using WaitUntilCompleted,
you might want to try to use
MTLSharedEvents instead.
MTLSharedEvents have lower overhead
and can help you reduce the timeline gaps.
The next thing to consider
is pipelining the workload.
If the algorithm has the data necessary
for the next batch to work on,
it's possible to encode one or
more batches in advance
before waiting on the MTLSharedEvents.
By doing so,
the GPU will not become drained
and will always have work to process.
If work can't be encoded
in advance on the same queue,
consider using a second queue
to overlap work.
Using multiple queues allows you
to submit independent work,
and they do not stall
the other submission thread
when waiting on an event.
This way, the GPU has the chance
to keep receiving and processing work.
In some cases, an algorithm
can encode work directly from the GPU.
Using indirect command buffer,
you can move the encoding of the
next batch directly on the GPU,
avoiding any need for synchronization.
For more details about indirect
command buffers, please check
"Modern Rendering with Metal."
The workload now removes
or minimizes expensive synchronizations
between CPU and GPU as much as possible.
But even with a busy GPU timeline,
scaling challenges may still exist.
Let's investigate.
This graph
is from an image processing workload
where images are processed
1 frame at a time.
A lot of back-to-back compute serial
dispatches can also limit scaling.
The GPU is busy,
but kernel synchronization
has a cost and additionally,
every dispatch has a small ramp up
where the threadgroups
are being distributed
and not yet saturating the cores.
Likewise, when threadgroups
finish and retire,
there might not be enough work
to fully saturate the cores anymore.
In this situation, the advice is to
overlap independent work when possible.
Let's see a visual example.
Here we have a workload processing
two images, one after the other.
Normally, kernels need to
synchronize between each other.
However, this is not the only
way to schedule work.
You can interleave independent work of
two images using concurrent dispatches.
Here the driver is able to
interleave different work,
thanks to concurrent dispatches.
We can see that the two kernels
that previously were back-to-back
are now separated
by some independent work.
However,
when you use MTLDispatchTypeConcurrent,
barriers must be put in manually.
Concurrent dispatches enable the
driver to pack the work more tightly,
hiding most of the synchronization cost
between dependent kernels,
as well as fill the ramp up
and tail end of the various kernels.
This optimization greatly improved
the workload performance
and scaling when
moving from M1 Max to M1 Ultra.
The workload runs 30% faster
with two images interleaved,
70% faster with 3 images in parallel,
compared to the previous scaling.
It's important to carefully consider
atomic operations that kernels are doing.
Let's make sure it is made in
the most efficient way.
Atomic operation
allows reading and writing data
from multiple threads in a safe manner.
Global atomics
are coherent across the whole GPU.
When many threads attempt to
read and write the same global value,
this leads to contention.
Increasing numbers of GPU cores doesn't
help and in fact leads to more contention.
Let's investigate how you can
improve atomics behavior
in an algorithm with an example.
Here is a reduction algorithm,
where all of the values in a buffer
will be summed up together.
The simplest approach is to perform
an atomic add operation
per thread in main memory.
However, this is not ideal because
that puts a great level of pressure
on a single value in main memory,
effectively serializing each memory write.
There are two things that the
hardware offers to help with
atomic memory contention:
Simd-group instruction
and threadgroup atomics.
SIMD instructions like prefix_exlusive sum
and simd_min and many more
allow to do operations and
exchange memory between registers
in a SIMD-group
without round trip to memory.
Threadgroup atomics are fulfilled by
the threadgroup memory.
Each GPU core
has its own threadgroup memory
allowing to scale
with the number of GPU cores.
Let's see how these two features
can help you improve your workload.
Here we have
the same reduction problem,
but this time it start using
a SIMD-group instruction,
an inclusive memory sum.
Such operation will leave the sum
of all the numbers in the SIMD-group
in the last thread.
The last thread from each SIMD-group
can then perform a single atomic add
in threadgroup memory to reduce
all SIMD-groups to a single value
in threadgroup memory.
In this way, using SIMD-group
instruction and threadgroup memory,
a whole threadgroup was reduced
without touching main memory at all.
Each group will be able to reduce
independently and in parallel.
Now that each threadgroup has
been reduced to a single value,
one thread per threadgroup can perform
a single atomic in main memory.
Not only this requires only
one atomic per threadgroup,
but since threadgroups complete
at different times,
it scatters atomics over time,
reducing memory contention even further.
To recap,
to maximize atomics effectiveness,
try to leverage memory locality,
try to use SIMD-group operation,
as well as to leverage
threadgroup memory atomics.
All this should greatly help reduce atomic
operation pressure that prevents scaling.
Now that GPU gaps are fixed, it's time
to see if the scaling is closer to ideal.
GPU Limiters in Xcode and
Metal System Trace help to optimize
any bottlenecks and inefficiencies in GPU
cores execution pipeline.
For example,
inefficient memory access patterns
always cause high Last Level Cache
or Memory Management Unit,
or MMU limiters,
and pretty low utilizations.
The first thing to address is the way
to tune threadgroups and memory layout.
The key in reducing memory span
and divergence
is to have a clear understanding
of the workload memory access pattern,
both spatially and temporally.
Once that's understood,
there are two possible tuning directions:
Re-organize the data layout to improve
data access locality,
or tune the access pattern
to better match the data layout
and improve memory and cache locality.
Let's see an example.
Here it is a memory buffer
where the data is laid out horizontally,
one row after the other.
However, when the compute kernel
is dispatched,
it is common to have a 2D like pattern
with square threadgroups
being distributed,
which is quite spatially localized.
This access pattern and data layout
is not great for data locality.
For example, when the first
SIMD-group access the data,
the requests are packed in a cache lines.
Most of the cache line won't be used,
however still
occupying space in the cache.
Re-arrange the data to fit
the access pattern better,
where, for example,
instead of spanning the whole row,
it is localized into stripes.
With this new memory layout,
a threadgroup will be able
to utilize
most of the data that will be requested
in a cache line, reducing divergence
and improving cache efficiency.
The other option is to change
how the 3D grid is dispatched
to better fit the current data layout.
Try to play with the threadgroup
size to create groups that map better
to your memory layout,
like a more rectangular shape,
for example.
In this case, the access pattern
is aligned with the memory layout,
giving a much higher cache efficiency.
You might need to experiment
to find the best fit for your workload.
Sometimes
you might need to make trade-offs,
sacrifice thread divergence
for memory locality, or vice versa,
change your data layout, grid dispatch,
or a combination of them all.
Every workload and access pattern
is different.
Now that you're aware of ways
to improve memory locality,
let's see a more concrete example
in Blender Cycles.
Cycles is Blender's physically-based
path tracer for production rendering.
It is designed to provide physically
based results out-of-the-box,
with artistic control and flexible
shading nodes for production needs.
This Instrument trace clearly shows low
Read Bandwidth, high Top GPU Limiter,
high Cache Limiter
and low Last Level Cache Utilization.
Keeping bandwidth and MMU limiters
in control is important for scaling.
If your Top limiter is the Last
Level Cache or MMU,
you need to reduce your memory span
and maximize data locality.
Let's see an example.
Cycles use sorting of data
to try to reduce divergence.
It does that by sorting
the ray hits by material type.
This is great to reduce thread divergence,
but it increases
spatial memory divergence,
resulting in a high MMU Limiter.
To help with this, we experimented with
partitioning the memory range
before sorting to increase data locality.
Let's visualize it.
When rays are shot into the scene
to simulate light traveling,
they hit objects and data is
collected into buffers.
At the point of intersection
we know many things--
the material type that was
hit, like glass, metal and so on,
the intersection position,
the ray, and more.
For simplicity,
let's focus on the material type only.
Here are the materials
in a buffer in memory.
Since a lot of data
is gathered per ray hit,
the memory buffer can become quite large.
To avoid moving a lot of memory around,
populate a list of indices
and sort those instead.
After the sort,
the indices for the same material type
are now packed closed together.
SIMD-groups can start loading
the indices and process the materials.
The SIMD-group will use the index
to load the corresponding data
in the original buffer.
However, the SIMD-group would be
reading across the whole memory span,
putting pressure on the MMU.
Let's investigate the new approach.
The memory range is partitioned
in an idealized partition
that simply won't
let indices from different partition mix.
When sorting, it is apparent that
the range of data accessed is contained
inside the partition instead of spanning
the full memory range like before.
It is a trade-off and balance between
thread divergence and memory divergence.
The number of partitions
and size that is ideal
is highly dependent on the workload.
You might have to experiment
to see which one works best.
Let's take another Metal System Trace
and let see if the workload improved.
Here we see the limiters and
utilizations for the optimized version.
The Top Performance limiter went down,
as well as Last Level Cache limiter.
As a result, bandwidth and shader runtime
substantially improved.
Let's see how much.
Top limiter and LLC limiter
reduced by around 20%.
That means data flow is more efficient.
GPU Read bandwidth increased
significantly,
allowing to push more data
to the GPU cores.
Overall, increasing
memory locality with this experiment
improved performance between
10 to 30%, depending on the scene.
This was just an example of many ways you
can try to improve memory access pattern.
Keep experimenting and optimizing
for the Top Performance Limiter.
The GPU tools have more useful
counters to tune for.
Xcode has a new theoretical occupancy
in the compiler statistic window.
Both Xcode and Instruments now have
several MMU related limiters and counters,
specifically a new MMU Limiter,
MMU Utilization Counter,
and MMU TLB Miss Rate Counter.
I have covered a lot of ground today.
I discussed GPU scalability and how
bottlenecks can shift when scaling up,
and how the tools can help
you find and fix scalability issues.
I also discussed how you might
need to experiment and make trade-offs
to get the best result
for your application.
I am looking forward to seeing all
your great apps scale amazingly well
on Apple silicon.
Thank you for watching.