♪ ♪
Hello everyone,
my name is Eric,
and I'm excited to tell you how to add
accessibility to your Unity games.
Accessibility is about
allowing everyone to use our products.
And today marks a huge leap forward
for accessible gaming
with the Apple Accessibility
plug-in for Unity developers.
We will focus on three Apple technologies
for making your games accessible.
VoiceOver is a screen reader which helps
users who are blind or low vision.
It reads items on the screen
and provides custom gestures
for users to interact with controls.
Switch control, which allows someone
with low motor control
to use an external switch
for device interaction.
And dynamic type,
which allows people to set
the text size
according to their reading ability.
To get started, clone the repository
and build all Apple's plug-ins
using the build script
in the root of the repository.
This will produce a Build folder
that is ready for integration
into your Unity projects.
Finally, add the Accessibility plug-in
to your own project
using the Unity Package Manager.
For more details, look at
the documentation in the repository
and watch the video about
all of Apple's Unity plug-ins,
called "Plug-in and play: Add Apple
frameworks to your Unity game projects"
Now that you have the plug-in,
I will guide you through three areas.
First is accessibility elements.
This allows you to add support
to assistive technologies
like VoiceOver or Switch Control
for your games.
Next is Dynamic Type.
We create this easy-to-use utility
that helps you scale text
according to user preferences.
And UI Accommodations.
These are utilities that helps you read
other user preferences.
Let's start with accessibility elements.
I built a simple card game
to help illustrate this concept.
You might see that you should tap
the "flip" button
to draw two random cards.
However, VoiceOver would not read
the text on screen
and an external switch
would not tap the button
since these are just pixels
on a screen right now.
We need to help the system understand
what can be interacted with.
Accessibility elements define the things
that assistive technologies can
interact with.
The text, cards, and the button on screen
should be accessibility elements.
And we can describe
each element with a label.
VoiceOver will read each label so the user
can understand what's on the screen.
And if the game supports
multiple languages,
we should localize these labels as well.
Now VoiceOver can describe
what is on the screen,
but it doesn't recognize that there's
a button that can be tapped.
We can use another property
called "traits"
to inform the system
of the element's type.
We should add the "Button" trait here.
Now, VoiceOver will read "Flip button,"
and an external switch
can control this button.
We can also add "Static Text" trait
on our text elements.
The "Static Text" trait is
usually given to labels and text areas
so that VoiceOver can provide
a better text interaction experience.
And there are many more traits
beyond "Button"
and "Static Text" that you can explore.
So what trait should we use for the cards?
Well, we don't need to use traits
on every accessibility element.
Our cards don't need any traits.
However, there's still a part of each card
that VoiceOver is not aware of:
the face value.
There's another property that we can
use for this called "Value."
Once we add a "Value" for each card,
VoiceOver will now read
"Card 1 with value 3 of clubs,
card 2 with value Ace of clubs."
And that's it.
Now that you understand the basics,
let's open Unity
to see how to add them to our project.
Here I am in a Unity Editor for this game.
I have already added
the Apple Accessibility
plugin to this project.
First we have the usual
scene objects like camera,
direct light, and a UI Canvas.
Under the canvas,
we have two text elements
and a button.
After that,
we have two game objects for cards.
Each is composed of two mesh components,
each rendering the front and back texture
for the card on each side.
Let's start by defining
our accessibility elements.
To do this, we need the Accessibility Node
component from this plugin.
Select all the objects in the hierarchy
that should be accessible.
And add the Accessibility Node component
to make them accessibility elements.
Next, we add labels.
Select the card object,
go to "Accessibility Node" component
on the right,
and find the "Label" field.
And make sure the label field checkbox
is checked to provide a custom label.
Then type "Card 1."
And the same for Card 2.
Text and buttons need labels too,
but we don't have to provide
an explicit accessibility labels for them
if we are using the standard controls
from Unity UI.
The plug-in already has
default implementations for those.
Next, we need
to add a trait to our button.
Select the flip button
and change the "Traits"
from "None" to "Button."
Select the two text elements...
And change "Traits" to "static text."
Great.
Lastly, we need to set an accessibility
Value for the card faces.
Since the cards are randomly drawn,
I need to add a script
to set the Value dynamically.
Select the two cards and add
a new script called AccessibleCard.
First, in one of my other C Sharp files,
I already have an enum for all
the card faces called Playing Card.
In my new AccessibleCard mono
behavior script,
we have a variable for the card type
and a boolean
for whether the card is facing up or down.
So now let's add
accessibilityValue to these cards.
First, we get the accessibilityNode
component attached to this gameObject.
Next, set the accessibilityValue
delegate to a function
that returns the card face value
dynamically.
Inside this function,
if the card is covered,
we return the "covered"
for the accessibilityValue.
Or if not covered,
we will enumerate all card faces
and return a description for each,
like "Ace of Spades."
And that's it.
Now let's build our project
and see it in action.
Here's our game.
Let's turn on VoiceOver.
Automated voice: VoiceOver on.
Eric's Game.
Card 2, covered.
Eric: I could swipe right
to move to the next element.
Automated voice: Card 1, covered.
Eric's card game.
Flip the cards.
Flip. Button.
Eric: You see that all five objects
are now accessible through VoiceOver,
which is awesome.
To tap the button when VoiceOver is on,
do a double-tap.
Automated voice: Flip.
Eric: Let's check the cards again.
Automated voice: Card 1, Two of Clubs.
Card 2, Ace of Clubs.
Eric: VoiceOver now reads
the updated card faces correctly.
Cool.
So we just made our game accessible
to millions of VoiceOver users
who can now fall in love with it.
And people who use external switch control
can also play our game.
So that was accessibility elements.
Next, let's talk about Dynamic Type.
Games can be difficult to play
for many people
because text is too small to read.
On iOS and tvOS, everyone can choose
the right text size
for their reading ability in Settings.
With the Accessibility Plugin,
you can read this setting
to make sure the text in your game
is displayed at the expected size.
Let's take a look at our game example
to see how we can use Dynamic Type.
Create a mono behavior script
called DynamicTextSize.cs.
In the start function, first store
the default text size into a variable.
Then inside the OnEnable function,
subscribe to setting changed event
using AccessibilitySettings.
onPreferredTextSizesChanged.
This allows us to update the UI as soon
as the user changes the text setting.
Next, inside the settingsChanged function,
first read the
PreferredContentSizeMultiplier.
Then multiply by your original text size
and assign it back to the text element.
Inside Unity Editor,
select all game objects
that have a Text element.
And add the DynamicTextSize component
that we just created.
Now our game is all set
for Dynamic type support.
Before we see the result in action,
first I am going to show you
a trick to quickly test
Dynamic Type in your games.
Open Settings, and find Control Center.
Scroll down until you see Text Size,
and add it to Control Center.
Now we can adjust text sizes quickly
by opening Control Center
and change the text size options.
Great–as I change the text size,
our game adjusts font sizes in real time.
The text percentage value shown
in Control Center
is exactly what we are reading
from that multiplier.
You can also adopt this setting
on non-text objects.
For example,
I can swap the card face assets
to Large Print when the size is increased.
First I create a script called
DynamicCardFaces.
Then same thing as before,
subscribe to the TextSizeChanged event.
Instead of reading a multiplier,
I read an enum of text size category
that is mapped to the ticks
on the Control Center slider.
I could swap the asset whenever
someone selects a larger text size.
And I simply choose
between a regular material
and a large print material.
Now if we select a really large size...
Users would see a large print version
of the cards,
which are great card faces that are much
easier to read for people with low vision.
Lastly, I want to talk to you
about UI accommodation settings
that you can access with this plug-in.
The first setting is Reduce Transparency.
When this setting is on,
the background is turned opaque,
instead of a blur or transparent effect.
It can help improve legibility when
those effects makes text hard to read.
To check this preference, call
AccessibilitySettings.
IsReduceTransparencyEnabled.
Next, the Increase Contrast setting.
Notice how the switches have
a darker grey that helps them stand out,
making controls easier to recognize
across the entire device.
You can increase contrast
for your own UI when this is enabled
by checking this setting using
AccessibilitySettings.
IsIncreaseContrastEnabled.
Next, the Reduce Motion setting.
Some people are sensitive to motion
like we have in this card flip animation.
We should remove that animation
when Reduce Motion is enabled.
Let's look at the code to do this.
In our CardController script,
we have this Flip function.
First we check if user's
reduce motion setting is on.
If not on, we should flip the card by
invoking an animation through Coroutine.
Otherwise we just set the rotation,
and no animations.
And that's it.
Now people who are sensitive to motion
would enjoy our game.
To recap, get started
with the Apple Accessibility plugin
by cloning the GitHub repository
linked in this session's resources.
Add accessibility elements
so that people can use VoiceOver
and Switch Control with your games.
Adapt your text size with Dynamic Type.
And check for UI accommodations
so everyone can have a great experience
with your game.
Thank you so much for joining me.
We look forward to seeing how you make
games available for everyone
with a great accessibility experience.