[spacey music]
Ernest: Hello and welcome.
My name is Ernest,
and I'm a software engineer
on the ScreenCaptureKit team.
Over the past couple of years,
we all have been more reliant
on remote collaboration,
which often involves screen sharing.
On top of that,
streaming gameplay using
a recording application like OBS Studio,
and content creation as a whole,
has been a continually growing area
for people's education and entertainment.
With this in mind,
we created a framework
that meets developers' needs
for performant and robust screen capture.
Meet ScreenCaptureKit!
ScreenCaptureKit is a brand-new framework
on macOS
that is designed to help you create
your application's
screen sharing experience.
ScreenCaptureKit provides APIs that
will let you choose the content
you want to capture,
with developer controls and toggles
for your application's needs.
And all of the filters and controls
can be updated on the fly.
The framework delivers
high quality and performance
up to the native resolution
and frame rate of your display,
all while having privacy
in mind with global safeguards.
In this session, I'll help you get started
with the ScreenCaptureKit framework.
Once you have the basics down,
take a look
at "Take ScreenCaptureKit
to the next level"
for more advanced topics.
First, I'll go over the key features
of the framework.
Next, I'll cover
the main ScreenCaptureKit constructs
in an API overview.
Then, I'll show you how to set up
your stream
with a filter and configuration.
And finally,
I'll walk you through how to stream
video and audio samples
to your application.
Let's start with the key features
of ScreenCaptureKit.
ScreenCaptureKit lets you specify
the type of content you want to share
or filter out.
You can capture screen content
from any combination of displays,
applications, and windows
as well as the audio that goes with it.
ScreenCaptureKit supports
a variety of developer controls,
including pixel format, color space,
frame rate, and resolution,
and on the audio side, controls
such as sample rate and channel count.
And all of these filters
and configurations
can be adjusted on the fly,
allowing for more flexibility
in application design.
And in order to deliver audio samples
up to 48kHz stereo
and video samples at up to your display's
native resolution and frame rate,
ScreenCaptureKit is performance focused
and leverages the power of Mac GPUs
with a lower CPU overhead
than existing capture methods.
And of course, ScreenCaptureKit
is built with privacy in mind,
providing global privacy safeguards
for all applications using the framework.
The framework will require consent
before capturing video and audio content,
and the choice will be stored
in the Screen Recording privacy setting
in system preferences.
Now that you've seen
what ScreenCaptureKit is all about,
I'll show you some
of the most important concepts in the API.
The ScreenCaptureKit framework
is centered on SCStream.
SCStream handles control methods
like start and stop
and is created along with
SCShareableContent,
SCContentFilter,
and SCStreamConfiguration.
These objects determine
what content you want to capture
and how you want to capture it.
Once created and started,
media samples will be delivered
to your application
through the SCStreamOutput protocol.
I'll explain more about that a bit later.
Now, I'll show you how to use the API
to set up a stream in your application.
Here are the objects you want to get
familiar with when setting up your stream.
These are the objects that
will determine what you capture
and the quality
and the performance of the capture.
The first one I want to go into
is SCShareableContent.
On this desktop, there are windows,
applications, and the display itself.
ScreenCaptureKit has
a corresponding class for each of these
that you can use to build
the content you want to share.
First, let's take a look at SCDisplay.
ScreenCaptureKit categorizes displays
as SCDisplays, with read-only properties
including display identifier
and size properties width and height.
Within the display, there may be
many different running applications,
and each of these will have
a corresponding SCRunningApplication.
SCRunningApplications have
read-only properties
for application-level information
such as bundle identifier,
application name,
and its process identifier.
In the example here,
there will be an SCRunningApplication
for Keynote and Safari.
And, of course,
these applications have windows.
These windows will have
a corresponding SCWindow
with read-only properties
that define the window
such as window id, frame, title,
and if the window
is on screen or minimized.
The SCWindow will also have
an owning application.
In this case, both Safari SCWindows
will have
the same Safari owning application.
SCWindows, SCRunningApplications,
and SCDisplays combine together
to give you the possible content you can
share
in SCShareableContent.
You can get a list
of all shareable content on the device,
or you can specify certain parameters.
Suppose you'd like to list
all the applications and windows
that are on screen
so people can choose
which ones they'd like to share.
Well, ScreenCaptureKit has
a simple API for that.
This short code snippet
is from the capture sample code available
on developer.apple.com.
Only windows that are on screen
are returned with the SCShareableContent,
which includes the associated SCWindows,
SCApplications and SCDisplays.
And now that you have
the shareable content,
you can create a filter.
There are two main types
of SCContentFilters:
A display independent window filter,
which will capture the window
as you move it across multiple displays,
and display dependent filters,
with options to include or exclude
specific windows and applications.
A quick note here is that audio capture
can only be filtered
at an application level.
I'll walk you through some examples
to demonstrate what a filter is
Imagine you're only interested
in sharing a keynote window.
You would choose
a display independent window filter
that will capture the window
as it moves across displays.
Even if you wanted to share
all of the content on a display,
there may be certain content
you'd like to exclude.
For example, you'll want to avoid
the hall of mirrors effect
by excluding your own capture application.
There may also be sensitive information
in a particular window or application,
and you'd want to exclude that
from the capture as well.
All these scenarios will be handled
by SCContentFilter,
so let's jump into the code
and see how to do this.
Here is the code snippet
I showed previously.
After the shareable content is queried,
the code looks for the application
with the same bundleIdentifier
as the capture sample app.
Then, a display dependent content filter
excludes the app from the stream.
In addition to content filters,
ScreenCaptureKit provides quality
and performance controls
that can be adjusted per stream.
These controls can be set
in SCStreamConfiguration.
Some of the video controls include
output resolution, frame rate,
and whether or not
to show the mouse cursor.
On the audio side, you can enable audio,
change the sample rate,
and adjust the channel count.
I'll take you through some scenarios where
these parameters might come into play.
When sharing low-motion screen content
where text clarity is important,
such as from notes or a spreadsheet,
set output resolution of the capture
to 4k, at 10 frames per second.
And because the content doesn't have
any audio,
you can leave audio disabled.
But in the case of high motion content,
such as sharing a video
of a recent vacation,
you should prioritize
frame rate over resolution
by lowering the output resolution
to 1080p
and increasing
the frames per second to 60.
And since cursor movement
could be distracting,
you may want to hide the cursor.
You can also have audio capture enabled
for a more immersive experience.
All of these controls can be set
through the different properties
in SCStreamConfiguration.
Here's one possible configuration
for sharing high motion content.
In this code sample, the output resolution
of the capture is set to 1080p.
Then, the minimum frame interval
is set to 1/60 in order to capture
at 60 frames per second.
And finally, the stream configuration
will hide the cursor.
On the audio side, first enable audio
by setting capturesAudio to true,
then, set the sample rate to 48kHz
and the channel count to 2.
With an SCContentFilter
and an SCStreamConfiguration,
you have the information you need
to set up screen capture
to your application's needs.
Together, you can now create an SCStream.
Let's go back to the overview.
You will need to initialize the stream
with your desired filter
and configuration.
And you can also pass in
an optional delegate
in order to handle errors.
Once set up, you can call start capture,
and ScreenCaptureKit will provide
the SCStream with samples
when they are available.
With a filter and configuration created,
starting a stream in code is easy.
Let me show you.
Once again, with the filter
and configuration you want,
you can initialize an SCStream object.
In the capture sample project, self
is passed as the error handling delegate.
With an SCStream created,
you can now call startCapture.
Once you've initialized
and started a stream,
the next step is to get media samples
to your application.
Audio and video samples are
sent to your application
in the form of CMSampleBuffers.
In order to get those media samples
from your stream,
you will need to add an object
that implements the
SCStreamOutput protocol to your stream.
When you add your stream output,
you may also specify a handler queue.
This may be useful if you want
your sample to be delivered
in a particular queue
without needing an extra dispatch.
If you don't specify a queue,
a default queue will be used.
With a stream started and an output added,
ScreenCaptureKit will provide a callback
when a new sample is available.
Now, I'll show you how
to get media samples in code.
Here's an implementation
of the SCStreamOutputProtocol
which will be called
when new media samples are available.
ScreenCaptureKit delivers
these samples as CMSampleBuffers
and provides the stream and sample type.
After implementing sample buffer handlers,
you simply need to add your streamOutput.
And with that, media samples
from the stream,
with the content you want,
in the format you want,
will be delivered to your application.
ScreenCaptureKit delivers samples
in the form of a CMSampleBuffers,
so let's talk a little bit
about how to use them.
On the video side,
the CMSampleBuffer is IOSurface backed.
ScreenCaptureKit
also provides attachments
to the CMSampleBuffer
in SCStreamFrameInfo.
This attachment provides information
about the video sample you're receiving.
Check frame status
for the current state of the stream.
A complete frame status indicates
that there is a new video frame.
An idle frame status
means the video sample hasn't changed,
so there's no new IOSurface.
Otherwise, the sample provided
is like any CMSampleBuffer,
so you can use existing
CMSampleBuffer utilities.
ScreenCaptureKit includes APIs
to help you get filtered screen
audio and video content.
On top of that,
the framework provides
many different developer controls
to suit your application's needs.
I also covered some basics
to get you started
with the different screen capture
experiences you will create.
With the release of ScreenCaptureKit,
older capture frameworks
CGDisplayStream and CGWindowList
will be deprecated in the future.
I hope you're as excited as I am
with this introduction
of ScreenCaptureKit!
When you're ready to look
at more advanced topics,
please hop over to "Take ScreenCaptureKit
to the next level."
Thanks for watching!
[spacey music]