♪ ♪
Drew Haas: Hi there.
My name is Drew Haas,
and I'm an engineer
on the Accessibility team.
I'm here to talk about how to create
accessible Single App Mode experiences.
Single App Modes let you
as a developer serve your users
in really unique ways
by restricting certain behaviors
on iOS and iPadOS devices.
Namely, these modes let you
lock the device to a single app.
Depending on the mode,
the restrictions are either initiated
by the system
or by your app.
This is great because you get to control
the timing between a restricted state
and an unrestricted state.
You're also able to apply additional
restrictions on top of single app mode,
like whether auto-lock is enabled or not.
Let's remember to consider
accessibility use cases.
You should make sure people
who rely using on accessibility features
have the ability to turn them on
so they can use them,
even if the device is restricted.
This ensures your app is inclusive
to people using assistive technologies.
I want to talk about some examples
of when to use Single App Mode.
Let's say you're developing an app
where customers order food or drinks
at a restaurant or event.
Or an app that will be used
in a medical office,
where patients are handling a device
shared by the medical staff
to fill out their information.
Or even an app that helps facilitate
a test for students in a classroom.
These are all scenarios
where Single App Mode restrictions
help create a focused environment
for the user.
And did you know your app
might be used in Single App Mode
even if you didn't write code for it?
That's right,
Guided Access is an accessibility feature
that lets users put any app
in Single App Mode.
First, I'll talk about Guided Access
and go over some considerations
you should have
for when people use your app
during this mode.
Next, I'll talk about single app modes
that you initiate programmatically
from within your app,
by adopting certain APIs and frameworks.
And finally, we provide accessibility API
designed for use
specifically during Single App Mode.
Use this API to turn on or off
certain accessibility features
to create a seamless
and accessible experience.
Let's dive in first with Guided Access.
To start Guided Access,
first make sure it's turned on
in accessibility settings,
then open the app you want to lock on to.
Triple click the side button
to perform the accessibility shortcut.
This shows the guided access workspace,
where you configure system restrictions.
Then tap Start to begin.
Now the device is in a restricted state.
It's locked to the frontmost app,
and the restrictions I configured
in the options menu are applied.
This helps creates a guided experience
for people with cognitive disabilities.
To exit Guided Access,
all you need to do
is perform the accessibility shortcut
again.
The options menu lets you restrict
touch interaction, display motion,
and the software keyboard,
as well as hardware button events,
like the volume buttons,
and the sleep/wake button.
Having a controlled environment in
this way is especially helpful
for people with cognitive disabilities,
but this feature is also enjoyed
by a range of users,
from accessibility users
to parents of young kids
who could all benefit from having
easy access to these device restrictions.
This is where you come in!
UIAccessibility API lets you
create custom restrictions
to tailor the experience
of your app during Guided Access.
Use this an opportunity
to restrict or adjust areas of your app
where someone with a cognitive disability
might feel lost
or overwhelmed with options.
I want to share some design considerations
for cognitive accessibility.
These are principles you should follow
all the time if possible,
but you should especially follow them
in your app during Guided Access.
First is to be forgiving of errors.
Try to mitigate errors before they happen,
by warning users before they perform
significant or irreversible actions,
like deleting or modifying account
information or payment information.
You should aim to reduce
dependence on timing
to act on certain things in your app,
because not everybody
processes information at the same speed.
Using timed alerts
or automatically performing actions
after a short time-out
makes your app harder to use.
And you should always, always,
give the user a chance to confirm
before making a payment,
this includes apps
that have one-tap purchases.
Designing your app with these
considerations promotes independence
for accessibility users.
I want to show you an example.
I'm working on an app
called Reading Observatory
which helps people keep track of how much
they've read during the week.
The home page of my app shows
reading progress and has two buttons:
account settings,
and a continue reading button.
I've added a custom restriction for my app
that will lock the Account Settings button
while Guided Access is active.
This gives my app a unique experience
under this restriction,
to help prevent users from getting lost
somewhere else,
like buried in account settings,
where they may make unintended changes.
This will also reduce the amount of times
someone may get stuck
and need help getting back on track
with the primary purpose of my app,
which is reading.
To do this, first conform your AppDelegate
to the UIGuidedAccessRestrictionDelegate
protocol.
You need to let Guided Access know
about each restriction
by providing an array of identifiers.
I've got just one.
You're also required to give
a user-facing title for each,
as well as an optional description
if you need to provide additional detail.
These strings will show up
in the options menu.
Finally, implement the
guidedAccessRestriction
(withIdentifier:didChange:) method
to receive a callback
when a restriction is toggled.
This is where your app could post
a notification to perform logic
which would accommodate
the restriction,
like turning off user interaction
for certain buttons
or introducing some of those
design principles from earlier.
Check if a custom restriction
is enabled at any time by calling
guidedAccessRestrictionState
(forIdentifier:) on UIAccessibility.
All of the system provided restrictions
and your custom app-based restrictions
make Guided Access extremely configurable,
which is why it is a fantastic
accessibility feature.
Guided Access can be found
in Accessibility Settings.
Other Single App Modes are available
for you to programmatically enter
a restricted session on device.
They share similarities with
Guided Access, but the key difference
is just that: you're programmatically
entering this mode.
This means there's plenty to talk about
for setting up,
starting, and customizing
your Single App Mode session.
Remember each of those scenarios
from earlier?
An iPad being used as a restaurant kiosk,
at a medical office, in a testing
environment–
single App Modes are the right solution
for all of these situations.
Even though each may have
slightly different needs,
they all benefit from locking the device
to a single app.
This prevents people from swiping
to go home,
modifying things in Settings,
or even looking something up in Safari.
Let's go through each of these
and I'll recommend a Single App Mode
based on the restrictions we'll need.
The first mode is the most basic,
and it's the easiest to deploy.
It's simply called Single App Mode.
This is the right solution
for when you have a device
that you intend to stay in a single app
pretty much in perpetuity.
It remains locked in-app after reboot,
and there is no manual intervention
needed for upkeep.
Great for a low-involvement approach.
A few considerations, though!
The device must be supervised.
Supervision tools
let you lock a high volume of devices
into Single App Mode at once,
so this is a very scalable solution
if you're working with a lot of devices.
Apple Configurator lets you manage
supervised devices in many ways,
including putting them in Single App Mode.
Select a supervised device, then under
Advanced, select Start Single App Mode.
The last thing you need to do
is select an app.
Once you do, it will launch automatically,
and lock into the foreground.
There is no other way to exit this mode.
As I mentioned, it will stay locked
to this app even upon reboot
unless you end Single App Mode
through your management software.
Autonomous Single App Mode
is better suited for situations
where a restricted state
is entered and exited often.
For example, at a medical office
where a new patient fills in
their information on an iPad,
and then hands it back to the staff.
This means there is manual intervention
between restrictions.
Your app gets to do this by itself,
by using a single API method call
to get in and out.
Again, considerations–
the device must be supervised,
and the app that wants to use this API
must be allow listed
on the device's configuration profile,
or the request to lock will fail
because it's not privileged.
The all-powerful method is
requestGuidedAccessSession(enabled:complet
ionHandler:) on UIAccessibility.
Hey, that looks familiar! Right?
This API taps right into the roots
of Guided Access.
You're essentially programmatically
entering and exiting this feature
with this code.
Isn't that cool?
That's because Guided Access
serves as the foundation
for other single app modes to exist.
Bet you didn't know that!
Let's see how this code might work
in action.
I have a method each for entering
and exiting this mode
that I'll call when I'm ready.
They're performing different actions
like starting a new patient sign-up sheet
when we enter a restricted state
and then bookkeep their information
upon exiting.
Of course, you'll want to properly address
the result of the completion handler
to know if something goes wrong.
If so, you may want to give
an alert to the user
and hold off on continuing the experience
forward, so they can try again.
Check if Autonomous Single App Mode
is enabled at any time
by calling isGuidedAccessEnabled
on UIAccessibility.
Also observe the
guidedAccessStatusDidChangeNotification
to trigger any additional code
when entering or exiting this mode.
And remember that the app which wants
to use this API must
have the proper supervision and
management,
including allowlisting the app's bundle ID
as an allowed application
for Autonomous Single App Mode.
And finally, assessment mode.
This is the right mode when your app aims
to prevent unfair advantages,
by restricting certain features
during testing.
Turn off autocorrect, spellcheck,
and single app mode locks to the app
so the test taker can't access
outside notes or resources.
Recently these frameworks
have been unified for iOS and macOS,
when we introduced the Automatic
Assessment Configuration framework!
To use this, the device does not need
to be supervised like the previous modes,
but you do need to apply to Apple for
an assessment entitlement for your app.
More information about applying
for the entitlement can be found
in the developer documentation.
My colleague Josh has
a fantastic WWDC session
that explains how to use the Automatic
Assessment Configuration framework,
including tons of code examples
and documentation resources.
Please go check it out.
Once you know which single app
mode solution is right for you,
or if you already have a solution working,
remember to keep in mind that people using
assistive technologies do use your apps.
There may be extra steps you need to take
to make this experience accessible.
In our classic example of an iPad
being used as a restaurant kiosk,
Let's consider that a blind customer
comes by to order.
If the device is plainly locked into
Single App Mode, then we have a problem.
You wouldn't be able to open Settings,
head to Accessibility,
and turn on VoiceOver for this customer.
So what can you do?
Apple Configurator and other
device management software
help you configure options
for Single App Mode.
A handful of accessibility features are
available for you to have always enabled,
and the Accessibility Shortcut,
also known as "triple-click" menu,
is configurable to let users
quickly toggle accessibility features
like VoiceOver, Zoom,
Invert Colors,
AssistiveTouch, and Voice Control.
When these features are always on,
or when they're assigned
to the accessibility shortcut,
you enable people who rely on these
technologies
to use them while they navigate your app.
It's pretty easy to set this up,
so don't miss your chance to do so.
But those options have to be configured
before entering Single App Mode.
So what about during Single App Mode?
Use API on UIAccessibility
to toggle certain accessibility features
directly with code.
It's a great alternative to toggling
a feature with the accessibility shortcut,
which is helpful when device is encased
in a kiosk enclosure
that blocks off hardware buttons.
We made this API so it's easy for you
to turn off accessibility features,
so you can do some housekeeping
and reset state between users.
To do this, call configureForGuidedAccess
on UIAccessibility.
You must pass in
a compatible accessibility feature,
and whether you want it enabled or not.
This works for Zoom,
VoiceOver, Invert Colors,
AssistiveTouch, and Grayscale.
So whether your app has custom
restrictions for Guided Access
or you build your entire experience
around Single App Modes,
it's important to know how to make sure
it's accessible.
The wrong kind of restrictions
make something less accessible to use,
so always consider the experience of
someone with a disability using your app.
I've shown you the APIs you need to create
an accessible Single App Mode experience.
Now go make something great,
and accessible!