[upbeat music]
- Hi! My name is Andrei.
I'm a GPU software engineer
with Metal Frameworks team.
Today, I'm excited to introduce to you
Metal mesh shaders.
Mesh shaders is the new
flexible pipeline in Metal
for GPU-driven
geometry creation and processing.
It improves on the vertex/fragment
pipeline, adding a lot of flexibility
and removing the limitations
of per-vertex processing.
It has multiple applications,
, but not limited to:
fine-grained geometry culling,
scalable procedural geometry
creation on the GPU,
and allowing custom geometry inputs
such as compressed vertex streams,
meshlets and complex procedural
algorithms.
I would like to
cover these three things today.
First, I will go over what
Metal mesh shaders are.
Then, I would like to tell you about
two mesh shaders use cases.
Mesh shaders are great
for generating procedural geometry
such as rendering procedural hair.
Mesh shaders also help
improve scene processing and rendering.
A primary example of this
is using mesh shaders
to implement
GPU-driven meshlet culling.
Let's start with introducing mesh shaders.
Here is the Stanford Bunny,
which represents a typical mesh
that you could render on the GPU.
In order to render this mesh,
the vertex and index data
would first have to be placed
in the device memory.
You would then have to use render
command encoder to execute a draw call.
A traditional rendering pipeline
consists of three fundamental stages:
A programmable vertex shader stage,
a fixed-function rasterization stage,
and a programmable fragment shader
stage.
The vertex shader stage
would take geometry
from device memory
as an input and process it.
The rasterizer would produce
screen space fragments,
and the fragment shader would
shade them to produce the final image.
This pipeline has been, and still is,
serving its purpose extremely well.
However, it lacks flexibility
and has certain limitations.
Let's step through an example.
Imagine that you want to generate
some procedural geometry on the GPU.
For example, you've decided
to add procedural fur to this bunny.
Let me show you how this task is handled
by the traditional geometry pipeline.
Traditionally,
in order to generate procedural geometry,
you would also need to have
a compute command encoder
that would perform
a compute kernel dispatch.
The compute kernel would take
the original mesh as an input,
generate procedural geometry and
output it back into device memory.
You would then use a render command
encoder to execute a draw call
that would take procedural geometry
as an input and produce a final image .
Not only does this approach require
two command encoders,
it also requires you
to allocate additional memory
to store the procedural geometry.
In case of indirect draw calls
or high expansion factors,
the amount of this memory can
be quite high and hard to predict.
There is also a barrier between the two
encoders, serializing work across the GPU.
Metal mesh shaders addresses all
of those issues.
Mesh shaders is a new geometry pipeline
that replaces the vertex shader stage
with two new programmable stages--
the object shader stage
and the mesh shader stage.
In this example, the object shader
would take geometry as an input ,
process it and output some data--
which we call "payload"--
to the mesh shader.
It is up to you
to decide what this data is.
The mesh shader, in turn, would use
this data to generate procedural geometry.
This procedural geometry
would only exist inside the draw call,
so it would not require you
to allocate any device memory.
It would be pipelined
straight to the rasterizer
and then to a fragment shader
that would produce the final image.
Mesh draw calls are performed using
the same type of render command encoder
as the traditional draw calls.
Mesh draw calls and traditional
draw calls can be mixed and matched.
Now, let's take a look at
two new programmable stages.
In contrast to vertex shaders,
object and mesh shaders
are similar to compute kernels.
They are launched
in grids of thread groups.
Each thread group is a grid
of individual threads that,
like compute threads,
can communicate with each other.
Additionally, each object thread group
can spawn a mesh grid
and programmatically define the size of
the mesh grid it launches,
providing plenty of flexibility.
Each object thread group passes
payload data to the mesh grid it spawns.
As the name suggests,
the object stage processes objects.
Object is an abstract concept that
you can define according to your needs.
It can be a scene model,
a part of a scene model or,
for example, a region of space where
you want to generate procedural geometry.
The mesh stage is designed
to build meshes
and send geometry data
directly to the rasterizer.
The next two examples will cover
the relation between objects and meshes.
The first one is using mesh shaders
to implement hair rendering.
To simplify this task, instead of
the Bunny model, I'll use a simple plane.
To generate a patch of hair,
I'll divide the input geometry into tiles,
where each tile will calculate
a level of detail
and the number of strands
it needs to produce,
and then generate
each individual strand of hair.
Let me show you how to
procedurally generate hair on this plane
using mesh shaders.
The plane can be split into tiles,
where each tile corresponds
to an object threadgroup.
Each object threadgroup will
calculate the number of hair strands
and generate the curve control
points for each strand.
This will become the payload.
Our object threadgroup then launches
a mesh grid,
where each mesh threadgroup
represents a single strand of hair.
Each mesh threadgroup
outputs the mesh to the rasterizer.
The new geometry pipeline
allows you to map
your geometry processing
closely to hardware
and enables you to take full advantage
of all the threads your GPU offers.
In a mesh render pipeline,
input geometry is split into tiles
for the object shader grid.
Each object shader threadgroup
can independently generate a payload
and launch a mesh grid.
Each mesh shader threadgroup from
the grid generates a metal::mesh
which is further processed in
the rest of the rendering pipeline.
Let's take a closer look at
the data produced by each of those stages.
The payload is defined
in the object shader.
Each object threadgroup
passes the customized payload
to the generated mesh grid
that an object threadgroup spawns.
In the case of hair rendering, the payload
consists of the curve control points.
Meanwhile, the mesh shader
outputs vertex and primitive data
through a new metal::mesh type, which
I will discuss in further detail in a bit.
The object and mesh stages
output mesh data
that is consumed by rest of the pipeline.
Similar to the vertex output
from the traditional pipeline,
the mesh data is first
consumed by the rasterizer,
then the fragment shader executes.
Let's take a deeper dive into how
to set up a hair rendering mesh pipeline.
First, the plane that is to be
covered in hair is split into tiles,
where each tile corresponds
to an object threadgroup.
The object threadgroup
determines the mesh grid size
and initializes the payload data
that it passes to the mesh grid.
In this case, the tile has six strands
of hair and generates a 3x2 mesh grid,
along with a curve
payload data for each strand.
Each threadgroup can generate
unique mesh grid sizes.
For the next threadgroup,
only four strands of hair
need to be generated,
so a 2x2 mesh grid is set
along with initializing curve
payload data for 4 strands.
This is how the object shader
that implements this approach looks like.
The object attribute
has been added to Metal
to specify what code
is an object shader.
In addition to the payload
attribute and object_data address space,
allow payload arguments
to be used in shaders.
The mesh grid properties argument
is used to encode the mesh grid size.
The next step is pipeline initialization.
First, allocate the
mesh render pipeline descriptor,
then initialize the object function and
specify the desired payload length,
along with the maximum number
of threads per threadgroup.
There are certain
constraints on object shaders.
Payload format and contents
are fully customizable.
However, payload size can't exceed
the limit of 16 kilobytes.
Also, the maximum number of
mesh threadgroups
that each object threadgroup
produces can't exceed 1024.
The next step after getting
the object shader stage ready
is initializing the mesh shader stage.
The mesh shader has the user
defined payload as an input.
In this example, the payload
is the set of curve control points.
Each mesh threadgroup produces
a metal::mesh,
which is a single strand of hair.
The output mesh of the mesh shader
must have a metal::mesh type.
A metal::mesh is a built-in structure
in Metal that provides you an interface
to output vertex and primitive data
to the rasterizer and fragment shader.
Each metal::mesh defines a vertex
data type, much like the output type
of a vertex shader,
a primitive data type,
the maximum number of vertices,
the maximum number of primitives,
and finally, the mesh topology--
either point, line, or triangle.
The mesh attribute was added to
Metal shading language
to specify what code is a mesh shader.
Metal::mesh is used as an output
structure in the mesh shader.
Mesh shaders are great for GPU-driven
geometry processing
as they allow you to produce
these metal::meshes on the fly
for the rasterizer to consume.
Mesh shaders leverage the metal::mesh
to their advantage
so you can put more
processing into render commands
without having additional compute passes.
Encoding a mesh is done across threads
within the same thread group.
In this example, the first 9 threads
of a thread group will encode the vertex,
index,
and primitive data of this hair strand.
Threads 0 through 4
each encode one vertex in the mesh.
The remaining threads in the thread
group do not encode vertices in the mesh.
Next, all 9 threads encode one index
into the mesh indices.
Next, the first three threads encode
primitive data for the three triangles.
The rest of the threads
don't encode any primitive data.
And lastly, one thread shall encode
the primitive count for the metal::mesh.
Let me show you the source code
for this mesh shader.
The mesh shader is organized to avoid
as much divergence in threads
as possible--following the
same steps to encode vertex,
index and primitive data,
and finally the primitive count.
Let's switch back to initializing
the mesh pipeline descriptor.
On the mesh pipeline descriptor,
the mesh function
along with the maximum threads
per mesh thread group, is set.
There are limits that metal::mesh
structure needs to adhere to.
Metal::mesh shaders
have the following limits:
metal::mesh supports up to 256
vertices and up to 512 primitives.
The total size of metal::mesh
cannot exceed 16 kilobytes.
Now that the mesh grid has
generated the metal::meshes,
these are then fed to the rasterizer
and finally the fragment shader is run.
So, similar to the traditional
render pipeline,
the fragment function
is set on the mesh pipeline descriptor.
Now that the descriptor has
been initialized,
the pipeline state is created
through the "make render pipeline
state with mesh descriptor" method
on the Metal device.
Encoding a mesh pipeline is very similar
to encoding a traditional draw call.
The pipeline state is set on the encoder.
Each stage in the pipeline
can have resources bound.
In this example the bound resources are:
an object buffer to an object stage,
a texture to a mesh stage,
and a fragment buffer to a fragment stage.
Next, I'm defining a few constants that
I'll need to launch the mesh pipeline:
object grid dimensions,
number of threads per object threadgroup,
number of threads per mesh threadgroup,
and use these constants to encode the draw
through the new
"draw mesh threadgroups" method.
The same approach that is used to
render a plane of hair
can be applied to the whole bunny
to procedurally generate fur
through a mesh pipeline.
Next, let's look at another way
to use mesh shaders.
Mesh shaders can be used to
efficiently process
and render large amounts of
geometry using meshlet culling.
The basis for this technique
is splitting the scene meshes up
into smaller pieces called meshlets.
Splitting scene geometry into meshlets
increases the granularity of the scene,
allowing more
efficient and fine-grained culling.
This allows you to greatly
reduce geometry overhead.
Leveraging meshlet granularity processing
allows for efficient occlusion
and culling algorithms
such as screen space
occlusion culling and normal filtering.
You can use mesh shaders to
implement a fully GPU-driven culling
and rendering pipeline.
Here is a traditional GPU-driven pipeline
that performs scene processing and
rendering
using one compute and one render pass.
The scene data is split into meshlets
and fed into the compute pass,
which is responsible for frustum culling,
LOD selection,
and encoding the draws to device memory.
The render pass then executes
the draw commands for the scene
and produces the final image.
Using mesh shaders, it is possible
to remove synchronization points
and avoid the intermediate
draw commands by merging two passes
into a single mesh shader dispatch.
Let me show you how it can be done.
Here is a single render pass
that executes a mesh shader dispatch.
The object shader performs frustum culling
and calculates LODs for
each of the visible meshlets.
The payload to the mesh shader is a list
of meshlet IDs that should be encoded.
The mesh shader then encodes
the metal::mesh objects
that shall be rasterized and shaded.
The final image is then
shaded in the fragment shader,
identical to the traditional pipeline.
The geometry processing is done entirely
within the mesh threadgroups command
and within a single encoder.
There is no longer a need
for an intermediate buffer
to store these draw commands,
as the triangle data
is encoded in the mesh shader.
Let's turn our attention to culling now--
specifically,
an implementation of meshlet culling.
The scene consists of models
represented by the shapes here.
In this implementation, each model of the
scene will become part of the object grid.
The mesh grids spawned by
the object shader threadgroups
will consist of meshlets--
patches of triangles
that make up the surface of the model.
The new geometry pipeline
is very flexible.
It is up to you to decide how to
map your scene onto an object grid.
In this example, I'm mapping
each model to an object threadgroup,
but you can use the mapping
that better suits your task.
Now, the object shader will determine
the visibility of meshlets
using the viewing frustum
and dispatch work only for
what will be presented in the final image.
Let's focus on two models from the scene.
The object shader launches mesh grids
based on determined visibility.
The mesh shader then processes
the meshlets and constructs metal::meshes.
The programmable mesh grid
size enables flexible dispatching
so only visible meshlets
get processed by the mesh shader.
This reduces the time spent processing
unseen geometry later in the pipeline.
The fixed function rasterizer only
receives surfaces that are known to be
visible and will reduce time spent
processing and clipping out
unseen geometry.
Finally, the programmable fragment shader
is invoked and produces the final image.
As you can see,
there are a wide variety of problems
that the new geometry pipeline
allows you to address
such as creating procedural meshes or
making your draw calls more efficient,
as demonstrated
in this meshlet culling example.
Metal now includes a new geometry
pipeline that is modern and flexible.
It is now easier than ever before
to create procedural geometry,
as demonstrated
in the hair rendering example.
Additionally,
the possibilities for GPU-driven work
in a single render pass have expanded
without requiring additional compute
passes or intermediate buffers,
as seen in the meshlet culling demo.
This new geometry pipeline is available
in Family7 and Mac2 devices.
To help you start learning and
experimenting with mesh shaders,
a sample code is available
on Apple developer web site
that shows how to use the new API.
I'm excited to see
how you use this feature
and utilize the massively
parallel nature of Apple GPUs
to fit your geometry processing needs.
Thank you so much for watching!