Hi, I'm Ben,
from Privacy Engineering,
and welcome
to Create your Privacy Nutrition Label.
At WWDC 2020,
we announced privacy nutrition labels
to provide people
with an easily glanceable
and understandable summary
about how the apps they use
collect and use data.
In this talk, we'll discuss strategies
for creating an accurate label
and highlight some definitions
and examples to keep in mind
as you build your label.
Nutrition labels are one of many ways
you can communicate
your app's privacy practices,
in addition to a privacy policy
and App Privacy Report.
Labels can help you explain to people
how you use the data your app collects.
Additionally, sharing a label is
a requirement
for all apps in the App Store.
On an app's nutrition label,
you can see data the app collects
that is used for tracking,
data that is linked to identity,
or associated with an account or profile,
and data that is not linked to identity.
In each section, the categories
of data collected are shown.
Alternatively, if data is not collected,
an alternate label is shown.
From an app's product page
in the App Store,
you can also view a more detailed version
of the nutrition label
that includes the specific types of data
the app collects
and how that data is used.
Today we'll be looking
at nutrition labels in more detail.
We'll walk through the process
for how to create your label
in App Store Connect,
and I'll share some resources
along the way.
Additionally, we'll provide
some more detailed definitions
and examples to help you
answer privacy questions for your app.
Let's begin with label creation process.
To create your label, you'll be asked
about what data your app collects,
use cases for each type of data,
and how that data is stored.
You might want to start
with creating an inventory
of your app's features
and data collection.
An inventory can be a helpful resource
for the next step,
where you'll enter information
about your app's privacy practices
into App Store Connect.
After you submit your label,
and as you update your data practices,
you should keep your label updated
as appropriate.
Lets dive right in and look
at how you can go about crafting
an inventory for your app.
When you submit
your label to App Store Connect,
you'll answer some questions
about how your app uses data.
You'll be asked about the categories
of data collected by your app,
the use cases for the data,
whether the data is linked to identity,
and whether the data is used for tracking.
However, as a developer,
you might not be thinking
about data categories in your app.
You're probably thinking about features,
and if you're not sure where to start
on building the nutrition label,
list out your app's features.
Then consider what data powers
each feature,
including what data is retained
and how that data is used.
You can then keep this list
as a reference for when you're asked
to enter specific details
into App Store Connect.
We recommend finding a framework
to document this information
that works for your app,
and you may have many strategies
to build an inventory
or other documentation.
When creating this inventory,
there are a number of resources
that you can use along the way.
Make sure to reach out to the stakeholders
working on your app.
For example,
you can check with your marketing team
to understand what data they use
and work with legal counsel to ensure
you document all data uses
described in your app's privacy policy.
We also recommend consulting
internal documentation in this process.
Consider looking
at your app's network traffic
using App Privacy Report
or a network proxy tool.
You can use this information to learn
what domains your app is contacting
and follow up with the owners
of those endpoints
to understand how data is being used.
Keep in mind that while a network audit
may be helpful in discovering
where your app sends data,
it is not comprehensive,
and you should use it
in combination with other strategies.
You should also audit any data
you retain on a server,
such as by reviewing database schemas
and checking what systems
have access to data.
Additionally, make sure to check
with any partners
that may be processing your app's data,
as you are responsible
for declaring the collection practices
of all data collected from your app,
including data collected
by third-party SDKs,
analytics tools, advertising networks,
or other external vendors.
Many SDKs provide documentation
of their privacy practices,
and some provide specific guidance
for nutrition labels
which you can use to ensure
your label is comprehensive.
When building this inventory,
you might also discover
that there is data that you're collecting
that you don't need.
Inventorying your privacy practices
can be a way to identify opportunities
to make changes to your app's practices
by minimizing data collection,
processing data on device,
and storing data not linked to identity.
For some new technologies you can use,
see What's New In Privacy.
Once you've built up an inventory
or documented your data practices
through your preferred process,
you'll work though responding
to the questions in App Store Connect.
In App Store Connect,
account holders, admins, and app mangers
can enter your app's privacy label.
From your app's page,
open the App Privacy section.
First, you'll be asked
about whether your app collects data.
Data is considered collected when it
is transmitted off device in a way
that is accessible for longer than
to service the request in real time.
So if you or any of your partners
retain data about interaction with the app
on a server,
such as server logs, a user profile,
or analytics,
your app likely collects data.
We designed labels
to describe all data apps collect.
You should declare all data
collected by your app,
even if people agree elsewhere
to the data collection or use.
Labels are a supplement
to a privacy policy
and any requirements
for user transparency
or consent for data collection.
We recommend working with legal counsel
to evaluate those requirements.
If you do collect data,
you'll be asked to declare
the categories of data
collected from your app,
such as email address,
phone number, or payment info.
You'll then be able to preview
your label in progress
and provide more detail
for each data category.
Let's work on phone number.
For each category of data,
you'll be asked to declare what use cases
the data collection supports,
such as analytics
or product personalization.
You'll then be asked to disclose
whether data is linked
to a user's identity.
Data is considered linked to identity
if it is associated with an account,
device, or user profile.
This can be an opportunity
for you to evaluate whether you need
to store data linked to identity,
and whether you can store data
in a way that isn't linkable
to any account or profile.
Finally, you'll be asked
whether each data type is used
for tracking purposes.
"Tracking" refers to linking data
collected from your app
about a particular end user or device,
such as a user identifier,
device identifier, or profile,
with third-party data
for targeted advertising
or advertising measurement purposes,
or sharing data collected from your app
about a particular end user
or device with a data broker.
As mentioned earlier,
nutrition labels are intended to reflect
all data your app may collect,
even for features where people
using your app
agree separately
to data collection or use.
Ensure you disclose any data categories
used for tracking on your nutrition label.
Additionally,
as all tracking must be with permission,
adopt App Tracking Transparency
if appropriate for your app.
For more information about tracking,
see Explore App Tracking Transparency.
Once you've submitted this information
for all data your app collects,
you'll be able
to preview and publish your label.
Your label will be published immediately,
independent from any updates to your app.
Now that you've created your label,
let's consider
when you'll need to update it.
You can update your label at any time,
and aren't required to release
a new version of your app.
We recommend re-evaluating
your app's label
when releasing new features
and on an ongoing basis.
As you change how your app uses data,
ensure your label remains up to date.
If you're adding new features to your app,
implementing new or updated integrations
with third-party partners or SDKs,
or using already-collected data
in new ways,
make sure to evaluate
whether any label changes are needed.
Now that we've worked through the process
of building your privacy nutrition label,
we'll discuss some additional guidance
around policy definitions and examples.
All of this information is available
in the Apple Developer documentation.
Today I'll be highlighting a few examples
based on our experience at Apple
building nutrition labels
for our own apps,
and from some questions
we have heard from developers.
You might wonder
how to disclose use of IP address.
IP addresses can be used
for multiple purposes,
including as an identifier
or to infer approximate location.
Our guidance is to declare
the collection categories
based on what the IP address is used for.
For example, if you use IP address
to show local content
or for location analytics,
declare location.
Another area to note is the categories
including product interaction.
Product Interaction covers data
collected about the user's interactions
inside the app, such as information
about which screens people open.
Browsing history refers
to collection of activity
that is not part of the app,
such as an in-app browser.
Search History is searches
performed within the app
for any content,
both in the app or in in-app browsers.
Labels are intended
to comprehensively describe
the app's primary functionality
and features encountered
by all of your app's users.
However, there are certain types
of collection
that are optional to disclose.
Collection that is infrequent, optional,
and independent
from the app's primary functionality,
clearly discloses all collection
at submission time,
and has limited use purposes, for example,
not used for tracking or advertising,
may be optional to disclose.
Feedback forms and report-a-problem flows
are some features
that may meet these requirements.
Full details and requirements
for the optional disclosure policy
are available on the "App privacy details
on the App Store" page
in Apple Developer documentation.
And that's a wrap!
Here are four things to keep
in mind while building your label.
Make sure to reach out to all stakeholders
working on your app
to inventory your collection
and ensure your label is accurate.
Remember to include
all collection from your app,
including from SDKs and other partners.
If applicable to your app, ensure
you request permission for tracking,
in addition to disclosing
any use on your nutrition label.
Finally, when you update your app
or change how you use data,
ensure your label is updated.
Thanks for joining me today.
Privacy Nutrition Labels
are a way to build trust
with people who use your app
and help people
understand how you use data.
The Apple Developer Documentation
and App Store Connect
have even more information
to reference throughout the process
of building and updating your label.
♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪