♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
♪ Sparse upbeat
electronic music ♪
♪
- Design, for me, is like a way
to express myself,
just like writing a song
or write a book,
but I don't know music,
and I can't write
good languages.
But I can code.
- Design is like an opportunity
where you can create things
that are not only beautiful,
but that also serve a purpose.
- Design is in
every aspect of life.
- Design influences
people's lives on all levels.
- Design can be
the difference between
having a great experience
or having a bad one.
- If no design,
there will be no surprise.
- It's not just how things look,
it's how things work.
- It's one of the most effective
forms of storytelling.
- To design something,
I think we often have to kind of
reduce it down
to a simplified version of it.
- It's like, yeah,
climbing a mountain,
step by step.
- You get to start with, like,
a blank piece of paper
and then you get to turn it
into something
hopefully really cool.
- When you actually make it work
and then you show it to someone,
and they actually can use it
in a simple way,
when it used to be
this really complex thing,
I think that's just
really cool to do.
- When we first met
on our first date,
he said that he's a UX designer.
And I thought,
will I be stupid if I say,
"What does it mean?"
[LAUGHS]
♪
- Real design
is far more functional.
- Delightful.
- Cute.
- Soothing.
- It's cozy.
- Powerful.
- Intriguing.
- Flashy.
- Tactile.
- Simple and joyful.
- Playful.
- And pretty!
♪
- Let me think,
do I love design?
[LAUGHS]
- Sometimes I hate it.
But yeah, it will not last
for a long time.
So basically,
I think I love the design.
- In some ways,
I can't escape designing.
- I can't imagine a life
without designing stuff.
- How could anyone hate design?
- It's kind of like magic.
- I couldn't do anything else.
- I know my user can feel
how I'm thinking in my app
through my design.
- I think design
really does change
the way we approach life itself.
♪ Whimsical music ♪
- I mainly get inspiration
from walking in nature.
Every time I do that,
I have ideas
that come to my mind.
- The inspiration could be
from anywhere.
It doesn't need to be
in the museum or gallery.
It's in the nature.
It's in the city.
- When it's nighttime,
when I know
everybody's sleeping,
when I know the world
is at rest,
it kind of makes it easier
for me to get into the zone.
- If I just spend time away
from technology,
away from my computer,
away from my phone,
that's the time when I can
really do deep thought.
- I just want to make everything
we cannot see in the real life.
- I was living in Bangkok.
There's a lot of cars.
There's a lot of traffic.
So also creating the game
pretty much designed
a way for you
to escape a little bit.
- Biggest challenges
for designing things
is that your assumptions
are usually wrong. [LAUGHS]
- I kind of had the idea
to focus on witchcraft
when the election was happening
in the United Kingdom
and there was a group
of individuals
who had decided they were
going to hex the government.
I think they were pagans.
♪ Piano lounge music ♪
- What's my biggest failure?
Just in general?
- Well, that's actually
a great question.
- Oh, greatest failure?
There's a lot of them.
OK, hold on.
- As a person
or in my career life?
- Uh...
- Let me --
I want to think and really...
- It's kind of hard to answer
without making somebody mad.
- Everything.
[LAUGHS]
- Failing is part of
any creation process.
- We spent, like, months
and months trying to iterate
and to do something great.
- Our biggest fail in the game
was actually at launch
that we didn't have
enough levels in the game.
- We had gotten rid
of the main feature of the app.
You know, overnight we lost,
I think, 20 percent
of our users.
Interesting, you know,
experience.
- We got some good feedback
from some customers,
and none of us really wanted
to admit that it kind of sucked.
- We're always happy
that we did change it.
- My adage was always,
if I came up with 50 ideas
in a day and 49
were absolutely useless
and one was really good,
that's a very good day.
- I think it was mostly
just staying too long
in situations that were
not where I wanted to be.
Management, economics,
and law seemed like
this super logical way to go.
But as soon as basically the
iPhone was announced in 2007,
that was all I was
just thinking about.
I think in hindsight,
my biggest failure
was actually a really good thing
because it led me
to where I am right now.
♪
Earlier last year,
I was working on an app
that helped people who are mute
to speak on the phone.
And then when I had made that,
I actually wanted
to make something similar
but the other way around,
so that if you're deaf,
and you're listening
to a phone call
that you can actually see
what's being said.
- It started for me just simply
trying to solve my own problem,
which is not drinking
enough water.
I could sit for hours working
until I feel like
I'm in the middle of the desert.
- Drinking water, it becomes
an exciting moment in your day.
- My kids will just --
they'll do something
as long as it's on a list and
they can strike it off later.
And so we wanted that moment
when you strike off that habit
for the day to really
just feel gratifying.
- I was walking around and saw
a broken neon sign
and that sparked the idea.
- We want to make
the best clock app in the world.
So to do that,
we visit many furniture shops
to see how the clock feels like
when you hold it in your hand.
- In the very first beginning,
we wanted to help ourselves.
Because we were in a meeting,
and we can't even
take proper notes
and at the same time,
be really engaged in
the meeting; talking to people.
So we want to do this app
to help ourselves.
- After really diving deep into
what inclusivity means,
it really changes
the way we build.
- I was riding up a gondola
and this family --
they were pointing out that
they really wanted to be able
to compare how they were doing
versus last year.
So I went home and wrote it,
and a week later
it was in the App Store.
- Don't pick up the phone
when you're focused
and don't open the lid off
the pot when cooking noodles.
These concepts run
through the Focus Noodles app.
A user can get
into the headspace
of covering their phones
and start to focus.
- If you love something,
you always find
a way to learn better.
And I want people
to love learning Chinese,
and I want to make it
more playful, more fun,
and people will enjoy learning.
- People see this as a game.
We can be
a lot more intentional
to create a game using our
technology to track your body.
Get you to move
your arms, move your body,
and basically get you
into the rhythm
and usually the game
is always like this.
That's where we took
the inspiration
to create Active Arcade.
Just like choreography;
just like teaching you
how to dance.
- We were in the middle
of quite a long project.
We realized it would be
really good fun
to just do a really fast project
and we could never
lose motivation for it.
- So the concept of the game
is you've murdered your husband,
and your goal is to make sure
other people don't find out.
[LAUGHS]
- The character
of Rebel Girls app
is like your feminist aunt
who is very kind
and who's full of stories.
And her goal is to make sure
that some of the best values
are instilled in you.
Empowering girls to become
the most confident
generation of girls.
- It's an app that is really
the friend you wish you had
when you lose a loved one.
It's the smart checklist
to telling you all the things
you need to do,
but at the same time,
only the things
you need to do right now
and what can wait, but also
allowing us to do it for you.
- For Behind the Frame,
it's basically
an escape room game.
Has that Ghibli kind of feel
to feel like playable anime.
We look at
the color scheme of Ghibli
and also Renaissance paintings.
- The idea behind Townscaper is
you just build beautiful houses.
That's all there is to it.
- The whole concept
is that you're finally
able to touch the artwork,
something that you're not
able to do in real life.
♪
- One of the biggest challenges
of designing tools
for creative people is that
a lot of the tasks
that artists want to create,
they're quite complex tasks.
So the challenge is
how do we take all that power
and make it really
usable and simple?
- It has to be easy for someone
who's jumping straight in
and hasn't really done
this kind of work before,
but it also has to be effortless
for professionals as well.
Making something simple
is quite complex.
- There are so many tiny details
that go into creating
an experience.
There was no way for it not
to feel really clunky.
The next four and a half years
of development
was a lot of kind of
stripping those things away.
And how do we get rid of the
things that might otherwise
distract people so that
they can actually focus
on this moment
that we're trying to create?
- It was incredibly hard.
Graphic design,
as we know it,
is kind of coming from
the desktop-world era,
and didn't really have a lot of
innovation in the last decades.
- I'd approached it similarly
to designing a building --
both you need
to navigate through.
With a website,
or even with an app,
you have different views.
You have an entrance.
At a certain point
you have an exit;
you have different rooms,
and the experience
needs to be good.
- My watercolor skills
are horrible.
My code development
is at the HTML levels.
So I also need to convince other
people, through my journey,
to build these things with me.
When we put it out, there was no
other watercolor game like it
or even watercolor app.
So I really worked heavily
with getting in
all the small details,
getting the water
to flow correctly
and getting it to just feel
really nice.
- Pushing the limits
has never been the problem.
The whole team loves to do that,
loves to see how far
they can take a character
or how much story
we can get into this scene.
The challenge
is to keep limits on that
so we can actually get it done.
- If you can create something
that people cannot see
in the real life, then sometimes
they will feel "wow"
at that moment
and we will feel so satisfied.
[LAUGHS]
Yeah, so this is why
we choose optical illusions.
For most people, when you see
some optical illusion,
you are just wowed.
- It was quite
a tricky problem to solve
of just making sure that
you could be playing on a bus,
but you don't notice
that you're on the bus anymore.
It's all of the little things
that build up the immersion,
not the big, obvious ones.
So the scuttling noises,
steam vents, things like that.
- We had huge geometries
and landscapes
and things that we wanted
to make really quick and custom.
We would just use our tool
that we designed,
and it would automatically
Lego-ify it.
- Our goal was to design
a very focused experience
for touch devices.
The player can interact
with this world
without having to think about.
That might sound simple,
but it's actually one of
the hardest things to pull off.
- Marvel Future Revolution
is an open-world, superhero,
action MMO RPG on mobile.
So it's got all your favorite
Marvel superheroes
saving the world with all
your buddies and friends.
The fact that
you could actually have
the true superhero experience
and you could actually take it
everywhere with you.
- I think that from
the very beginning we knew
we wanted to make a game
that was a mix
between music and story.
I mean, everything is in
the name of the game, you know.
So there's this character,
Gabrielle, who's in a coma.
You have to play music
to unlock memories.
To make this whole game,
it was a gigantic process,
but I mean,
it was a fantastic one.
- I thought,
"Cameras are so delightful;
maybe we can bring, like,
a semblance of that delight
to an iPhone camera."
I get emails every month --
every week, sometimes --
of people saying, like,
"I really enjoyed that.
It really helped a lot."
And that's so cool.
[LAUGHS]
- This app that we had created
actually convinced people
to get rid of their vehicle
and made riding
public transit fun.
And from that point on,
I think the motivation
became that transit
can have an impact on
people's transportation choices.
- Mental health was one
of those glowing beacons of need
where the skillset of a designer
and a product thinker
are deeply needed,
directing a lot of our attention
toward traditionally
underrepresented populations
and showing up in a way that,
we like to say,
opens a front door to care.
- Apps and games
have to tackle social change.
- An inclusive game
or app is something
that everyone feels at home.
Everyone can...
- ...have fun,
yet still connect with people.
- That authenticity allows us
not to just have
kind of symbolic diversity,
but actual diversity.
- I think if we want
to see social change,
then we need to exhibit it,
especially in entertainment
because it shows people
where we can go.
- I think I really
started to think,
"Hey, I can now make things
that help people
and solve the world
a little bit."
- I think over the last
two years, especially,
like, we're seeing
where we're going,
where we're going to spend more
and more of our lives digitally
in this world.
And how do we, as people, shape
those everyday experiences?
- A tip I could give
to the young developers
is stick to your original idea.
- If you're only
getting inspiration
from all the other games
that you love,
it's just going to be
another game.
- Try, fail, and try again.
And fail. And try again.
- Make as much as you can.
They don't have to be huge.
They don't have to be exciting.
But the more you make,
the more you learn how to make.
- When to leave it alone
and stop tinkering on it.
- Really figure out
what the game is
before bringing people on.
- Don't get frustrated.
- Let go of some
of your assumptions.
- Trying to decide what
the market wants
doesn't really make sense.
It's like, do something that
you're going to be motivated
to keep working on,
that you actually want
to exist in the world.
- You can steal,
but steal from the best
and always add your own
kind of magic fairy dust.
- Get inspired.
Get inspired by what's out there
and what's adjacent.
And look at what techniques
are in there
and how you can approach it
from a totally fresh start
with the things
and the biases that you have.
- The Apple Design Award,
it is like the Oscar. [LAUGHS]
- I couldn't believe it.
I was like, in tears, basically.
- I didn't know who I can tell.
It's like, oh my God.
I think something --
the most amazing thing happened
and there was no one in the room
I could share it with.
- I remember seeing
some tears in his eyes.
It means a lot to me as well,
because I was the one
that asked him to quit his job.
- Are they still asleep?
I mean, come on.
It's the Apple Design Awards
happening over here.
- Very first reaction
when I received the email.
OK, it's probably a spam.
Then I was like, hmm,
it's a good spam.
And then I started
talking about it with the team,
and, like, everyone was like,
"What?!" [LAUGHS]
- Well, what would I want to say
to my fellow finalists?
Best of luck.
You've built something
that's amazing,
whether it gets an award or not.
- And now we become the
Apple Design Awards finalists.
It's like every day I'm in
the highest point in my life.
- We made it!
[LAUGHS]
- I remember the moment
when I first heard it,
it was quite emotional for me.
So I hope they're also looking
back at their progress
and their work
over the last year or more.
- Great job and congratulations.
- Congratulations to everybody.
- Congratulations.
- Congratulations!
- It's an honor
to be amongst you.
- Great job.
And let's keep on building it.
- Your continuous work
and creation and your effort
will make a difference.
♪ Upbeat electronic music ♪
♪