♪ ♪
Hi, and welcome to WWDC.
My name is David,
and I'd like to tell you about
how you can explore
more content with MusicKit.
The MusicKit framework
was launched in 2021,
providing a set of APIs to access
and play music natively in Swift.
This framework makes it easy for
your app to integrate with Apple Music,
providing access
to the entire Apple Music catalog.
Today, I'd like to talk about
some of the major enhancements
we've made to MusicKit.
I'll start off with some additions to get
even more out of the Apple Music catalog,
with new music item types,
new requests, and new metadata.
After that, I'll discuss how
you can fetch personalized content
to provide a tailored experience
for each of your users.
Next up, I'll go
beyond the Apple Music catalog.
This year, you can take your app
to a whole new level
by including music
from your user's library.
Finally, I'll discuss
how to actively interact with the library,
such as adding items to the library
or a playlist,
as well as creating and editing playlists.
Let's dive into
the catalog content additions.
The initial release of MusicKit
introduced a new model layer for music,
including core types like Songs,
Albums, and Playlists.
This year, we're making it easier
to discover new music
with MusicKit
with the addition of two new types:
Curator and Radio Show.
Beyond that, MusicKit now also allows you
to build great UI
for searching through the catalog,
access top charts to get
the most popular songs, albums,
and more, and fetch new attributes
such as higher quality audio metadata
like Spatial Audio with Dolby Atmos.
Let's start with curators and radio shows,
which are fantastic resources
for music discovery.
Here, we're taking a look
at an example Curator, Nike.
Other examples of curators
are Shazam and Beats by Dr. Dre.
Here, we can easily find all of
the playlists generated by this curator.
This functionality allows people to get
quick access to playlists they may love,
finding new songs
or revisiting old favorites.
Now let's dive
into the more technical details.
Curators host a variety of attributes.
Some of the primary attributes
of this new Curator type are name,
url, artwork, and kind.
The kind property is an enum that can
either be "editorial" or "external"
indicating whether a given curator is
an Apple curator or a third party curator.
Curators also have
a playlists relationship
showing playlists made by that curator,
truly servicing
the music discovery notion we just saw.
Next, we have the Radio Show type.
Radio Shows like
"New Music Daily by Zane Lowe"
and "Pop Hits Radio by Brooke Reese"
are another way to discover
new music through seasoned professionals.
Much like the Curator type,
radio shows also have
a playlists relationship
to find the music a radio show features.
Just as these two new types
hold relationships to playlists,
we are also exposing two new
relationships on the Playlist type,
"Curator" and "RadioShow" for
the reversed logic: that given a playlist,
we can easily get the structure
of which entity generated said playlist.
MusicKit allows searching the catalog
for content from a plethora of types,
and now we're adding support for our new
item types, like curators and radio shows.
The list just continues to grow,
and as a result,
building good UI becomes
more and more challenging.
That's why this year,
we're making it much easier for you
through top results and suggestions.
Let's take a look at the utility
these enhancements bring to a UI.
When typing to search for content,
you may want to provide strong,
music-related auto-complete support.
That's where suggestions come into play,
providing terms
that people may be trying to reach.
You can even take it a step further
and display top results
for quick access
to what people may be searching for.
For the best results, you may not care
about the type of the item,
but instead want to focus on relevancy.
This is the power of top results.
Now, let's take a look at what
implementing this would look like,
starting with Top Results.
Here we have the existing way to create
a catalog search request,
requiring a search term
and the types of items
that you want represented.
The response includes collections
categorized by the requested types,
meaning multiple lists
of type specific results.
Although this is great,
we want to expose a single list
of the most relevant results
that is type agnostic.
And requesting this information
is as simple as adding one line.
Here we're setting the includeTopResults
property on the request to true,
and a new property
is filled in the response.
This new property is named topResults
which contains items
of any of the requested types.
Here's what the output
of the print statement looks like.
We can see that the top results
returned are a mix of songs, artists,
and albums in a single collection
and is ordered by relevancy.
Now I'll show you how to help
people get to their search destination
faster with Suggestions.
Simply create a suggestions request
with a string term.
Upon calling response,
you'll get back a suggestions response.
The response contains
an array of Suggestions.
And each suggestion includes a display
term which is suitable for your UI,
as well as a search term.
When people select a suggestion,
you can fetch the corresponding results
by performing a search request
with the search term.
Catalog charts are a great way to stay
up-to-date with the most popular songs.
MusicKit offers various types of charts
to see what's trending.
The types of charts
being offered are top charts,
such as Top Songs or Top Albums,
which correspond to the most played music,
city charts, and daily top 100.
You may also specify the requested charts
to be filtered by a specific genre.
Retrieving these charts
through code is extremely simple.
The catalog charts request
follows established patterns
already used
in the catalog search request.
First, initialize a charts request.
You can then specify
the kinds of charts you'd like.
By default,
this will fetch the most played content,
but you can also include daily
global top charts and city top charts.
Lastly, just specify the types
you want your charts to contain.
And that's it.
When we access the first playlist chart
in the response,
we get a MusicCatalogChart
representing the daily global top charts.
Its items are playlists like "Top 100:
Global" and "Top 100: USA".
If you've been fetching catalog charts
using MusicDataRequest in the past,
you no longer need to,
as MusicKit will do the work for you,
with pagination support
built into the collection of items.
In 2021,
we introduced
groundbreaking audio experiences
with true multidimensional sound
and clarity:
Spatial Audio with support
for Dolby Atmos.
This immersive experience is
already available for thousands of songs,
and now you can access this data.
MusicKit exposes which audio resources are
available for any song or album
through Audio Variants, so now,
you can relay this information to others.
Examples of audio variants
are the previously mentioned
Spatial Audio with Dolby Atmos,
Lossless Audio, and much more.
We are also exposing a new
boolean property alongside audio variants,
is Apple Digital Master, which is
the highest quality master supported.
Since this metadata is
exposed at the item level,
audio variants
are perfect for a detail view,
allowing you to achieve UI like this.
Here we have a detail view of an album.
And here,
we can see the appropriate badges
based on the audio variants
property mentioned earlier,
letting users know
what audio quality they can expect.
In this case,
spatial audio and lossless audio
are available for this specific album.
Now let's see how we can write
code to achieve this.
Loading audio variants are like loading
any other extended attribute.
Take an existing album or song,
in this case an album,
and use the with method to load
the audioVariants extended attribute.
Now your detailedAlbum has
the audioVariants property populated.
Here we can see
the audio variants property,
which is an array
whose element is an AudioVariant.
With these values, you can indicate
in your UI the available audio resources
for that particular element,
just like we saw earlier.
Now, this is great,
but you may want to show these
audio badges on more than
just top level or detail views.
That's why
we're also taking it one step further
and exposing the active audio variant
for the music player.
Accessing the active audio variant allows
for a visual indication
of the quality of audio
for the currently playing item,
such as Dolby Atmos in this view.
And the MusicKit player API
automatically chooses
the correct audio quality based on
user settings and network conditions.
To access the active
trait from the player,
first, we access the
ApplicationMusicPlayer's playback state
in an observed object.
We can then access the active audioVariant
directly from the playback state
Now,
we simply check the audioVariant property
to see if it's dolbyAtmos,
and add additional UI if it is.
Because the playback state
is an observed object,
this view will automatically update
whenever the currently
playing item changes,
making sure your view is
always up-to-date.
Now that we've gone over
some catalog additions,
let's dive into
fetching personalized content.
Personalized content is data
specific to a subscriber,
providing a unique and tailored
experience for every user in your app.
Normally, personalized content
requires special authentications
and user tokens,
but in the MusicKit framework,
we've made this all automatic so you don't
have to deal with any of the hassle.
The personalized content
we're bringing to developers
is access to recently played items
and personal recommendations.
Recently played content is
a valuable piece of data
for a person's
music consumption experience.
It allows for quick and easy access
to music items you know they enjoy.
And when listening to new music,
it allows people to later go back
and refer to their history.
To fetch recently played
containers like albums, playlists,
and stations, you can create
a recently played container request.
Note that if you play a song
from a playlist or album,
the container type will be retrieved.
In the response,
you will find recently played music items,
which offer convenience accessors
for the title, subtitle, and artwork.
You can also fetch recently played items
of more specific types,
like songs or stations.
Here, we create a recently played request,
specifying the Song type
through the generic parameter,
indicated by the angle brackets.
Our response now only contains
the songs that we have played.
Now, onto personal recommendations.
Personal recommendations let your app
experience feel more intimate and engaging
as they are generated based off
the user's library and listening history.
Recommendations are
nicely organized by themes,
resulting in groupings by genres, artists,
collections like "Made for You," and more.
To fetch personal recommendations,
simply create
a personal recommendations request.
The response is
a collection of recommendations.
When we log the first recommendation,
we can see that this particular element
represents the "Made for You"
recommendation.
Recommendations have an ID,
title, and nextRefreshDate.
The nextRefreshDate represents
the date time for when this recommendation
should be refreshed
for the most up-to-date suggestions.
The playlists property contains all
of the playlists that are made for me.
Let's take a look at another
example of a recommendation.
Here we'll print out the second element
of the recommendations response.
I listen to a ton of alternative music,
and this recommendation contains
a mix of different types,
in this case, Albums and Playlists.
Those are grouped
in a single collection of items,
which are ordered by relevancy,
much like top results for catalog search.
Now, let's take it a step further
and talk about how you can create
even more relevant experiences
around music
by incorporating content
from your user's library into your app.
This year, MusicKit allows your app
to fetch items from the library
with two types of requests:
the library request
and the library sectioned request,
search for content in the user's library,
and load extended attributes
and relationships
specifically from the library.
Before we see the technical details,
let's see how we can use library content
to enhance your app.
I've been working on a fitness app
called Music Marathon
that will track your outdoor runs.
By incorporating MusicKit in the project,
we allow people to play music
directly through the app
instead of context switching between
the Apple Music app and this one.
Let's start a new workout
and look for music content.
Here we see some
recommended playlists retrieved
from the personal recommendations request,
to give people quick access
to playlists we think they'll love.
Going to the library tab,
we can see it's an empty view.
It would be great to be able to see
all of my personal playlists,
so let's write that feature.
I already have some UI set up
to handle the basics of this view,
and now I want to load
the playlists from my library.
First, I'll make library request...
Specifying playlist
in the generic parameter
to indicate that we want the playlists
from the user's library.
And I'll store it in a local variable
I'll name "request."
Next I'll take this request
and call the response function.
This method is an async throwing method,
so let's add the try and await keywords.
and once again store it
in a response variable.
Then, I'll update the state object
to receive this response.
Now all that's left to do
is update the list
so we can see the playlists in my UI.
I'll iterate through the items
in the response using a ForEach...
And retrieve each playlist
in the MusicItemCollection.
Now that we have the playlists,
I'll pass them into a PlaylistCell
I've already made.
Now if we re-run...
And navigate back to the app,
we can see all of my personal
playlists in the library.
Now, I can choose to listen
to personal recommendations,
anything from the Apple Music catalog,
and my own personal library.
Now that we've seen how easy
it is to access library content,
let's look at what else
the library request can do.
The music library request
is a powerful API
to fetch items from the user's library.
On iOS, unlike other requests
to fetch content from the music catalog,
MusicLibraryRequest will not
actually load data from the network.
Instead, it will load items
from the copy of the user's library
that is stored on device.
The basics of this request
only require you to specify
which music item type is desired.
This item type is passed
through the generic parameter
of the MusicLibraryRequest.
You can apply a variety of filters
and sort options on the request
in order to finely tune your call
to match your requirements.
This request is also capable
of fetching already downloaded content,
supporting a fully offline experience.
Let's start with the simple, base request,
the same request we wrote
in the Music Marathon app, but this time,
ask for the Albums in the library.
The album type is specified
through the generic parameter.
To perform the request,
call the response function.
Looking at the output,
we have a MusicLibraryResponse,
where its items are a MusicItemCollection
of all the albums found
within the user's music library.
Here we notice that these Albums are
the same Album structure that you would
get from one of our various catalog
requests and have the same capabilities.
Whereas in this example we are
fetching every album in the library,
we know there are scenarios where
you only want a specific subset of albums.
That's why MusicLibraryRequest
also enables you to be more specific
about what items
you want to fetch from the library.
Let's take the same request
we wrote before and add a filter.
Here, we want to load all albums
where the isCompilation property
is equal to true.
When you call filter method,
Xcode's autocompletion will only offer
specific key paths that are supported
for the type of item you are requesting.
Now, the response only has
albums which are compilations.
But that's not all the power
the MusicLibraryRequest has to offer.
You can chain multiple filters,
giving you a more refined request
with each addition.
What if we wanted all of
the compilations of a particular genre?
We can add another filter to the request.
For example, here we have
an instance of Genre named "Dance."
You can filter by the genre's relationship
to restrict the results
to only include compilations
that contain this specific genre.
Now our response
only contains dance compilations.
How about only including dance
compilations that are already downloaded?
To do that,
just set the includeOnlyDownloadedContent
to true on the request.
And that's it.
The response is
the same MusicLibraryResponse,
but the items now only contain
elements that are downloaded.
As you can see,
the music library request is very powerful
and unlocks new capabilities that weren't
possible with a custom MusicDataRequest.
But MusicKit offers even more options
to fetch data from the user's library.
Meet the Library Sectioned Request.
The sectioned request is able
to fetch items grouped by sections.
As a result, the sectioned request
takes in two distinct generic parameters.
The first representing the section type,
and the second, the item type.
The library sectioned request
supports the same capabilities
as the regular library request,
such as a variety of filter
and sort methods which you can apply
to either the sections or the items.
Here's how you can fetch
all albums sectioned by their genres
using the library sectioned request.
The sectioned Response holds a property
named "sections" where each element
corresponds to the first generic parameter
of the request, Genre in this case.
Each genre not only exposes
its own attributes, but it also contains
a collection of albums,
accessible via the items property.
Those items correspond
to the second generic argument.
Here, the highlight shows albums
whose genre is Alternative.
And as mentioned before,
the capabilities of filtering and sorting
are also available
for this sectioned request.
Let's say we want the same albums,
sectioned by genres,
but the albums sorted
by their artist's name.
We add a sort filter.
By specifying the artistName keyPath
on Albums and saying that we want
these to be ascending,
we're sorting the response.
Notice that the method is sortItems
as we are specifying the sorting
to be applied to the items
and not the sections.
Had we wanted to specify the sections,
a set of filterSections
and sortSection methods are available.
Let's take a look at the new response.
We can now see that our albums
are ordered alphabetically by artist name
instead of by their titles.
Both the library request and library
sectioned request are extremely powerful,
but you might also want to complement
your music search UI
by adding search results
from the user's library.
So we've added a new structured request
which operates almost identically
to catalog search,
but instead of loading results
from the catalog, it finds
relevant items in the user's library.
Just like its catalog counterpart,
the library search request
only requires a search term
and an array of types.
Now that we've seen the different ways
to retrieve items from the user's library,
what about loading extended
attributes and relationships?
As you may know, the initial release
of MusicKit introduced the with method,
loading these properties from
Apple Music API in a straightforward way.
This year,
we're augmenting the current with method
to also take in
a preferred source parameter.
This preferred source indicates where
to load data from, for extended attributes
and relationships that are available
in both the Apple Music catalog
and the user's library.
And for the properties that only live
in either the catalog or the library,
they will still fetched
regardless of the preferred source
to make sure nothing is ignored.
In addition,
you can use this functionality
no matter where
the initial item came from,
whether it be a catalog request,
a library request, or elsewhere.
It all just works.
Here we have the known way of
receiving a relationship of a music item.
We're loading the tracks of an album,
and when we display the output,
we can see
all of the tracks for that album.
However, with the new addition
of the preferredSource property,
we can specify that we would like to fetch
this relationship from the library.
Now our output only contains the tracks
of the album found in the library.
With the various ways you can
now fetch items from the user's library,
it only makes sense to allow users
to be able to interact
with their library
directly through MusicKit.
Let's jump back into my sample app,
Music Marathon,
to see some of the capabilities
the library offers.
As I'm working out,
I want to browse through some
of my personal recommendations.
As I look through the tracks,
I realize that one of these songs
would be perfect for my workout playlist.
If hold down one of these cells,
a contextual menu pops up,
allowing me
to add this song to a playlist.
When we press it, a pop-up
of all of my playlists appear again.
Let's write code to add the selected track
to whichever playlist I pick.
I've already piped the selected item
to our AddToPlaylistCell cell,
so all we have to do is access the
MusicLibrary through the shared instance.
We'll call the "add" method,
specifying our selected track
and which playlist we want to add to.
This method is also
an async throwing function,
so we add once again
the try and await keywords.
Lastly, we'll dismiss the picker
by setting the isShowingPlaylistPicker
binding variable to false.
Now if we re-run
and add a track to a playlist
and select one of our playlists,
we should expect to see this item added.
Navigating back to the library tab
within the app,
we can see the song is
now added to our workout playlist.
And that's how simple it is
to add an item to a playlist.
Let's look at some of the other
functionality the library offers.
The various other ways to interact
with the library are adding content
to the library, creating playlists,
and editing playlists' metadata
and track list.
Adding content to the user's music library
allows people to find specific songs
or albums in the library tab
of the Apple Music app,
as well as synchronizes across all devices
when "Sync Library" is turned on
in Settings.
Providing this functionality
directly in your app saves people
from context switching between
the Apple Music app and yours,
so they can stay engaged
in the content you're providing.
Also, by integrating adding to the library
along with the newly introduced
library requests,
your app can immediately benefit
from these results,
giving users easy access
to content they love.
Even with this powerful service,
you may still want to craft
specific musical experiences.
So this year, we're bringing
playlist creation and editing to MusicKit.
You can now create playlists
on behalf of your users.
We're also allowing items,
such as songs or even whole albums,
to be added to any eligible playlist
in the user's library.
Creating playlists are fantastic
for grouping content that people love
or fitting any mood your app wants to set.
And by adding content
to existing playlists,
you allow for the various
music discovery tools MusicKit offers
to directly affect people.
You can now also edit playlists
that you've created,
being able to edit the track list
and metadata to make sure
everything is just as you want it.
And those are the ways you can
interact with users' libraries
from within your app.
To wrap up, MusicKit received
some major upgrades this year.
Easily incorporate our catalog
enhancements for new types, properties,
and search augmentations to your existing
apps for an even better experience.
Integrate library content
and functionality
to unlock brand-new capabilities
and let users be in control
of their experience.
And using MusicKit can enhance
multiple different types of apps.
Fitness apps, games,
social media apps, mapping apps,
and more can all benefit
from playing or sharing music.
To go even further, make sure
to check out some related sessions.
Dive deeper into Swift
and learn about the new additions
to the language to get the most out of
MusicKit and other Apple Frameworks.
Check out the MusicKit session from 2021
to learn how to set up your app
to use the framework, initiate playback,
and present subscription offers.
And if you're interested in integrating
with Apple Music on Android or the web,
we have another session that goes over
how to use Apple Music API directly.
I hope you enjoyed our session,
and make sure to stay updated
and engaged through our developer forums.
Thank you for watching,
and enjoy WWDC 2022.