♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Namaskar!
Hello and welcome to WWDC22.
My name is Vrushali Mundhe,
engineer on the Create ML team,
and I am excited to share with
you what's new in Create ML.
Create ML allows you
to easily train
powerful machine learning models
with data you have collected
to deliver unique experiences
and enhance your apps.
Create ML ships as an app
bundled with Xcode,
letting you quickly build
and train Core ML models
right on your Mac with no code.
Create ML is also available
as a Swift framework
shipping in SDK.
Using its APIs, you can easily
automate model creation
or create dynamic experiences
powered by training
directly from
within your own app.
To learn more about Create ML's
core capabilities,
you can check out
these previous sessions.
In this session, we'll talk
about what's new in Create ML.
We will start with new features
in the Create ML app
that can help evaluate
the accuracy
and utility of your models.
We will then turn our attention
to the Create ML framework,
its extended capabilities,
and ability to now highly
customize models
for your own app.
Let's start by reviewing
a typical workflow
for model creation.
Given an identified task,
you begin by collecting
and annotating data.
Take, for example, wanting
to visually identify groceries.
For this image
classification task,
your starting point would be
collecting and labeling images;
here, some fruits
and vegetables.
Create ML will then help you
train a model from this data,
which can be used in your app.
However, before using
this model,
an important step is to evaluate
how well it performs;
here, seeing how accurate
the model is on images,
which were not part
of the training set.
Depending on evaluation,
you may iterate on the model
with additional data
and modified training settings
or, once the model is
performing well enough,
you're ready to integrate it
into your app,
I would like to focus
on this evaluation step further.
When performing an evaluation,
we often turn
to a set of metrics measured
by testing your model
on new data held out
from training.
You may start by looking
at a top-level accuracy metric
or dive into
per-class statistics
to get a general sense
of the model's behavior
and ability to generalize
beyond what it was trained on.
Ultimately, the model will be
responsible for empowering
data-driven experience
in your app,
and during evaluation,
you want to identify the model's
main strengths and weaknesses
in terms of categories
of inputs or scenarios;
it works well or may fall short
of expectations.
There are new features in the
Create ML app that can help you
on this part
of your model-creation journey.
Let me show you a project
that I'm working on.
Here, I have a project
set up to create a model
to identify groceries.
I started with collecting
various fruit
and vegetable images
as my training data
and labeled them appropriately.
Here are my different classes
and number of images
for each class.
I have already trained my image
classifier for 25 iterations.
Next, when I click
on the Evaluation tab,
I can add new test data --
a set of images
apart from training data that
I had set aside for testing.
I will next click Evaluate
to begin testing.
After it finishes evaluation,
the UI provides details
of the results.
On the top, there is
a high-level summary section
which gives a quick sense
of test accuracy.
Here, the accuracy
of this test data is 89 percent.
Below in this Metrics tab,
a table provides a wealth
of metrics for each class.
You can adjust what is shown
here using these drop-down menus
and add additional metrics
like false positive
and false negative.
Let's review one
of these classes.
How about Tomato?
The model classified 29 of
the 32 tomato images correctly.
It also shows the precision
for this class is 91 percent,
which means nine percent
of the time
the model says something
is a tomato, it is incorrect.
While these numbers
and statistics are super useful,
it's sometimes even more
important to look at them
in the context
of the data itself.
When I click the precision,
it takes me to the images
that were incorrectly
classified as tomato.
Here are three of these cases
in the test data.
For each image,
the app displays its thumbnail,
the class the model
has predicted,
and the true label below it.
In this first example,
while the model classified this
as Tomato,
it was labeled as Potato.
But this sure appears
to be a tomato to me.
This seems like a case
of a mislabeled test data.
In fact, all three of these
examples seem to be mislabeled.
This should be easy to address.
I'll make a note to double-check
and revisit
my test-set labeling.
This was clearly
an error on my part,
but is it the only source
of error?
I got here
by exploring the metrics
on a random class of my choice.
You may wonder,
"Where should I start?"
Or, "What should I
explore next?"
The top-level summary section
is here to help you out.
The app has selected
some of the most important
evaluation details
that can serve as a great place
to start your exploration.
Let me restart from the top
and review the successful cases.
Clicking here,
this correct count...
Here, we can get a quick
glance of all the 162 images
the model correctly classified.
Next, let me contrast this with
a review of all the failures
by clicking on the incorrect.
There are 21 failures in total.
Here is that mislabeled
tomato again.
Let me check if there are
any other types of errors
that can stand out.
How about... this one?
This image is labeled
as Carrot,
but the model predicts
as Potato.
It's hard to tell
in this small thumbnail,
but let's confirm by clicking on
this image to get a better view.
Well, this looks like
a foot to me.
This clearly is not a long,
skinny carrot shape I'm used to
but can be easily confused
as a potato.
Perhaps I should consider
adding more shape variations
to my training data for carrots.
Let me make a note
of this as well.
This time, I will click on
the arrow next to the filename
to bring me to this image
in the Finder.
I will right-click
and label this as red,
as reminder of it being
something I want to revisit
in my next round
of data collection.
Let me continue my exploration
from within this expanded view.
Note that this view also shows
full prediction results,
listing the model's confidence
in every class.
It also lets me navigate
through examples
using these left
and right arrows.
I'll move to another example
from here.
This is an interesting case.
It has multiple vegetables
in a single image.
It says it's an eggplant
and it's true
that there are eggplants here
but other things as well.
I need to think about whether
this is an important use case
for me to consider in my app.
Perhaps the UI can guide
my users to make sure
they only point to one type
of grocery at a time,
or if I want to support
multiple types,
I may want to consider
using an object detector --
another template in the app --
rather than the whole
image classifier.
Coming back
to the summary section,
let me check out this line
about the top confusion.
Here it says
it's 'Pepper' as 'Bean'.
Let's click
to explore this case.
Four images labeled as peppers
are incorrectly
classified as beans.
These look like
spicy peppers to me,
but I guess they are green
like beans as well.
I wonder if the model is having
trouble with peppers in general.
Let me switch this query option
from Incorrect to Correct...
...to contrast these failures
to correctly classified peppers.
It correctly classified
32 images;
however, I do notice that
most of these are bell peppers.
I should check my training data
to make sure
I have a good representation
of multiple peppers as well.
This quick exploration
was a great reminder
of how important
the quantity, quality,
and variety of training and test
data are for machine learning.
In a matter of a few minutes,
the app helped me
visually identify
some issues with labeling
and representation.
I need to make some tweaks
to my training data
and see if it fixes
the issues we saw.
It also revealed something
I hadn't considered before:
what happens if a user
captures multiple vegetables
in a single photo?
I need to think about
my app design some more.
All of this exploration
was possible
because I had a collection
of labeled data to evaluate.
But what if I have unlabeled
examples I want to quickly test,
or consider whether or not
I should explore
more camera angles
or lighting conditions?
Here is where
the Preview tab can help.
I can drag a few examples my
colleague just sent to me here
and see how well it does.
Or I can even test this live,
using my iPhone
as the Continuity Camera.
As I point
to these actual vegetables,
the model is able
to correctly classify them live.
Here, this is a pepper
and a tomato.
To recap, you can now
dive deeper
into a trained model's behavior
on any labeled dataset.
The Evaluation pane provides
a detailed metric summary
with its extended options.
A new Explore tab provides
options which lets you filter
and visualize
the test evaluation results
along with the associated data
in a new interactive UI,
currently available
for image classifier,
hand pose classifier,
and object detection templates.
Live preview enables
immediate feedback.
It's expanded
to image classifier,
hand action classifier, and body
action classifier templates.
We have also extended
the feature to allow you
to select from
any attached webcam
and we also support
Continuity Cameras
on macOS Ventura.
That's a quick summary of
what's new in the Create ML app.
Let's shift over
to discuss what's new
in the Create ML framework.
The Create ML framework
is available on macOS,
iOS, and iPadOS.
This year, we are expanding
some of its support to tvOS 16.
The programmatic interface
not only lets you
automate model creation
at development time
but also opens up
many opportunities to build
dynamic features that learn
directly from users' input
or on-device behavior,
providing personalized
and adaptive experiences
while preserving user privacy.
Note that task support
does differ per platform.
For example, while tabular
classifiers and regressors
are available everywhere, some
of the tasks with larger data
and computation requirements,
such as those involving video,
require macOS.
One common question
you may have is,
"What if I can't map my idea
into one of these Create ML's
predefined tasks?"
To help answer this question,
we are introducing a new member
to the Create ML family:
Create ML Components.
Create ML Components exposes
the underlying building blocks
of Create ML.
It allows you to combine them
together to create pipelines
and models customized
to your use case.
I highly recommend you
checking out these sessions
to learn more.
In "Get to know
Create ML Components,"
you will learn about
the building blocks
and how they can
be composed together.
In "Compose advanced models
with Create ML Components,"
you dive deeper into using
async temporal components
and customizing training.
There are endless capabilities;
let me showcase one
that I am personally
excited about:
action repetition counting.
When I am not working, most
likely you'll find me dancing.
I'm a professionally trained
Indian classical dance
Kathak artist.
To improve my form,
I often rely on repeatedly
practicing my routines.
As a choreographer/teacher,
I would like my performers
to practice steps for certain
counts and submit them to me.
The new repetition counting
capabilities in Create ML
can help me actually do that!
Here, this a chakkar -- twirl --
an integral part
of Kathak dance.
I would like to practice this
for certain counts daily
to build my form and my stamina.
I have an iOS app built using
Create ML that counts my moves.
Let's try it in action.
As I take my chakkars,
the count increases
to correspond to it.
Here, I have done five chakkars,
and the count reflects
exactly that.
Next, let's try a different
small routine
that consist of right-
and left-side movements.
The counter counts them as one.
Here, the count shows three.
Let me try another
quick one-side arm movement.
That's four.
When combined
with Action Classification,
this will allow you to count and
categorize repetitive actions
at the same time.
Repetition counting is available
as a runtime API.
It requires no training data,
and adding this functionality
to your app can be
just a few lines of code.
Its implementation is based
on a pretrained model
designed to be class-agnostic.
Meaning, while it works
on fitness or dance actions,
such as jumping jacks,
squats, twirls, chakkars,
it's also applicable
to a wide variety
of full-body
repetitive actions.
You can find out more
about this model
and potential use case
by checking out the sample code
and the article linked
to this session.
So that's a quick overview
of what's new in Create ML.
Interactive evaluation
and live previews
in the Create ML app
lets you dive deeper
into understanding
the models you train.
The Create ML framework
adds tvOS support,
repetition counting,
and has expanded
to give you access to a rich
set of underlying components
to help you build models
highly customized
to your app needs.
Thank you,
and I hope you enjoyed all
these exciting new features,
and we can't wait to see
what you do with them!
♪