♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi, folks. My name is Pavlo.
I work on security technologies
that help keep you
and your users safe.
Today I'm going to tell you
about some upcoming changes
that may impact the way
you develop, test,
and deploy your applications.
First, I want to tell you
what Developer Mode is,
the reasoning behind
why it was created,
the security benefit it brings,
and the workflows
that it will affect.
Then, we will discuss
when and how
to turn on Developer Mode.
And then we will finish off
this session with a walk-through
of the tools we built
to support automation flows
for when you're working
with many devices,
like in a testing lab
environment.
OK, so what is Developer Mode?
It's a new mode in iOS 16
and watchOS 9
that enables common
developer workflows.
Developer Mode
is disabled by default
and requires you
to explicitly enroll the device
into Developer Mode.
Your enrollment persists across
reboots and system updates.
And of course,
we have built tools
that enable you to automate
Developer Mode setup
if you want.
A natural question
you will have is,
"Why are we introducing
Developer Mode?"
The reason is that
powerful developer features
are being abused
in targeted attacks.
Meanwhile,
the vast majority of users
do not need such functionality
and so they shouldn't
be enabled by default.
This way we can retain
the development capabilities
that you rely on and increase
the security for users
with mitigations that otherwise
would get in your way.
Now having said that,
most common distribution flows
will not require Developer Mode.
For example, deploying your
application through TestFlight
or using Enterprise
in-house distribution
does not require Developer Mode.
And of course,
distributing your applications
through the App Store
does not require Developer Mode.
It's only required for when you,
the developer,
are actively developing
your application on your device.
All right, by this point
I'm sure you can't wait
until I tell you
how you would get started
with using Developer Mode.
So let's go through when you
need to turn on Developer Mode
and how to do it.
You should turn Developer Mode
on if you need to
run and install development
signed applications,
including applications signed
by using a Personal Team;
debug and instrument
your applications;
or you want to use testing
automation on your device.
Turning on Developer Mode
is straightforward,
but first you need to connect
your device to Xcode
for the Developer Mode
menu item to appear.
The beta releases
that you have downloaded
will have the menu item always
visible for the time being.
Installing a development-signed
application without Xcode,
like through Apple Configurator,
will also make
the menu item visible.
Once you've done that, you can
find the Developer Mode controls
under Privacy & Security
in Settings.
And for automation,
you can use the new devmodectl
that ships by default
on macOS Ventura,
but more on that later.
OK, so let's walk through
with how you would turn on
Developer Mode.
In front of me,
I have an iPhone 13 Pro
that I just picked up
to run my code on.
First, I'm going
to plug it in to my Mac
that has Xcode already running.
As you can see, Xcode recognizes
that this device
does not have
Developer Mode enabled
and will prevent me
from running this application.
But now that
I have plugged it in,
I can go into Settings,
Privacy & Security,
Developer Mode.
Turning on Developer Mode
requires that you reboot
your device,
so let's go ahead and do that.
Once the device has rebooted,
you will be prompted once again
to confirm your decision.
Once you tap Turn On,
you will be good to go.
Now, Xcode sees that the device
has Developer Mode enabled,
and I can run my application.
While this flow works
when you're working
with a single device,
this process
can be time consuming
if you're dealing
with multiple devices.
For this reason,
we've built tools
that help you automate
this process.
Automation flows
have one limitation:
only devices without a passcode
can have Developer Mode
automatically enabled.
This is because
when you restart your iPhone
you need to unlock your device
before your device
can be interacted with.
To support automation,
macOS Ventura
ships with devmodectl
that you can use to either
enable Developer Mode
on a single device
that you have already connected,
or in Streaming Mode
that will automatically turn on
Developer Mode
on all devices that you plug in.
Here I have two devices
plugged into my Mac.
They don't have passcodes,
and I don't want to manually
set up Developer Mode on them.
So I'm going to run devmodectl
with the streaming subcommand.
This will automatically reboot
the connected devices
and set up Developer Mode.
Once Developer Mode
has been set up,
you will get a notification
on the device.
And now these devices
are good to go.
All right, that's all I have
for you today.
To wrap it up,
in iOS 16 and watchOS 9
you will have to enable
Developer Mode
to perform common
development activities
like deploying and debugging
your applications.
And if you need to automate
Developer Mode setup,
you can use devmodectl,
which ships in macOS Ventura.
If you want to learn more
about security changes
that may impact your
macOS distribution workflows,
check out the "What's new in
notarization for Mac apps" talk.
I hope you have
a great rest of your day
and happy coding!
♪