[upbeat music]
- Howdy. I'm Jake,
a designer on the Xcode team.
Multiplatform app development is being
taken to the next level in Xcode 14.
A single app target can now
support even more destinations
across multiple platforms,
all while maintaining a single common
codebase, sharing settings by default,
and allowing new ways to
conditionalize where needed.
First, we'll cover what
a multiplatform app target is,
and in which cases it works best.
Next, we'll modify our project to support
multiple destinations and platforms,
then we'll update our project to get it
building and running on the new platform.
We'll ensure our app looks great on each
supported platform...
and finally we'll integrate Xcode Cloud
with our project changes.
First, let's understand
which technique we want to use
to allow our app
to support multiple platforms.
Before Xcode 14,
if you wanted your app to support iOS
and macOS,
you would need two separate targets.
This is great if your project
needs significantly different codebases,
shares very few of its settings
between its different platforms,
or if each app target relies heavily
on a different underlying technologies.
If that's still the case
with your project today,
your best bet would be to continue to use
separate targets for each platform.
In Xcode 14, a single app target can
declare support for many destinations
like iPhone, iPad, Mac, and Apple TV.
This is great for an app
that uses a common codebase
and shares most of its settings
across all its destinations
while still allowing for
customization when needed.
Let's take a look at how
multiplatform apps work in Xcode 14.
If we're starting from scratch,
a great way to begin
would be to use the new,
improved multiplatform app template
when making a new project in Xcode.
The multiplatform app template uses
SwiftUI for its lifecycle and interface,
which starts us out with a target
configured by default to support iPhone,
iPad, and Mac.
This is a fantastic configuration
for new projects.
Because we're using SwiftUI,
we have access to the full
feature-set of each platform's SDK,
allowing the creation of amazing new apps
that take advantage of
what each platform has to offer.
Existing projects
can also declare support
for multiple destinations
in their app target
and use SwiftUI to get access to
the full power of each platform's SDK.
Let's take a look at how to add a
Mac destination to an existing iOS app.
I've been building a Food Truck app,
and it works great on iPhone and iPad.
I'm pretty happy with this iOS app,
and now I want to bring it to the Mac
and embrace the platform and its features.
Let's take a look at what our
project looks like in Xcode.
If we take a look at my app target,
we can see a list of all
the destinations my app supports.
You can see I have a Mac destination
already--Designed for iPad.
This allows Mac computers with Apple
silicon to run my unmodified iOS app.
This is a great way to get
started supporting the Mac,
but I want to take my Mac support
to the next level.
Let's add a "Designed for Mac" experience,
so to speak.
We can easily edit our list of
supported destinations
and add a Mac destination to our app.
There are a couple options
for Mac destinations:
Mac, Mac Catalyst, and Designed for iPad,
the last of which is grayed out,
because my app already supports it.
Choosing between Mac and
Mac Catalyst mainly comes down to
which technology
we're most interested in using.
If our app made heavy use of UIKit
or Storyboards at the core of our app,
Mac Catalyst would be a great way
to convert our existing iPad app
into a compatible Mac app.
However, our app uses SwiftUI,
which makes the "Mac option"
the best choice to craft our,
well, Mac app.
We'll get the amazing Mac look and feel
right out of the box,
with the full power of
the macOS SDK without any limits.
Meaning, we'll have the freedom
to use UIKit in our iOS app,
and AppKit in our macOS app,
if we want that flexibility.
With all that in mind, let's choose Mac,
the best option for working with SwiftUI.
Once I make my choice,
Xcode will alert me
to some changes necessary
to prepare my project for Mac support.
In this case,
Xcode will update my target
to only include dependencies and
frameworks that are supported on Mac.
It's important to note Xcode
won't make changes to my code,
so if I'm calling API
that isn't available on Mac,
I'll need to resolve those issues myself.
Once I pick my Mac option, it's added
to my list of supported destinations.
It's totally valid to have more
than one Mac destination
when I'm developing in Xcode.
This is especially useful if I'm
transitioning from "Mac Catalyst"
or "Designed for iPad" to a full Mac app.
This means I can continue testing out
each of my Mac products within Xcode.
And I'm not necessarily restricted to
a single choice when developing my app.
However, if I were to publish
my native Mac app to the App Store,
my Designed for iPad app wouldn't
be available anymore to my customers,
so Xcode offers a quick way
to remove this destination.
But I'll consider removing
this destination
once I'm happy
with my native Mac experience.
Whether I'm starting from scratch
or adding a new destination
to an existing app,
using a single target in Xcode
lets me share code
and build settings by default.
There may be cases where I want
to customize an individual setting,
like my app's display name
or a minimum deployment version.
Let's take a look at how to do that in
the improved target editor in Xcode 14.
Many app target settings now include
a way to conditionalize its value.
On supported settings,
I can reveal an editor
that lets me set the default value for
each build configuration in my project.
I have a custom Beta configuration
that I added,
as well as the standard Debug
and Release configurations
that come with new Xcode projects.
I want to give my app
a different display name
when built with a beta configuration,
so I can just edit the name right here.
As I type, we'll see our app's
display name in Xcode
has been replaced with a readout
of all possible values
the display name can now have.
If needed, I could also add a condition,
letting me specify a value based on
which SDK is being used.
This allows me to say
set a specific name
for the beta configuration
when building for Mac.
Okay, I think we're done with the edits
we want to make in the General tab.
Let's take a look at the
Signing and Capabilities tab
for any other changes we need to make.
The good news is,
with Automatic Signing turned on,
there are no extra steps to take.
When I added my Mac destination,
the necessary Signing Certificate
and Provisioning Profile for the Mac
was generated on my behalf.
Both my iOS and macOS app products
use the same bundle identifier by default,
which is awesome, because that means
when I publish them to the App Store,
they will be made available
for Universal Purchase.
So folks who buy my iOS app
will also get my Mac app automatically.
My app also makes use of
capabilities like push notifications.
Any capabilities
I've been using for my iOS app
that are applicable to my macOS app
get applied with no extra work from me.
They even get combined
into a single entitlements file.
Now that we've added support
for multiple destinations to our app,
our next goal is to get it to build.
It's normal to run into issues
building an app for a new destination,
especially if a new SDK is involved,
like our new Mac support.
So let's take a look
at some of these common issues.
Some frameworks
are not available to all platforms.
We'll need to make sure
we're not importing or linking
any unavailable frameworks.
Remember that Xcode won't change our code
when adding support for a new destination,
so we'll need to conditionalize
our code based on SDK,
similar to how we conditionalized
our app's settings.
This is also true for API.
Some features are marked as unavailable
based on which SDK we're building with.
Swift offers a way to conditionalize
portions of our code
to only include features available
for the SDKs we're building with.
Xcode also lets us specify
if an individual file should be compiled
when building for some SDKs.
If I build my project right now...
I don't see any issues.
That's because I still have
a destination selected in my toolbar
that uses the iOS SDK.
I'll need to pick "My Mac" from the list
to build against the macOS SDK.
Building now reveals some new issues,
and as we expected,
they're mainly related to availability.
In one of my files, I'm importing ARKit,
which is not available on Mac.
I could wrap this import statement
in #if canImport to conditionalize it out.
This is useful if I don't want to manage
a list of known platforms
a framework is available for
and simply say if it's not available,
don't include it.
However, I'm still using ARKit
throughout this file,
so sometimes it makes more sense
to conditionalize out
an entire file for an SDK.
If we navigate back to our target
and go to the Build Phases tab,
I can search for my file...
And specify
it should only be compiled for iOS.
After building,
once I've made those changes,
Xcode reports a new issue--
a framework that is available on Mac,
SwiftUI,
has a feature that's
been marked as unavailable.
Specifically,
I'm using EditMode on iOS to allow users
to make edits and select content
in Tables and Lists,
but on macOS EditMode doesn't exist!
Users can already freely select
and edit rows of content on Mac,
so let's make sure this code
is only runs on iOS.
I can condition out
my environment property
and any place I was using EditMode below.
Now, I need to make sure any places
I was using this property
are also conditioned out,
like this onChange modifier.
I can wrap the entire modifier
in an "if os" condition.
And finally, I'm using an EditButton view
in the toolbar, which is also iOS-only.
Okay, let's try running our app.
Ah! It lives!
Our app now builds and runs on Mac!
Just because our app now builds
and runs on our new platform
doesn't mean our job is done.
There will be cases where you want to
refine your app experience
for what users on
your new platform will expect.
Also, trimming out our iOS-only
features isn't the end of our journey.
We now have all the features
of the macOS SDK to play with.
Now that I see my app running on Mac,
I'm noticing a quirk about my app
that doesn't feel natural
in its new context.
These donuts in this grid view
seem much too large!
That's because our grid items
were designed for touch.
Situations like this arise when you
declare a point size for a UI element
or otherwise customize a control
with only a single platform in mind.
On the Mac, we don't need to
make our buttons or thumbnails so large,
since we have a much more
precise pointing device.
This is a great case to conditionalize
a constant in our project
to vary based on which SDK
we're building for.
When we bring our app to other
platforms it's important to reconsider
many of these choices with
our new platform's expectations.
Let's take a look at specifying
a different value
based on which SDK we're building for.
One technique I often use is
making a constant a computed property,
and using "#if os" to
conditionalize what is returned.
Let's convert this to a computed property
and return what previously
was a constant...
but only return that value on iOS.
Ah, 80 feels much more naturally sized.
Now, as for making use of the macOS SDK,
there's a cool new feature in SwiftUI
that allows us to add
our own UI element to the Menu Bar.
I have a summary view for my app
that I'd love to let my users
have quick and easy access to.
Let's go to my App declaration,
and here, I can add a new Scene
for my Menu Bar Extra.
Note, though,
because this is a macOS-only feature,
I do need to conditionalize it
for the macOS SDK.
Let's build and run and take a look.
Ah cool, my truck icon
now shows up in the menu bar.
Awesome, now my Mac users
can see a quick glance
at today's information
right from their menu bar.
When we use SwiftUI, we get access
to the full SDK of each platform
and can utilize its awesome features.
It's important to note,
when we bring our app to other platforms,
we'll often need to
reconsider many past choices
when working in the context
of our new platform.
SwiftUI bakes platform expectations
directly into the API.
Many interface elements
will gain an automatic appearance
that looks great on each platform.
Conversely, that means we can lose
that automatic styling
when we heavily customize
our controls and other pieces of our UI,
so we should always double-check
our UI looks great everywhere.
All that said,
as we construct our cool app,
we should ensure we're following
the best practices
laid out by the human interface
guidelines.
Now that we're happy with
our local changes to our app,
it's time to archive our app products
and upload them to App Store Connect,
which we can do from Xcode
or automate it with Xcode Cloud.
Once we're ready,
we can then share the app
with internal and external testers
on TestFlight
and release it to the App Store.
We'll need to archive our products
to upload them to App Store Connect.
Just because we have a single target
doesn't mean we only have
a single product.
We'll need to archive for each platform
and upload those individually.
If you're building and archiving locally,
you'll need to select a destination
that has the SDK
you want to create an archive for.
If I want to produce my macOS app,
I'll need to select "My Mac"
from the list of destinations,
otherwise I'd select an iOS device
to produce my iOS app.
Once I have a destination selected,
I can choose "Product Archive"
to create the archive.
Once my archives are complete,
I can use the Organizer window in Xcode
to upload them to App Store Connect.
If I'm using Xcode Cloud,
I can add actions to my workflow to build,
test, and archive my products.
In my list of actions in my workflow,
I can create new items to build,
test, analyze,
and archive each of my products.
In this case,
I have an iOS app and a macOS app.
I can take it one step further
and include a deployment preparation
to automate uploading my app
to App Store Connect,
and I can even send those builds to
my internal TestFlight team right away
and start getting feedback
on the changes hot off the presses.
To summarize, Xcode 14
takes multiplatform app development
to the next level
with streamlined app targets
which can now support even more
destinations across multiple platforms.
With a single app target,
you can maintain a common codebase
and shared settings by default.
As demonstrated, we can conditionalize our
settings and code based on our needs,
letting us customize our app to
best match platform expectations.
The rest is up to you.
To learn more about new features
and improvements in Xcode this year,
check out "What's new in Xcode."
I can't wait to see what
incredible ideas you bring to life
with the power of Xcode and SwiftUI.