♪ ♪
Alex: Hello, my name is Alex,
and I work on Developer Tools.
Today I want to talk to you about the new
C++ 20 features supported in Xcode 14.
I will specifically focus on
how C++ 20 concepts simplify
and improve the type safety
of generic C++ code.
I will demonstrate how to use concepts
and will explain how to create
your own concepts as well.
I will end the talk by listing several
other new C++20 features supported
in Xcode, and will touch
on how some of them can be used
to improve the performance
of your C++ projects
through the power
of compile time code evaluation.
Before diving into C++ concepts,
let's first go over a quick overview
of how to write generic code in C++.
Let's say I want to write a function
that checks if a number is odd.
I can write a function
that takes in an 'int' parameter,
and it would work with any value
that can be represented by the 'int' type.
What would happen if I pass in
a 64 bit unsigned integer value to it?
A concrete function like this one does
not behave correctly with 64 bit values,
as they get truncated
to fit into the 'int' type.
To fix this,
I can make 'isOdd' a function template.
Now that I have a function template,
I can pass in the 64 bit
unsigned integer value to it.
The compiler will now automatically
generate a specialization of 'isOdd'
that works correctly
with the 'uint64_t' type.
This is really useful as it means
I don't have to write two versions
of 'isOdd'
that operate on two different types.
You can use C++ templates
to write generic functions like 'isOdd',
and generic container classes as well.
Let's take a look at how
'isOdd' can be used.
This function is tested with several
test cases that I added in my test file.
Unfortunately, I have made a mistake
in one of my tests.
The compiler caught the mistake,
but instead of pointing
to where I made the mistake,
the compiler shows an error
inside the 'isOdd' template.
It looks like I made a typo and wrote
out '1.1' in my test instead of '11'.
Because of that, the compiler generates
a specialization of 'isOdd'
that takes in a 'double' type.
Unfortunately,
it took me some time to find this typo
as Xcode didn't point me
to the specific location
where 'isOdd' was invoked
with incorrect type.
Can the language and the compiler
help me find mistakes like this faster?
Well, in the current example,
the requirements for what types
are allowed into 'isOdd'
are not specified explicitly.
There's only a documentation comment
that states that I must call isOdd
using integer types.
Prior to C++20,
C++ programmers did not have a good way
to specify template requirements
when writing generic C++ code.
They often had to resort
to documentation comments,
specific parameter names,
or complicated enable_if checks
when specifying template requirements.
Well, as you might've heard,
C++ 20 introduces
a new C++ feature called concepts.
You can use concepts to validate template
requirements in your generic C++ code.
Let's take a look at how concepts
can help me validate the types
that can be passed into 'isOdd'.
First, let's go back
to the declaration of 'isOdd'.
Currently, I use the 'class' keyword
to specify that type ‘T’ that's used by
this template can be any type.
C++ 20 allows me to use a concept
instead of the 'class' keyword
to restrict the set of types
that this template can be used with.
I can use the 'integral' concept
provided by the standard library
to restrict this 'isOdd' function template
only to the built-in integer types.
The compiler will not even try
to specialize this function template
when T does not satisfy this concept.
The integral concept is declared
in the C++ standard library.
So I need to include the concepts
header to use it in my code.
Now that I added an 'integral'
requirement to the type _T_
in the 'isOdd' function template,
the compiler is able to provide
a much clearer diagnostic
that points directly
at where I made the mistake in my tests.
Turns out, '1.1' is a double,
and therefore, it does not satisfy
the 'integral' concept.
The compiler is able to explain this to me
with a clear error message
that helps me find and fix this typo
much quicker than before.
In addition to helping me fix the bug,
constraining the type passed to 'isOdd'
gives me the peace of mind
that all the test cases
that I have for is 'isOdd'
work only with integer types,
and that they're actually testing
the intended behavior of the algorithm.
You can use concepts
to declare the intent
for which types your templates
are meant to be used with.
The compiler will then validate
the type requirements
before your templates are specialized.
Let's take a closer look
at how concepts can be used
and which core concepts are provided
by the C++ standard library.
The C++ standard library
provides a concepts library.
It implements a set
of core language concepts
that you can use to validate
the core behavior of a type.
You can access this library by including
the concepts header in your code.
I've already shown
how I can use the 'integral' concept
in my earlier example.
Now, let's take a look at the other
concepts provided by this library.
This library provides a number
of useful core language concepts,
like concepts that test
if a type is one of the built-in types.
For instance,
the 'floating_point' concept is satisfied
by built-in types
like 'float' and 'double'.
The 'static_assert' shown here
validates that this is indeed the case.
It also provides
a lot of other useful core concepts
that check if types are constructible,
destructible, convertible,
or are they the same as another type.
For instance,
the 'convertible_to' concept tests
if a type can be converted
to another type.
and the 'move_constructible' concept
is satisfied by types
that can be constructed directly
from another value of the same type.
This library also provides
several comparison concepts
that test if types can be compared
to other types.
For instance, the 'equality_comparable'
concept is satisfied by types
that have a valid '==' operator
that works with a value of the same type.
In addition to concepts
mentioned on this slide,
this library provides numerous
other core language concepts.
It also provides concepts that test
if a type can be moved or copied.
In addition to that,
it also provides concepts
that check if a type
is some callable object.
Now that we've looked over
the concepts provided to us
by the C++ standard library,
let's take a look at how concepts
can be used to constrain templates.
Like I've shown earlier, you can use
a concept instead of the class keyword
in a template to restrict which types
are allowed for this template.
In addition to that,
you can use a 'requires' clause
in a template declaration if you ever need
to constrain a type to multiple concepts.
Let's take a look at a slightly different
example to see how it can be done.
Here I have
'isDefaultValue' function template.
It returns true if the given value
is equal to the default value of its type.
I can use two concepts from
the standard library to test
that this type supports these operations
before this template is specialized.
I'm going to add the 'requires' clause
to restrict the set of types
which are allowed
for this function template.
Let's see which concepts from
the concepts library can help me
validate the type here.
First, the 'equality_comparable' concept
tests if _T_ can be compared
to another value of the same type.
Then, the 'default_constructible' concept
tests if _T_ is a type
with a default constructor.
The logical and operator between them
instructs the compiler
to validate both concepts.
This ensures that this function template
will only be specialized
with supported types.
Let's go over what we've learned
so far about concepts.
You should use concepts to restrict
the types which are allowed
to be used in your templates.
The compiler will then be able
to show clearer diagnostics
as the template won't have to be
specialized if a type mismatch occurs.
You should reuse the concepts
from the concepts library
if you need to validate
some core behavior of a type.
You should add the 'requires' clause
to your templates
when you need to test if types conform
to multiple requirements.
We've now seen how to use concepts
in C++ programs.
C++ allows us to declare custom concepts
that validate specific behavior of a type.
Let's take a look
at how to create our own concepts
that validate specific type behavior.
Before we do that, though,
we need to take a look
at how to identify
the behavioral requirements
that must be validated
by the concept we want to declare.
I'm going to use a new example
to illustrate
how to validate specific type behavior
using concepts.
Say I am building a C++ library
that can render various two-dimensional
shapes to an image.
I would like to support
various shapes in my library.
I'm starting out with a circle shape,
as it's the simplest to render.
I'm going to use a C++ class
to store its properties,
like position and radius.
In order to render the circle,
I'm going to use a distance-function based
rendering algorithm
that runs on each pixel
in the rendered image.
This algorithm needs to compute
the distance to the shape's surface
in order to render it.
The 'getDistanceFrom' method
in the Circle class computes it.
It returns a negative distance
inside the circle,
and a positive distance
outside the circle.
In addition to the circle,
I would like to render other shapes.
For instance, by geometrically subtracting
one circle shape
from another circle shape,
I can render a crescent shape as well.
I'm going to represent shapes
like Crescent that I would like
to render using classes as well.
Each new shape class includes
the 'getDistanceFrom' method.
After creating several shape classes,
I now would like to try rendering these
shapes to verify their implementation.
I have a couple of options for how
I can create the rendering function
that works with any shape.
I can create a class hierarchy
for the shapes,
and use a virtual method to compute
the distance to the shape's surface.
However, I'm going to use a function
template instead for performance reasons,
as I want to avoid
the virtual call overhead
as this function is going to be called
millions of times during rendering.
This is why I created
this rendering function template.
The computePixelColor function
takes in a shape value,
and checks if the given pixel
is inside the shape.
If it's inside,
it returns a plain white color.
This now allows me to verify
that shapes can be filled in correctly.
This function is a template,
which makes it work with any shape type,
be it a circle, crescent,
or any other matching type.
Even though a template works well here,
I would like to use concepts
to constrain the type
that can be passed to this function.
Constraining the type
that's passed to this function
will allow the compiler to produce clearer
diagnostics when a type mismatch occurs.
In addition to that, constraining the type
that's passed to this function
will also allow me to add
additional overloads of this function.
In order to constrain the type,
I'm going to create a Shape concept.
This concept
will validate the type's behavior,
and will accept classes
like circle, crescent,
and any other shape class
that I might want to add in the future.
In order to create a concept like 'Shape',
I first need to identify the requirements
that must be validated by this concept.
Let's see how this can be done.
This function template uses type 'T'
as the generic type.
An argument named 'shape' of type 'T'
is then passed to this function.
The 'shape' argument is then used
inside the function,
when I call
the 'getDistanceFrom' method on it.
As you can see,
this is the only requirement
I want to validate in my concept,
as no other operations are being performed
on shape in this function.
You can use the 'requires' expression
to test if a type behaves
in a specific manner.
Let's take a look at how I can use
'requires' to create the Shape concept.
I need to provide a set of expressions
that test the behavior
of a type inside the 'requires'.
I already identified the call
to 'getDistanceFrom'
as a single requirement I need to test,
so now I can go ahead
and create the 'Shape' concept.
I declared the shape concept
using the 'concept' keyword.
I then added the 'requires' expression
to this concept to validate the type.
I added an argument list
to the 'requires' expression.
This argument list allows me
to declare a value 'shape' of type 'T'
that I will then be testing
inside the 'requires'.
You can use an argument list in a requires
expression to declare values of any type.
You will then be able to use these values
inside the requires.
The body of the 'requires' expression
contains a set of requirements
that must pass
in order for this concept to be satisfied.
The 'shape' concept has just
one simple expression requirement
that checks whether a method call
to 'getDistanceFrom' is valid.
This expression isn't actually
going to be executed in the program.
It's only needed at compile time
to validate the type's behavior,
and it's discarded after the validation.
You can use expression requirements
to validate the type's behavior
by testing if a particular expression
compiles or not.
This particular expression
is not yet complete though,
as we're missing the arguments
to the 'getDistanceFrom' method call.
I know that I want this method
to take two values of type 'float',
so I can use two floating point literals
to complete this expression.
I am going to add an additional check
to test that 'getDistanceFrom' method
returns a float value,
as that's what is being assumed
by my generic code.
I'm currently using a simple
expression requirement
to test if the type has
the 'getDistanceFrom' method.
However, I can use a compound requirement
instead of the expression requirement
to test that it returns a float value.
The arrow operator can follow
a compound requirement.
The arrow operator expects a constraint
on its right hand side,
so this is where I can use a standard
library concept like 'same_as'
to validate that the call
to 'getDistanceFrom' method
returns a float value.
Now this concept looks ready to me.
I can go ahead and use it
to constrain the types
that can be passed
to my 'computePixelColor' function.
Now my generic
'computePixelColor' function
will only work with types
that satisfy the 'Shape' concept.
This means that classes like
Circle and Crescent will be rendered
using this particular generic
'computePixelColor' function,
as both of these types
satisfy the 'Shape' concept.
After seeing the plain shapes rendered,
I would like to create a different version
of 'computePixelColor'
that adds colors to some of my shapes.
Let's say I want to add a colorful
GradientCircle class to my shape library.
I now need a new function to compute
the pixel color in the image.
C++20 allows me
to create multiple variants
of the 'computePixelColor'
function template.
Each variant must be constrained
using different concepts.
I am going to create
a new GradientShape concept
that will be satisfied
by classes like GradientCircle.
This concept will then constrain
a new variant of 'computePixelColor'
that only works
with shapes that have a gradient.
This concept is implemented
using a 'requires' expression,
just like the Shape concept.
However, since I want GradientShape
to satisfy the original Shape concept
as well,
I include it as the first requirement
in the new concept.
This ensures that a class
that satisfies the GradientShape concept
also satisfies the Shape concept,
which means I can still call
the 'getDistanceFrom' method
for values of such class.
I then use the logical and operator
and the 'requires' expression
to ensure that the GradientShape
concept can only be satisfied
by classes that have
the 'getGradientColor' method.
Now that I have created
the GradientShape concept,
I can go ahead and create
a new variant of 'computePixelColor'.
This function template only works
with shape classes with a gradient,
like the GradientCircle class,
as it is constrained
by the GradientShape concept.
Now that I have all the pieces in place,
I can go ahead and try rendering a circle
with a gradient.
Here I'm rendering a GradientCircle.
Let's see which overload
of 'computePixelColor'
the compiler is going to pick
inside the 'render' function.
Even though GradientCircle can
be safely used with both variants
of computePixelColor, the compiler picks
the overload that is constrained
with the GradientShape concept
as it's more specific
than the first overload.
Because the compiler picks the most
matching overload of 'computePixelColor',
I can see this beautiful gradient circle
rendered when I test my library.
Amazing!
Now let's go over what we've learned
about creating concepts.
You can create concepts by identifying
the behavioral requirements
in your existing generic code.
You should use the requires expression
to create concepts
to validate the behavior of types.
You can also use concepts
to create more specific variants
of generic functions and classes.
We've now seen how to enhance
your generic C++ code with concepts.
In addition to supporting concepts,
Xcode 14 has improved its support
for other C++20 features as well.
More specifically,
I would like to highlight
the improved support for compile-time
C++ code evaluation in Xcode 14.
Compile time code evaluation is useful
as it can reduce the cost
of initialization
for variables in your C++ code.
This could help reduce
your app launch time
if your app has a lot of C++ code
that depends on
complex initialization sequences.
In addition to that,
compile time code evaluation
can help you validate constants
that require validation at compile time.
This could help you catch bugs
before your code even runs.
Let's take a look at an example
to see how I can use compile time code
evaluation in C++.
Here I have a snippet of code
that initializes a color palette
in my shape rendering library.
This library is then used in an iOS app
that renders the shapes to the display.
Each color in the palette is initialized
by parsing a string literal
with the HTML hex code of the color.
Currently, the 'fromHexCode' function
needs to parse three string literals
during the initialization of the array.
Complicated constant initialization
operations like this one
can have a measurable impact on the launch
time of my app if I have a lot of them.
I can use compile-time code evaluation
to ensure that this array is initialized
with constant color values instead.
Let me show you can this can be done.
The 'constexpr' keyword enables
compile-time code evaluation in C++.
I must add it in several places
in my example
in order to ensure
that palette is a constant color array.
First, I need to add the 'constexpr'
keyword to the 'fromHexCode' function.
The compiler will be now be able
to execute the code in this function
at compile time when it's used
in a compile time initialization sequence.
You should make your C++ functions
'constexpr' when you want them
to be evaluatable at compile time.
The compiler will let you know
if the code in such function
cannot be evaluated at compile time
by showing an error
when you use it in a 'constexpr'
initialization sequence.
However, you can also examine
a function before adding 'constexpr'
to see if it can be evaluated
at compile time.
Let's take a peek into fromHexCode
to see how to check
if a function like this one
can be a good candidate
for compile time code evaluation.
This function uses
a number of language constructs
like if statements,
and primitive operations like comparison
operators and arithmetic operators.
All of these operations can be evaluated
at compile time.
Also, this function makes several calls
to another function; hexToInt.
I have already annotated
hexToInt function with 'constexpr',
so calls to this function
can be evaluated at compile time.
Overall, it looks like
fromHexCode contains code
that the compiler should be able
to evaluate at compile time,
so I think it's safe to proceed and use it
in a compile time initialization sequence.
After making sure that fromHexCode
can be evaluated at compile time,
I then need to add the 'constexpr' keyword
to the 'colorPalette'
variable declaration.
The compiler now guarantees
that it will evaluate
the entire initialization sequence
for this array at compile time.
More specifically,
the compiler will evaluate each call
to the fromHexCode function.
The evaluation will produce
a constant color value
that will replace the original call to
the function in the palette's initializer.
Since all the calls to fromHexCode
are now replaced by constant color values,
the 'colorPalette' variable
is now guaranteed to be initialized
by an array literal
that contains constant color values.
This means that now my app
doesn't have to pay additional cost
for parsing the color values
when this palette is initialized.
This is great
for the launch time of my app,
as it reduces the amount of work
this C++ library
inside the app has to do at startup.
You should make
your C++ variables 'constexpr'
when you want to ensure that they are
initialized with constant values.
Xcode 14 has actually greatly improved
its standard library support
for compile time evaluation.
This year we've added
the 'constexpr' support
to several different
standard library types and algorithms,
which can now be used during
compile-time code evaluation.
In addition to that,
Xcode 14 has greatly improved
its C++20 standard support.
All of the features shown here
can now be used in C++ 20 mode.
You should switch to C++ 20 mode today
if you haven't already done so.
You can use
the "C++ Language Dialect" setting
in your Xcode project
to upgrade to C++ 20.
Switching to C++20 will let you use
features like concepts in your code.
C++20 does not require
a minimum deployment target,
so you can still ship your code
for the same OS version
that you're currently targeting.
Try C++20 today.
Thank you!
Enjoy the rest
of the developer's conference.