♪ ♪
Hi, my name is Nik,
and I'm an engineer on the Video team.
Today I'm excited to talk to you
about media metadata publishing
and playback interactions.
So what exactly does that mean?
There are a number of places
on Apple devices
where playback information is displayed,
and where playback can be controlled.
For example, the Now Playing section
of Control Center displays the artwork,
title, and progress for media
that is currently playing on the device.
It also lets you play, pause,
or even skip forward or backward.
Expanding the Now Playing tile shows more
details, like the artwork and progress.
it also allows you to scrub
and increase or decrease the volume.
Lock Screen also displays
the same information and controls,
giving users a convenient place
to check in on progress, pause,
or even AirPlay to another device
without needing to unlock.
No matter what device is playing,
the Now Playing app on Apple Watch
provides the same experience.
It even has an Apple TV remote built in.
On tvOS when using AVKit,
the info overlay
when controls are presented
will show title and chapter information.
When you swipe down to the info pane,
more details like the artwork
and description are shown.
Holding the TV button on
your Apple TV remote shows Control Center,
which like iOS has a Now Playing tile
that also can be expanded.
When audio content starts playing
from the background on tvOS,
be it from pressing the play button
on the remote,
or from selecting a track
in the Music app from another device,
a notification with the Now Playing
information is presented.
Additionally, after a brief period of
inactivity on tvOS when playing audio,
a full screen overlay showing
what's currently playing is presented.
Lastly, on iOS,
the Control Other Speakers and TVs button
lets you view the Now Playing information
on all of your devices,
as well as control playback.
With the growing number of devices and UIs
where Now Playing information is presented
and where playback can be controlled from,
properly publishing
Now Playing information
and responding to remote commands
is more important than ever.
Over the course
of the rest of this session,
we will cover responding
to playback interactions
in the form of remote commands,
automatic metadata publishing,
publishing with AVKit,
and manual publishing.
When using AVFoundation
for media playback,
the best way
to publish Now Playing metadata
and respond to playback interactions
is using the MPNowPlayingSession class.
Historically, this class has only
been available on tvOS,
but is now available on iOS 16.
It is used to represent
a distinct playback session,
and offers control over Now Playing status
if your app contains
multiple active sessions.
It supports both
manual metadata publishing,
as well as the new automatic publishing
available in iOS and tvOS 16.
MPNowPlayingSession shouldn't be used
on tvOS when using AVKit,
which has its own
automatic publishing mechanisms
we'll cover later in the session.
Being the "Now Playing" app means
that your app is what will populate
Control Center, Lock Screen, etcetera,
and receive the playback controls
when the user, for example, presses
pause from one of those interfaces.
With MPNowPlayingSession,
you can represent multiple
concurrent playback sessions
within a single app.
However, when using multiple sessions,
your app must promote one
as the active session
that will appear throughout the system
when remote controlling your app.
For example, with Picture in Picture
you may have two
concurrent playback sessions,
where the full screen playback
should be considered
the active Now Playing session.
The system also has a few heuristics
to qualify apps as Now Playing eligible.
First, you must register a handler
for at least one remote command.
As you can imagine, an app that won't
respond to any playback interactions
is most likely not an ideal candidate
to show up as the Now Playing app.
Second, your apps AVAudioSession
must be configured
with a non-mixable category
and category option.
Mixable playback categories
and options are generally used
when playing back notifications,
and therefore this is a good indication
to the system that whatever is playing is
also not a good candidate for Now Playing.
Here's a few examples
to help understand playback sessions.
In this example there is a single piece
of content playing,
so this would be represented
using a single MPNowPlayingSession.
If your app supports PiP,
you would have two MPNowPlayingSessions:
one for the main player,
and one for the PiP playback.
A more complex scenario would be
a single MPNowPlayingSession
that has several players.
In this example, we have four players, one
in each quadrant,
showing different points of view
for the same race.
Players added to the same
MPNowPlayingSession
should always be part of the same content.
And here's how each of these
example sessions would be instantiated.
The first, we're just playing
a single piece of content,
so we have the single session
with the single player.
The second example
is using Picture-in-Picture,
so we have two sessions,
each with a single player.
The first being the full screen content,
and the second being the content in PiP.
The last example, the multi-view race,
is represented
with a single session with four players.
When an app does have multiple sessions,
it's the apps responsibility for promoting
a given session as active when applicable.
For example,
if media is playing in Picture-in-Picture,
if the user expands it to be full screen,
the previously full screen session
should no longer be active,
or Now Playing, and the PiP session
that is now full screen
should become active.
This transition can be done
by calling becomeActiveIfPossible
on MPNowPlayingSession.
Now that we've covered the basics
of setting up instances
of MPNowPlayingSession
and controlling the Now Playing session,
let's talk about receiving
and responding to remote commands,
be it from Lock Screen,
or from a HomePod in another room.
Let's start off with a basic example
of registering
for the play and pause command.
Doing so will enable your app
to receive callbacks
when the user presses play or pause
from another device,
or issues that command using Siri.
First, we instantiate
our MPNowPlayingSession.
Since we only have one session,
we don't need to invoke
the 'becomeActiveIfPossible' method.
When you only have one session,
it will be the default session
when your app is the Now Playing app.
Each MPNowPlayingSession instance has
its own MPRemoteCommandCenter instance,
which is used to declare
which remote commands
your playback session can respond to.
Next we add a handler for the playCommand
where we invoke the play method
on our player, and return success.
Then we do the same for the pauseCommand.
You should add handlers
for every command that your app supports
and that is applicable
for the currently playing content.
Another example is the skip forward
and skip backward command.
This command should be used
for most content,
and wouldn't be applicable, for example,
live streams
where jumping forward isn't possible.
First we have to indicate
what our preferred intervals are,
or the number of seconds we prefer
to jump in either direction.
In this case, we use 15 seconds.
Then similar to what we did
for the play and pause commands,
we add a handler that will be invoked
when the user presses
the skip forward button
or asks Siri to skip forward.
In our handler, we will be receiving
an MPSkipIntervalCommandEvent,
so first we will cast the event
to that type.
We then calculate the new elapsed time
by taking the current time,
and the interval provided to us
in the MPSkipIntervalCommandEvent,
seek to it, and return success to indicate
that we jumped to the new position.
It's also possible
that your app has situations
where a command
is temporarily not allowed,
for example skipping forward
while in an advertisement.
In that case,
the skipForwardCommand can be disabled.
Now that we're responding
to remote commands,
we will cover
automatic metadata publishing.
Automatic publishing takes the hard work
out of keeping metadata accurate
by automatically maintaining
metadata properties it can observe
directly from the player such as duration,
the current elapsed time,
the playback state, and playback progress.
If the content has ads baked into it
that shouldn't contribute
to the total duration and elapsed time,
it can also take care of calculating
the net time and report that instead.
Other metadata such as the title,
description, and artwork can be added
to the AVPlayerItems directly
using the nowPlayingInfo property.
In this example,
we will use automatic publishing
to do the bulk of the work
and set the title and artwork ourselves.
First, we create
a new MPMediaItemArtwork instance,
passing in the artwork image.
Most apps will perform a network request
to fetch this.
Then we set the string title
of the content.
Then we take our artwork and title
and set them
as the nowPlayingInfo dictionary
on the current player item using
MPMediaItemPropertyTitle
and MPMediaItemPropertyArtwork.
Now Playing metadata can consist of
both MPMediaItemProperty's
and MPNowPlayingInfoProperty's.
Lastly, we create
our MPNowPlayingSession instance
passing in our player,
and set automaticallyPublishNowPlayingInfo
to true.
Once automaticallyPublishNowPlayingInfo
is set to true,
the MPNowPlayingSession instance
will begin observing the player
for state changes such as scrubbing,
play/pause events,
or the current player item changing.
Here's another example where we will show
how to use automatic publishing
for instances where
ads are baked into the asset
and you don't want the total duration or
current elapsed time to include ad time.
To do this, we'll create instances
of MPAdTimeRange
for every ad that we have baked in.
In this example,
we have a single 30-second ad
that starts at the very beginning.
So we create it with a starting point
of zero, and a duration of 30 seconds.
Similar to how we did the title
and artwork earlier,
we simply add an array of MPAdTimeRange's
to the nowPlayingInfo dictionary
on the player item using
the MPNowPlayingInfoPropertyAdTimeRanges.
Then just as we did before,
create the MPNowPlayingSession
and enable automatic publishing.
Next is metadata publishing with AVKit.
Publishing Now Playing metadata with AVKit
on tvOS works very similar
to MPNowPlayingSession:
metadata is added
directly to the AVPlayerItem,
and values like elapsed time, duration,
and playback state are published
and kept up to date for you.
The metadata gathered from the player
and asset directly,
combined with the metadata provided
by your app on the AVPlayerItem
are also used to populate the info pane
in the player UI.
AVKit also takes care of registering for
and responding to remote commands.
Using AVKit is the best and easiest way to
integrate with the platform features
we've discussed so far, as well as others
such as AirPlay and Picture-in-Picture.
Setting the metadata when using AVKit
is done using the externalMetadata array
on the AVPlayerItem, which consists of
the AVMetadataItem instances
to describe your content.
You usually up setting three values
on each AVMetadataItem.
First, the identifier, which is the key
to indicate what metadata
the AVMetadataItem represents.
For example,
AVMetadataCommonIdentifierTitle
for the content title,
or AVMetadataCommonIdentifierArtwork
for the artwork.
Second is the value.
For title, this would
be a string containing the title.
For artwork, this would be an NSData
instance containing image data.
The dataType is used to indicate
the format of the artwork provided.
If it contained JPEG data,
kCMMetadatabaseDataType_JPEG
would be used.
Lastly, the extendedLanguageTag
is used to indicate the language used
for strings
such as the title and description.
Most of the time, the value
"und" should be used here
to ensure all audiences
see the same values.
You may be tempted to use
"en-us" if the values are in English,
but doing so would cause devices with
the language set to any other language
such as Spanish to not show the metadata.
Here we have an example where
we are setting the artwork and title.
First, we grab the artwork image data
from our bundle.
Most apps will fetch this
from a network resource.
Then we instantiate
a new mutable AVMetadataItem.
We set the identifier
to .commonIdentifierArtwork.
Then we set the value as the raw
artwork image data as NSData.
Since the image data is JPEG,
we set the dataType
to kCMMetadataBaseDataType_JPEG.
If your artwork was instead a PNG,
you would use
kCMMetadataBaseDataType_PNG.
Because we want this metadata
to be visible
to users with devices set to any language,
we set the extendedLanguageTag
to "und," or "undefined."
We then repeat the same steps for
the title, using .commonIdentifierTitle,
and the string title for the value,
and "und" once again
for the extendedLanguageTag.
Once we've set up
all of our metadata items,
we add them to an array and
set it to the AVPlayerItem's
externalMetadata property.
Now that we have the artwork and title
added to the player item,
you can see how this maps to what is shown
in Control Center and Lock Screen on iOS.
Like artwork, there are other
metadata types that can be set
such as the description,
subtitle information, and content rating.
Your app should set
as many of these as possible
to provide the user with
as rich of an experience as possible.
So far we've covered automatic publishing
with MPNowPlayingSession
and publishing with AVKit.
But MPNowPlayingSession
and its automatic publishing feature
require passing
an AVPlayer instance to it.
That may not be an option for all apps,
and manual publishing is still possible.
Publishing manually requires
that you provide values for all metadata.
Unlike automatic publishing,
information such as elapsed time
and playback rate can't be determined
by the system for you.
This means that you have manual fine grain
control over low level playback state,
and your app is responsible for keeping
it accurate over time as playback changes.
Note that registering for
and responding to remote commands
is still required as well,
and because we are not using
MPNowPlayingSession,
the shared instance
of MPRemoteCommandCenter must be used.
Here's a basic example showing how
to update the Now Playing Info dictionary.
First, we create an MPMediaItemArtwork
instance containing the image,
similar to what we did
for automatic publishing.
Then, we create a dictionary containing
the metadata that we have available.
In this case, we set the title, artwork,
and the player values duration,
elapsed time, and playback rate.
We then set it on
the MPNowPlayingInfoCenter
default instance.
Updates to this metadata should be made
any time significant changes happen
during playback,
such as a play or pause,
the user scrubs forwards or backwards,
or a new piece of content begins playing.
You do not need to update
elapsed time periodically.
The system will always infer
the correct elapsed time
based on how much time has passed
since the last update.
Now that you are familiar with all of
the different ways to publish Now Playing
metadata and respond to remote commands
from other devices and interfaces,
you should integrate to maximize
the user experience.
It's easier than ever.
Existing integrations can benefit too–
switching to automatic publishing is an
easy way to prevent future regressions
and minimize the amount of code
you must maintain.
For more information,
see MediaPlayer on developer.apple.com.
Thanks for watching.