♪ ♪
Hello!
My name is Tom,
and I'm part of the Swift team at Apple.
Today I'd like to share what it takes to
extend an iOS application into the cloud.
Many of our applications start out
focusing on a single device,
usually the iPhone.
As usage grows,
we find ourselves wanting to bring it
to additional devices like the Mac,
the watch,
or other Apple platforms and devices.
Xcode helps us organize and build
our application for these platforms.
We can share code using packages
while embracing the unique aspects
of each device
in the platform specific application code.
As systems continue to grow and evolve,
applications often need to complement
the client application
with a server component.
These server components enable
the client application
to extend their functionality
into the cloud.
For example,
offload tasks that can be done
in the background,
offload tasks
that are computational heavy,
or tasks that require access to data
that is not available on the device.
Often, server components need to be built
using different tools and methodologies
from their client counterparts,
creating duplication of effort
and integration challenges.
Using Swift for
building server components
help bridge this technology gap,
providing a familiar environment
across the stack.
Let's see what building a server
application in Swift looks like.
Server applications are modeled
as Swift packages.
The package defines an executable target
that maps the application entry point.
To make the application
into a web application,
we can add a dependency
on a web framework
that helps us structure our code
and provides basic utilities like routing.
In this example,
we use the Vapor web framework,
an open source community project
popular for building web services.
As with other Swift based executables,
the program's entry point is best modeled
using the @main annotation.
To integrate the web framework,
we add the relevant bootstrap code
to the main function.
The Application type used in this example
is provided by the Vapor web framework.
With the basic bootstrapping in place,
we can make our application
do something useful.
For example, let's add code to greet users
making a request to the server.
We use the web framework to define
an HTTP endpoint
and point it to a method
that provides the greeting.
Taking a step further,
we add a second HTTP endpoint,
this one handling an HTTP post request,
and echoing the content
of the request body back to the caller.
Let's see this in action.
Here we have our server application
in Xcode.
Since we're just getting started,
we can run the server locally
on our own machine to test things out.
To run it locally,
we pick the "MyServer" scheme
that was generated for us by Xcode,
use the “My Mac" as the destination,
and hit "run".
Once the application has launched,
we can use Xcode console to examine
log messages emitted by the server.
In this case,
we can see that the server started
and listening on the localhost address
(127.0.0.1) port 8080.
We can use this information
to test our server.
Let's switch over to the terminal,
and make a request
to the advertised server address.
We use a utility called "curl"
to make the request.
Use our first endpoint.
And our second one.
Pass in some data to echo.
Nice!
Using the terminal sure was fun,
but what we really want to know is
how to call our server from an iOS app.
Let's dig into that.
Here is an example
of a Swift data structure
we can use to abstract the interaction
with the server.
We model the server APIs as async methods
on our abstraction,
because networking is
inherently asynchronous.
We use URLSession
to make an asynchronous request
then parse the server response
and finally return it to the caller.
In this case,
the server response is a plain string,
but in reality,
it is likely to be more sophisticated.
For example,
the response may be encoded in JSON,
in which case we can decode it using
Swift's Codable system.
Let's put this all together in Xcode.
We are using an Xcode workspace
to build and test
the iOS and server applications
side by side.
We already have the iOS application
server abstraction ready to go.
Let's change the default SwiftUI
ContentView to fetch the server greeting
using the code we put together.
First we create a state variable
called serverGreeting.
Next, we bind the serverGreeting
to the Text display.
Finally,
we add a task to call the server API,
and set the state.
With the code ready, we can run
the application in the simulator.
We pick the "MyApp" scheme,
a simulator,
and hit "run".
Oh, no! We got an error!
Hmm, this seems to be
some sort of a connection error.
The address seems right,
so we must have forgotten
to start the local server.
Let's switch back to Xcode,
pick the server scheme,
and run the server.
Now, let's restart our application,
cross our fingers...
And whoo-hoo! It worked!
To complete this part of the demo,
let's deploy our application to the cloud.
There are many cloud providers
to choose from, including AWS,
Google Cloud, Azure, Heroku,
and many others.
In this example, we will use Heroku.
Heroku has a convenient
git push to deploy system
for small projects like this
demo application.
Let's switch over to the terminal
to kick off a deployment.
After setting up our account,
and configuring our application
with the Heroku service, we can git push
our code to the Heroku remote.
[silence while typing]
And off it goes!
Heroku uses a technology called buildpacks
to compile the application remotely,
then deploys the binary artifacts
to an ephemeral host.
Heroku swift buildpack was built
by members
of the Swift open source community,
and it is available
for all Swift on Server users.
With our application deployed,
we can test it using curl,
as we have done with our local server.
Let's test the first endpoint.
Copy the address here.
And our second one.
This time, we'll send a different payload.
Sweet,
our application was successfully deployed!
Before we continue, let's pause here
and review the main takeaways
from this part of the talk.
If you're already using Swift
to build iOS or macOS Applications,
you could also be using it for
developing the server side of the system.
Xcode helps us develop and debug
the different components of the system,
both the client and the server,
all in one Workspace.
And finally,
you have a choice of cloud providers
for deploying
Swift based server applications.
Additional information about deploying
to these cloud platforms
can be found
on the Swift Server documentation
at swift.org.
Now that we have seen a basic setup,
let's look at a more real example–
Food Truck!
You've probably seen this application
used in many of our sessions.
Let's peek under the hood
and see how data is managed.
Hmm, looks like the donut list
is hard coded.
This means that users of the application
may see a different menu of donuts
from what is actually available.
While this may be useful
for a small Food Truck operation,
one that can make
any kind of donut on the spot,
we want to build a donuts empire
where the menu is centralized and
the trucks are all about customer service.
Let's design how our centralized
Food Truck system may look like.
We are starting out with our iOS app,
with its in-memory storage.
To centralize the menu, we can extract
the storage from the iOS app
and move it to the server.
This will allow all users of the app
to share the same storage,
and thus, the same donuts menu.
Similar to the example
in the first part of the talk,
our server will expose an HTTP based API.
The iOS app will use an abstraction
for working with these APIs,
then tie them back together
to the presentation tier,
in this example, SwiftUI.
Our design is complete.
Time to write some sweet code.
You can follow along by downloading
the Food Truck sample app
from the developer resource kit.
We start building our Server
with an application skeleton,
then define an HTTP endpoint
for the "donuts" web API,
and point it to the "listDonuts" method
on our server abstraction.
You may have noticed that the API returns
a Response of type Donuts
and that Response.Donuts conforms
to a protocol called Content.
The Content protocol
is defined by the web framework
and helps us encode the response
as JSON on the wire.
You may have also noticed
that the API includes an array
of a mysterious Model.Donut,
which we have yet to define
So here it is,
our data model in all of its glory:
Donut, Dough, Glaze, and Topping.
One interesting point to make here
is that we copied the definition
of this model from our Food Truck iOS app,
as we need the data models of the server
and the client to roughly align.
Another interesting point is the
conformance to the Encodable protocol.
This is required so that our server
can encode the model objects
as JSON over the wire.
With the data model
and basic APIs in place,
we can expand our logic
to include a storage abstraction.
The storage will provide the Application
with the list of available donuts.
At this point, we should have
a fully functional server.
But wait!
Our donuts menu is empty!
Where should we get
the our centralized menu from?
Storage is always an interesting topic
when designing server side applications.
There are several strategies
to choose from,
depending on the use case.
If the application data is static
or changes very slowly and manually,
files on disk may provide
a good enough solution.
For user-centric data or global datasets,
iCloud provides a set of APIs that you can
use directly from the iOS application,
without deploying a dedicated server.
When dealing with dynamic
or transactional data,
databases provide an excellent solution.
There is a variety of database
technologies available
for server-side applications.
Each technology is designed
for specific performance,
data consistency,
and data modeling needs.
Over the years,
the Swift open source community
developed database drivers
that help interact natively
with most databases technologies.
Partial list includes Postgres, MySQL,
MongoDB, Redis, DynamoDB,
and many others.
For the purposes of simplifying this demo,
we will only demonstrate
a static file storage strategy,
but you can learn more
about using databases
on the Swift Server documentation
at swift.org.
Since we are using
a static file storage strategy,
we start off by creating a JSON file
that captures the donut menu.
After creating this file,
we can make it accessible
to the application
using SwiftPM's resources support.
With that in place, it is time to make our
storage abstraction more sophisticated.
Namely, we add a "load" method.
This method finds the resource file path
using SwiftPM's
generated resource accessor,
then uses FileManager APIs to load
the content of the file into memory.
Finally, we use JSONDecoder
to decode the JSON content
into the server application data model.
One interesting change is that
Storage is now defined as an actor.
We chose to use an actor because Storage
now has a mutable "donuts" variable,
and which the "load" and "listDonuts"
methods might access concurrently.
Actors,
which were first introduced in Swift 5.5,
help us avoid data races
and deal with shared mutable state
in a safe but easy way.
Prior to the introduction of actors,
we would have needed to remember
and add synchronization blocks
when accessing mutable state
using APIs such as Locks or Queues.
With the storage updates done,
we can tie it all together.
We add a "bootstrap" method
to our server abstraction
and load the storage from there.
Then we wire up the bootstrap
to the executables entry point.
Note that since storage is now an actor,
we access it in an async context.
Our server is ready.
Let's switch over to the client side.
We start by adding a Server abstraction
that will help us encapsulate
the server APIs.
We use URLSession to make the HTTP request
and a JSONDecoder
to decode the server response
and transform it from JSON into our iOS
application model.
At this point,
we can remove the hard coded menu
and replace it with an asynchronous fetch
from the server.
Finally, we make the call to the server
from the ContentView load task.
Time to test!
This time,
let's not forget to start the server.
We'll select
the "FoodTruckServer" scheme here.
Hit run.
And with the application running,
let's jump on the terminal
and see that we can access the APIs.
Copy the address again.
This time, we're going to use
a utility called jq
to print the JSON output more nicely.
This looks pretty good.
All right, time to test with our App.
Switch to Xcode.
Pick the Food Truck scheme here.
Simulator.
And run it.
And there we have it,
the three donuts
from our centralized menu.
We can cross reference that
with what we see from the server.
Let's switch back to the terminal.
To make the comparison easy, we will use
jq to query just the name of the donuts.
Deep space, Chocolate 2,
Coffee Caramel–
exactly what we expected.
That was amazing!
But we can do even better.
As it stands,
our server and client applications
both have identical copies
of the data model code.
We can avoid repetition
and make serialization safer,
by sharing the model
across the iOS and server applications.
Let's review how to set this up
at a high level.
First, we create another package
for a library named "Shared"
and add it to the Xcode workspace.
We can then move the data model code to
the Shared package,
add Shared as a dependency
of the server application,
and as a dependency of the iOS
application,
using the Target Frameworks
and Libraries settings.
At which point,
we can refactor our client code
to use the shared model
and do the same
to the server code.
Things look much nicer now.
Before we conclude, here are some ideas of
where we can take the application next.
To take full advantage of the fact
that we have a centralized server,
we are likely to want and define APIs for
adding, editing, or deleting donuts from the menu.
This will require that we move our storage
from a static file to a database.
With a database in place, we can also
implement buying and ordering APIs.
Such APIs can help us
monetize our donut business.
They also provide a signal,
which we can use to implement
dynamic pricing,
like sales and discounts
for those donuts that are less popular.
The opportunities are endless.
To wrap up,
in this session we have seen
that Swift is a general purpose language,
useful for both client and server
applications,
sharing code between the server
and client applications
can reduce boilerplate
and make our system serialization safer,
URLSession is a key tool for interacting
with the server asynchronously,
and finally, Xcode is
a powerful development environment
for the entire system.
Thank you so much for watching,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.