♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hey, my name is Daniel, and I'm
on the Security Engineering
and Architecture team.
I'm going to give you
an update on Endpoint Security.
Endpoint Security
is an API that we provide,
so you can build
security products for the Mac.
It is a C API, providing a rich
security event stream
to third-party anti-virus,
Endpoint Detection
and Response,
and data-leakage
prevention solutions.
We first introduced Endpoint
Security in macOS Catalina
as a replacement for
the deprecated KAuth KPI,
the unsupported MAC
Kernel Framework,
and the also deprecated
OpenBSM audit trail.
By making this functionality
available
in the Endpoint Security API,
we removed the need
for you to have to develop
kernel extensions.
The introduction
of Endpoint Security
has been
a resounding success.
We are thrilled with
the positive feedback we receive
and with the security products
that it is enabling.
For an introduction
to Endpoint Security,
refer to
the WWDC 2020 session
"Build an
Endpoint Security app."
In this session,
we'll be covering new events
added in macOS Ventura,
improvements
to muting functionality,
as well as a new utility
called eslogger.
Let's start with the new events.
As of macOS Monterey,
Endpoint Security supports
over a hundred event types.
Up until now, these events
focused on critical events
that happen within the kernel,
such as forking a process
or opening a file.
In macOS Ventura,
we're expanding the set
of observable events to include
security-relevant events
happening in user space.
Specifically, we are adding
visibility into authentication,
login and logout,
and Gatekeeper's XProtect.
The new authentication event
covers the situation
where a user authenticates
to the operating system.
This includes logging
into local user accounts,
but also authenticating
in other places,
such as to authorize an
operation as an administrator.
These events are typically
used by security products
that wish to observe
suspicious access patterns.
Previously, if you wished to
observe authentication events,
you still had to rely on the
deprecated OpenBSM audit trail
to do so; this will now
no longer be necessary.
And compared
to their audit counterparts,
these new events are
much richer in information,
and also provide visibility into
Auto Unlock using Apple Watch,
which wasn't available in audit.
In a similar vein, we're adding
visibility into user sessions.
Login events cover situations
where someone or something
logs on to the system,
either locally at the console
or remotely over one
of the supported methods
of remote access.
These events go substantially
beyond what was available
with the OpenBSM audit trail.
They allow you to gain
more comprehensive visibility
into access to systems,
including lateral movement
across enterprise fleets.
Part of Gatekeeper's mission
is to detect and block
known malicious software.
Starting with macOS Ventura,
Endpoint Security
will provide visibility
into both the detection
of malicious software
and into actions taken to stop
and remove malicious software.
This information was previously
unavailable in a structured way.
It is now available through
the Endpoint Security API.
We expect that
with these additions,
most Endpoint Security clients
no longer need
to rely onto the deprecated
OpenBSM audit trail at all.
The audit trail has been
deprecated since macOS Big Sur
and will be removed
in a future version of macOS.
Let's move on to muting.
Since macOS Catalina, we have
supported muting processes
by audit token
or executable image path.
Muting is an important tool
we give you
to prevent deadlocks, hangs,
and watchdog timeouts,
and to manage the performance
impact of your solutions
based on Endpoint Security.
In macOS Monterey last year,
we started to address
frequent causes
of system instability
by muting some event types
for a small set
of executables by default.
You are free to unmute those,
but we do recommend
you keep them muted in the
interest of system stability.
In macOS Ventura, we are
taking muting one step further
by introducing muting
based on target path.
For many real-world use cases,
this allows for scalpel-like
precision over muting.
You can now mute file events
pertaining to certain paths
or path prefixes
that your application
is not interested in receiving.
This shows how
you might mute all events
having a target path
under /var/log
when you're not interested
in events for log files.
The second example shows
how you might use
es_mute_path_events
to mute only write events
to a single file,
such as /dev/null.
And what's more, we're even
introducing the possibility
to invert muting logic.
Instead of suppressing events
based on specified process,
executable path, or target path,
we now allow you to invert
any of these
three types of muting.
Effectively, you can now select
processes, executable paths,
or target paths
you are interested in
to only receive events
that match --
instead of don't match --
anything you've muted.
For example, this now allows you
to select file events
only for certain
persistence locations.
Here's how you would use
es_invert_muting
to invert muting
for target paths.
You would then proceed to remove
previously existing target paths
from the mute set,
and then select only events
with the target-path prefix
that you are interested in.
We expect this to allow for much
improved muting strategies,
and ultimately,
to make it easier
to provide a great
user experience
with products
based on Endpoint Security.
And finally,
we're introducing eslogger.
We have had many requests
for a capability
to provide
Endpoint Security events
without the need
to write a native client.
Starting in macOS Ventura,
you will be able to harness
the power of Endpoint Security
via a command-line utility
that brings deep introspection
into the OS.
eslogger taps into the
Endpoint Security event stream
for specific events and emits
JSON-formatted event data
to standard output or
to the unified logging system.
Data is structured just
like the C representation
native clients use.
eslogger supports all
80 NOTIFY events
that Endpoint Security
supports in macOS Ventura.
We hope eslogger will be useful
not only for engineers
working on
Endpoint Security clients,
but also for security analysts
and other security practitioners
who need visibility into
security-relevant events
on macOS.
eslogger ships with the OS
and is already entitled
for Endpoint Security.
Like all Endpoint Security
clients,
eslogger must be run
as superuser
and requires the user
to have authorized
the responsible process
for Full Disk Access,
such as Terminal.app or SSH.
eslogger is not intended
to be used by applications.
Its output is subject to change
in software updates.
It is neither meant
to provide the same
performance characteristics,
nor the same feature set,
as natively interfacing with
the Endpoint Security API does.
Applications will continue
to interface natively.
With that out of the way,
let's use eslogger
to explore some
of the new events.
I'm going to use eslogger
to log the start
and end of an SSH session
by subscribing
to the openssh_login
and _logout events
and redirecting output
to a file.
Now in this other tab,
I'm using SSH
to locally log in
and log out again.
[KEYSTROKES]
Back in the first tab,
I'm interrupting eslogger.
Let's have a look at the
Endpoint Security event data
in its raw JSON form.
[KEYSTROKES]
It's very likely that you will
have your own favorite way
to work with JSON data.
Here, I will use jq
to examine the events further.
[KEYSTROKES]
This is a lot of information.
I'll just drill down
to some interesting fields.
Like all Endpoint Security
events,
we have information on
the process that emitted them.
[KEYSTROKES]
We can see that both events
were emitted by the SSH daemon.
We can also inspect,
for instance,
its audit token to glean
the PID of the process
that emitted the events.
[KEYSTROKES]
And finally, let's have a look
at the event-specific fields
of these events.
[KEYSTROKES]
We can see that this was
a successful SSH login
into my user account,
followed by a logout.
I love how I can get visibility
into Endpoint Security
events this way,
whether I want to observe
malicious software behavior,
or to just quickly prototype
a detection approach.
We look forward to seeing
your security solutions
take advantage
of the new events
as well as of the improved
muting capabilities.
Thanks for joining us at WWDC.
♪