♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Hi! My name is Bea, and I'm
a human interface designer
on the Documentation team.
I'm going to share how to
improve the discoverability
of your Swift-DocC content.
In this session, I'll talk about
the new navigation experience
available for Swift-DocC
documentation on the web
and share tips for how
to optimize your content
for discoverability.
If you need some additional
context on what Swift-DocC is
and how you can make
great documentation
for your frameworks
and apps with it,
check out these other
WWDC sessions.
Now, let's jump in and check out
the new navigation on the web.
This year, when you publish
your documentation site,
you get a new
navigation experience
that brings out
the best in your content.
The page contains
two main sections.
To the left is a navigator
and filter bar that allow you
to navigate through
your documentation
and find APIs quickly.
To the right
is the content view.
It's optimized to be flexible
in multiple screen
and navigator sizes.
Since the navigator
is separate from the content,
it's easy to quickly switch
between different pages.
You can also use
the disclosure indicators
to explore deeper
in the tree
and understand
the API hierarchy.
All of these features
make it way easier
to explore documentation.
On the other hand, if you know
what you're looking for
and you want to get there
as quickly as possible,
you can use the Filter bar
to refine the results
in the navigator.
Let's see the filter in action.
Let's say that
you're looking for "Habitat."
When you click on
the Filter bar and type that in,
you'll get a filtered view
of the pages
you actually care about,
right now.
You can clear the filter
to reset the navigator.
And you can also filter
to see articles, tutorials,
and even hide deprecated pages
by selecting tags.
For example, if you select
the Tutorials tag,
it's super convenient to find
the "Meet SlothCreator"
tutorial.
Now that you're up to date
with what's new in navigation,
I'm going to talk about
how to make the most
out of this new experience.
Here are some tips and tricks
for how you can optimize
your content so developers
find the pages
they're looking for
as smoothly as possible.
Let me show you how
I optimized the documentation
for my framework,
SlothCreator, as an example.
You can use SlothCreator
to catalog sloths
you find in nature and to create
new, adorable virtual sloths.
I just finished working
on my framework documentation,
so I haven't written
any markdown
to organize my pages yet.
As a starting point,
I'm taking advantage
of Swift-DocC's
automatic organization.
This means my navigator
is organized by types,
like tutorials, articles,
protocols, and structures.
This is already a great start,
but I can do a better job
guiding developers
through my documentation.
To optimize my content,
I'm going to follow three steps.
First, define the main
high-level themes
of what I can do
with this framework.
Then, I'll organize my pages
by importance and specificity.
Last but not least,
I'll optimize my group titles
to make sure they're as clear
and helpful as possible.
I think of this process
as creating a map.
It helps people
understand the boundaries
and general characteristics
of a region
and figure out how to get
from one place to another.
Likewise, the documentation
navigator helps developers
understand what you can do
with a set of APIs
and how to navigate to the pages
they're looking for.
I'll start by helping developers
understand what they can do
with my APIs by defining
the main high-level themes
of SlothCreator.
These themes will show up
on the navigator
on the SlothCreator page,
the top-level page
of my documentation.
It'll be one of the first things
developers see
when they land
on my documentation website.
This is my opportunity
to make a great first impression
and help developers
have a good understanding
of what this framework does.
Now, let me think
about my first theme.
One of the main functionalities
of SlothCreator
is creating sloths.
They have names, colors,
and even special powers.
To summarize, I'll call this
topic group "Sloth Creation"
Later, I'll decide what pages
to include in this group,
so I'll just leave
a placeholder for now.
After you create a sloth,
you can visualize it
in many different ways,
like on an app screen,
in a map view.
I'll call this "Sloth Views"
And of course,
sloths are a lot of work.
They need to be fed,
entertained, taken care of.
I'll call this "Management"
There's already
a lot of functionalities
you can achieve
in these three groups.
And putting myself
in the shoes of a developer
who's never used
SlothCreator before,
I'd love to have
an easy way
to see how to get started
with this framework.
With this in mind,
I'll create a topic group
with high-level
introductory content.
I'll call it "Essentials."
Awesome! Even though
there are hundreds of things
you can do with SlothCreator,
I'm only highlighting
the four most important,
overarching topic groups.
By reducing the number
of options that are available,
I'm increasing
developers' chances
of successfully taking
the next step.
There's no magic number
for how many topic groups
I should create,
but I generally try
to stick to under
10 per page.
Thinking back
to the idea of a map,
I want to give developers
step-by-step guidance
on where they can go next.
The order of my groups is vital
to create a great experience.
Taking another look
at my topic groups,
they're mostly in a good order.
First, you have
to create a sloth,
then you can visualize it,
then you can manage it.
The only thing
I'd change here for now
is moving Essentials
up to the beginning of the list,
so developers see
that beginner content first.
Now, it's time to decide
the pages and themes
that should be organized under
each one of these categories.
Let me start with Essentials.
This will be at the very top
of the navigator
and probably one of the first
things developers will see.
So I want to make sure
this features
the most important
introductory content.
This is a great spot
to highlight
introductory articles
and tutorials.
This enables developers
to find step-by-step
code examples quickly,
which is, personally,
my favorite way to learn.
With these considerations
in mind,
I decided to organize
three groups under Essentials:
the "Meet SlothCreator"
tutorial,
the "Getting Started
with Sloths" article,
and the Sloth struct, one of
the core APIs in my framework.
I'll repeat this same process
for the three other groups.
This feels approachable
because I see the most important
and broad themes first.
As I explore deeper in the tree,
the groups get more specific
and advanced.
For instance, inside Essentials,
I'll find
Getting Visual Attributes.
And inside
Getting Visual Attributes,
I'll find
Getting the Standard Colors.
Great, my documentation
is organized in a way
to guide developers through
the content successfully.
Next, I want to make sure
the titles of my topic groups
are also high quality.
The first characteristic
to a great topic group title
is that it should be
clear and descriptive.
A good title makes sense
on its own
and doesn't need much
additional context.
Thinking back
to my topic titles,
there's some room
for improvement.
The last topic title I wrote
is "Management."
This group of APIs is all
about what you can do
to manage your sloth's
well-being: Activity,
CareSchedule, FoodGenerator,
and Sloth.Food.
At first glance,
this seems like a good title.
However,
upon further consideration,
"Management"
is such a broad term;
it could mean a ton
of different things.
So it's not ideal.
To make this clearer
and more descriptive,
I'm going to call it
"Care and Feeding."
Now, I understand
this group is all about
taking care of my sloths
and giving them food.
For that reason,
it's also important
that topic group titles
be mutually exclusive.
If I have titles
that are interchangeable,
it's hard to know which one
contains what I'm looking for.
For example,
Fueling Superpowers,
Getting Magical Abilities,
and Casting Enchantments
are very similar themes
and could probably be organized
under a single title.
By keeping the names as
mutually exclusive as possible,
I'm making it simpler
for developers
to figure out
where to go next.
The more work I put into
organization and page titles,
the more likely developers
will have a smooth path
to the page
they're looking for.
Also, the more likely
I'll encourage serendipity;
in other words,
happy accidents.
By organizing well-thought-out
themes next to each other,
I'm enabling developers to find
relevant, related pages.
For example, as I'm learning
about SlothCreator Essentials,
I'm delighted to find Getting
Magical Abilities in the list.
All of these tips and tricks
really brought my documentation
to the next level.
It's so much better!
Now, let's review how you can
improve the discoverability
of your content and make it
approachable for developers.
First, identify the main themes
of your documentation.
Then, organize your content
by importance and specificity.
Next, encourage serendipity,
by organizing related themes
next to each other.
Last but not least, write clear,
mutually exclusive titles
for your pages and groups.
Thank you for taking the time
to learn how to make
your documentation better.
I'm sure developers
will deeply appreciate it.
Have a great WWDC!
♪