♪ ♪
Halden: Hello, I'm Halden.
Lilian: And I'm Lilian.
Halden: Today, we're going to show you
how to design an effective chart.
Lilian: Charts are powerful tools
for making your apps more engaging
and informative.
People can use charts of
weather forecasts to make plans,
stock prices to make financial decisions,
and fitness data to reflect
on their activities and set new goals.
Halden: When you design a chart in an app,
you first need to design
the app's experience.
By identifying your app's needs,
you can decide when to use charts,
how to use charts,
and what design system will unify them.
To learn about this important first step
of the design process,
see this year's talk called
"Design app experiences with charts".
Lilian: In this talk, we'll dive into
the next part of the design process:
how to design a chart.
In particular,
designing an effective chart,
which means a chart that's focused on
what you want to communicate,
approachable, and accessible
for people with disabilities.
To do that, we'll walk through
the design of a chart in an app for
a food truck
selling international pancakes
in San Francisco and Cupertino.
This finished app has
an entire system of charts
to help plan and manage pancake sales.
Today, we'll focus on how to design
one of these charts,
which visualizes pancake sales
over the last 30 days.
Halden: Good chart design begins
with identifying the chart's goal.
For this page in our app,
our goal was communicating:
"how were pancake sales
in the last 30 days?"
Goals like this can go in many directions.
It might be useful for our food truck
owners to see the pattern of recent sales
to understand how sales have fluctuated
or their range,
to get an idea of how big
these fluctuations were.
Identifying values could be useful
to examine specific days.
Other insights of interest
could be maximum sales, outlier days,
or comparisons between days of the week
or location.
The list can go on and on.
Which of these insights are most important
for our food truck owners?
An effective chart focuses on
a few key pieces of information.
Design charts with intention.
With regards to pancake sales,
our food truck owners primarily want to
examine how their sales fared over time
and on specific days.
That means we'll want to focus
on communicating pattern,
range, and values.
How did we get from
these three priorities to this chart?
Let's walk through the design process
step by step.
Lilian:
Our design process involves five topics.
Marks, which are a chart's
visual building blocks,
like the bars in a bar chart.
Axes, to provide framing for these marks.
Descriptions, which make charts more
approachable and easy to interpret.
Interaction,
which empowers deeper exploration of data
and is critical to accessibility.
And color, which adds personality,
and, as we'll show with a second chart,
can also enhance clarity.
Halden: Our first step is to figure out
what kind of form we want for our chart,
using the visual building block
of charts called marks.
A mark is the bar in a bar chart,
the line in a line chart,
and the point in a scatterplot.
They're the visual elements
that represent items in data.
There are many kinds of marks,
and with any one mark,
you have a rich variety of ways
to express data.
Take bars, for example.
You can line them up
to represent data's change over time.
You can stack them to show proportions:
how different categories add up
to a total.
Or you can put them side by side
to compare values
between different categories.
These are just a few examples of the many
rich ways you can express data with marks.
So what options make sense for our chart?
When it comes to marks, you need
to design for your goals and data.
As we decided earlier,
our chart should focus on three insights
about pancake sales in the last 30 days:
pattern, range, and individual values.
As we choose our mark,
we'll pay close attention to pattern.
It would be useful for our food truck
owners to see any fluctuations
or trajectories in their sales.
We'll start with time
on the horizontal axis
and pancake sales on the vertical axis.
These axes are incomplete;
we'll fill them in later.
One option for a mark is to use points
to represent each day of pancake sales.
When we envision nice smooth data for
the chart like this, points look great!
But real data is rarely this neat.
With realistic data,
we can see that using points
makes it difficult
to make out any pattern.
It's important to test your designs
with real data early.
While point marks are a great
at revealing some insights,
such as identifying outliers
or clusters in data,
our needs call for something else.
To make the pattern of sales
easier to see,
we can connect sales counts
by using a line mark.
Lines are great
at representing rates of change.
Here, patterns and trajectories are clear.
But what if, in one month,
our food truck needed to close
for five alternating days?
In this situation,
the pattern of sales becomes less clear
because the segments connecting
far-apart values
become more prominent
than the values themselves.
Remember to design for a variety
of scenarios in your data.
Bar marks are a more flexible option
for our chart.
Here, zeros are visible
without creating a distraction.
This chart is also intuitive to read:
more white means more sales.
Since sales are cumulative,
the visual weight of all the bars
corresponds directly
to the number of sales made
in the last 30 days.
Lilian: Great!
We've chosen a mark that makes the pattern
of pancake sales visually apparent.
But we also need to follow
an important tenant of accessible design:
for all information you show visually,
you also need to design
how to represent it non-visually.
In other words,
you need to make sure these marks
and the information they represent
are also accessible with VoiceOver.
VoiceOver is a screen reader.
It lets people read information on
their screen through Braille or speech
so people who are blind and others
can use apps without needing to see.
VoiceOver: 1,234 pancakes.
Lilian: You can use VoiceOver
to navigate content,
like the elements on a chart.
VoiceOver: May 8th.
54 pancakes.
May 9th. 36 pancakes.
One year, button two of two.
Lilian: You can also use it to interact.
VoiceOver:
Selected: one year, two of two.
Lilian: And through a feature
called audio graphs...
VoiceOver: Audio graph.
Lilian: Play a sonification of the chart
VoiceOver: Play audio graph.
[phone chiming]
Complete.
Lilian: To make your chart's marks
non-visually accessible,
you need to 1. design how VoiceOver
will navigate over data values,
and 2. use audio graphs.
Conveniently, charts implemented
with the Swift Charts API
automatically include customizable
accessibility labels for marks
and an implementation of audio graphs.
To learn more about audio graphs
and Swift Charts,
check out developer documentation,
last year's talk "Bring accessibility
to charts in your app",
and this year's talk,
"Hello Swift Charts".
Nice!
We've designed our marks
for our goals and data,
and made them accessible in VoiceOver.
With our decisions,
we addressed one part of the question,
"how were pancake sales
over the last 30 days?"
Specifically, their pattern.
Now our food truck owners can see
recent fluctuations in their sales.
But what about the range
of these fluctuations,
and values on specific days?
Halden: For that, we'll design axes.
Axes frame marks to provide references
for their values.
For example,
in our chart of pancake sales,
when we label the horizontal axis
with the start and end dates,
it becomes clear that our chart shows
the 30 days from May 8th to June 6th.
What about the vertical axis?
The values here are entirely dependent
on the sales of the food truck.
With axes like this,
it's important to consider the range.
A range can be either fixed or dynamic.
An example of a fixed range
is the vertical axis
of the battery chart in the Settings app.
We know that the battery level
will always go from 0 to 100%.
Fixing the vertical axis to this range
helps us see, at a glance,
when the battery is full, empty,
or somewhere in between.
While it'd be confusing to change
the vertical axis range for this chart,
it can be necessary for others.
Consider the step count chart
in the Health app,
which uses a dynamic range.
There is no fixed maximum step count,
so it makes sense to dynamically adapt
the vertical axis range to fit the data.
This way,
even when the step counts are low,
the bars can make full use of
the vertical space available,
making fluctuations easier to see.
Let's return to our chart
on pancake sales.
As with steps, there is no limit to how
many pancakes the food trucks will sell.
So let's use a dynamic range
to automatically adapt
the upper bound
of our vertical axis to our data.
Notice how we still fix
the lower bound to 0.
Doing so is generally a good idea
when using bar marks
as it keeps the heights
of the bars meaningful.
This way, a bar that's twice as tall
as another has twice as many sales.
While labels for the lower
and upper bounds of each axis are helpful,
we still need more structure to interpret
sales in the middle of the chart.
That leads to our next concept.
We need to tailor the density
of our axis grid lines and labels.
Grid lines give you reference points
to estimate the values of marks.
The more grid lines you have,
the easier it is to estimate these values.
Some charts don't need grid lines
and labels at all,
such as this trend platter
in the Health app.
These charts tend to be sneak peeks
of larger charts in another view,
so an idea of the data's pattern
is all you need.
Grid lines and labels
would add distraction.
Grid lines and labels appear
in the follow-up detailed chart,
where you may want to analyze values
more precisely.
Earlier, we pointed out
that our food truck owners
want to examine the range
and values of their sales.
Right now,
we have two horizontal grid lines:
one at zero and another at roughly the
maximum number of sales for the month,
which is too few for estimating the range
of sales in the middle of the chart.
At the same time, too many grid lines
and labels can be distracting.
Here, having seven horizontal grid lines
might be overwhelming.
Balance these factors to choose
the appropriate density.
For our chart's context and intended use,
it's more effective to use around
four horizontal grid lines
and adjust
as the range of the axis changes.
Note that as we place
these grid lines and labels,
we use intuitive values
to make the chart approachable–
in this case, multiples of 20.
In the same way, it's intuitive for people
to read time in steps of seven days,
which gives us
five grid lines for a 30-day period.
So we've designed our axes
by considering their range
and tailoring the density of grid lines
and labels.
We've gone a long way towards
making our chart effective,
but charts are complex visual elements,
and our example still needs work
before it's approachable.
How can we convey the meaning
behind the marks and axes
in a way that's quick and intuitive?
Lilian: That brings us
to our next topic: descriptions.
Descriptions are important
for framing the intent of our chart
and making it approachable and accessible.
Use descriptions,
or text preceding the chart,
to provide context to make
the chart more approachable.
They can make it clear that our chart is
about pancake sales in the last 30 days.
This text can be brief
and should be a part of
the user interface around a chart.
When we look at this chart
in the UI of our app,
the screen's title "Total Sales"
already gives some context,
and the label on the segmented control
that says "30 Days"
quickly establishes our time range.
That's a start.
Something else we need to clarify
is what the vertical axis is showing.
Are we looking at sales in terms of money?
In number of pancakes?
One solution could be adding
an axis label.
We can write "Pancakes sold"
above the vertical axis.
But here it's small and off to the side.
We want the meaning of this chart
to be obvious.
An alternative is to contextualize
the data with a title.
By using "Pancakes sold"
as a heading for the chart,
the chart's meaning is front and center.
Providing this context is important
for framing the chart.
We can make these descriptions
even better
by summarizing the main take-away
of the chart.
A lot of charts use this approach.
For example, the text above
a precipitation chart in Weather
describes its main take-away.
In this example,
it's: "Light Rain Forecasted–
Light rain is expected to start
in 9 minutes and last for 36 minutes"
There are many ways to present takeaways,
from sentence descriptions
to glyphs comparing historical data.
We'll take a simple approach
for our chart.
Let's bring out a main take-away
for our chart
by rewriting our chart title
to say "Total Sales: 1,234 Pancakes".
This description grounds our chart
with a concrete value
and summarizes
the most critical information.
Providing descriptions
that contextualize the data
and summarize key take-aways
eases readers into your charts.
It makes a chart more approachable
and accessible for everyone.
It sets up what to expect or look for,
which can be especially helpful
for people with certain disabilities
that make examining the details
of the chart particularly time consuming
or challenging.
Speaking of accessibility,
using audio graphs for our chart adds
important descriptions for VoiceOver.
With audio graphs...
VoiceOver: Audio graph.
Lilian:
VoiceOver can non-visually describe
what the axes are.
VoiceOver: Describe chart.
The x-axis is time. The y-axis is sales.
There is one data series.
Lilian: Audio graphs also provide
several summaries about the data,
including one you can customize.
These descriptions,
especially of the x and y axes,
are critical for non-visually
communicating the chart.
If audio graphs isn't an option,
make sure VoiceOver still has immediate
access to these types of descriptions
some other way,
like through accessibility text labels.
Halden: Now that we provide context,
summarized the main take-away,
and use audio graphs or an equivalent
source of descriptions,
our chart has all its essential parts.
But we could make it
even more effective with interaction.
You can design interaction
to empower people to explore
and understand their data
at a deeper level.
For example, you can use interactions
to highlight sections of a chart
to explore how their data fits
in a broader context,
or toggle between days,
weeks, months, and years.
We have an opportunity to enhance
our pancake sales chart with interaction.
Our food truck owners would find it
useful to see exactly
how many pancakes were sold
on a particular day.
We can offer that
with an interactive tooltip,
which lets us touch the chart to highlight
and read these specific values.
To make these touch-based interactions
easy to use,
make sure to use large touch targets.
So instead of making touch targets
on our chart the same size as our marks,
adding padding and stretching targets
to the full height of the chart,
makes it easy to use our tooltip because
you can touch any part of the chart
including the white space above the bars.
Lilian:
Interaction isn't only about touch.
People use a variety of other ways
to interact with devices,
depending on factors
like situation or disability.
So you need to design
for multiple types of input
to make chart interaction approachable
and accessible.
In other words, for every interaction
you design for touch or mouse clicks,
you need to design the same experience
for inputs like keyboard,
Voice Control,
Switch Control, and VoiceOver.
As you design these interactions,
it's important to make changes
on the screen visible,
like sizing the focus indicator
for Switch Control
or VoiceOver to be large,
the same way
we designed our touch targets.
Part of providing support for VoiceOver
is that you also need to design
good accessibility labels.
Recall how when we designed our marks,
we made sure VoiceOver can navigate
the chart's data values.
We made it so that when VoiceOver
navigates onto one of the bars,
it reads out values like
"June 1, 36 pancakes".
Let's examine what makes this label
a good design.
It's succinct.
We don't repeat unnecessary information,
like the axis names "Time" or "Sales"
which audio graphs already describes.
We spell out entire words
instead of using abbreviations.
That way, VoiceOver reads out
"June" instead of "Jun" or 6-dash-1,
and we make it clear
that 36 is the number of pancakes.
We also order the contextualizing
data value,
in this case, the date,
to come first.
This ordering makes it easier
to quickly look for a specific value.
VoiceOver: May 27th.
May 28.
May 29.
May 30th, 41 pancakes.
Lilian: It also makes the data
easier to interpret,
especially since you can jump
to different parts of the chart
and getting the context first
lets you know where you are.
The kind of labels you design
depend a lot on the goals of the chart.
For example, the charts on elevation
changes in cycling routes from Maps
don't show individual values,
but a route's pattern of elevation
gains and losses,
and use many vertical bars–
too many to navigate over individually.
A well-designed accessibility label
could then label a section of bars with:
"From 3.6 miles to 4.4 miles:
Climb 100 feet, descend 5 feet".
In contrast, if a chart is a tiny preview
inside a button
for opening the same chart in more detail,
it might make sense
to summarize the entire button,
chart and all, with one label.
Now that we've designed our interactions
to serve the focus, approachability,
and accessibility of our chart,
there's one more topic
we'd like to talk about.
Halden: Color.
Color can add personality
and enhance clarity in a chart.
So far, we've been designing
in black and white.
Color can give our chart
more pop in our app.
But it can also convey so much more.
You can use color
to distinguish categories,
as with the three activity rings
in the Fitness app.
You can also use it
to communicate intensity,
such as heat in a weather forecast.
You can even remove color
to draw attention to features of a chart.
Here the health app does so
to highlight your minimum and maximum
heart rate within a day.
Consider using color to enhance.
You ideally use color as an addition
to make the chart easier to understand
and not the only means
to convey critical information.
To help explain, let's use a scenario
of tracking two food trucks in our app:
one in San Francisco
and the other in Cupertino.
We want to modify our total sales chart
to allow us to compare sales
in these two locations.
How do we do this?
We could use a line for each city's sales,
but we can't tell which line
belongs to which city.
No label or layout distinguishes the two.
We can clarify the association
by placing a symbols on each line
to mark individual days.
Here we use circles for San Francisco
and squares for Cupertino.
Notice that we need a legend now.
We can add color
to enhance this difference.
It's important that color is added
on top of the symbols here.
Some people with colorblindness may not be
able to distinguish the lines otherwise.
This practice is especially important
for system settings
like Differentiate Without Color.
When choosing colors to represent data,
there are a few things to consider.
First,
consider how color can carry meaning.
For example, red and green
for low versus charged battery levels.
Culture can inform
the meanings of colors too.
In the US,
it makes sense to color code Stocks
with green for gains and red for losses.
In some countries like China, however,
people expect the opposite,
with red indicating gains
and green indicating losses.
For our chart,
system blue and green work well.
There is no obvious meaning tied to
these colors in the context of cities.
But what if we wanted to customize
the colors
to match the look and feel of our app?
When choosing colors for categories,
balance visual weight.
If one color overpowers the other,
a hierarchy can be implied.
Say we started with a deep purple
for San Francisco
and this vibrant pink for Cupertino.
Notice how in this case
the prominence of Cupertino's pink
compared to the darkness
of San Francisco's purple
makes Cupertino look more important.
We can fix that by evening out
the saturation and luminosity.
That's better.
And while these color choices
still need some work,
now they have equal weight
and don't suggest one city as primary
and the other, secondary.
Note that adjusting color
for visual weight is a tool.
Sometimes it's useful to use a color
with more visual weight
when we want to draw attention
to specific values or sections in a chart.
Trend charts in the Fitness app
use this strategy
to highlight your recent activity.
When choosing a palette,
it's also important to choose
visually distinct colors
to improve accessibility and readability.
A good rule is to pick colors
that are easy to differentiate by name
and contrast well from each other.
So instead of purple for San Francisco
and purpley-pink for Cupertino,
let's use purple and green.
Let's also make sure
they're not just distinct from each other,
but also from the background.
Ensuring that colors have high contrast
both from each other
and the rest of the chart
makes the chart more accessible
for people with visual impairments and
is a better overall design for everyone.
Remember to also try making your colors
distinct for people with color blindness.
You can check your choices
with color blindness filters.
Finally, make sure your chart respects
system settings by designing colors
to adapt for both Dark Mode
and Light Mode,
as well as Increase Contrast.
All right, let's recap.
What did we do today?
Lilian: Well, we designed a chart
for our pancake food truck app.
To do so, we chose marks that most
effectively communicate our goal,
and represented them in VoiceOver,
set our axis range and gridlines
to better communicate values at a glance,
added descriptions to ease people in
with context and overviews,
incorporated interaction
to offer details on demand,
added a splash of color as the butter
on top of our pancake chart,
and further used color to enhance
our second chart
for comparing how our pancake sales
between cities stack up.
At every step of the way,
we made design decisions to ensure
that our chart was focused,
approachable, and accessible–
in other words,
that we made an effective chart.
Halden:
Remember, the chart we designed
is part of an entire system of charts
within the rich context of an app.
You can use the same design process
to make these other charts on pancakes
flippin' fantastic.
Now I want some pancakes.
Lilian: Yeah, me too.
Halden: Thanks for watching.