[upbeat music]
Suzy: Hello and welcome to "Author fast
and reliable tests for Xcode Cloud."
I'm Suzy, and I work on XCTest.
In this session, I'm going to share
the most effective ways
to start testing for Xcode Cloud.
Our teams designed Xcode Cloud
to be a powerful tool for all developers.
In fact, we use it to test Xcode itself,
and I love it.
One of my favorite features of Xcode Cloud
is its ability to substantially broaden
a given test suite.
By configuring most tests
to run in the cloud,
you now have a practical way
to run tests on multiple destinations,
including those running differing
operating system versions
to leverage diverse platforms
such as an iPhone, iPad,
Apple Watch, Apple TV, and Mac,
and to run various test plan
configurations,
allowing for runtime analysis tools
such as address and thread sanitizers.
Once we have passed
such a thorough test suite,
we can be confident
the code is ready to ship.
Offloading tests to Xcode Cloud
allows for running a broader set of tests
without impacting the developers’
desktop cycle of code, compile, and test.
With this now expanded test suite,
there is a potential for an increased
number of unreliable tests.
This situation can become unmanageable.
As such,
ensuring reliability is essential.
In addition to reliability,
such a large number of tests
also needs to run efficiently
so as to limit their impact
on the continuous integration process.
Let’s address reliability first.
I will demonstrate how to author
more reliable tests for Xcode Cloud
using Food Truck.
Food Truck is an app that converts
taps and swipes into delicious donuts.
By running the test suite in Xcode Cloud,
we are able to validate
that all Apple platforms
support ordering my favorite donut,
chocolate with sprinkles.
Each improvement
to the Xcode Cloud Workflow
will be identified and demonstrated.
For more information about getting
started with Xcode Cloud Workflows,
watch "Meet Xcode Cloud.”
The first step
to author more reliable tests
is to ensure each test’s setup
and tear down is thorough.
Tests run in Xcode Cloud make use
of a fresh simulator
which may not meet
developers’ original assumptions.
Let’s identify a number of
device configuration assumptions
sometimes seen in test code.
Certain tests may rely on
specific dates and times.
For example, a server may be running
in a different time zone.
Tests should avoid
being time zone specific.
Locale-based values,
such as number formatting
and language directionality,
can lead to unexpected results.
Avoid this problem by explicitly
setting your simulator’s locale.
Another problematic assumption is
reliance on certain device permissions
such as internet access.
It’s best to mock device permissions
in a unit test
and use an alert handler in a UI Test.
Finally, some tests depend
on preloaded data.
For example, a test may expect
to have an empty documents directory.
While explicitly configuring the simulator
is sometimes the easiest choice,
enhancing the test’s setup method
is generally more robust.
For example,
the Food Truck depends on a menu file.
As part of instantiating
the truck object in the setup function,
we generate a mock data file
containing the donut menu items.
Note that rather than relying on teardown
methods to prepare for subsequent tests,
we recommend establishing
all state preparation in the setup method.
In many cases, read-only files
can be checked into the repository
and later accessed by tests.
However, when these files
need to be constructed,
Xcode Cloud supports
running a custom build script
where you can generate the file once
for multiple tests to access.
For more details
on how to configure your script,
watch "Customize your advanced
Xcode Cloud workflow."
That wraps up proper simulator setup.
Now, let’s cover how to handle tests
that fail to meet preconditions.
XCTSkip is an error
that instructs the XCTest Runner
to cease executing the current test
and mark it as skipped.
This may be used to bypass a yet-to-be
supported OS version or device type.
You could also leverage XCTSkip
by setting an environment variable
to skip tests specific to staging
or production environments.
Let’s go over how we can control
test flow using an environment variable.
Environment variables
can provide parameters
to both the XCTest test runner app
on your device
and the test host running xcodebuild.
In Xcode Cloud, environment variables
prefixed with TEST_RUNNER_
get passed into the XCTest test runner.
This prefix will be stripped prior to
the variable being made available
to your code.
So, for example,
a variable in your test code
named BASE_URL would be passed in
as the environment variable
named TEST_RUNNER_BASE_URL.
Test plans require the same format
as test code.
Namely, we do not add
the TEST_RUNNER_ prefix.
Environment variables may be
referenced anywhere in test code.
For example,
they could be used with XCTSkip
to skip the test for actually
ordering donuts
when we are in a production environment.
Unless you are hungry, of course.
It’s important to keep in mind
that redefining an environment variable
in multiple places,
such as both a test plan and the Xcode
Cloud User Interface,
can lead to unexpected results.
In this particular case,
Xcode Cloud’s Environment variables
will take precedence over what’s
specified in your project’s test plans.
Now that we are referencing our
environment variable within our test code,
we can set its value
in the Xcode Cloud User Interface.
To do this,
navigate to your Cloud Reports,
and control-click on Food Truck.
To edit our environment variables
within our Workflows,
we will select
"Manage Workflows" in the context menu.
We are editing
the integration workflow specifically,
so we will double click on it.
Now, in the sidebar,
we can select "Environment,"
and in the middle of the sheet,
under “Environment Variables,"
we can add the variable’s name and value.
As an alternative to setting
the environment variable
in the Xcode Cloud Workflow,
we could instead set it
within the test plan.
In this example,
we don’t yet have a test plan.
To enable test plans,
open the scheme editor,
select "Test" in the sidebar,
and then click on
“Convert to Use Test Plans."
Okay, now we have a test plan
I called "Food Truck."
To add the environment variable,
we need to click on the test plan
to open its editor.
Near the top, we can select between
"Tests" and "Configurations."
Let’s select "Configurations."
Now, within the "Arguments" section,
we will add the variable
by clicking on "Environment Variables."
A popup will appear where we can enter
the variable’s name and value.
Now our test will be skipped
when in the production environment.
To learn more about skipping tests,
watch "XCTSkip your tests."
Now that we covered utilizing environment
variables to control XCTSkip,
let’s talk about expectation timeouts.
It is possible for a test to fail
due to an unexpected timeout.
For example, this could be the result
of a slow server
or an overly anxious user interface test.
One approach to resolve either issue
would be to increase
the XCTestExpectation timeout
so the interaction would
have enough time to finish.
In this example,
we increase the OrderDonut timeout
from 5 to 10 seconds to allow the server
more time to respond.
It is usually preferable to instead
replace both the app
and test code timeout handling
with async/await.
This approach allows the test to pause
until the await call finishes
without any timeout.
We have resolved time dependent tests,
so let’s handle any test failures
within the test suite.
For example, we have a test
that relies on a service
within the staging environment
that is down for maintenance.
We can use XCTExpectFailure instead
of disabling or skipping this test.
With XCTExpectFailure,
your test executes normally
and the results are transformed as
follows:
a failure in a test will now be reported
as an expected failure,
while that failed test within its suite
will be reported as a pass.
This approach eliminates the noise
generated by expected failures.
For example, testOrderDonut is failing.
I know that the service
that provides ordering donuts
is under maintenance right now,
so I added a call here
to XCTExpectFailure.
To learn more about XCTExpectFailure
watch "Embrace Expected Failures
in XCTest."
Now that we've declared expected failures,
let’s leverage test repetitions
to substantiate code
and diagnose unreliable code.
Test repetitions is a tool that
runs the same test multiple times
waiting for the following:
the first failure, the first success,
or a statistical result.
For example, at our desk,
we run our new code
and test cases multiple times
with repetitions to confirm initial app
and test code reliability
before checking in the code.
We were able to detect that testOrderDonut
had only an 80% success rate.
Uh-oh!
Knowing the failure exists, we now use
the repeat-until-failure mode
to locally diagnose the bug.
This is another way
of utilizing test repetitions.
For tests that rely
on an unreliable external service,
you may want to leverage
the retry-on-failure repetition policy
to confirm a test can succeed.
While retrying tests
is a powerful approach,
it’s preferable to instead mock
external services when possible.
Advantages of a mocked service include
deterministic reliability and speed.
To learn how to mock your dependencies,
watch “Testing Tips & Tricks.”
Let’s explore how test repetitions
can be enabled.
To enable test repetitions
in your test plan,
go back to the test plan editor
and select "Configurations."
Then, under the "Test Execution" section,
there is a popup to select
your test repetition mode.
In this case,
we will select "Retry on Failure,"
which is used primarily to work around
unreliable external services.
Now we have
our test repetition mode enabled.
For more information on
leveraging test repetitions,
watch "Diagnose unreliable code
with test repetition."
So we have gone over a variety of tools
that can be used
to improve test reliability.
For more information
about writing quality tests,
watch "Write tests to fail."
Now that our tests are reliable,
let’s make them run fast!
A number of configuration options exist
for achieving faster results.
Let’s do what we can to reduce
the time it takes to run the test suite.
One technique we use
to improve performance
is to split our tests
into multiple test plans.
Sometimes, two is enough.
You can identify a reduced set of tests
to verify
as part of each open or update
to a pull request.
For example, we could run the unit tests
along with just a key subset of user
interface tests for a single platform.
The full set of tests on all supported
platforms can still be run,
but now in the background,
and not blocking pull requests.
This approach allows us
to add tests and new platforms
while keeping our continuous
integration process timely.
Let’s set up a workflow to
run a select set of tests.
In this example, we have already
created a new test plan
called “Pull Requests,"
and have it open in the test plan editor.
Near the top we can selectw
between "Tests" and "Configurations."
Let’s select "Tests."
Here we have chosen a subset of tests
to be verified for a pull request.
Now to setup a Workflow
to run our “Pull Requests” test plan,
we will go back to
Xcode Cloud Manage Workflows
just like we did when we added an
environment variable for skipping tests.
To create a new workflow,
we will click the "Add" button
at the bottom left
of the “Manage Workflow” sheet.
For simplicity, let’s also name
our workflow “Pull Requests”
and choose a start condition.
We want this workflow to prevent
any check-ins with failing tests.
In the sidebar,
to the right of "Start Conditions,"
we will click the "Add" button.
A menu will appear
showing the start condition options.
In our case,
we will select “Pull Request Changes."
Now, we now have
a pull request start condition.
Running tests require that
the Food Truck app first be built.
To do this, we need to add a build action.
Again in the sidebar,
below the “Start Conditions,”
let’s add an action.
We will click the "Add" button
next to “Actions,"
and then select “Build”
from the context menu.
Now that we have an action
that builds our app,
we will add another to run our tests.
Again we will click add action,
but this time we will select "Test."
Great, we have a test action.
Let’s select the test plan to run.
In the middle of the sheet,
there is a drop down for test.
Here we can select
our “Pull Requests” test plan.
Awesome!
Now our Workflow is configured
to run our test plan on pull request.
To create a second workflow that will run
your complete test suite on a schedule,
you can follow a similar set of steps.
However, this time,
select the start condition
to be “On a Schedule for a Branch”
and then set the workflow
to run your full suite test plan.
We have both Workflows
configured in Xcode Cloud
and running their associated test plans.
To learn more about test plans,
check out "Testing in Xcode."
Now we have created pull request
and scheduled workflow test sets.
Another improvement we can make for speed
is to run tests concurrently.
By default, Xcode Cloud
tests your platforms in parallel.
In addition, you can enable Xcode
to run tests in parallel
on a target and test object class level.
To enable parallel test execution
in Xcode,
we will again go to our test plan editor
and select "Tests."
Then, to the right of our
“Food Truck Tests" test bundle,
we click the “Options” button.
One of the options allows us
to “Execute in parallel” when possible.
If the server has enough cores available,
multiple targets and test object classes
can be executed concurrently.
So let’s enable this option to improve
our test suite turnaround time.
Now our tests are configured
to run in parallel.
Note that tests must be designed
to run independently
to take advantage of parallel execution.
Proper setup and teardown are essential
to reliable test case behavior.
With our tests running in parallel,
it’s time to turn our attention
to runaway tests.
Runaway tests are those tests
that don’t end in a timely manner.
Some examples include an infinite loop
or waiting indefinitely
for a failed server.
We can halt these tests by setting an
execution time allowance in our test plan.
The execution time allowance specifies
the number of seconds for a test to run
before it fails with a timeout error.
This prevents a test suite from
getting stuck on an individual test.
In this case,
the fifth test got stuck for some reason.
By setting the execution time allowance,
this runaway test was eventually halted
and marked as a failure.
The XCTest Test Runner then continued
running the next test in the suite.
Let’s configure an execution
time allowance for our test plan.
To set an execution time allowance,
we will go to our test plan editor
and select “Configurations."
Under the “Test Execution” category,
we can enable “Test Timeouts”
and specify the number of seconds to wait.
Note that the default is 600 seconds.
Having configured the maximum
execution time allowance,
a single runaway test will no longer
disrupt our testing workflow.
For example, an overnight test suite can
now complete on time
and provide a full set of useful results.
Yay!
We finally stopped those runaway tests,
so we are able to move on
to the next improvement.
As you may recall, we were able
to leverage test repetitions
to increase reliability
of tests that rely on external services.
We configured our test plan
to retry on failure
and selected
a sufficient repetition value.
However, these repetitions can add to
the time it takes to run the test suite.
Unnecessary repetitions are wasteful
and you may want to optimize
test repetition value to a lower number.
Furthermore, you may consider
removing the problematic test altogether
from the pull request workflow.
Let’s go over how we might do this.
Let’s return to the test repetitions
configuration in the test plan editor.
Earlier we set the test repetition mode
to “Retry on Failure."
Now we can adjust
the "Maximum Test Repetitions” value.
For example, we may have chosen
to allow up to 10 attempts
for a test that relies
on an external server
that fails 5% of the time.
Most of the time,
we will succeed on the first attempt.
However, if that same test
has an unrelated bug,
it will fail every time
and use all 10 attempts.
Maybe 3 attempts would be sufficient
and a better choice.
While we want to reduce retries
to improve performance,
note that earlier we recommended
increasing retries
to improve reliability in some cases.
As such, this minimally chosen value
must continue be sufficient
to run those tests reliably.
That wraps up
configuring for faster results.
To go into more detail
on getting faster test results,
check out "Get your test results faster."
To recap,
we covered the most effective ways
to begin testing for Xcode Cloud.
We focused on configuring tests to be both
reliable and fast
so that you can avoid irrelevant failures
and verify your code changes quickly.
Thank you, and I hope you enjoy
the rest of your WWDC!
[upbeat music]