♪ ♪
Hello, everyone.
My name is Adrian, and I'll be talking
to you about how to set up your project
for a great debugging experience
with LLDB.
LLDB is the underlying debugging
technology that ships with Xcode.
LLDB allows you to set breakpoints
in your application,
pause its execution,
inspect the state of variables
and objects,
explore your code, and much more.
LLDB can help you understand
what your code is doing
and it enables you to find the point where
the behavior of your code
diverges from your expectation.
It's a powerful tool for
understanding and exploring code.
If you want to learn more about LLDB,
please check out earlier videos,
for example "Discover breakpoint
improvements" from WWDC21.
Today we are going to look at
some advanced workflows
that have unique implications
on debugging Swift code.
Maybe you are integrating
a third-party framework into your app.
Maybe your app and your team has grown
to the point
where most of your code is being built
by a continuous integration system.
Maybe you are using a custom
build system to integrate
with your company's infrastructure.
Maybe you are building software
for other software developers.
Or you just want to learn more about LLDB.
My goal is to provide a better
understanding of how LLDB works,
and what information it needs from
the build system in order to function.
I have a little project here that we are
going to use as our running example.
I'm a compiler engineer,
and I like games,
so in my spare time
I write parsers for text adventures.
This one I recently started in pure Swift.
Let me show you what I've got so far.
The game uses a text interface
so I'm running it in Terminal.
As in every good adventure,
we'll start by checking our inventory.
This game takes place
in a contemporary setting.
I see that I have an iPhone.
Next, let's have a look
at our surroundings.
Hmm, this sensor looks intriguing.
Maybe we can use the iPhone on the sensor?
I dropped the iPhone?
Uh, that's not what I wanted to show you.
I think that my game has a bug.
Good thing this is a debugger talk.
Let's set a breakpoint in the parser
and run our command again.
[typing sounds]
We should first verify
that the command was read correctly.
The "words" variable contains
the tokenized command.
Ah, this did not go as expected.
I don't know what's going on here.
Yesterday I was using the debugger
with no problems,
and then last night I integrated
this UI framework
for styling text on the terminal.
The developers of that framework
have a continuous integration system
that cranks out nightly builds
of the framework,
and I'm linking
directly against the latest one.
I wonder if this framework has something
to do with my debugging troubles.
Case in point, I already noticed
that I can't step
into the framework's source code,
even though I explicitly downloaded
the debug build.
Look at that.
I only see disassembly.
Let's try to understand
what happened there,
and let's start by figuring out
why I couldn't see any source code.
What does LLDB need
in order to show source code?
When the compiler compiles a function,
it generates machine code.
And it leaves breadcrumbs for the debugger
so an address in the executable
can be mapped to a source file
and line number and vice versa.
These breadcrumbs are called debug info.
On Apple platforms
debug info is stored in object files.
For archiving and distribution, debug info
can be linked into .dSYM bundles.
The debug info linker is called dsymutil.
LLDB uses Spotlight
to locate .dSYM bundles,
so it's quite flexible
in terms of where on disk they are.
Now that we know how debug info works,
let's get back to the example.
First, let's verify that LLDB has actually
found the dSYM for the framework.
We can do this
with the image list command.
The UI framework
is called "TerminalInterface".
Yes, LLDB did find the dSYM
for the framework.
That means it has access
to the debug info.
We can use "image lookup"
to get more info
about the current address.
By the way, if you want to learn more
about the various options,
LLDB has an excellent built-in help.
Ah, I think I see
why there is no source code:
This source path here points to where
the sources were on the build server,
not to where they are on my local machine.
We can fix that.
LLDB has a built-in source map
that we can use to redirect these paths.
We could type in the command right now,
but I'd rather make this change
more permanent.
In the Scheme editor, which you can
bring up by going to Product, Scheme,
Edit scheme,
or by just option-clicking
onto the play button,
you can define
a per-project LLDB init file.
I already added one for this project.
Now that we set up LLDB,
let's run our project again.
And we have source code.
LLDB can remap source paths
using "settings set target.source-map".
You can put this command
into your project's .lldbinit file
to have this run automatically.
Alternatively, each .dSYM bundle contains
a XML .plist file
where you can put a path prefix
remapping dictionary.
If you have a download script that
fetches the latest builds from a server,
you could modify that script
to automatically inject
the appropriate remapping dictionary
into the downloaded .dSYM.
You can learn more about this process
on the LLDB website.
Source paths
are not language-specific at all,
so this method works for Swift,
C++, and Objective-C projects alike.
To learn more about
symbols on Apple platforms,
check out "Symbolication:
Beyond the basics" from WWDC21.
When source code is compiled
on a build server farm,
the remote paths to source files could be
different from machine to machine.
To avoid having to define
one remap prefix per machine,
we can instruct the compiler
to canonicalize source paths
before putting them into the debug info.
This is done using
the -debug-prefix-map option.
This way the machine-specific
path prefix can be replaced
by a unique, canonical placeholder name
that can then be remapped
to the local path in LLDB.
Before we went on the source tangent,
I was trying to print
the object description of "words".
That did not work.
In fact, even just evaluating
the expression "words" did not work.
At least we can see the variables
in the variables view.
The console equivalent
of the Xcode variable view
is the "frame variable" or "v" command.
If you want to learn more about
the nuances between these commands,
check out "LLDB: Beyond 'po'"
from WWDC19.
So what is po
and why is it still not working?
To understand what this means,
we need to learn more about LLDB.
As a reminder, LLDB is a debugger.
But LLDB is not just a debugger.
It is also a compiler!
In addition to the functionality
of a debugger,
LLDB also includes a fully functioning
copy of the Swift and Clang compilers.
These compilers power
LLDB's expression evaluator,
which you may know through
p and po command aliases.
With the expression evaluator
we can go beyond looking at variables,
we can perform computation,
call functions,
and even change the state of the program.
Check out "Advanced Debugging
with Xcode and LLDB" from WWDC18
to get some ideas for what's possible
with those commands.
How does a debugger format
a local variable?
The debug info provided by the compiler
tells the debugger
where in memory a variable is stored.
But with that information alone,
LLDB would only be able to show us
a random assortment of raw bytes.
So how does LLDB turn that into
nicely formatted output?
The answer is types.
Type information allows LLDB
to understand the structure
and memory layout of a source variable.
With type information, LLDB knows
what fields an aggregate type has
and types allow LLDB to use
the appropriate data formatters
to pretty-print them.
Now let's look at
where type information comes from.
On the debugger side, where the frame
variable and v commands live,
LLDB gets type information
from Debug Info.
And LLDB also gets types
from Swift reflection metadata.
On the compiler side, where the expression
evaluator and po live,
LLDB gets type information from Modules.
This clean separation is new in Xcode 14
and explains why the variable view
can be fully functional
even if the expression evaluator isn't.
Modules are how the compiler organizes
type declarations.
The Swift compiler knows
many ways of importing modules,
but before we dive into that,
I want to show you a handy new feature.
How do we start diagnosing an issue
that is happening on the compiler side?
This year LLDB has added
a new "swift-healthcheck" command.
It's your first stop for figuring out
if a module import failed.
Let me show you how this works.
By running swift-healthcheck
after a problem occurred,
we can get access to a log of the Swift
expression evaluator configuration.
At the end of the log
we see that LLDB had trouble importing
the "TerminalUI" Swift module.
Based on the name, I assume
that this is an implementation detail
of the TerminalInterface framework.
This missing module is a problem
because the type of self is generic
over the UI implementation and
without the module containing that type,
the expression evaluator cannot realize
the dynamic type of "self".
I'm sending a message
to the developers of the framework
and ask them to investigate.
In my experience,
they have always been very responsive.
Who knows, maybe we can even find
a solution before the end of this video.
In the meantime, let's take a look at
how LLDB's compiler finds Swift modules.
My app has its own Swift module.
It may import a system framework,
such as Foundation.
System frameworks are textual stable Swift
interface files that live in the SDK.
Any Swift module
might import a Clang module,
which is a fancy name for one or more
header files that are grouped together
with the help of a module map file.
Clang modules
can depend on other Clang modules.
My app might also import a Swift module
that belongs to a locally built framework.
It could also import textual
Swift interface files
that are not part of the SDK.
If you want to learn how, check out
"Binary Frameworks in Swift" from WWDC19.
My app might also link against
a static library that contains Swift code,
and then that comes
with a Swift module too.
Hmm, we're not done, though.
I should mention there are also
bridging headers,
which can also import Clang modules.
Finally, as a special feature
in LLDB only,
some module contents can be reconstructed
from debug info alone.
That's a lot of sources!
How does LLDB find them all?
It's the build system's job to package up
the modules so LLDB can find them.
Modules from system frameworks
stay in the SDK.
LLDB will find a matching SDK to read them
from as it's attaching to your program.
When debugging
straight from the object files,
LLDB will find all non-SDK modules
where they were at build time.
Dsymutil can package a debug info archive
called a .DSYM bundle
for every dynamic library,
framework or dylib, and executable.
Each .dSYM bundle can contain
binary Swift modules,
which may contain bridging headers,
textual Swift interface files,
and most importantly, debug info.
That covers everything.
Everything?
Everything except Swift modules
that belong to static archives.
In order for a Swift module
to be picked up by dsymutil,
it needs to be registered with the linker.
For dynamic libraries and executables,
the build system will do this
automatically for you.
But static archives are
not produced by the linker,
they are just collections of object files,
like a zip file.
That means that the responsibility
for registering any Swift modules
with the linker
falls onto every executable
or dynamic library
that links the static archive.
In many cases, Xcode's build system
will do this for you.
But if you are maintaining
your own custom build system,
or if you have defined custom build rules,
this is something to be aware of.
When using the Apple linker,
Swift modules need to be registered
with the -add-ast-path option.
Check your build log to verify
that this is the case.
You can also use dsymutil to dump
the symbol table of your executable
and grep for "swiftmodule"
to verify that it worked.
On other platforms like Linux,
the swift driver supports
a -modulewrap action
that converts binary Swift module files
into objects
that you can link into your binary
together with the rest of the debug info.
LLDB will find it there.
The developers of the framework
were incredibly responsive.
As we suspected, it turns out that
as a part of the framework's build system
a static archive is used.
And it was the Swift module
that belongs to that static archive
that was missing from the dSYM bundle.
I have now installed a fixed version
of the framework.
It has registered the missing
static module with the linker
and so dsymutil was able to collect it.
Now self can be resolved.
And we can print the object description
of "words".
Since we're using the console anyway,
I'm using the s alias
to step into the parseFrom function.
And now we can also easily find the bug,
which is just a copy-and-paste error here.
[typing sounds]
And with that, we not only solved
the puzzle of the missing Swift module,
but also the first puzzle of the game.
Before we wrap up,
I have one more detail to watch out for.
The Swift compiler will serialize
Clang header search paths
and other related options into
the binary .swiftmodule files.
This is great because it makes
importing their Clang module dependencies
just work during the build.
But when building on a different machine,
these local paths can be detrimental.
So before shipping a binary .swiftmodule
to another machine,
consider building with the
-no-serialize-debugging-options
Compiler flag.
In Xcode this is controlled via the
SWIFT_SERIALIZE_DEBUGGING_OPTIONS
setting.
You can reintroduce these search paths in
LLDB with one of the following settings.
Let's recap what we learned.
If you want to ship code
from one machine to another,
you should ask yourself what level of
debugging you expect to be doing.
For example, if you ship
a binary framework to another developer
and you don't expect them
to step into your code in the debugger,
it's best to just ship the Swift module
as a textual .swiftinterface file.
But if you are setting up a build server
or a continuous integration system,
where developers are expected to debug
the downloaded build artifacts,
you will want to make sure to build
a binary Swift module
and consider turning off
search path serialization.
You can also canonicalize the source paths
on the server
in the debug info
using the -debug-prefix-map option.
That's all I have for you.
Today we learned about LLDB's dual nature
as a debugger and a compiler.
The debugger needs debug info
and reflection metadata to function
and provides the Xcode variable view,
and the v command.
The compiler needs Modules
and is sensitive to search paths.
It's behind the expr, p, and po commands.
A good way to get at
the compiler diagnostics
is the new swift-healthcheck command
in LLDB.
Thank you for watching!  ♪ ♪