♪ Mellow instrumental
hip-hop music ♪
♪
Franklin Schrans: Hello,
my name is Franklin,
and I'm an engineer
on the Swift-DocC team.
Together with
my colleague Ethan,
I'm excited to give you a tour
of Swift-DocC in Xcode 14,
packed with great new tools
to help you create
even better documentation.
We introduced Swift-DocC
last year in Xcode 13,
allowing you to guide developers
through your Swift frameworks.
With Swift-DocC,
you write comprehensive content,
from reference documentation
for individual APIs
to conceptual articles that
provide a higher-level story
for using these APIs together,
all the way
to step-by-step tutorials
that walk the user
through a task.
This year, with Xcode 14,
Swift-DocC unlocks
brand-new, exciting workflows.
In addition to documenting
frameworks,
we're thrilled to now
support app projects as well,
so that you can easily
collaborate with your team.
You can now also document
Objective-C and C APIs
using Swift-DocC,
allowing you
to describe all your project's
APIs together.
Publishing your content
to a website
is now dramatically easier,
with out-of-the-box support
for static hosting environments
like GitHub Pages.
And thanks to the powerful new
navigation sidebar,
developers will be able
to discover your content
easier than ever before.
Also, with Swift-DocC now being
an open source project,
these new features
were developed
in close collaboration
with the open source community.
In this session,
we'll take a tour of Swift-DocC
and the exciting new workflows
it unlocks in Xcode 14.
First, we'll discover how
to document your project's APIs
right inline with
your source code.
Then, we'll take a look
at seamlessly
publishing your content
to a website.
And finally, we'll discover
the brand-new navigation sidebar
on the web.
Let's start with
writing documentation.
Good documentation is essential
to any software project.
As your project evolves,
it's important to describe
its functionality and design
so that developers
have a solid reference point
when contributing.
Swift-DocC in Xcode
gives you the tools you need
to create fantastic
documentation,
using the same tools you use
to develop code.
And this year,
we're excited
to expand Swift-DocC
to app projects.
Let's dive right in.
We'll document an app
I'm working on with my team
called Slothy,
which contains both Swift
and Objective-C source files.
Even with a brand-new project,
where I haven't written
documentation yet,
you can open the Product menu
and select Build Documentation,
and Xcode opens
the documentation window,
where you'll see stubs
that Swift-DocC
automatically generates
for your APIs.
This provides a great starting
point for filling in these pages
to help contributors
navigate the project.
So, let's take it step by step
to turn this content
into a rich and complete guide
for contributing to our app.
A good place to start
is to teach how each API
works individually,
and from there,
to provide higher-level content
using a documentation catalog.
Let's start by describing
a view called SlothView.
For this documentation
to be visible to Swift-DocC,
start your comment
using three slashes.
Then, add a concise summary
for your view.
In the built documentation page,
this translates to text
displayed prominently
right below the view's name.
Then, add more details
using additional paragraphs.
This content appears in the
Overview section of the page.
And use Swift-DocC's link syntax
to turn references to APIs
into active links,
allowing you to quickly jump
to Pages to learn more.
DocC even validates these links
when you build,
so you get warnings
if they go out of date.
Finally, if you wish
to provide an example
of how to use this view,
add a code listing using the
Markdown code block syntax.
Now, contributors know
at a glance
how to use this view.
In just a few steps,
my view's documentation
is now much more helpful
to contributors of this project.
Next up, let's document
an initializer.
Again, start by writing
a summary.
For initializers and methods,
it's a good idea to describe
each parameter individually.
You do so by adding
a parameter list item,
with a short description
of what the parameter is.
Notice how the content appears
in a separate
Parameters section.
Now let's take a look
at the Objective-C APIs
defined in this project.
New in Xcode 14,
we're excited to bring
Swift-DocC's
comprehensive tooling
to document Objective-C code.
Using the same familiar Markdown
syntax you know and love,
and updated support
in Xcode's source editor,
you can now
describe and organize
all your project's APIs
together.
And for code that can be called
from both Swift and Objective-C,
there's a nifty language toggle
to browse the page in
the language you're coding in.
Check out the developer
documentation linked below
for more details.
Now, let's apply this
to our Slothy project.
I'll describe the SLOSound class
and its initializer.
Notice that because this class
can be used from both Swift
and Objective-C code,
Xcode displays a language toggle
allowing you
to browse the content
in the language you're using.
Let's describe the class
and initializer
using the same Markdown syntax
you use for Swift code.
Great, this looks much better.
I've added a summary,
an overview,
and for the initializer,
a parameters section.
And that wraps up
describing individual APIs.
By writing a few documentation
comments in source code,
developers contributing
to my project
have a better understanding
of how to use its APIs.
Now, let's focus on creating
a great top-level page
for our app.
This is the first page
contributors will see,
so I'd like to provide
a great introduction
to what the app does
and how to contribute to it.
To customize the top-level page,
start by adding
a documentation catalog.
To do so, right-click
on your project's source folder
and select New File.
Then select
Documentation Catalog.
A Documentation Catalog
complements your
source code documentation
and contains additional
Markdown files and media.
Xcode automatically adds a file
for the top-level page
of your app.
Let's fill it in with an
overview of what the app does.
Using the same syntax you use
for documentation comments
in source code,
I added a summary,
an overview, and even embedded
rich content like images.
Great, this looks
much more inviting.
Now contributors know at a
glance what my app is about.
And that's it!
I've dramatically improved
documentation for my app
and provided
a great reference point
to my project's contributors.
They can browse
the top-level page
for an overview of the project,
and jump into each page
to get detailed information
about each of its APIs.
Now that we've seen how to write
and build documentation,
it's time to publish it
to a website
so that contributors
can easily browse it.
Over to you, Ethan.
Ethan Kusters: Thank you,
Franklin.
We've been developing
the Slothy app in a modular way
alongside a more generally
useful Swift Package
called SlothCreator.
I think it would be great
to publish SlothCreator
to a wider audience
so that other developers
making sloth-related apps
can make use of it.
As a part of this effort,
I want to be sure
SlothCreator's documentation
is easily shareable on the web,
so let's walk through
Swift-DocC's brand-new,
simplified publishing workflow.
When you build documentation
in Xcode,
Swift-DocC produces
a static bundle
containing your documentation.
This bundle is called
a DocC archive
and is a portable container
for your documentation.
You can export it directly from
Xcode's documentation window
and send it to colleagues.
They'll be able to open
and browse the documentation
by just double-clicking
on the archive.
But a DocC archive isn't just
a portable container
for opening documentation
in Xcode.
It also contains
a fully featured website
right out of the box.
And new in Xcode 14,
that DocC archive
is also directly compatible
with most web servers.
This makes publishing
your documentation to the web
easier than ever.
In most cases, you can
deploy your documentation
by just copying the contents
of your built DocC archive
into the root
of your web server.
This also means
that DocC archives
are now compatible with most
managed hosting services,
including GitHub Pages.
GitHub Pages is a popular way
many developers
host their documentation
that's integrated
right into GitHub.com.
And since we've been
using GitHub
for the source control
of SlothCreator,
it makes sense for us to publish
our documentation there
as well.
If you're familiar
with using GitHub pages,
you'll know that,
unlike a standard server,
your website is not published
at the root path of the URL
but at a specific base path.
In this kind
of hosting scenario,
you'll need to specify
your website's base path
with an additional build setting
to produce a DocC archive
that's compatible.
To fully understand
how this works
and why we only need
this configuration
in certain hosting scenarios --
like on GitHub Pages --
let's take a look at how
we would expect the URL
of a DocC archive hosted
on your own domain might look.
Let's assume we already have
a website for the Slothy app --
slothy.example.com --
and we'd like to publish the
documentation for SlothCreator
as a part of that
existing website.
If we just take the content of
the SlothCreator DocC archive
and copy it to the root
of our web server,
the reference documentation
for SlothCreator will appear
at slothy.example.com/
documentation/slothcreator.
Any tutorials for
the SlothCreator package
would be at a neighboring
"tutorials" path.
However, in this case,
we're not going to be publishing
to our own domain.
Instead, to keep
the documentation
with our GitHub repository,
we'll publish to the domain
GitHub Pages provides.
When you create a GitHub
Pages site for a repository,
the URL of that website
is not at the root path;
instead, it's at
a specific base path
corresponding to the name
of the repository.
Generally that will be something
like your username.github.io
forward-slash
your repository name.
Any reference and tutorial
documentation paths
are appended to that base path.
Because this base path
is unique to your repository,
it's important to tell
Swift-DocC what it is
before building a DocC archive
for publishing to GitHub Pages.
There's a new build setting
exposed in Xcode 14
for just this use case.
After configuring
the DocC Archive Hosting
Base Path setting
to be the name
of your GitHub repository,
you'll be ready to go
for all of your future
documentation builds.
Let's take a look at how
this works in practice.
Here, I've opened the
SlothCreator Swift package
Franklin showed you earlier
as a dependency
of the Slothy app.
Since we're getting close
to publishing this package
for wider use,
I'm going to go ahead
and publish the documentation
we've prepared to GitHub Pages.
I'll begin by opening the
framework's project settings
by moving my mouse
to Xcode's Project navigator
and selecting
the SlothCreator item.
Next, I'll select
the SlothCreator target,
and then open
the Build Settings tab.
In this case, I'm looking for
a Swift-DocC-related setting,
so let's filter for DocC.
Now I'll set the DocC Archive
Hosting Base Path setting
to be the name of our
repository: sloth-creator.
Great!
Next, let's build documentation.
I'll move my mouse
up to the Product menu
and select Build
documentation.
After Xcode finishes
compiling my project
and generating
documentation for it,
the documentation window
will open.
Here's the top-level page for
SlothCreator's documentation.
Let's go ahead and export it.
I'll move my mouse over
to the documentation navigator
and the SlothCreator
technology item.
Next I'll click on the
context menu and select Export.
I'm going to export it
to a directory named "docs"
in the root of my repository
because this is how
I've configured GitHub Pages
to publish
my documentation website.
Now I just need to commit and
push my changes up to GitHub.
Back in the main Xcode window,
I'll move my mouse
up to the Source Control menu
and select Commit.
I'll select the docs directory
that has
my documentation content
and write a commit message.
Let's go ahead
and push the changes.
And that's it.
Let's go check out
the published site.
I'll open up my repository
on GitHub.com.
I'd already placed a link
to the documentation site
in the README,
so I'll just click on it.
And here we are.
I'm so excited to have
the documentation
we worked on for SlothCreator
easily accessible on the web.
I think this is going to be
really helpful for folks
interested in using SlothCreator
in their own projects.
Now that we've deployed
the documentation
for SlothCreator once,
I'd really like
to set up automation
to perform a deployment
any time the documentation
in the repository changes.
Since we're releasing
SlothCreator as a Swift Package,
the new Swift-DocC
Swift Package Manager plug-in
is going to be
a great help here.
You can use
the Swift-DocC plug-in
to really simplify the process
of building documentation
for Swift packages.
The plug-in's documentation
is linked below
and I recommend
checking it out
as a great starting place
for configuring automated
documentation deployments
to GitHub Pages
and other hosting services.
And of course, Swift-DocC
continues to have
great command-line support
for Xcode projects
with the xcodebuild docbuild
command-line interface
that was introduced
in Xcode 13.
Documentation for how
to get started using xcodebuild
to automate GitHub Pages
deployments is linked below.
We're thrilled to be releasing
an all-new enhanced browsing
and navigation experience for
Swift-DocC on the web this year.
Let's take a look at how
the new navigation sidebar
can help readers of the
SlothCreator documentation
explore what the framework
has to offer.
We're back on the GitHub Pages
site for SlothCreator,
and over on the left side
of the page
is the new navigation sidebar.
I'll move my mouse over
to the CareSchedule item
and expand it by clicking
on the disclosure triangle.
Now I can see the pages
that are organized
as children of CareSchedule
without even needing
to fully open the page.
In this case,
I'm interested in
jumping straight
to the type's initializer.
I can continue navigating
through the framework,
expanding other items like
FoodGenerator and SlothFood,
eventually opening
the twig page.
As I'm navigating between pages,
the state of the navigation
sidebar stays constant,
allowing me to keep track of
the pages I've already visited.
This allows for a natural
exploration of the framework
that I really appreciate.
But what if I'm already familiar
with the SlothCreator framework
and am looking for information
about a specific symbol?
The filter field at the bottom
of the new navigation sidebar
is perfect for this.
I'm interested in an API
that will help me
increase the energy level
of my sloths.
I'll move my mouse to the bottom
of the navigator,
select the filter bar,
and insert "energy."
Perfect!
This documentation
on the energyLevel property
is exactly what
I was looking for.
The new browsing experience
offered by Swift-DocC
in Xcode 14
is going to bring
your documentation site
to the next level.
We're so excited
for you to try it out.
Swift-DocC's integration
in Xcode now offers support
for documenting
all of your projects.
This includes your
Objective-C and Swift code
in application
and framework targets,
whether packaged as Xcode
projects or Swift Packages.
The DocC archive
produced by Xcode 14
is immediately compatible
with popular hosting services,
including GitHub Pages.
This is a game changer for
distributing your documentation
to an even wider audience.
And finally, Swift-DocC offers
a powerful new navigation
experience on the web.
The navigation sidebar
is going to unlock new ways
of exploring and finding
the documentation on your site.
To learn more about
the new Swift-DocC sidebar
and how to best author
your documentation
to take advantage
of its new features,
check out the
"Improve the discoverability
of your Swift-DocC content"
session.
And to take your documentation
even further,
check out the "Build interactive
tutorials using DocC" session
to learn how to build
step-by-step walk-throughs
to guide developers
through your app or framework.
We are so excited to see
all of the documentation
you write and publish
with Xcode 14.
Thank you for watching.
♪