♪ ♪
Hello, everyone.
I'm Elliot Garner.
I'm an engineer
on the Internet Technologies team,
and today I'm going to be discussing
how to build device-to-device experiences
using Network framework,
and its new companion framework,
DeviceDiscoveryUI.
We'll start off by learning
about cross-device connectivity,
and how it can improve your apps.
We'll explore how a new framework,
DeviceDiscoveryUI,
which pairs with Network framework to make
that connectivity as simple as possible.
We'll walk through a code example
of how to update your apps
to use DeviceDiscoveryUI,
including an in-depth look
at how to discover devices
using the new system device picker,
And how to connect to those devices
using Network framework.
So let's start
with cross-device connectivity.
Connecting to,
and exchanging data between,
nearby devices is often essential
for building seamless,
integrated experiences within your apps.
Fitness and meditation apps
often work best on a large screen
where a coach can demonstrate moves.
People benefit
from seeing their heart rate,
calorie burn, and movement data
collected from their Apple Watch.
Likewise, gaming experiences
can be made more immersive
with input and actions
from a connected iPhone,
or augmented by extending a second-screen
experience to a nearby iPad.
All of these experiences–
games, fitness, and wellness apps–
all share a need for reliable and
easy-to-use cross-device connectivity.
And that all starts
with discovering a device.
To help kickstart that discovery,
we're introducing DeviceDiscoveryUI–
a new framework that provides secure,
privacy-preserving discovery
of nearby devices.
New in iOS 16, DeviceDiscoveryUI
pairs with Network framework
to enable device-to-device connectivity
between your Apple TV apps and nearby
iPhones, iPads, and Apple Watches.
DeviceDiscoveryUI provides system UI
for easy discovery of nearby devices.
Once a device has been discovered,
your app can easily open a connection
to that device.
Because this connection was established
using system UI,
you don't need to worry about managing
permissions for local network access.
And because the system handles
securely establishing this connection,
you no longer need to implement
your own key exchange,
because the platform encrypts
transmitted data for you.
Here we can see that system UI in action.
On the left, your app's icon is displayed,
along with a required
usage description string
explaining what your app does
with cross-device connectivity.
On the right
is the list of discovered devices.
Because some apps may only be available
on specific platforms,
you can filter discovered devices
by platform.
Upon selection of "Adam's iPhone",
the system prompts for permission
to create a connection
between those devices.
With this explicit user consent,
you no longer need to request access
to the entire local network.
And once permission has been granted,
your app will be launched
on the selected device
to handle incoming connections.
This means your app no longer needs
to be running on both devices
before a connection can be established.
When permission is granted on
"Joe's Apple Watch",
the system immediately launches your app
so the two devices can connect.
And if your app isn't installed
on that device,
the system offers to take people
to the App Store.
That way they can immediately
download your app
and begin using your new features.
Here's how that looks on watchOS.
Tapping the button will immediately launch
your app's page in the App Store,
for a quick and easy download.
So now that we've discussed what
DeviceDiscoveryUI can do for your apps,
let's look at how to adopt
this new framework.
In previous sessions,
we built the Tic-Tac-Toe app
using Network framework.
Today we're gonna be updating it
to use DeviceDiscoveryUI
for discovery of
and connections to nearby devices.
In earlier iterations,
our app only supported
playing games between iOS devices.
So to start, we've updated our project
for Universal Purchase
and added a tvOS and watchOS target
that all share the same bundle ID.
And we've changed the app so that instead
of competing against another player,
you're using your device
to play against an AI on the TV.
Next, we need to make additions
to the Info.plist
on both our tvOS application
as well as the other platforms
to declare our new Tic-Tac-Toe
application service.
Finally, we'll present the new device
picker and use the resulting endpoints
to make our connection.
Now I'm gonna shift over to Xcode
and show you
what those new Info.plist keys are,
and how they need to be added to the app.
On tvOS, our app needs to tell the system
what application services to discover,
and what the platforms
those services support.
To do that, we need to add our new
"Application Services" Info.plist.
This dictionary will map to
one of two different arrays.
On tvOS, we need to declare
the "Browses" array,
which contains all of the application
services that our app discovers.
Each entry represents
a different application service.
Our first item represents
our Tic-Tac-Toe application service.
It is a dictionary
containing our service identifier,
usage description,
and platforms this service supports.
The service identifier is the name
of our service, "TicTacToe".
The usage description is a string that
will be displayed in the device picker
to explain why our app needs access
to other local devices.
Finally, we have our platform support.
This array contains the platforms
supported by the service,
and the system will filter
discovered devices accordingly.
You can see here that our service supports
iOS, iPadOS, and watchOS devices.
We've already updated the Info.plist
used for iOS and iPadOS
with the corresponding "Application
Services" dictionary.
Now we're gonna update
the plist for watchOS.
This time,
we declare the "Advertises" array.
Because DeviceDiscoveryUI will launch
our app when it's not running,
the system uses this array
to know which services to advertise.
Our entry in the "Advertises" array only
needs the "TicTacToe" service identifier.
Make sure that the service identifier
is the same for every platform
that was declared in the tvOS Info.plist.
Now that Tic-Tac-Toe is configured
to browse for
and advertise our application service,
let's have it actually display
the device picker UI.
Our usage description appears on the left.
We made sure this string is active
and that it informs people
of why they want to connect a device
and what data they're sharing.
For Tic-Tac-Toe, we're using the connected
device as a controller to play the game.
Back in Xcode, because DeviceDiscoveryUI
replaces the need
to manually browse for nearby devices
and secures the connection for us,
we can remove the PeerBrowser file
and our passcode extension
to NWParameters
since they're no longer necessary.
Now, we need parameters to describe how
we'd like to connect to nearby devices.
First, we use the new convenience initializer,
applicationService, on NWParameters,
which gives us everything we need
for this kind of local connectivity.
Next, we can use our existing framer
for communicating gameplay actions,
without any changes, and simply add it to
the protocol stack in those parameters.
Now, we're ready to create
and show the device picker.
The device picker is how
our application discovers nearby iPhones,
iPads, and Apple Watches.
First, we need to check to see
if the device picker is supported
on the current device.
To do that, we call the
isSupported function
with the browse descriptor and parameters
that we'll be using with the picker.
Assuming it returns true, we can go ahead
and create the device picker.
We instantiate the device picker
with the parameters we created earlier,
and a browse descriptor
of type .applicationService,
specifying the name of the application
service that we defined in the Info.plist.
Now that the device picker
has been created,
we need to present the view controller.
The device picker needs to always be
presented as a full screen modal view.
Next, we need to access
the picker's async endpoint property.
Once the connection has been confirmed
and our application has been launched
on the remote device,
we'll receive an NWEndpoint,
and execution will continue.
Now that our application
has received an NWEndpoint,
we can use it to connect
to the selected device,
just like we did
in prior Tic-Tac-Toe versions.
We'll use the same parameters
when opening the connection
as provided to the device picker.
Aside from the parameters,
opening a connection to this device
looks exactly the same as it did before.
Moving to the selected device,
once our application has been launched,
we need to immediately fulfill the promise
our application made to the system
by creating an NWListener.
The NWListener needs to be created
as soon as the app is launched
to accept any incoming connections
for that application service.
The NWListener needs to be created
with the exact same parameters as before,
and we need to set the application service
on the listener
using the identifier from the Info.plist.
When the TV opens
a connection to this device,
the listener that we established
will receive that connection here,
in the new connection handler,
same as before.
So now that the connection
has been properly established,
we need to handle
application state transitions.
When our application is backgrounded,
the connection will transition
to the failed state with the associated
error ECONNABORTED.
If we want to continue
communication between the devices,
we establish a new connection
from the TV to the same endpoint.
Once started, this new connection stays
in the preparing state
and moves to the ready state once
the app is resumed on the selected device.
On that device,
the new connection will be delivered
to the same NWListener
and can be used to resume our activity.
And that's it.
Everything we need to do to migrate
to DeviceDiscoveryUI is now complete.
Let's see our game in action.
The app launches on the TV,
and we press Find Opponent
to present the device picker.
When we choose a device,
it prompts for permission.
When granted, the app is launched
immediately into our game session.
Now, we can play against the TV
by placing emojis on the board.
Great.
And that's how easy it is
to connect devices to Apple TV.
Tic-Tac-Toe is available
on the developer website,
so you can download it and explore
all of the code we discussed today.
If you have any questions,
post them on the Developer Forums.
Consider adopting DeviceDiscoveryUI
in your apps
to provide seamless device-to-device
experiences.
And please provide us feedback.
We know that device-to-device
communication is an essential experience.
DeviceDiscoveryUI was created
in response to developer feedback.
We want to build these features with you,
so please file reports
in Feedback Assistant
for anything that you'd like to see
in DeviceDiscoveryUI.
We're excited
to improve this technology together
to help make your apps even better.
Thank you so much for joining me,
and have a great WWDC 2022.