[upbeat music]
- Welcome to "Build your first
app in Swift Playgrounds."
I am Collett Charlton, an engineer
on the Swift Playgrounds team.
- And I'm Connor Wakamo,
another engineer
on the Swift Playgrounds team.
- Swift Playgrounds has been a great
tool for learning to code in Swift,
and now you can take things
a step further and build apps too!
Today, we're going to walk through
building an app in Swift Playgrounds,
starting with a blank template.
We'll then show how to debug issues
using previews and the console,
and finally,
we'll submit our app to TestFlight.
Something our team really loves
is making and drinking tea.
We love it so much
that we want to make an app for that.
Connor and I are going to build
a little app to help us at tea time,
giving us a list of teas to
help us pick what to drink each day.
Swift Playgrounds
works great on Mac and iPad.
I've got my Mac with me today,
so I'm going to start
building this app there.
Whether you are new to coding,
or are an experienced developer,
Swift Playgrounds offers a variety
of templates and instructional content
to get you started.
For our tea app, we'll begin by clicking
the blank App template
in the bottom left corner of the screen.
Now that we have our template,
let's double click to open.
Great. On the right is a live interactive
preview showing the Hello World text.
Before we start coding, let's customize
the app a little using the App Settings.
To do this,
I'll click the app settings button
in the top left corner of the sidebar.
Here, you can customize various
project properties like the app name
and the accent color.
You can also add a custom
or placeholder app icon,
capabilities, or purpose string,
and a bundleID.
I'll update the app's name to Tea Time.
I'll set the accent color to brown.
And I'll update
the placeholder icon to the mug.
Great. Now that the important part's
out of the way,
let's start writing some code
by selecting the template text
and replacing it
with our first View from the Library.
The Library can be accessed by clicking
the plus button in the project toolbar.
It contains easy-to-use snippets
of different Views,
Modifiers, SF Symbols, and Colors.
We'll be using a List View
to display our list of teas,
so I'll type list into the search field
and click it to insert one.
Now that we have our List View,
let's add some tea items to it.
I'll start typing Text...
and use the return key
to accept and insert
the code completion suggestion
from the inline code completion panel.
Alright, now we have our List View
with one tea added.
Let's add some more.
Wait, it looks like I accidentally
added Jasmine Green twice.
In order to avoid duplicating our teas,
we should store them as an orderedSet.
Luckily for us, Apple's swift-collection
package offers just that.
So, let's add the swift-collection package
to our project.
To do this, let's open the File Menu
and select Add Package.
I'll begin by entering the URL
for the swift-collections package,
and then press the return key.
After the package is fetched,
we can see the package version
and other products
that can be added to our project.
For this app, we'll only select
Collections then click Add to Project.
Now we have swift-collections added to our
project in the sidebar under Packages.
Let's create an OrderedSet of String
to store our list of teas.
Wait. It seems like we have an issue.
Let's take a look
by clicking the issue icon.
"Cannot find type ordered set
in scope."
Oh, I see what the problem is.
I forgot to import the Collections module
in our project.
Let's import that,
and the issue should be resolved.
Now that we have resolved that issue,
let's update our List View to use
the collection we just created.
To do this, we'll use a ForEach View.
Alright, there we have it--
our list of teas being displayed
from our tea collection.
As I'm working on this project,
I'm getting more and more ideas
on features to add.
It would be so cool if our app
could listen for whistling tea kettles
to let us know when it's time to pour.
I'm not going to implement this now,
but let's walk through the steps
we would take
to explain to users
why our app needs to use the microphone.
To add this,
let's go back into our app settings...
and click Capabilities.
Using the plus button
in the top righthand corner,
we'll get a list of capabilities
we can add to our project.
Let's find microphone and click it to add.
For the purpose string, we'll write:
"Tea Time uses the microphone
to listen for whistling tea kettles."
I'll click add,
and then close app settings.
Alright, we've done a lot today,
and I'm excited to share the project
and the cool ideas I have with Connor.
I'll share it with Connor by adding it
to our shared iCloud folder.
But first, let's give it
a better filename than My App.
Now, I'll drag it to the shared
iCloud Folder.
Now that I'm done, I'm going to hand it
over to Connor to finish the app.
Thanks Collett.
I'm going to pick things up on iPad.
Since we're sharing our project
via an iCloud Shared Folder,
it doesn't show up
in the main list of projects.
But if I tap on "Locations,"
I can get access to projects
from elsewhere in iCloud,
or even from
third-party document providers.
I'm already in our Shared Folder,
so I'll tap on Tea Time
to open the project.
Any changes I make will automatically
be reflected in the shared project.
It looks like Collett
is such a good engineer
that just uploading the project to iCloud
added some extra features!
She implemented a TabView here
so we don't just have a list of teas
but also an Assistant.
If I tap on the Assistant tab,
it's a little bit bare-bones,
but it does the job.
I can ask for a recommendation,
and it'll give me a tea I should drink.
Seems today I should have
the Jasmine Green.
Now I know Collett was working on
a fun new way to pick teas
to give this a little extra pizzaz.
Let's open the sidebar to try to find it.
TeaWheelView seems promising,
so let's tap on that to open it.
We've got a View
which takes a collection of data.
Let's add a view preview
so we can try TeaWheelView out
before it's a part of the main app.
I'll scroll to the bottom of the file...
And I'll begin typing "preview provider."
I'll accept the code completion
suggestion by pressing the Return key,
and I'll name it TeaWheelView_Previews.
Page dots have now appeared
at the bottom of the preview area,
which tells me that Swift Playgrounds
recognizes my preview provider.
If I tap on the right chevron
underneath the app preview…
then I can use my view preview
instead of the app preview.
Right now it just says "Hello, world!"
so let's add in some code
to create a TeaWheelView.
First I'll add an array with a few items
in it as a static property
so it can be used by my preview.
I'll leave the insertion point
between the two square brackets
and then I'll drag on the closing bracket
to create placeholders for a few items.
Next, I'll replace the placeholders with
a few strings that'll serve as our items.
Now that we've got a few items,
let's add in the TeaWheelView.
I'll select the Hello, world! example
and replace it with a TeaWheelView
that displays my items.
I'll also add in a little bit of padding.
Great! Now our view preview
is showing a wheel,
and what a beautiful wheel it is!
I can spin it, and it'll pick different
items based on where it lands.
Let's go back to the assistant tab
and add this wheel in.
I'll use the sidebar to open
the AssistantTab Swift file,
and I'm going to delete the Button and
replace it with a TeaWheelView instead.
TeaWheelView
optionally takes an action closure
which is called
when the wheel stops spinning.
I'll use it to set last picked tea
to the selected tea,
and I'll set show pick alert to true
so SwiftUI knows to show the alert.
Okay, great! We've got our wheel in here,
so now let's try it!
I'll swipe to spin it...
and it told me to drink Byte's Oolong.
I'll swipe it again...
And it's still Byte's Oolong.
One more time.
Hmm. Something seems wrong.
Even though it's landing on
different spots on the wheel,
it's always telling me
to drink the Byte's Oolong.
While that is a good tea,
I'd like a little bit of variety.
Let's switch back to the wheel view
and try to figure out what's up.
It's not obvious from this
what's going wrong,
since the wheel does spin
and land on different spots.
Let's add a print statement
into our view preview
to check if the preview is broken too.
Now when I spin the wheel...
A console message pops up
at the bottom left of the source editor.
Item one...
item one…item one.
Aha! Each spin gives us item one,
which suggests something
isn't quite hooked up right!
Since it's giving me
the first one every time,
I'm going to use project-wide find
to search for first.
I'll tap in the search field
at the top of the sidebar
on the left hand side of the screen
and then type "first" and press Return.
That result seems promising,
so I'll tap on it.
Ah, it looks like Collett left
some debugging code in here
that made it return the first item
every time instead of the right result.
Let's fix that up real quick
and then give it another spin.
Item two...
item four.
Great! It seems to be working now.
If we switch back to our app preview
by tapping on the left chevron
underneath the preview,
we can try it out in the real app.
I'll spin the wheel, and it's telling me
to have the English Breakfast.
So now we've got a working assistant.
Awesome! Just to confirm
the app works well at all sizes,
I can run it in its own window
by pressing the Run button
in the upper left of the screen.
Okay, seems like everything is here.
I've got my list of teas,
and I've got the assistant here
with the wheel and everything.
I can go back to the project
in Swift Playgrounds
by tapping on the little Swift icon
in the status bar,
and then by selecting the "Show Project"
button in the sheet that pops up.
I'm ready to test this app myself
and with my friends and family.
Swift Playgrounds makes it easy to test
because you can submit
directly to TestFlight
from within Swift Playgrounds!
If I bring up the app settings sheet
and scroll to the bottom,
there's an
"Upload to App Store Connect" button.
If I tap on that, Swift Playgrounds
does all of the hard work
of creating an app record and
uploading my app to App Store Connect
so I can distribute it on TestFlight
and eventually the App Store.
Now that my app is uploaded,
I can go to App Store Connect
and submit it for Beta App Review.
After waiting a bit,
we can go over to the TestFlight app
and install it from there, even on iPhone!
I'll tap "Install" to install Tea Time.
Now that it's installed,
I'll tap "Open" to open it.
I'll tap to the test notes,
as well as these instructions
on how to provide feedback.
And there you have it--
our app is running on iPhone.
What tea should I have today?
Looks like I'm having
the Matt P's Tea Party.
Today, Collett and I showed you
how you can use Swift Playgrounds
on your Mac and iPad to build apps.
We demonstrated using the library
and code completion to insert new code,
we shared our project
via iCloud Shared Folders,
and we used view previews and the
console to debug an issue with our code.
We even submitted an app to TestFlight,
right from iPad!
Hopefully you've learned
a thing or two along the way,
and we can't wait to see what
you build with Swift Playgrounds.
Thank you for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC!