♪ ♪
Jeremy:
Hi. I'm Jeremy,
and I'm here to show you how to create
a more responsive media app
using AVFoundation.
When using media assets in your app,
you might like to do more
than just play them.
You might like to show thumbnails,
combine media into new compositions,
or get information about your assets.
These tasks require loading data,
and with big files like video,
that might take some time to complete.
Unfortunately, it can be easy
to introduce latency issues in your app
if this work is done synchronously
on the main thread.
A great way to keep your app responsive
is to load data asynchronously,
and update your UI when it's finished.
AVFoundation has tools to make this easy.
So here's what we'll talk about today.
First, I'll introduce you
to some new async APIs in AVFoundation.
Then, I'll give you an update
on asset inspection
using the async load(_:) method
we introduced last year.
And I'll show you how to optimize
custom data loading for local
and cached media
using AVAssetResourceLoader.
But first,
let's jump into the new async API.
Grabbing still images from a video
with AVAssetImageGenerator
is a great way to create thumbnails.
But image generation isn't instantaneous.
To generate an image,
image generator needs to load frame data
from your video file.
And for media stored on a remote server,
or on the internet,
that loading will be much slower.
That's why it's important how
you generate your images.
Using a method
that loads data synchronously,
like copyCGImage, on the main thread
can cause your UI to freeze
as it waits for video to be loaded.
This year, we've added
the image(at: time) async method
which uses async/await
to free up the calling thread
while image generator loads data.
Image generator returns a tuple
with the image
and its actual time in the asset.
There are a few reasons the actual time
may vary from the time you requested,
but if you only want the image,
you can directly access it
with the .image property.
Some frames in compressed video
are easier to load than others.
iFrames can be decoded independently,
while other frames
rely on nearby frames to be decoded.
For your requested time,
image generator by default
will use the nearest iFrame
to generate your image.
It might be tempting
to set the tolerances to zero
to get the exact frame
for your requested time.
But keep in mind that
that frame will likely be dependent
on other nearby frames that
image generator will also need to load.
Instead, consider setting wide tolerances
that will still give you the result
you're looking for.
Wide tolerances help image generator
to minimize data loading
by giving it more frames to pick from.
The fewer frames it needs to load,
the faster it can return an image.
To get a series of images
at several times in an asset,
image generator has had
generateCGImagesAsynchronously(forTimes:).
However in Swift, there is some nuance
to watch out for to use it.
New this year we've added
the images(for: times) method.
It now takes an array of CMTimes,
so you don't need to map them
to NSValues first.
It also provides its results
using an Async Sequence.
In Swift, sequences let you iterate
over their items using a for in loop.
For a sequence of items
that aren't ready all at once,
an async sequence lets you await
the next element after each iteration.
For each successfully generated image,
the result includes
the originally requested time
and the actual time alongside the image.
If it fails,
the result has an error to explain why.
And if you are only interested
in the image,
the result has properties
to directly access its values,
which can also throw errors
if generation fails.
To learn more about async sequences,
I recommend checking out
the "meet async sequence" session.
For a task like image generation,
it's a little easier to see
how it involves loading data.
But there are some other
synchronous areas of AVFoundation
that are harder to pick out
as problem spots.
AVMutableComposition
is one of these areas.
Insert time range for asset
needs information about the asset's tracks
to add references to them
in the composition.
It synchronously inspects the tracks,
so if the tracks aren't already loaded,
they'll be synchronously loaded
to create the new composition tracks.
Previously, the solution would've been
to await loading the asset's tracks
before inserting them
into the composition.
However, this year, we're introducing
an async version of insertTimeRange,
which will async load the tracks for you,
as needed.
Video composition
and mutable video composition
have additional methods that require
loading the asset's properties too.
New this year,
the "propertiesOf asset" constructor,
and isValid(for:timeRange:) method
now also have async counterparts.
These new methods will asynchronously
load the tracks and duration of the asset,
so there's no need
for you to pre-load them either.
These new async methods
make it easier to interact with assets
by loading the properties they need
asynchronously.
But for when you need to load
the properties of an asset yourself,
let's get a refresher
of async asset inspection.
You may have noticed there are two ways
to inspect an asset's properties.
When AVFoundation was introduced,
the best way to inspect properties
was with async key value loading.
Last year, we introduced async load(_:).
It uses type safe keys
to identify the properties to load,
where the old async key value loading
technique used hard coded strings as keys.
Typos in these string keys
are difficult to catch.
Misspelling a key prevents it
from being loaded asynchronously,
and when the property is later used,
it'll block while it loads.
It's also very easy to forget to add
new properties to the keys to load
or to forget async loading them entirely.
For these reasons, this year,
we're deprecating async key value loading
and the synchronous properties in Swift,
in favor for async load.
Async load uses type safe identifiers
to prevent typos.
It directly returns property values
as requested
to avoid accessing unloaded properties.
And since all of this is checked
at compile time,
you'll prevent introducing
any new IO bound performance issues.
Async load is now the only recommended way
to asynchronously inspect properties
on AVAsset, AVAssetTrack,
AVMetadataItem, and their sub classes.
However, a handful of these classes
will still offer
synchronous property inspection.
That's because the data for their
properties is already available in memory.
Let's take another look at
mutable composition to see why.
We'll use a mutable composition
to splice together segments
of two existing video tracks.
We'll start by creating
an empty composition
and adding an empty video track.
Then, we can synchronously insert
part of the first video track
into the composition track.
Behind the scenes,
this step isn't loading any data.
Instead, it adds a new track segment
that points to the desired track.
Then we can append part of
the second track in the same way.
Since the composition itself
is backed by an in memory structure
and not a file, we can safely inspect
its properties synchronously
without needing to load them first.
Again, for this reason,
synchronous property inspection
will remain available on these classes
and all classes will use async load
for asynchronous inspection.
All of these new async methods
in AVFoundation
will make it easier to prevent blocking
while loading media data.
But, introducing concurrency into your app
for the first time can be tricky.
Check out these sessions from
WWDC 21 for help getting started
with Swift concurrency and for migrating
to AVFoundation's async load in your app.
For our last topic, let's talk about
optimizing custom data loading
for your assets.
To start, lets take a look
at how AVAsset loads data by default.
When you create an AVAsset with a URL,
the media can either be on the network,
or stored locally on device.
If it's on the network,
AVAsset will dynamically cache
a certain amount of data
to ensure smooth playback.
If the media is local,
AVAsset can bypass the cache
and load data as needed to play.
In some cases,
you might not be able to give
AVAsset a direct pointer to your media.
Maybe you store the raw bytes of an mp4
inside of a custom project file.
For situations like this,
AVAsset can use an AVAssetResourceLoader.
Resource loader provides the asset
with a way to request arbitrary bytes
from your media
that you have a special way to load.
But since the asset is no longer
handling reading in data,
it can't predict how long it'll take
each chunk to load.
So it assumes that accessing the media
involves network communication,
and waits until it caches data
before it becomes ready to play.
This year, if your media
is locally available,
you can enable
entireLengthAvailableOnDemand
for your resource loader.
Setting this flag tells the asset
that it can expect to receive data
as it's requested,
so it can skip caching.
For local media,
entireLengthAvailableOnDemand
can help reduce your app's memory usage
during playback,
since it won't need to cache extra data.
It can also decrease the time it takes
to start playback,
since the asset won't have to wait
for the cache to fill up first.
Use caution when enabling this flag,
though.
If loading requires
any network operations,
including network file storage,
it's likely playback will be unreliable.
That's the new enhancement
for resource loader.
Now lets wrap things up
with some next steps for your app.
When working with media, use async/await
to keep your app responsive
while it loads in the background.
Consider increasing tolerances when
using image generator for faster results.
And if you are using resource loader
for locally available media,
enable entire length available on demand
to help increase performance.
That's everything I have for today.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy WWDC 22.