♪ ♪
Welcome to Visualize and Optimize
Swift Concurrency.
My name is Mike,
and I work on the Swift runtime library.
Hi, I'm Harjas,
and I work on Instruments.
Together, we're going to
discuss ways to better understand
your Swift Concurrency code
and make it go faster,
including a new visualization tool
available in Instruments 14.
Let's start off with a really quick recap
of the various parts of Swift Concurrency
and how they work together,
to make sure you're up to speed.
After that, we'll demo
the new concurrency instrument.
We'll show you how we use it
to solve some real performance issues
with an app using Swift Concurrency.
Finally, we'll discuss the potential
problems of thread pool exhaustion
and continuation misuse
and how to avoid them.
Last year,
we introduced Swift Concurrency.
This was a new language feature
that includes async/await,
structured concurrency, and Actors.
We've been pleased to see a great deal
of adoption of these features since then,
both inside and outside Apple.
Swift concurrency adds
several new features to the language
which work together to make concurrent
programming easier and safer.
Async/await are basic syntactic
building blocks for concurrent code.
They allow you to create and call
functions that can suspend their work
in the middle of execution,
then resume that work later,
without blocking an execution thread.
Tasks are the basic unit of work
in concurrent code.
Tasks execute concurrent code
and manage its state and associated data.
They contain local variables,
handle cancellation,
and begin and suspend execution
of async code.
Structured concurrency makes it easy
to spawn child tasks
to run in parallel
and wait for them to complete.
The language provides syntax
which keeps the work grouped together
and ensures that tasks are awaited
or automatically canceled if not used.
Actors coordinate multiple tasks
that need to access shared data.
They isolate data from the outside,
and allow only one task at a time
to manipulate their internal state,
avoiding data races
from concurrent mutation.
New in Instruments 14,
we're introducing a set of instruments
that can capture and visualize
all of this activity in your app,
helping you to understand
what your app is doing,
locate problems, and improve performance.
For a more in-depth discussion
of the fundamentals of Swift Concurrency,
we have several videos
about these features
linked in the Related Videos section.
Let's take a look at optimizing an app
using Swift Concurrency code.
Swift concurrency makes it easy to
to write correct concurrent
and parallel code.
However, it's still possible to write code
that misuses concurrency constructs.
It's also possible to use them correctly
but in a way that doesn't get the
performance benefits you were aiming for.
There are a few common problems
that can arise when writing code
using Swift concurrency that can cause
poor performance or bugs.
Main Actor blocking
can cause your app to hang.
Actor contention and thread pool
exhaustion hurt performance
by reducing parallel execution.
Continuation misuse
causes leaks or crashes.
The new Swift Concurrency instrument can
help you discover and fix these problems.
Let's take a look at each of these,
starting with main Actor blocking.
Main Actor blocking occurs
when a long-running task
runs on the main Actor.
The main Actor is a special Actor
which executes all of its work
on the main thread.
UI work must be done on the main thread,
and the main Actor allows you to integrate
UI code into Swift Concurrency.
However, because the main thread
is so important for UI,
it needs to be available and can't be
occupied by a long-running unit of work.
When this happens, your app appears
to lock up and becomes unresponsive.
Code running on the main Actor
must finish quickly,
and either complete its work
or move computation
off of the main Actor
and into the background.
Work can be moved into the background
by putting it in a normal Actor
or in a detached task.
Small units of work can be executed
on the main Actor to update UI
or perform other tasks
that must be done on the main thread.
Let's see a demo of this in action.
Thanks, Mike.
Here we have
our File Squeezer application.
We built this application
to be able to quickly compress
all the files in a folder.
It seems to work alright for small files.
However, when I use larger files,
it takes much longer than expected
and the UI is completely frozen
and does not respond to any interactions.
This behavior is very off-putting to users
and may make them think
that the application has crashed
or will never finish.
We should strive to ensure
that our UI is always responsive
for the best user experience.
To investigate this performance problem,
we can use the new Swift Concurrency
template in Instruments.
The Swift Tasks and Swift Actors
instruments provide a full suite of tools
to help you visualize
and optimize your concurrency code.
When you're just starting
to investigate a performance problem
you should first take a look
at the top-level statistics
provided to you
by the Swift Tasks instrument.
The first of these is Running Tasks,
which show you how many tasks
are executing simultaneously.
Next, we have Alive Tasks,
which show how many tasks are present
at a given point in time.
And finally, Total Tasks;
graph the total number of tasks
that have been created
up until that point in time.
When you're attempting to reduce
your application memory footprint,
you should take a close look at
the Alive and Total Tasks statistics.
The combination of all of these statistics
give you a good picture of how well your
code is parallelizing
and how many resources you are consuming.
One of the many detail views
for this instrument is the Task Forest;
shown in the bottom half of this window,
it provides a graphical representation
of the parent-child relationships
between Tasks
in structured concurrency code.
Next, we have our Task Summary view.
This shows how much time
each Task spends in different states.
We have super-charged the view by allowing
you to right-click on a Task
to be able to pin a Track
containing all the information
about the selected Task to the timeline.
This allows you to quickly find and learn
about Tasks of interest
that may be running for a very long time
or stuck waiting to get access
to an Actor.
Once you pin a Swift Task to the timeline,
you get four key features.
First, is the track that shows you
what state your Swift Task is in.
Second, is the Task creation backtrace
in the extended detail view.
Third, is the narrative view
that provides more context
about the state a Swift Task is in.
Such as, if it's waiting on a Task,
it will inform you
which Task you are waiting on.
Lastly, you have access to
the same pin action in the narrative view
as you did in the summary view.
So, you can pin a child Task, a thread,
or even a Swift Actor to the timeline.
This narrative view will be instrumental
in finding how a Swift Task is related
to your other concurrency primitives
and the CPU.
Now that we have seen a brief overview
of some of the features
in the new instrument,
let's profile our application
and optimize our code.
We can do this by pulling up our project
in Xcode and pressing Command-I.
This will compile our application,
open up instruments,
and pre-select the target
to the File Squeezer application.
From here you can pick the Swift
Concurrency option in the template picker
and start recording.
Once again,
I'll drop the large files onto the app.
Again, we see that the app starts spinning
and the UI is not responsive.
We will let this run
for a few more seconds
so that Instruments can capture
all the information about our application.
Now that we have a trace,
we can start investigating.
I'm going to fullscreen this trace
to better see all the information.
We can use option-drag
to zoom in on our area of interest.
In the process track,
Instruments shows us exactly
where this UI hang was occurring.
This can be useful for cases
when it is not clear
when the hang occurred
or how long it lasted.
As I mentioned earlier,
a good place to start
is the top-level Swift Task statistics.
What catches my eye right away
is the Running Tasks count.
For most of the time,
only one Task is running.
This tells us part of the problem is that
all of our work is being forced
to serialize.
We can use the Task State summary
to find our longest running Task
and use the pin action
to pin it to the timeline.
The narrative view for this Task tells us
that it ran on a background thread
for a short amount of time,
and then ran on the Main Thread
for a long time.
To further investigate, we can pin
the Main Thread to the timeline.
The Main Thread is being blocked
by several long running Tasks.
This demonstrates the issue of
Main Actor blocking that Mike spoke about.
So the questions
we have to ask ourselves are,
"What is this Task doing?"
and "Where did this Task come from?"
We can switch back to the narrative view
to answer both of these questions.
The creation backtrace in
the extended detail view
shows that the task was created
in the compressAllFiles function.
The narrative shows that
the Task is executing closure number one
in compressAllFiles.
By right-clicking on this symbol,
we can open this in the source viewer.
Closure number one inside this function
is calling our compression work.
Now that we know where this Task
was created and what it is doing,
we can open our code in Xcode and adapt it
so that we don't run
these heavy computations
on the Main Thread.
The compress file function is located
within the CompressionState class.
The entire CompressionState class
is annotated to run on the @MainActor.
This explains why the Task also ran
on the Main Thread.
We need this entire class to be on the MainActor
because the @Published property here
must only be updated from the Main Thread,
otherwise,
we could run into runtime issues.
So, instead we could try to convert
this class into its own Actor.
However, the compiler will tell us
that we can't do this
because essentially we would be saying
that this shared mutable state
needs to be protected
by two different Actors.
But that does give us a hint
for what the real solution is.
We have two different pieces
of mutable state here within this class.
One piece of state,
the 'files' property,
needs to be isolated to the MainActor
because it is observed by SwiftUI.
But access to the other piece of state,
the logs,
needs to be protected
from concurrent access,
but which thread accesses logs
at any given point doesn't matter.
Thus, it doesn't actually need
to be on the Main Actor.
We still want to protect it
from concurrent access, though,
so we wrap it in its own Actor.
All we need now is add a way for Tasks
to hop between the two as needed.
We can create a new Actor
and call it ParallelCompressor.
We can then copy the log state into the
new Actor,
and add some extra setup code.
From here, we need to make these Actors
communicate with each other.
First, let's remove the code
that referred to the logs variable
from the CompressionState class,
and add it
to our ParallelCompressor Actor.
Then finally,
we need to update CompressionState
to invoke compressFile
on the ParallelCompressor.
With these changes,
let's test our application again.
Once again, I'll drop the large files
onto our application.
The UI is no longer hung,
which is a great improvement,
but we aren't getting the speed
that we would expect.
We really want to take full advantage
of all the cores in the machine
to do this work as fast as possible.
Mike, what else
should we be watching out for?
Mike: We've solved our hang
by moving work off of the Main Actor,
but we're still not getting
the performance we want.
To see why,
we need to take a closer look at Actors.
Actors make it safe for multiple tasks
to manipulate shared state.
However, they do this by serializing
access to that shared state.
Only one task at a time
is allowed to occupy the Actor,
and other tasks
that need to use that Actor will wait.
Swift concurrency allows for parallel
computation using unstructured tasks,
task groups, and async let.
Ideally, these constructs are able
to use many CPU cores simultaneously.
When using Actors from such code,
beware of performing large amounts of work
on an Actor
that's shared among these tasks.
When multiple tasks attempt
to use the same Actor simultaneously,
the Actor serializes
execution of those tasks.
Because of this, we lose the performance
benefits of parallel computation.
This is because each task must wait
for the Actor to become available.
To fix this, we need make sure
that tasks only run on the Actor
when they really need exclusive access
to the Actor's data.
Everything else should run
off of the Actor.
We divide the task into chunks.
Some chunks must run on the Actor,
and the others don't.
The non-Actor isolated chunks
can be executed in parallel,
which means the computer
can finish the work much faster.
Let's see a demo of this in action.
Harjas: Thanks, Mike.
Let's take a look at the trace
of our updated "File Squeezer" application
and keep in mind
what Mike has just taught us.
The Task Summary view shows us
that our concurrency code
is spending an alarming amount of time
in the Enqueued state.
This means we have a lot of Tasks waiting
to get exclusive access to an Actor.
Let's pin one of these Tasks to learn why.
This Task spends quite a while
waiting to get onto
the ParallelCompressor Actor
before it runs the compression work.
Let's go ahead
and pin the Actor to our timeline.
Here we have some top-level data
for the ParallelCompressor Actor.
This Actor Queue seems to be getting
blocked by some long running Tasks.
Tasks should really only stay on an Actor
for as long as needed.
Let's go back to the Task narrative.
After the enqueue on ParallelCompressor,
the Task runs in closure number one
in compressAllFiles.
So let's start our investigation there.
The source code shows us that this closure
is primarily running our compression work.
Since the compressFile function
is part of the ParallelCompressor Actor,
the entire execution of this function
happens on the Actor;
blocking all other compression work.
To resolve this issue,
we need to pull the compressFile function
out of Actor-isolation
and into a detached task.
By doing this, we can have
the detached task only on an Actor
for as long as needed
to update the relevant mutable state.
So now the compress function
can be executed freely,
on any thread
in the thread pool,
until it needs to access
Actor-protected state.
For example, when it needs
to access the 'files' property,
it'll move onto the Main Actor.
But as soon as it's done there, it moves
into the "sea of concurrency" again,
until it needs to access
the logs property,
for which it moves on
to the ParallelCompressor Actor.
But again, as soon as it's done there,
it leaves the Actor again
to be executed on the thread pool.
But of course, we don't have just one task
doing compression work;
we have many.
And by not being constrained to an Actor,
they can all be executed concurrently,
only limited by the number of threads.
Of course, each Actor
can only execute one task at a time,
but most of the time,
our Tasks don't need to be on an Actor.
So like Mike explained,
this allows our compression tasks
to executed in parallel
and utilize all available CPU cores.
So let's make this change now.
We can mark the compressFile function
as nonisolated.
This does result in a few compiler errors.
By marking it as nonisolated,
we told the Swift compiler
that we don't need access
to the shared state of this Actor.
But that isn't entirely true.
This log function is Actor-isolated and it
needs access to the shared mutable state.
In order to fix this,
we need to make this function async
and then mark all of our log invocations
with the await keyword.
Now we need to update our task creation
to create a detached task.
We do this to ensure
the Task does not inherit
the Actor-context that it was created in.
For detached tasks,
we need to explicitly capture self.
Let's test our application again.
The app is able to compress
all the files simultaneously
and the UI remains responsive.
To verify our improvements,
we can check the Swift Actors instrument.
Looking at the ParallelCompressor Actor,
most of the work executed on the Actor
is only for a short amount of time
and the queue size never gets out of hand.
To recap, we used the Instrument
to Isolate the cause of a UI hang,
we restructured our concurrency code
for better parallelism,
and verified performance improvements
using data.
Now Mike is gonna tell us about
some other potential performance issues.
Mike: There are two common problems
I'd like to cover
beyond what we've seen in the demo.
First, let's talk about
thread pool exhaustion.
Thread pool exhaustion
can hurt performance
or even deadlock an application.
Swift concurrency requires tasks to make
forward progress when they're running.
When a task waits for something,
it normally does so by suspending.
However, it's possible for code
within a task to perform a blocking call,
such as blocking file or network IO,
or acquiring locks, without suspending.
This breaks the requirement
for tasks to make forward progress.
When this happens,
the task continues to occupy the thread
where it's executing,
but it isn't actually using a CPU core.
Because the pool of threads is limited
and some of them are blocked,
the concurrency runtime is
unable to fully use all CPU cores.
This reduces the amount
of parallel computation
that can be done
and the maximum performance of your app.
In extreme cases, when the entire
thread pool is occupied by blocked tasks,
and they're waiting on something
that requires a new task
to run on the thread pool,
the concurrency runtime can deadlock.
Be sure to avoid blocking calls in tasks.
File and network IO must be performed
using async APIs.
Avoid waiting on condition variables
or semaphores.
Fine-grained, briefly-held locks
are acceptable if necessary,
but avoid locks
that have a lot of contention
or are held for long periods of time.
If you have code
that needs to do these things,
move that code
outside of the concurrency thread pool–
for example,
by running it on a Dispatch queue–
and bridge it to the concurrency world
using continuations.
Whenever possible,
use async APIs for blocking operations
to keep the system operating smoothly.
When you're using continuations,
you must be careful to use them correctly.
Continuations are the bridge between Swift
concurrency and other forms of async code.
A continuation suspends
the current task
and provides a callback
which resumes the task when called.
This can then be used
with callback-based async APIs.
From the perspective of Swift concurrency,
the task suspends,
and then it resumes
when the continuation is resumed.
From the perspective of the callback-based
async API, the work begins,
and then the callback is called
when the work completes.
The Swift Concurrency instrument
knows about continuations
and will mark
the time interval accordingly,
showing you that the task was waiting on
a continuation to be called.
Continuation callbacks have
a special requirement:
they must be called exactly once,
no more, no less.
This is a common requirement
in callback-based APIs,
but it tends to be an informal one
and is not enforced by the language,
and oversights are common.
Swift concurrency
makes this a hard requirement.
If the callback is called twice,
the program will crash or misbehave.
If the callback is never called,
the task will leak.
In this code snippet
we use withCheckedContinuation
to get a continuation.
We then invoke a callback-based API.
In the callback,
we resume the continuation.
This meets the requirement of calling it
exactly once.
It's important to be careful
when the code is more complex.
On the left, we've modified the callback
to only resume the continuation
on success.
This is a bug.
On failure,
the continuation will not be resumed,
and the task will be suspended forever.
On the right,
we're resuming the continuation twice.
This is also a bug,
and the app will misbehave or crash.
Both of these snippets
violate the requirement
to resume the continuation exactly once.
Two kinds of continuations
are available: checked and unsafe.
Always use the withCheckedContinuation API
for continuations
unless performance is absolutely critical.
Checked continuations automatically
detect misuse and flag an error.
When a checked continuation
is called twice, the continuation traps.
When the continuation
is never called at all,
a message is printed to the console
when the continuation is destroyed
warning you that the continuation leaked.
The Swift Concurrency instrument
will show the corresponding task
stuck indefinitely
in the continuation state.
There is much more to look into
for the new Swift Concurrency template
in Instruments.
You can get graphic visualization
of structured concurrency,
view task creation calltrees, and inspect
the exact assembly instructions
to get a full picture
of the Swift Concurrency runtime.
To learn more about how Swift Concurrency
works under the hood,
watch last year's session on
"Swift Concurrency: Behind the Scenes."
And to learn more about data races,
watch "Eliminate data races
using Swift Concurrency."
Thanks for watching!
And have fun
debugging your concurrency code.