[spacey music]
Nicholas: Hi.
I’m Nicholas Felton,
a designer
on the Human Interface team.
Today I’ll be talking about how to build
great app experiences using charts.
Charts are a great way to communicate
complex information.
We use them throughout Apple
to enhance our products.
Health uses charts to help us understand
our bodies,
Fitness inspires us
to stay active with charts,
and Weather displays charts
to help us plan our day.
We know that developers love them as well,
and we see inspiring examples
in every category.
From the detailed workout analysis
in Strava
to the playful progress charts
in Duolingo.
Charts can be found everywhere, and when
well-designed,
can reveal subtleties in data
that you cannot communicate easily
through text.
In addition to their utility, charts
are also an opportunity
to support the personality of your app
and add visual interest to your UI.
To demonstrate how an app can be enhanced
with charts,
let’s look at one made
for the owner of a food truck
selling pancakes.
The app currently has a tab
for entering orders,
and another for viewing
recent transactions.
This works fine for keeping track
of sales,
but this information could be
much more useful.
This year, we’re introducing Swift Charts.
With this framework, making charts
for Apple devices has never been easier.
In the following sections, I will share
the principles we follow
when designing experiences
with charts at Apple.
We will apply these concepts to create
wireframes
for a more informative version
of the food truck app.
In order to build a great experience
with charts,
we should consider three things:
when to use charts,
how to use them,
and how they relate to each other
in a chart design system.
Let’s begin by discussing
when to use charts in an app.
Here are some common cases
where a chart can elevate
the information being presented:
When showing historical
or predicted values,
a chart can vividly demonstrate
changes in data.
By visualizing a portion of a whole,
we can use charts to show the state
of something that is completing,
progressing towards a goal, or emptying.
When comparing items or categories, we can
easily evaluate their values with charts.
To decide whether any
of these approaches
are appropriate for your app,
consider what the experience needs first.
How will a chart support
the core goals of your app?
When used correctly, charts provide focus.
As an app creator,
there are many things you could visualize,
but only the most important information
should become a chart.
For someone using an app,
charts are a strong signal.
They direct attention to the information
you want them to understand.
The goal of the food truck app
is to improve the operation
of the businesses using it.
If we can use charts to turn
a list of transactions
into actionable information,
food truck owners
will welcome the improvement.
Here is some key information that we know
will be useful to food truck owners:
viewing recent sales,
understanding what items are popular,
and knowing the best location
to visit each day.
As you consider your app, remember
that charts should direct attention
and provide focus to the most
important information in your experience.
Now that we’ve established
what we want to communicate,
let’s look
at how to achieve this using charts.
To illustrate recent sales,
a chart showing change over time
will be appropriate.
One way of doing this is to use
a bar chart showing sales totals
for each of the last 30 days.
We will add axis labels soon,
but first, it needs a description
to tell someone what the chart represents.
A title like "Sales in the Past 30 Days"
labels the elements of the chart
but doesn’t communicate anything more.
How can we summarize
the information being shown?
A chart should be accompanied by text
that describes the chart contents.
If read in isolation,
it should be informative.
Adding the total number of pancakes sold
transforms the title
into a self-contained description.
Now someone can quickly gather
key information from the text,
while the chart
provides supporting details.
When a chart is not straightforward,
using a complete sentence
for the description can make
it easier to understand.
For example: "Sales in the past 30 days
totaled 1,234 pancakes."
Another way of framing the chart
is to interpret the data.
For example: "Sales for the past 30
days are up 12%,
totaling 1,234 pancakes."
This will help someone understand
if the level of recent sales
is high or low
or if it is increasing or decreasing.
This technique can make
a description more meaningful,
particularly when the data is unfamiliar.
Each of these approaches is
a good way of describing a chart,
but this overview is just one way
of explaining our sales data.
What else can we do
to illuminate these transactions?
Try to incorporate details
from other perspectives.
It’s important to summarize your data,
but when we find ways
to elevate categories or highlight
individual records,
a chart becomes multi-dimensional.
Here are some additional perspectives
to consider:
At a macro level, we look for ways to
describe the entire data set,
like a total, or average value.
At a medium scale,
we look at sub-sets of data.
These might be time-based,
like comparing weekdays to weekends
or investigating changes
related to the time of day.
Other approaches might categorize
sales by the style of pancake
or the city where they were sold.
At the micro level,
we focus on individual data points.
The last transaction or largest sale
are important small-scale details
you may want to call out in your charts.
The more carefully you observe a data set,
the more detail will emerge.
Some of the perspectives
we’ve identified could be useful
to food truck owners planning
their inventory or sales locations.
It would be useful to augment
the recent sales chart
with some of these details.
To do this, we can use a set
of tappable rows under the chart.
Each row provides a summary statistic,
and when tapped,
the chart is updated to match.
We can show the daily average value
or the difference between weekday
and weekend sales
or the best sales day.
These overlays can be extremely useful,
but this amount of information
requires a large surface
to work effectively.
As the functionality of a chart increases,
so will its size.
Smaller charts tend to be static.
Examples include Watch complications,
the repeating thumbnail charts
in Stocks,
and the trend platters in Health.
Static charts rarely exist in isolation.
They tend to provide a preview
of a larger chart in another view.
As they are generally small,
static charts don’t require grid lines,
labels, or interactivity,
since they create the expectation
that additional detail is just a tap away.
Interactive charts tend to be larger,
and include much more detail,
like the charts in Stocks and in Health.
An interactive chart will typically be
the width of your view,
but not full-height.
You should include axis lines and labels
so that values can be estimated.
Interactivity is recommended at this size
for accessing precise values
in the chart
and the ability to change the time range
or time scope will aid exploration.
The largest and most interactive charts
allow for deep investigation of data
and require the most vertical space.
As charts become more powerful,
it’s important
to introduce
additional functionality gradually.
You should progressively reveal
chart complexity
so that someone can choose
the level of information
that matches their interest.
Use a small static chart higher
in the navigation hierarchy
to offer a path to expanded versions
of the chart.
When you create a link
between two versions of the same chart,
that progression should maintain
continuity
by preserving values, context and state.
Keep in mind that when someone
expresses interest in a chart,
they want to see more of what
they have already seen.
This means that a chart
should retain its shape
and any numbers apparent
in an earlier view should be preserved.
You can add information,
but showing something different
can be frustrating or disorienting.
While we’re considering the functionality
of different sized charts,
let’s revisit our food truck app
to determine where our planned charts
will go.
We currently have two tabs,
one dedicated to placing orders,
and a second that shows the sales history.
These records
are what we will be visualizing,
so it makes sense to adapt
this view to include our charts.
Let’s clear the tab by moving
the sales to a separate view
behind a "View all sales"
navigational element.
We now have a prominent canvas
for our charts.
As a result,
it’s appropriate to use a static chart
that lets someone scan the data
and decide whether they want to see more.
Here’s the static chart
showing recent sales.
Tapping the platter
leads to an expanded interactive chart.
We now have
a complete recent sales experience.
This interactive chart
will support detailed analysis
with 30-day and 1-year views,
touch states,
and tappable summary statistics.
As you’re working on your app,
remember that charts need descriptions
to inform the contents
and provide a key takeaway,
the details in your data can add richness
to your charts,
and that you should progressively reveal
chart complexity within your app.
Now let’s look at chart design systems.
When your app includes
more than one chart,
you’ve created a chart design system.
Here are some things to remember
when planning multiple charts:
Use familiar forms.
Start with common chart styles
to aid comprehension.
If someone has
already used a similar chart,
they will be more likely
to understand yours.
Bar charts and line charts are forms
that many people encounter and use daily,
while a scatter plot
is less common and may require
extra guidance to ensure that
it is interpreted correctly.
If you want to do something unique,
it should be introduced clearly,
as demonstrated here
in the onboarding flow for Activity.
After the activity rings are introduced,
they are split apart to show the move,
exercise, and stand components.
Ideally, a new form is central
to your app, not supplementary.
The prominence you give a novel chart
will encourage people
to explore and understand it.
When creating supporting charts,
familiar forms are more important,
as they will not be given
as much prominence.
Differences matter,
and the variations between charts
are a signal that something has changed.
To demonstrate this, let’s start
with two copies of our recent sales chart.
I’ll slowly update the chart on the right
to communicate different information,
and we'll show how the design evolves
to signal these distinctions.
First, I’ll change the time scope
of the chart on the right.
Rather than showing recent sales,
it now shows sales for the last 12 months.
I have changed the description and updated
the chart to show 12 months of data.
Minimal changes
are required for this modification.
If I want to change the type of data
being displayed in the right-hand chart,
it may not be sufficient
to only change the description.
Noticing this change in text
could be easily missed,
so an additional change is necessary.
Giving each of these charts
a distinct color helps.
Now it is easier to notice
that these charts are unique.
Creating this difference
makes it more likely
that someone will now read
the description.
Finally, I want to update the chart
on the right
to show the range of daily sales
for each of past 12 months.
This requires both a change
to the description
and the way that the data is represented.
To underscore
the significance of this change,
modifying the styling
of the bars is appropriate.
The chart on the right
now conveys a different subject,
different time range,
and different metrics.
The design is purposefully distinct
to ensure that these differences
will be noticed.
We can apply these principles
to the two other charts
we need for our food truck app.
To compliment the recent sales,
I’d like to add another chart
that shows
the most popular style of pancake.
One way of showing the most popular style
is to compare the relative sales level
for each pancake.
Since we are interested
in the last 30 days as a whole,
we only need one bar to compare
the popularity of styles.
If I separate the bars,
I can compare their sizes more clearly,
but this starts to look
like a time series chart again.
By making the bars horizontal,
I can accentuate the difference
between this chart
and the recent sales chart.
The horizontal orientation also
lets me make the bars longer
without needing to make the platter
on the sales tab taller.
In this preview platter, I’ve omitted
labels to focus only on the top style.
In the detail view, each bar is labeled,
and the relative values are visible.
For our final chart,
we would like to show sales
in the two cities where the truck operates
for each day of the week.
For this, we will need to do
something a bit specialized.
The context for this chart
is sales by day of the week.
In this case, we want to look
at each day independently.
Here are the average daily sales
for each day of the week
over the past 30 days.
As the food truck operates
in both Cupertino and San Francisco,
we need to split these bars
to represent each location.
Finally, let’s convert these bars
into lines to focus on the daily changes.
I’ve added this chart to the sales tab
and included a description
to summarize the data.
In this case, the best sales day
over the past 30 days
was Sunday in San Francisco.
The subsequent detail page
is the last chart we will add to the app.
It provides additional interactivity
and details,
including keys for the two lines.
We’ve now sketched out the set of charts
we plan to add
to the pancake food truck app.
Using charts to show recent sales,
popular items,
and top days and locations
will dramatically improve
the utility of this app.
As you work on your app, remember
to use familiar chart forms
to assist comprehension
and intentionally create differences
between your charts
to improve their interpretation.
In this talk,
we discussed when to use charts,
how to use them, and how they relate
to each other in a chart design system.
Applying these principles will help you
communicate data in your app
with more clarity and appeal.
To continue learning about chart design,
you can watch "Design an Effective Chart,"
or for an introduction to Swift Charts,
watch "Hello Swift Charts."
[spacey music]