♪ Mellow instrumental
hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello, my name is Anders.
In this video,
I'll show you how to get started
with Swift package plugins.
Swift Packages were
introduced in Xcode 11.
They provide a great way
of distributing libraries
as source code.
Xcode 14 extends this approach
to your development workflow,
letting you use plugins
to do things
like generating source code
during a build,
or automating
your release tasks.
We'll start by taking a look
at what package plugins are
and how they work,
and then talk in more detail
about the two kinds of package
plugins that Xcode 14 supports:
command plugins
and build tool plugins.
So first of all,
what is a plugin?
A package plugin is
a Swift script that can perform
actions on a Swift package
or an Xcode project.
A plugin uses API
that Xcode provides
especially for this purpose.
Package plugins are
implemented as Swift packages.
A package can provide plugins
together with libraries
and executables,
or a package could focus
only on providing plugins.
A package plugin
can be implemented
using more than one source file,
and a Swift package can define
more than one plugin.
A highly specialized plugin
can be private to the package
that provides it,
and in that case, it's available
only within that package.
But a general-purpose plugin
can be made available
to other packages by defining it
as a package product.
That lets other packages
use it too,
in a way that's similar
to how a package
can use a library
from another package.
But unlike a library,
a dependency on a plugin
does not bring in runtime
content into your app.
Instead, it lets you
access development tools
that run on your own machine
or in your build automation.
So what can
a package plugin do?
Well, in Xcode 14 there are
two kinds of package plugins:
command plugins
and build tool plugins.
Command plugins
implement custom actions
that you can run
whenever you want to.
They can run source code
formatters or linters,
or they can perform other tasks
as part of your
development workflow.
That might include updating
contributor lists
or copyright dates in source
files based on Git history,
or other things you might have
arbitrary scripts to do today.
If it needs to,
a command plugin
can ask for permission to modify
the files in a package.
And that's especially useful
for code formatting.
Not all command plugins
need write permission.
Some commands could create
reports or calculate metrics
about your code, without
needing to make any changes.
Build tool plugins extend the
build system's dependency graph.
They're particularly useful
for generating source code
or resources
as part of a build.
Unlike command plugins,
which are invoked
for a whole package
or a project at a time,
build tool plugins are applied
to each target that needs them.
Let's take a look at using
a command plugin in Xcode.
Here's a little iOS app
that shows various kinds
of geometric shapes.
It's composed of an app project
and a local package.
The package implements a library
that provides the core data
types and logic for the app.
I'm thinking of splitting out
the package
into its own repository
so that others can use it,
and as part of this, I'd like
to create a contributor file
that lists everyone who has
committed code of this package.
I could write
a custom script to do this.
But I know of a package
that provides
some useful plugins
for working with code,
and I think it has a plugin
that does exactly what I want.
To get access to those plugins,
I'll do the same thing
as if I needed a library
from another package:
I'm going to add
a package dependency
in the manifest
of my local package.
When I save the manifest,
Xcode fetches the remote package
and it appears in the
Package Dependencies section.
I notice that Xcode has
also fetched SwiftFormat,
which is a popular tool
for formatting code.
This is because
one of the command plugins
in the utility package in turn
has a dependency on SwiftFormat.
Now that I've added
this dependency,
I have access
to any plugin commands
that the package provides.
I use the context menu
on the package
I want to apply the command to.
Now there are three new commands
in the menu;
one is for reformatting
source code using SwiftFormat,
and two others provide
specialized actions.
One of them generates
or updates contributor lists
based on
the commit history in Git,
and another updates
the copyright dates
in my source files.
The command in the middle
there does exactly what I want.
When I invoke the plugin
command on my package,
Xcode lets me choose
which of its targets
to pass to the plugin.
In this case, I'm going to
invoke it on the whole package.
And if the plugin
takes custom arguments,
I can pass those here as well.
I click Run,
and because the plugin
is going to modify
the file system,
Xcode warns me about that.
I can see the plugin
author's stated reason
for wanting to modify my code,
but I want to take a peek
at the implementation
of the plugin as well.
So I choose Show Command,
and Xcode takes me to the code.
What this plugin
is doing is safe,
so I'm going to invoke
the command again
and this time,
I will choose Run.
I'll tell Xcode to remember
my choice for this plugin.
This particular plugin uses
Git history to generate
a file listing showing
the names of contributors,
but there's a lot of flexibility
in what command plugins can do.
Now that we've used
a command plugin in Xcode,
let's take a closer look at how
plugins work under the hood.
Package plugins
are Swift scripts
that are compiled and run
when they are needed.
Each plugin runs
as a separate process.
Plugins have access
to a distilled representation
of the input package,
including its source files.
A plugin also gets information
about any dependencies
of the package.
Many plugins call
command-line tools
as part of doing their work.
Plugins can also create
files and directories,
and can perform other actions
using standard libraries
such as Foundation.
A plugin runs in a sandbox
that prevents network access
and that only allows writing to
a few places in the file system,
such as the build outputs
directory.
But command plugins
can ask for permission
to also modify files
in the package source directory.
If the user approves,
the sandbox is configured
to allow writing
to those locations.
The plugin can also send
results back to Xcode.
It can emit
warnings and errors,
and build tool plugins
can define tool invocations
for Xcode to run
during the build.
All package plugins use API
from the PackagePlugin module
provided by Xcode.
This API allows the plugin
to access the input package,
and if appropriate,
to return results to Xcode.
The main source file
that implements the plugin
also defines
the main entry point.
This should be a class
or a struct that conforms
to the protocol that matches
the type of plugin.
The specific entry point
function that Xcode calls
depends on what
kind of plugin it is.
You can learn more about
the PackagePlugin API
in the "Create Swift Package
plugins" video.
Earlier,
we used a command plugin
to make changes to our package.
Let's look at some more of the
specifics of command plugins.
Command plugins extend
the development workflow.
They are applied directly
to a package,
not during a build.
Not all command plugins
modify the file system --
there are useful actions
that don't involve
changing any files.
But if a command does want
to write to the file system,
it must declare that
in the manifest of the package
that implements the plugin.
This causes Xcode
to ask the user
for permission before
letting the plugin run.
Plugins are usually
quite small,
and often depend on other
tools to do the actual work.
Earlier, we saw
that one of the plugins
uses SwiftFormat
for all the real work.
Dependencies on tool packages
can be either binaries
or source code --
Xcode will build
any required tools from source
before the command is invoked.
Note that the plugin can be
provided by a different package
than the tool it relies on.
In the implementation
of command plugins,
the main type conforms to
the CommandPlugin protocol,
and the plugin implements
the performCommand entry point.
This entry point takes a context
and any custom arguments
provided by the user.
Let's look at a different way
of invoking command plugins.
I'm going to use
the same project as before,
and because I added
the dependency
on the SourceCodeUtilities
package earlier,
I can invoke the same plugins
in Terminal.
First I'm going
to change directory
into the CoreLibs package,
since that's the package
that I want to apply
the command plugin to.
Swift Package Manager 5.6 has
a new subcommand for plugins.
I'll type
"swift package plugin --List"
to see what plugins
are available.
This shows the same plugins
as in the menu in Xcode.
Here on the command line,
each command also shows
the verb that should be used
to run it.
I'll use the verb
for regenerating
a contributor list,
as I did in Xcode.
This plugin wants permission
to write to the file system,
since it's going
to create a file.
I type "yes" to allow this,
and the plugin can run
and update the contributor list.
I could also have used
a package manager option
that allows the plugin
to write to the file system
without asking.
This is particularly useful
if you're invoking it
from a CI system
or other build automation.
But be sure you know
what the plugin is doing
before using that option.
Just like in Xcode,
I can pass command line
arguments to the plugin.
Any arguments after
the plugin's action verb
will be passed to the plugin.
In this case,
I pass a verbose flag
to see more output
from the plugin as it runs.
Each command plugin defines
what arguments it supports.
Until now, we've been talking
mostly about command plugins.
But there are
a few more things to say
about build tool plugins.
Unlike a command plugin,
a build tool plugin does not
do its work immediately.
Instead, it creates and returns
build tool invocations
for Xcode to run later
when the package is built.
Each of those tool invocations
has a command line to run,
and it also has
inputs and outputs
that tells Xcode when to run it.
Build tool plugins
can define commands
that run during the build
or before the build.
We'll take a look at
the difference in a minute.
Commands returned by build tool
plugins are usually configured
to write their outputs
to the build directory,
so they persist between
incremental builds.
And like the plugins
themselves,
the commands defined
by a build tool plugin
run in a sandbox
that prevents network access
and any changes to the package.
In the implementation
of a build tool plugin,
the main type conforms to
the BuildToolPlugin protocol
and the plugin implements
the createBuildCommands
entry point.
This entry point takes
a context and the target
to create build commands for.
It returns any
custom build commands
that should run
when the package is built.
There are two basic kinds
of build commands
that a build tool plugin
can return.
Ordinary build commands
specify input and output paths,
and only run
when the outputs are missing
or the inputs have changed.
Prebuild commands
run before the build starts,
and can be used when
the names of the outputs
are unknown ahead of time.
Prebuild commands
run before every build,
so they should make sure
to do as little work as possible
when there are no changes.
Build commands
and prebuild commands
are great for generating
source code or resources.
So how does Xcode know
which build tool plugins
to apply to a package target?
In SwiftPM 5.6 and later,
there is a new
plugins parameter
in the package manifest
that lists the build tool
plugins that a target wants.
This parameter specifies
any build tool plugins
needed by the target,
and just as with any
runtime libraries it depends on,
those plugins can be
either in the same package
or in another package.
Let's go back to Xcode.
I'm going to configure
my geometry app
to use a build tool plugin.
In this particular case,
I have a custom command line
tool that generates Swift code
based on some data files
in my Core Library target.
The specific details
aren't important,
but what I want to end up with
are generated type-safe
Swift accessors
for each piece of data.
In addition to my data files,
I've been using a custom tool
to generate source code that
I've checked into my repository.
I have been manually
running this tool
to regenerate Swift wrapper code
and committing the changes
whenever my data files change.
But with the build tool plugin,
I can do better.
I can generate the code
during the build
and avoid having to keep the
generated code in my repository.
To get access to the plugin,
I go to the package manifest
and add a dependency
on the package that provides
the source generator plugin
I want to use.
The targets in my package
now have access
to any build tool plugins
defined in that package.
Now I go to the target
that needs to use the plugin,
and I add a plugins parameter
to its definition.
This tells Xcode that it wants
to apply a particular build tool
from that package to my target.
Now I can go and delete
those generated source files
from my repository.
They'll be created or updated
as needed during the build.
There, that's much cleaner.
And now when I build
and run my app,
my build tool plugin
tells Xcode to invoke
my code-generation tool
whenever my data files change.
The generated code
will be stored
along with the other build files
in my build folder,
keeping my repository clean.
In this video,
we've talked about
what Swift package plugins are
and how they work.
We have discussed some
of the similarities
and differences
between command plugins
and build tool plugins.
Both types of plugins
let you replace a variety
of random scripts
with a more structured kind of
extensibility in your packages.
Build tool plugins let you
extend the build system
to generate sources
and resources,
or to do other custom work
as part of your build.
Command plugins
let you automate
common development
tasks with custom actions.
They might be tailored
to a particular workflow
or could be written to be useful
in a wide variety of cases.
To learn how to create
your own package plugins,
be sure to check out
the "Create Swift
Package plugins" video.
Thanks for watching
and enjoy the rest of WWDC 2022.
♪