♪ instrumental hip hop music ♪
♪
Hello! My name is Konrad
and I'm an engineer
on the Swift team.
Welcome to "Meet distributed
actors in Swift."
In this session,
we'll learn how you can take
your Swift concurrency-based
apps beyond a single process.
Swift actors were designed
to protect you
from low-level data races
in the same process.
They do this by compile time
enforced actor isolation checks.
Distributed actors refine
the same conceptual actor model
and extend it
to multiple processes,
such as multiple devices
or servers in a cluster.
So just in case you are not yet
familiar with Swift actors,
we recommend you first watch
the "Protect mutable state
with Swift actors" session
from WWDC 2021.
The app we'll work on
during this session
is a tic-tac-toe-style game
I've been developing recently:
Tic Tac Fish!
The fun idea here
is that you can select
a team you're playing for,
which then corresponds to emojis
that will be used to mark
your moves as you play the game.
Then, as you mark
your moves on the field,
emojis from your team
will be placed on the field
until one of the players wins.
Right now, I have only
implemented an offline mode,
where I can play against
a bot opponent,
but I'd like to introduce
a few multiplayer modes
to take my app
to the next level.
I'm already using actors in
this app to manage concurrency
and model players
involved in the game.
Let's see what it takes
to migrate those player actors
to different processes,
and how distributed actors
can help me do this.
Before we jump to the code,
let us take a step back
and visualize why actors
are so well-suited
for building concurrent
and distributed applications.
Throughout WWDC sessions,
you may hear us use the term
"sea of concurrency"
when talking about actors.
This is because
it's a great mental model
to think about them.
Each actor is its own island
in the sea of concurrency,
and instead of accessing
each other's islands directly,
they exchange messages
between them.
In Swift, sending those
messages across islands
is implemented as asynchronous
method calls and async/await.
This, in combination
with actor state isolation,
allows the compiler to guarantee
that once an actor-based
program compiles,
it is free from low-level
data races.
Now let us now take
this same conceptual model
and apply it to our game,
reimagined as
a distributed system.
We can think of each device,
node in a cluster,
or process
of an operating system
as if it were an independent
sea of concurrency,
here marked as
the smaller dark rectangles.
Within those, we were able
to synchronize information
rather easily
since they were still
sharing the same memory space.
And while the same concept
of message passing
works perfectly well
for concurrency
as well as distribution,
there are a few more
restrictions
distribution needs to put
into place for it all to work.
This is where distributed actors
come into the picture.
By using distributed actors,
we're able to establish
a channel between two processes
and send messages between them.
In other words,
if Swift actors were islands
in the sea of concurrency,
distributed actors are the same
in the vast sea
of distributed systems.
From a programming model,
not much has really changed --
actors still isolate their state
and still can only communicate
using asynchronous messages.
We could even have
more distributed actors
in the same process,
and for all intents
and purposes,
they are as useful
as local actors,
with the difference
that they're also ready
to participate in remote
interactions whenever necessary.
This ability to be potentially
remote without having to change
how we interact
with such distributed actor
is called
"location transparency."
This means that regardless
where a distributed actor
is located,
we can interact
with it the same way.
This is not only
fantastic for testing,
as we execute
the same logic in local actors,
but also enables us
to transparently move our actors
to wherever they
should be located,
without having to change
their implementation.
OK, I think we're ready
to look at some code
and convert our first actor
to a distributed actor.
First, let's have a quick look
at the general game UI,
and how it interacts
with my player actors.
The view is a pretty standard
SwiftUI code,
and I have a few
text and button elements
representing the game field.
As a user clicks a GameCell,
we ask the player actor
to generate a move
and update the view models
that power the UI.
Thanks to Swift concurrency,
all those updates are
thread-safe and well-behaved.
Currently, the actor
representing user input
is implemented
as an offline player.
Let's have a look at it next.
This actor encapsulates
some state that allows it
to generate game moves.
Specifically, it needs to track
how many moves it already made
and what team it is playing for.
Because each team
has a number of emojis
to chose from for each move,
use the number of moves made
to select
the emoji character ID.
I also need to update the model
once a move has been created.
The model is
a MainActor isolated class,
so mutations of it
are thread-safe.
I do need to use "await"
as I make
the userMadeMove call, though.
Lastly, the offline player
also declares a method that is
going to be called whenever
the opponent has made a move.
The only thing we need to do
here is update the view model,
which will make
the game field active again
so the human player
can select their move,
and the cycle continues
until the game ends.
Our bot player is also
represented using an actor.
Its implementation
is actually quite a bit simpler
than the offline player
since it does not have to worry
about updating the view model;
it just keeps track
of the GameState
and generates game moves.
Since the bot player
is a bit simpler,
I think it's a good one
to start our conversion
to distributed actors.
OK, I think we're ready
to look at some code
and convert our first actor
to a distributed actor.
The first step towards our
distributed Tic Tac Fish game
will be to convert
the BotPlayer type
to a distributed actor,
while still only
using it locally.
Let's open Xcode
and see how we can do that.
In order to declare
a distributed actor,
I'll need to import
the new distributed module,
which we introduced
in Swift 5.7.
This module contains
all the necessary types
I'm going to need to declare
and use distributed actors.
I can now add
the distributed keyword
in front of the BotPlayer actor
declaration, like this.
This will cause the actor
to automatically conform
to the DistributedActor
protocol,
and enable a number of
additional compile time checks.
Let's see what kind of errors
the compiler will ask us
to fix now.
The compiler helpfully tells us
that the BotPlayer does not
declare an ActorSystem
it can be used with.
As distributed actors
always belong to some
distributed actor system,
which handles all
the serialization and networking
necessary to perform
remote calls;
we need to declare
what type of actor system
this actor is intended
to be used with.
Since, for now, my only goal
is to have the bot player
pass all the distributed
isolation checks,
without actually running it on
a remote host, I can use the
LocalTestingDistributedActor
System
that comes
with the Distributed module.
I can tell the compiler
about the actor system
we're going to use
by either declaring
a module-wide
DefaultDistributedActorSystem
typealias,
or an ActorSystem typealias in
the body of the specific actor.
The latter bit is a bit more
specific, so let's go with that.
The next error is about
the "id" property,
that I had previously
implemented manually
in order to conform
to the Identifiable protocol
that both my player actors
need to conform to.
The error now says
that the ID property
cannot be defined explicitly
as it conflicts
with a distributed actor
synthesized property.
IDs are a crucial piece
of distributed actors.
They are used
to uniquely identify an actor
in the entire distributed actor
system that it is part of.
They are assigned by
the distributed actor system
as the actor is initialized,
and later managed
by that system.
As such,
we cannot declare or assign
the ID property manually --
the actor system
will be doing this for us.
In other words, I can simply
leave it to the actor system
and remove my manually
declared ID property.
The last error
we need to deal with here
is the distributed
actor's initializer.
The compiler says
that the actorSystem property
has not been
initialized before use.
This is another compiler
synthesized property
that is part
of every distributed actor.
Not only do we need to declare
the type of actor system
we want to use,
but we also need to initialize
the synthesized
actorSystem property
with some concrete actor system.
Generally,
the right thing to do here
is to accept an actor system
in the initializer,
and pass it through
to the property.
This way, I could pass in
a different actor system
implementation in my tests
to facilitate easy unit testing.
We'll also have to pass
an instance whenever we create
a new bot player,
so let's do this now.
Awesome! We're done with
all the declaration side errors.
But there's still
some call-site errors
we need to address though.
It seems that
only distributed methods
can be called on potentially
remote distributed actors.
This is similar to annotating
only some actors in your system
as distributed actors.
Not every method
on a distributed actor
is necessarily designed
to be called remotely.
They can have
small helper functions,
or functions
which assume the caller
has already been authenticated.
This is why Swift asks you
to be explicit about
the distributed API surface,
you want to expose
to remote callers.
Thankfully, this is also
easily fixed by just adding
the distributed keyword
to those functions.
As both makeMove
and opponentMoved methods
are intended
to be called remotely,
let me add the distributed
keyword to them to both of them.
OK! With that,
there's only one last thing
we need to take care of.
As distributed method calls
can cross network boundaries,
we need to ensure
that all of their parameters
and return values conform
to the serialization requirement
of the actor system.
In our case, the actor system
is using Codable,
Swift's native
serialization mechanism.
Specifically, the compiler
tells us that,
"Result type GameMove
does not conform
to the serialization
requirement Codable."
Let me have a quick look
at the GameMove type.
Luckily, it seems that
it's a clean little data type
that I can easily make Codable
by just adding
the necessary conformance.
The Swift compiler
will synthesize
the necessary Codable
implementation for me.
And with that, we're done!
I can check
the game runs as expected.
OK, a point for team fish!
And although
the bot player still executing
on the same local device,
we have already paved the way
for the exciting next step.
In this step, we'll actually
reap the benefits
of the bot player's newly gained
location transparency powers.
I have already prepared
a WebSocket-based
sample actor system
that we can use for this.
By making use
of this actor system,
we'll be able
to move our bot player
to a server-side
Swift application,
and resolve a remote reference
to it from our mobile game.
As far as the actor
is concerned,
we only need to change
the declared ActorSystem
from the LocalTesting
DistributedActor System
to the
SampleWebSocketActorSystem
that I prepared
for the sample app.
The rest of the actor code
remains the same.
Next, let us resolve
a remote bot player reference,
rather than
creating one locally.
It is worth keeping in mind that
the terms "local" and "remote"
are a matter of perspective when
it comes to distributed actors.
For every remote reference,
there is some corresponding
local instance
on some other node
in the distributed actor system.
Creating a local instance
of a distributed actor
is performed much the same way
as any other Swift object:
by calling its initializer.
Obtaining a remote reference
to a distributed actor, however,
follows a slightly
different pattern.
Instead of creating an actor,
we will attempt to resolve
an actor ID
using a concrete actor system.
The static resolve method allows
us to ask an actor system
to attempt to give us
an existing actor instance
for an actor with that ID
or, return a remote reference
to an actor identified by it.
Actor systems should not
perform actual remote lookups
when resolving identifiers
because as you can see,
the resolve method
is not asynchronous,
and therefore
should return quickly
and not perform any networking
or otherwise
blocking operations.
If an identity looks valid,
and seems to be pointing
at a valid remote location,
systems shall assume
that such actor exists and
return a remote reference to it.
Keep in mind that
at the time of resolving an ID,
the actual instance
on the remote system
may not even exist yet!
For example, here we're
making up a random identifier
for an opponent bot player
that should be dedicated
to playing a game with us.
This bot does not exist yet,
but it will be created
on the server-side system
as the first message
designated to this ID
is received.
Now moving on to
a server-side Swift application.
Thanks to the sample WebSocket
actor system I prepared,
implementing that
will be a breeze.
First, we create the WebSocket
actor system in server mode,
which makes it bind
and listen to the port
rather than connect to it.
And we have the app wait
until the system is terminated.
Next, we'll somehow need
to handle the pattern
of creating actors on demand
as we receive messages
addressed to IDs
that are not yet assigned
any actor instances.
Generally, the actor system
will receive incoming messages,
attempt to resolve
their recipient IDs
in order locate a local
distributed actor instance,
and then execute a remote call
on the located actor.
As we just discussed though,
our bot player IDs
are literally made up,
so the system can't possibly
know about them
and even less so create the
right type of actor by itself.
Thankfully, our sample actor
system implementation
has just the right pattern
prepared for us:
on-demand actor creation.
Please note here
that this is only a pattern,
and not something built in
or provided by
the distributed actor module.
It is, however,
a great example of how flexible
and powerful actor system
implementations can be.
A system can offer
various patterns
and make complex tasks
simple to deal with.
Using this pattern,
the actor system attempts
to resolve a local actor
for all incoming IDs as usual.
However, when it fails
to find an existing actor,
it attempts to
resolveCreateOnDemand.
Since we are in control
of both our client code
making up the IDs
and the piece of server code,
we can help
the actor system out
by creating
the necessary actors on demand.
Since the bot identifiers
we have been making up
on the client are using some
recognizable naming scheme --
like adding tags
to the ActorIdentity
or just using
some recognizable names --
we can detect those IDs
and create a new bot opponent
for every message that does not
have one active yet.
We'll only create
a new bot player
for the first message
designated to it,
as subsequent remote calls
will simply resolve
the existing instance.
And that's all there is to it!
Our server implementation
is complete
and we can now play a game
with our remote bot player.
We can run the server from the
command line using Swift run,
or using Xcode
and selecting the server scheme
and clicking Run as usual.
As we're done
making our first move,
we ask the bot player to do
the same by calling makeMove
on the remote player reference
we have created.
This triggers a resolve
in the server-side system.
It can't find an existing bot
for this ID,
so it attempts and succeeds,
creating a bot on demand.
The bot receives
a makeMove call,
and replies with the GameMove
it generated.
That was pretty great already!
While we did have to do
some up-front work
to convert our bot player
to a distributed actor,
actually moving it
to the remote system
was pretty straightforward.
And we didn't have
to deal with any networking
or serialization implementation
details at all!
All the heavy lifting
was done for us
by the distributed actor system.
And while there aren't
many hardened
feature-complete implementations
available just yet,
this ease of going distributed
is something we're striving
for with this feature.
Next,
let's see how we can build
a true multiplayer experience
for our game.
Our previous example
used distributed actors
in a client/server scenario,
which you may be
familiar with already
from other apps you worked on.
However, distributed actors
can also be used
in peer-to-peer systems,
where there isn't a dedicated
server component at all.
This matches another idea
I had for our game.
Sometimes when traveling,
you end up in these locations
that don't really have
great internet,
but the local Wi-Fi works great.
I'd like to still
be able to challenge
and play with my friends --
which are connected
to the same network --
as I end up in such a situation.
I went ahead and implemented
another actor system
implementation,
this time using
local networking features
offered by Network framework.
While we don't dive into
the implementation
of that actor system
in this talk, you can watch
"Advances in Networking, Part 2"
from WWDC 2019
to learn how you would implement
such custom protocol.
It is also worth pointing out
that access to local network
can expose very
privacy-sensitive information,
so please take care
to use it respectfully.
Since this time
we'll be dealing with
already existing distributed
actors on other devices,
we can no longer
just make up the IDs
like we did in the previous
example.
We have to discover
the specific actor
on the other device
we'd like to play a game with.
This problem isn't unique
to distributed actors,
and is generally solved using
service discovery mechanisms.
However, in the domain
of distributed actors,
there is a common pattern
and style of API
actor systems are expected
to offer that allows you
to stick to strongly-typed APIs
throughout all your code.
We call it
the receptionist pattern,
because similar to a hotel,
actors need to check in with it
in order to become known and
available for others to meet.
Every actor system
has its own receptionist
and they can use whatever means
most suitable for the underlying
transport mechanisms
to implement actor discovery.
Sometimes this may rely on
existing service discovery APIs,
and only layer a type-safe API
on top of them,
or it may implement
a gossip-based mechanism,
or something else entirely.
This, however,
is an implementation detail
from the perspective
of the user of the actor system;
all we need to care about
is checking in our actor
to make it discoverable
and look up actors
by some tag or type
when we need to discover them.
Let's have a look at a simple
receptionist I have implemented
for our
SampleLocalNetworkActorSystem.
It allows an actor to check in,
which enables all receptionists
in the distributed actor system
to discover it.
We can then get a listing
of all actors of a specific type
and tag as they become
available in that system.
Let's use this receptionist
to discover
a concrete opponent actor
we'd like to play a game with.
Previously, our GameView
directly created --
or resolved -- an opponent
in its view initializer.
We can no longer do this,
as we need to asynchronously
wait for an opponent
to appear on the network.
To do this, let me introduce
a matchmaking view
that will show a "Looking for
opponent..." message
while we're trying
to discover one.
As this view appears,
we'll kick off the matchmaking.
The matchmaking will be done
in a new unstructured task
in which we'll ask
the local actor system's
receptionist
for a listing
of all actors tagged
using the opposing team's tag.
So if we're playing
for team fish,
we'll be looking for players
from the team rodents,
and vice versa.
Next,
we'll use an async for loop
to await incoming
opponent actors.
As the system discovers
a nearby device with an opponent
we could play with,
this task loop will be resumed.
Let's assume the opponent
is always ready to play a game
and immediately store it
in our model
and start a game with them.
We use a helper function
to decide
who should make the first move,
and finally,
tell the opponent that we want
to start a game with them.
Be sure to return here,
in order to break out
of the async for loop,
as we only need one opponent
to be done
with our matchmaking task.
For this gameplay mode,
we do have to change
our OfflinePlayer implementation
a little.
Let's call it
LocalNetworkPlayer,
and it'll be using the
SampleLocalNetworkActorSystem.
What's most interesting about it
is that the makeMove method
of the the actor
representing a human player
may now be invoked remotely!
But making the move is actually
the responsibility
of a human player.
In order to solve
this challenge,
we introduce
a humanSelectedField
asynchronous function
to our view model.
It is powered by a @Published
value that is triggered
when the human
user clicks on one of the
fields.
As the human player
clicks a field,
our makeMove function resumes,
and we complete the remote call
by returning the performed
GameMove to the remote caller.
And again,
that's all there is to it!
We had to change
the actor implementation
a little to handle our
true multiplayer game mode,
but nothing really changed
in the overall design
of the system.
And most importantly,
nothing in our game logic
changes was really specific
to the fact we'll be using
local networking.
We discover an opponent
and play a game with them
by invoking distributed methods
on player actors.
To demo this game mode, I'll
need an opponent to play with.
Let's ask my fluffy assistant
Caplin the Capybara.
I heard he's pretty good at it!
OK, he's pretty smart.
He is pretty good at it.
Let me try here.
Oh, he got me!
This time you win,
little critter,
but we'll play another session.
Thanks for your help, Caplin!
Last but not least,
let me give you an idea
of what we can achieve
by combining
different actor systems.
For example, we can use
the WebSocket system to register
device-hosted actor
player actors
in a server-side lobby system
that will pair them up
and act as a proxy
for distributed calls
between them.
We might implement
a GameLobby actor,
with which device-hosted
player actors
are able to register themselves.
As devices enter
the play online mode,
they would discover the
GameLobby using a receptionist,
and call join on it.
The GameLobby keeps track
of available players
and starts a game session
when a pair of players
has been identified.
A game session would act
as the driver of the game,
polling moves and marking them
in the server-stored
representation of the game.
As the game completes,
we can collect results
and report back to the lobby.
More interestingly though,
we can scale
this design horizontally.
We can of course create
more game session actors
to serve more games
concurrently on a single server,
but thanks
to distributed actors,
we could even create
a game session on other nodes
in order to load balance
the number of concurrent games
across a cluster.
That is, if only we had
a cluster actor system.
And, in fact, we do!
We open-sourced a feature-rich
Cluster Actor system library
for you to use
in such scenarios.
It's implemented using SwiftNIO,
and specialized
for server-side
data-center clustering.
It applies advanced techniques
for failure detection,
and comes with it's own
implementation
of a cluster-wide receptionist.
We encourage you
to have a look at it,
as it is both an advanced
reference implementation
of an actor system,
and because of its powerful
server-side applications.
Let's recap what we learned
during this session.
First, we learned about
distributed actors
and how we provide additional
compiler-assisted
actor isolation
and serialization checking.
We learned how they enable
location transparency,
and how we can make use of it
to free our actors
from the necessity of being
located in the same process
as their caller.
We also saw a few actor system
implementations in action
to get you inspired about
what you could build
using distributed actors.
Distributed actors are only
as powerful as the actor systems
they are used with.
So for your reference,
here is a list of actor systems
we saw during this session.
The local testing system, which
ships by default with Swift,
and two sample actor systems:
a client/server style
WebSocket-based one
and a local
networking-based system.
These systems are rather
incomplete,
and served more
as an inspiration
for what you might build
using distributed actors.
You can view them
in the sample code app
associated with this session.
And last but not least,
an open source
fully featured server-side
clustering implementation.
Available as
a beta package now,
and it will be matured
alongside Swift 5.7.
To learn more about
distributed actors,
you can refer
to the following resources:
the sample code associated
with this session,
which includes all the steps
of our Tic Tac Fish game
so you can deep dive
into the code yourself.
The Swift evolution proposals
associated with the distributed
actors language feature,
which explain the mechanisms
powering them in great detail.
You can also reach out
on the Swift forums,
where you can find
a distributed actors category
dedicated to actor system
developers and users alike.
Thanks for listening, and I'm
looking forward to seeing
what you'll use distributed
actors for in your apps!
♪