♪ ♪
Ken Greenebaum: Hi everyone!
Welcome to WWDC 2022.
My name is Ken Greenebaum,
and I'm with the Color and Display
Technologies team at Apple.
We are thrilled to have three EDR talks
this year.
Hope you've had an opportunity
to watch "Explore EDR on iOS,"
where we announced
EDR API support for iOS,
as well as "Display EDR content
with Core Image, Metal, and SwiftUI."
Some of you may have also watched
my EDR talk last year,
where we demonstrated
how to use AVPlayer
to play back HDR video, using EDR.
In this talk we're gonna go deeper,
and explore how to use
Core Media interfaces to provide,
not only EDR playback,
but also how to decode
and playback HDR video,
into your own EDR layers or views.
Then we'll continue beyond
simply playing back content,
to show how to access the decoded
video frames in real time,
via Core Video's display link,
send those frames to CoreImage Filters,
or a Metal Shader,
to add color management, visual effects,
or apply other signal processing,
and finally, plumb
the resulting frames to Metal to render.
We're going to start by reviewing
the EDR compatible video media frameworks,
to help you decide which best matches
your application's requirements.
Next we will briefly discuss
the high level AVKit
and AVFoundation frameworks,
that can do all of the work
of playing HDR video,
if your application
requires straight forward playback.
And finally,
we'll discuss best practices
for using decoded video frames,
with Core Video and Metal,
in your EDR playback, editing,
or image processing engine.
Let's begin by taking a quick survey
of Apple's video frameworks;
Starting with
the highest level interfaces;
which are the easiest to use;
and continuing to lower level frameworks
that offer more opportunities,
at the expense of adding
complexity to your code.
It is best to use
the highest level framework possible
to take advantage of the optimizations
provided automatically for you.
This will get us ready to dive into
the body of the talk,
where we will be exploring
a number of scenarios,
from simple EDR playback
to more sophisticated plumbing
of decoded video frames
to CoreImage or Metal
for real time processing.
At the highest level, there is AVKit.
With AVKit you can create
user interfaces for media playback;
complete with transport controls,
chapter navigation,
Picture in Picture support,
and display of subtitles
and closed captions.
AVKit can playback HDR content as EDR,
as we will demonstrate
using AVPlayerViewController.
However, if your application requires
further processing of video frames,
you will have to use a media framework
that can give you more control
over your pipeline.
Next there is AVFoundation.
AVFoundation is
the full-featured framework
for working with time based audio visual
media on Apple Platforms.
Using AVFoundation,
you can easily play, create,
and edit QuickTime movies
and MPEG 4 files,
play HLS streams,
and build powerful media functionality
into your apps.
We'll be exploring use of AVPlayer
and the related AVPlayerLayer interface
in this talk.
Core Video is a framework that provides
a pipeline model for digital video.
It simplifies the way
you work with videos
by partitioning the process
into discrete steps.
Core Video also makes it easier
for you to access and manipulate
individual frames,
without having to worry about
translating between data types
or worrying about display synchronization.
We'll be demonstrating
use of DisplayLink,
and CVPixelBuffer's with Core Image.
And CVMetalTextureCache, with Metal.
Next there is Video Toolbox.
This is a low-level framework
that provides direct access
to hardware encoders and decoders.
Video Toolbox provides services for
video compression and decompression,
and for conversion between
raster image formats
stored in Core Video pixel buffers.
VTDecompressionSession
is a powerful low-level interface
that is outside of the scope of this talk,
but advanced developers
might want to investigate further.
And finally, there is Core Media.
This framework defines
the media pipeline used by AVFoundation,
and the other high-level media frameworks.
You can always use Core Media's
low-level data types and interfaces
to efficiently process media samples
and manage queues of media data.
In the remainder of this talk
we will demonstrate how and when
to use these frameworks in your app.
First, how to use AVKit
and AVFoundation
to easily playback HDR video
rendered as EDR.
Then a series of more sophisticated
applications of AVPlayer:
to render to your own layer,
to access individually decoded frames
via CADisplayLink
and send the resulting CVPixelBuffers
to Core Image for processing,
and finally, accessing the decoded frames
as Metal textures
via the CVMetalTextureCache
for processing and rendering in Metal.
Now that we have an overview of
the video media layer on Apple platforms,
we'll focus on AVKit
and AVFoundation frameworks.
Let's get things started
by first discussing playback
of your HDR video content
using AVFoundation's AVPlayer interface.
An AVPlayer is a controller object,
used to manage the playback
and timing of a media asset.
The AVPlayer interface can be used for
high-performance playback of HDR video,
automatically rendering
the result as EDR when possible.
With AVPlayer, you can play local,
and remote file based media,
such as QuickTime movies;
as well as streaming media,
served using HLS.
Essentially, AVPlayer is used to play
one media asset at a time.
You can reuse the player instance
to serially play additional media assets,
or even create multiple instances to play
more than one asset simultaneously,
but AVPlayer manages the playback
of only a single media asset at a time.
AVFoundation framework also provides
a subclass of AVPlayer
called AVQueuePlayer
that you can use to create
and manage the queuing and playing
of sequential HDR media assets.
If your application requires
simple playback of HDR video media
rendered to EDR, then AVPlayer
with AVPlayerViewController,
may be the best approach.
Use AVPlayer with AVPlayerLayer
to playback your own views
on iOS or macOS.
These are the most straightforward ways
of using AVPlayer.
Let's look at examples of both.
First we will look how you can
use AVFoundation's AVPlayer interface,
in conjunction with AVKit's
AVPlayer View Controller.
Here, we start by instantiating AVPlayer
from the media's URL.
Next we create
an AVPlayerViewController,
then set the player property
of our viewer controller
to the player we just created
from the media's URL.
And present the view controller modally
to start playback of the video.
AVKit manages all the details for you
and will automatically play back
HDR Video as EDR
on displays supporting EDR.
As I mentioned, some applications will
need to play back HDR video media
into their own view.
Let's look at how to accomplish this
using AVPlayer with AVPlayerLayer.
To play HDR video media as EDR
in your own view,
we again start by creating an AVPlayer
with the media's URL.
However this time
we instantiate an AVPlayerLayer
with the player we just created.
Next we need to set the bounds
on the player layer,
which we get from the view.
Now that the player layer
has the bounds from the view,
we can add the player layer
as a sublayer to the view.
Finally,
to play back the HDR video media,
we call AVPlayer's play method.
That's all that is needed to play back
HDR video media as EDR
in your own layer
using AVPlayer and AVPlayerLayer.
We just explored
the two most straightforward
HDR video playback workflows
using AVPlayer.
However, many applications require more
than simple media playback.
For example, an application
might require image processing,
such as color grading or chroma keying
to be applied to the video.
Let's explore a workflow that gets
decoded video frames from AVPlayer,
applies Core Image filters
or Metal shaders in real time,
and renders the results as EDR.
We will be demonstrating how to use
AVPlayer and the AVPlayerItem
to decode EDR frames
from your HDR video media,
access the decoded frames
from the Core Video display link,
send the resulting pixel buffers
to Core Image or Metal for processing,
then render the results
in a CAMetalLayer
as EDR on displays with EDR support.
With this in mind,
let's first demonstrate
setting a few key properties
on the CAMetalLayer,
which are required to ensure HDR media
will render correctly as EDR.
First we need to get the CAMetalLayer
that we will be rendering
the HDR video content to.
On that layer
we opt into EDR by setting
the wantsExtendedDynamicRangeContent
flag to true.
Please be sure to use a pixel format that
supports Extended Dynamic Range content.
For the AVPlayer example that follows,
we will set the CAMetalLayer to use
a half float pixel format,
however a ten bit format
used in conjunction with a PQ
or HLG transfer function would also work.
To avoid limiting the result to SDR,
we also need to set the layer
to an EDR compatible
extended range color space.
In our examples we will be setting
the half float metal texture
to the extended linear display P3
color space.
We just scratched the surface
regarding EDR,
color spaces, and pixel buffer formats.
You might want to check out
my session from last year,
"HDR rendering with EDR,"
as well as this year's "EDR on iOS,"
for more details.
Now that we have set the basic properties
on the CAMetalLayer,
let's continue the demonstration
by adding real time image processing
using a Core Image, or Metal shader.
We'll be using a display link
in conjunction with AVPlayer
to access the decoded video frames
in real time.
For this workflow, you start by creating
an AVPlayer from an AVPlayerItem.
Next, you instantiate
an AVPlayerItemVideoOutput,
configured with appropriate pixel buffer
format and color space for EDR.
Then you create
and configure a Display link.
And lastly, you run the Display link
to get the pixel buffers
to Core Image or Metal for processing.
We will demonstrate a CADisplayLink
as is used on iOS.
Please use the equivalent CVDisplayLink
interface when developing for macOS.
This time we choose
to create an AVPlayerItem
from our media's URL,
and instantiate an AVPlayer with
the AVPlayerItem that we just created.
Now we create a pair of dictionaries
to specify the color space
and pixel buffer format
of the decoded frames.
The first dictionary,
videoColorProperties,
is where the color space
and transfer function are specified.
In this example we request
the Display P3 colorspace,
which corresponds to the color space
of most Apple displays,
and the linear transfer function
which allows AVFoundation
to maintain the extended range values
required for EDR.
The second dictionary,
outputVideoSettings,
specifies the characteristics of
the pixel buffer format
and also provides a reference
to the videoColorProperties dictionary
we just created.
In this example, we request wide color
and the half float pixel buffer format.
It is very helpful
that AVPlayerItemVideoOutput,
not only decodes video
into the pixel buffer format we specify
in the output settings dictionary,
but also automatically performs
any color conversion required
via a pixel transfer session.
Recall, a video might contain
multiple clips,
potentially with different colorspaces.
AVFoundation automatically manages
these for us,
and as we'll soon be demonstrating,
this behavior also allows
the resulting decoded video frames
to be sent to low level frameworks
like Metal
that don't themselves provide
automatic colorspace conversion
to the display's colorspace.
Now we create
the AVPlayerItemVideoOutput
with the outputVideoSettings dictionary.
As the third step,
we setup the Display link,
which will be used to access
the decoded frames in real time.
CADisplayLink takes a call back
that is run on each display update.
In our example we call a local function
that we will explore in a moment
to get the CVPixelBuffers that we will
be sending to Core Image for processing.
Next we create a video player item
observer
to allow us to handle changes
to specified player Item properties.
Our example will execute this code
every time for the player item's
status changes.
When the player item's status
changes to readyToPlay,
we add our AVPlayerItemVideoOutput
to the new AVPlayerItem
that was just returned,
register CADisplayLink
with the main run loop set to common mode,
and start the real time decoding
of the HDR video
by calling play on the video player.
Finally, we will take a look at an example
CADisplayLink callback implementation,
which we referred to earlier
as the `displayLinkCopyPixelBuffers`
local function.
Once the HDR video begins to play,
the CADisplayLink callback function
is called on each display refresh.
For instance it might be called 60 times
a second for a typical display.
This is our code's opportunity
to update the frame displayed
if there is a new CVPixelBuffer.
On each display callback,
we attempt to copy a CVPixelBuffer
containing the decoded video frame
to be displayed
at the current wall clock time.
However,
the `copyPixelBuffer` call might fail,
as there won't always be a new
CVPixelBuffer available
at every display refresh,
especially when the screen refresh rate
exceeds that of the video being played.
If there is not a new CVPixelBuffer,
then the call fails
and we skip the render.
This causes the preceding frame to remain
on-screen for another display refresh.
But if the copy succeeds,
then we have a fresh frame of video
in a CVPixelBuffer.
There are a number of ways that we might
process and render this new frame.
One opportunity is to send
the CVPixelBuffer to Core Image
for processing.
Core Image can string together
one or more CIFilters
to provide GPU accelerated
image processing to the video frame.
Please note that not all CIFilters
are compatible with EDR
and might have trouble with HDR content,
including clamping to SDR or worse.
Core Image provides
many EDR compatible Filters.
Use filter names with
CICategoryHighDynamicRange,
to enumerate EDR compatible
Core Image filters.
In our example, we will be adding
a simple sepia tone effect.
Now let's return to our example
and integrate Core Image.
On each display link callback
that yields a fresh CVPixelBuffer,
create a CIImage from that pixel buffer.
Instance the CIFilter
to implement the desired effect.
I am using the sepia tone filter
because of its parameter-less simplicity,
however there are many CIFilters
built into the system,
and it is straightforward
to write your own, too.
Set the CIFilter's inputImage
to the CIImage we just created.
And the processed video result
will be available
in the filter's outputImage.
Chain as many CIFilters together as are
required to achieve your desired effect.
Then use a CIRenderDestination
to render the resulting image
to your application's view code.
Please refer to the WWDC 2020 talk
"Optimize the Core Image pipeline for your video app"
to learn more about this workflow.
Another opportunity, is to process
and render the fresh CVPixelBuffer
using Metal and custom Metal shaders.
We will briefly describe the process
of converting the CVPixelBuffer
to a Metal texture.
However, implementing this conversion
maintaining best performance
is a deep topic
best left for another talk.
We instead recommend
deriving the Metal texture
from the CoreVideo Metal texture cache,
and will walk through that process
as the final example in this talk.
Generally speaking, the process is to get
the IOSurface from the CVPixelBuffer,
create a MetalTextureDescriptor,
and then create a MetalTexture
from the MetalDevice,
using `newTextureWithDescriptor`.
However, there is a danger
that the textures may be re-used,
and over-drawn,
if careful locking is not applied.
Further, not all PixelBuffer formats
are natively supported by MetalTexture,
which is why we use
half float in this example.
Because of these complications,
we instead recommend
directly accessing Metal textures from
Core Video, as we will now demonstrate.
Let's further explore Core Video
and Metal.
As mentioned, CVMetalTextureCache
is both a straightforward
and efficient way
to use CVPixelBuffers with Metal.
CVMetalTextureCache is handy
because you get a Metal texture
directly from the cache
without need for further conversion.
CVMetalTextureCache
automatically bridges between
CVPixelBuffer's, and MetalTexture's,
thereby both simplifying your code
and keeping you on the fast path.
In conjunction with CVPixelBufferPools,
CVMetalTextureCache
also provides performance benefits,
by keeping MTLTexture
to IOSurface mapping alive.
Finally, using CVMetalTextureCache
removes the need
to manually track IOSurfaces.
Now the final example in our talk:
how to extract Metal textures
directly from Core Video
using CVMetalTextureCache.
Here, we start by getting
the system default Metal device.
We use that to create
a Metal Texture Cache,
and then instantiate
a Core Video Metal Texture Cache
associated with the Metal Texture Cache.
That can then be used to access
decoded video frames as Metal Textures,
which conveniently,
can be directly used in our Metal engine.
In this example, we create and use
the Metal system default device.
Next we create the CVMetalTextureCache
with CVMetalTextureCacheCreate,
specifying the Metal device
we just created.
We get the height and width
of the CVPixelBuffer
needed to create the Core Video
Metal texture.
Then we call
`CVMetalTextureCacheCreateTextureFromImage`,
to instantiate a CVMetalTexture object
and associate that
with the CVPixelBuffer.
Finally we call
`CVMetalTextureGetTexture`,
to get the desired Metal texture.
Swift applications should use
a strong reference for CVMetalTexture,
however, when using Objective-C,
you must ensure that Metal is done
with your texture before you release
the CVMetalTextureRef.
This may be accomplished using
metal command buffer completion handlers.
And that's all, folks!
To review,
we explored a number of workflows
that will render your HDR video media
to EDR,
for playback, editing,
or image processing.
You learned how to go from AVPlayer to
AVKit's AVPlayerViewController,
for playback of HDR media.
You also learned how use AVPlayer,
along with AVPlayerLayer,
to display HDR media on your own view.
And finally, we explored how to add
real time effects during playback.
Connecting AVFoundation's AVPlayer
to CoreVideo
and then to Metal for rendering.
And applying real time effects
using CoreImage filters,
as well as Metal shaders.
If you want to dig deeper,
I recommend a few WWDC sessions
related to creating video workflows,
as well as integrating HDR media with EDR.
I especially want to call out the session
"Edit and play back HDR video
with AVFoundation".
This session explores use
of AVVideoComposition
with `applyingCIFiltersWithHandler`
for applying effects to your HDR media.
In this session you'll also learn
how to use custom compositor,
which can then be used
with a CVPixelBuffer,
when each video frame becomes
available for processing.
As I mentioned at the beginning,
this year we're also presenting
two other sessions on EDR:
"EDR on iOS,"
where we announced EDR API support
has expanded to include iOS,
and "HDR content display with
EDR using CoreImage, Metal and SwiftUI,"
where we further explore integrating
EDR with other media frameworks.
Hope you incorporate HDR video
into your EDR enabled applications
on both macOS and now iOS.
Thanks for watching.