♪ Bass-heavy electronic music ♪
Now that I have
your attention,
here's your day three
status report.
♪
We started our training
with Lynn
exploring new ways
to design shortcuts for apps.
- You're well on your way
to an amazing
App Shortcuts experience.
- Then we discovered how
to make desktop-class iPad apps
with Mohammed.
- This allows apps
to express the layout
that's most appropriate
to their content,
while bringing
more functionality
to the forefront of the UI.
- Then found out
how to take advantage
of the latest iOS
camera capture features.
- This app has one more trick
up its sleeve.
I can tap around
and point a spotlight
at different objects
in the scene.
- We also showed off
powerful tools
to create cool new layouts
and views for apps with SwiftUI.
- SwiftUI provides
a rich set of building blocks
that you use to compose
your app's interface.
- Tomorrow's reports
look something like this.
♪
- Go get 'em, tiger.
- That's all for now.
Await further instructions.
♪